<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 2: The Almost Christian</title>
                <title type="subtitle">A Sermon preached at St. Mary’s, Oxford, before the
                    University, on <date when="1741-07-11">July 25, 1741</date>
                </title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-21</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon002</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 2: The Almost Christian</title>
                            <date when="1741-07-25"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="131" to="141"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="109"/>
            <introduction>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 1-4]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As we have seen, these first four sermons in this first volume of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> were ‘prefixed’ to the other eight on the advice of
                    friends, and also as proof of the consistency of Wesley’s new preaching, whether
                    before the University of Oxford or to the masses in Moorfields. But they also
                    serve another function, unavowed but crucial: they mark out the successive
                    stages of Wesley’s alienation from any further career as a reformer within the
                    university, as he made the radical shift in his commitment to the Revival as his
                    new vocation.</p>
                <p>Along with other ordained Oxford M.A.s, the brothers Wesley were subject to
                    occasional appointment as preachers in the <hi rend="italic">rota</hi> of
                    university services on Sundays and saints’ days (most of them in the Church of
                    St. Mary the Virgin, but others in St. Peter’s in the East and certain college
                        chapels).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Oxford University Statutes, tr. by G. R. M. Ward (1845), Vol. I, ‘The
                            Laudian Statutes’ (1636), Title XVI, chs. 1-7.</p>
                    </note> Attendance
                    upon these services was a stated obligation of ‘all doctors, masters, graduates,
                    and scholars’, who were enjoined to ‘be present at them from their beginning to
                    their end…’; no one was ‘permitted to wander abroad to another church, or
                    churches, under pain of chastisement…’, etc. (ch. 10). Even though these
                    injunctions were often honoured in the breach, such occasions were still
                    splendid sounding boards for eloquent preachers with earnest messages.</p>
                <p>John Wesley’s first ‘university sermon’ had been delivered in St. Mary’s on
                    November 15, 1730, ‘On Gen. 1:27’ (see No. 141, Vol. IV); a second on July 23,
                    1732 (‘A Consecration Sermon’, not extant); a third on January 1, 1733 (‘The
                    Circumcision of the Heart’; see No. 17 below). This last may be reckoned as a
                    landmark in the development of Wesley’s theology, and must also have made a
                    favourable general impression, for in the next two and a half years he was
                    invited to deliver <pb n="110"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">six</hi> more university
                    sermons: March 26, 1733 (Easter); April 1, 1733 (Low Sunday); May 13, 1733
                    (Whitsunday); February 10, 1734; June 11, 1734 (St. Barnabas’s); September 21,
                    1735 (St. Matthew’s). This is out of all proportion to any typical rotation, and
                    even if Wesley was serving as substitute for other appointed preachers, that
                    would have required the approval of the Vice-Chancellor (cf. <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>, XVI, ch. 6). The least that this can mean is that John
                    Wesley was more widely appreciated at Oxford as a preacher than the popular
                    stereotypes have suggested.</p>
                <p>This fact sheds some light on the arrangement by the university officials for
                    Wesley to preach again in Oxford soon after his return from Georgia (probably in
                    expectation of his resumption of his duties there); the new appointment was set
                    for the Festival of St. Barnabas, June 11, 1738. By that time, of course, Wesley
                    had undergone the radical change of heart and mind described in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for May 24, about which his Oxford colleagues
                    would have known nothing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Intro., above, p.4; see also Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Wesley</hi>, I.141-95, for a careful analysis of the
                            theological developments involved in this ‘conversion’; JWJ, Feb. 7-May
                            28, sheds light on Wesley’s mood as he revised his sermon for this
                            crucial new occasion.</p>
                    </note> Meanwhile, he had already tested his
                    ‘new gospel’ (‘salvation by faith alone’) in several churches in and near
                    London, and his presentation of it had almost invariably stirred up more offence
                    than conversions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, Feb. 5 (Milbank, Westminster); Feb. 12 (St. Andrew’s,
                            Holborn); Feb. 26 (thrice in London, the first, in St. Lawrence Jewry,
                            being the most blessed ‘because it gave the most offence’); Mar. 6
                            (after being counselled by Böhler to ‘preach faith <hi rend="italic">till</hi> you have it; and then, <hi rend="italic">because</hi> you
                            have it, you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> preach faith’); Mar. 17, 26,
                            and 27; Apr. 2, 25, 26; May 7, 9, 14, and 21 (this last being also the
                            day of Charles Wesley’s experience of assurance).</p>
                    </note> In most of
                    these instances, as he records with a trace of self-righteousness, he had been
                    thenceforth barred from this pulpit and that. The Aldersgate experience had not
                    produced a new doctrine, but a new resolution to make the most of his
                    opportunities to expound the one to which he had already come.</p>
                <p>He was by now very well aware of the controversial character of his message, and
                    he could not have expected a sympathetic hearing at Oxford. ‘Salvation by Faith’
                    was, however, the first public occasion after his ‘Aldersgate’ experience for a
                    positive evangelical manifesto. It is worth noting that its Moravian substance
                    is qualified by echoes from the Edwardian <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, as in
                    the claim that salvation involved a power not to commit sin (<hi rend="italic">posse non peccare</hi>). There is also an obvious Anglican nuance in the
                    definition of saving faith presented here.</p>
                <p>When his turn as university preacher came round again (<date when="1741-07-25">July 25, 1741</date>), the Revival was in full swing and Wesley had found
                    in its <pb n="111"/>leadership an alternative career. He had not only begun to
                    shift his loyalties from Oxford to his own Societies; he had also become one of
                    Oxford’s harsher critics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This may be seen in the Latin and English versions
                            of a sermon on Isa. 1:21 which he had first prepared in 1739, probably
                            in connection with his exercises for the B.D. degree which, as Fellow of
                            Lincoln College, he was expected to take in due course (see below, Nos.
                            150, 151).</p>
                    </note> John Gambold had already advised him that he would
                    face a hostile audience, but Wesley was in no mood to mollify them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, June 18,
                            1741: ‘All here [Gambold had said of the Oxford community] are so
                            prejudiced that they will mind nothing you say.’ Wesley’s reaction: ‘I
                            know that. However, I am to deliver my own soul, whether they will hear
                            or whether they will forbear’ (one of Wesley’s standard formulae of
                            alienation). A fortnight later even Wesley and Gambold had come to a
                            parting of their ways (cf. JWJ, July 2). Earlier, he had finally got
                            round to reading ‘that celebrated book, Martin Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Comment on the Epistle to the Galatians</hi>’; his
                            negative reaction to it was intemperate (see JWJ, June 15).</p>
                    </note>
                    Indeed, the whole <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> record for June and July
                    reflects a mounting tension, as if Wesley was aware of the crisis. On June 28 he
                    preached ‘at Charles Square [London], to the largest congregation that, I
                    believe, was ever seen there, on “Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian”
                    [cf. Acts 26:28]’. This was the sermon that, revised and with its new
                    ‘application’ explicitly aimed at Oxford, he delivered on the festival day of
                    St. James the Apostle, July 25.</p>
                <p>Its theme—the radical difference between nominal and real Christianity—was
                    already a familiar one in Puritan preaching;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, proem and n.</p>
                    </note> it was, however, already
                    conventional to ignore the text’s plain reference to Agrippa’s being almost
                    persuaded to become a Christian rather than to his already being a nominal one.
                    Wesley draws out the distinctions between the two stages of Christian experience
                    (‘almost’ and ‘altogether’). Part I paints a vivid picture of the high-minded
                    hypocrite (the ‘almost Christian’) and concludes with Wesley’s confession ‘that
                    this had been his own state in all his days at Oxford’ (I.13). Part II
                    delineates the ‘altogether Christian’ according to his new conceptions, and
                    openly expresses doubt that there are many such in Oxford even now (II.7-9).
                    There are no records of this sermon’s reception on this occasion, but it would
                    not have been lost on his Methodist readers that their leader had bearded the
                    Anglican establishment in one of its citadels and had survived.</p>
                <p>In the following year Charles Wesley came up for an appointment as preacher in
                    St. Mary’s on <date when="1742-04-04">April 4, 1742</date>. His evangelical
                    conversion had preceded his brother’s, either on <date when="1738-05-03">May 3,
                        1738</date> (when ‘it pleased God to open his <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> so
                    that he saw clearly what was the nature of [saving] <pb n="112"/>faith…’) or on
                        <date when="1738-05-19">May 19</date> (when he ‘had found rest to his
                        soul’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            both CWJ and JWJ for these dates and experiences.</p>
                    </note> In any
                    case, Charles was more exuberant in temperament and rhetoric than his elder
                        brother.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            above, p. 2, n. 6: ‘…in connection I beat you; but in strong, pointed
                            sentences you beat me.’</p>
                    </note> He had already preached a sermon on
                    justification ‘before the university [July 1739] with great boldness…’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">CWJ, Sunday, July
                            1, 1739; this is followed (on Monday) by a note that the Vice-Chancellor
                            and ‘all were against [that] sermon as liable to be misunderstood’. Had
                            this been Charles’s reinforcing sequel to John’s <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>?</p>
                    </note> His bidding prayer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the
                            unpublished MS of a sermon on Rom. 3:27-28.</p>
                    </note> indicates that
                    this preaching service had been held in Christ Church Cathedral rather than St.
                    Mary’s. On June 30, 1740, he reports having spent a week in Oxford ‘preaching
                    repentance’ but also in discovering that ‘learned Gallio cared for none of these
                        things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 18:17 for this analogy between a Roman proconsul’s and Oxford’s
                            indifference.</p>
                    </note> Now, he was scheduled to preach in St. Mary’s
                    itself—for the first and last time.</p>
                <p>Charles’s message, with a barrage of invidious questions for its climax, fell
                    largely on deaf ears; this is reported by a visitor who was in the audience:
                    Thomas Salmon, a popular historian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The times of the day the University go to this
                            church are ten in the morning and two in the afternoon, on Sundays and
                            holidays, the sermon usually lasting about half an hour. But when I
                            happened to be at Oxford, in 1742, Mr. Wesley, the Methodist, of Christ
                            Church, entertained his audience two hours, having insulted and abused
                            all degrees from the highest to the lowest, was in a manner hissed out
                            of the pulpit by the lads;’ Thomas Salmon, <hi rend="italic">A
                                Foreigner’s Companion through the Universities of Cambridge and
                                Oxford</hi> (1748), p. 25, and quoted in CWJ, Apr. 15,
                        1750.</p>
                    </note> Charles Wesley’s denial of Salmon’s report appears in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for April 15, 1750, and is emphatic;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘And it would
                            have been high time for them to do so, if the historian [Salmon] said
                            true. But, unfortunately for him, I measured the time by my watch and it
                            was within the hour; I abused neither high nor low, as my sermon in
                            print will prove; neither was I hissed out of the pulpit or treated with
                            the least incivility, either by young or old….’</p>
                    </note> he may have
                    been right about the time, since the sermon as printed can be read aloud in
                    thirty minutes. On the other hand, Charles’s accusations must surely have
                    aroused resentment in his auditory, and Salmon would have been a competent judge
                    of that. In any case this sermon would have persuaded any Methodist reader of
                    Charles’s wholehearted identification with his brother’s cause and theirs. <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> is then a lively evangelical
                    statement, a personal identification with the Revival and a valedictory to
                    Oxford.</p>
                <p>By August 1744 the Revival was gaining momentum, the network (‘connexion’) of the
                    Methodist Societies had extended over into Wales <pb n="113"/>and had come under
                    serious persecution by English mobs, the first ‘conference’ had just been held
                    (June 25-29), and John Wesley had found his true mission in life. Even so, his
                    turn as university preacher came up yet again for August 24 (another festival,
                    this one for St. Bartholomew). This, of course, was an anniversary of the
                    notorious Massacre of Paris (in 1572) and, again, of the Great Ejectment of the
                    Nonconformists in England in 1662, in which both of Wesley’s grandfathers had
                    suffered. Benjamin Kennicott’s explanation of Wesley’s appointment was that ‘as
                    no clergyman [could] avoid his turn, so the university can refuse none;
                    otherwise Mr. Wesley would not have preached.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">At this time, Kennicott was an undergraduate
                            at Wadham College, but he was destined to set Old Testament studies in
                            England upon a new level with his great <hi rend="italic">Vetus
                                Testamentum cum Variis Lectionibus</hi> (Vol. 1, 1776; Vol. 2,
                            1780). His account of Wesley’s sermon appeared in <hi rend="italic">WMM</hi>, 1866, 47-48.</p>
                    </note> Actually, though, that rule was
                    flexible; there was ample precedent for substitutions. One must wonder,
                    therefore, how the appointment came about. Was it a gesture of academic freedom?
                    Did Wesley have a stronger base in Oxford than would appear from the record?
                    There is no indication that he had claimed his turn as by right, but it would
                    never have crossed his mind to avoid it. Thus, the stage was set for a
                    confrontation—and another valedictory.</p>
                <p>Parts I-III of <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> constitute a
                    positive account of Wesley’s conception of the ‘order of salvation’ (Part I), an
                    interesting missiological perspective (Part II), and an early statement of
                    Wesley’s eschatological ideas (Part III)—the sum of these parts is evangelical
                    and Anglican. The mood changes in Part IV where he comes to his ‘plain and
                    practical application’. Here the judgment is passed, with scant charity, that
                    Oxford’s hypocrisies are an intolerable offence to God and a general hindrance
                    to the Christian mission. Kennicott’s uncharitable suspicion was that this final
                    salvo ‘was what [Wesley] had been preparing for all along…’:</p>
                <quote>[In the conclusion] he fired his address with so much zeal and unbounded
                    satire as quite spoiled what otherwise might have been turned to great
                    advantage…. I liked some of his freedom: such as calling the generality of young
                    townsmen ‘a generation of triflers’…. But considering how many shining lights
                    are here that are the glory of the Christian cause, his sacred censure was much
                    too flaming and strong and his charity much too weak…. Having summed up the
                    measure of our iniquities, he concluded with a lifted up eye in this most solemn
                    form, ‘It is time for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, Lord, to lay to <hi rend="italic">thine</hi> hand’—words full of such presumption and seeming
                    imprecation that they gave an universal shock…. Had these things been omitted
                    and his censures moderated, I think his discourse, as to style and delivery,
                    would have been uncommonly pleasing to others as well as to myself. He is
                    allowed to be a man of great parts, and that by the excellent Dean <pb n="114"/>of Christ Church;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John Conybeare, who succeeded Joseph Butler as
                            Bishop of Bristol, and author of <hi rend="italic">Defence of Revealed
                                Religion…</hi> (1732), one of the eighteenth century’s more famous
                            replies to Tindal and other deists.</p>
                    </note> for the day he preached
                    the dean generously said of him, ‘John Wesley will always be thought a man of
                    sound sense, though an enthusiast!’ However, the Vice-Chancellor<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Walter Hodges,
                            Provost of Oriel.</p>
                    </note> sent for the sermon, and I hear that the
                    heads of college intend to shew their resentment.</quote>
                <p>Another eyewitness report of the same event was recorded by William Blackstone,
                    already a Fellow of All Souls and on his way to the fame he would earn as author
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Laws of England</hi> (1765-69). In
                    a letter to a family friend (Aug. 28) the young Blackstone reports on Wesley’s
                    sermon, which seems to have become the talk of the town:</p>
                <quote>We were last Friday [Aug. 24] entertained at St. Mary’s by a curious sermon
                    from Wesley the Methodist. Among other equally modest particulars, he informed
                    us, 1st, that there was not one Christian among all the Heads of Houses; 2ndly,
                    that pride, gluttony, avarice, luxury, sensuality and drunkenness were general
                    characteristics of all Fellows of Colleges, who were useless to a proverbial
                    uselessness. Lastly, that the younger part of the University were a generation
                    of triflers, all of them perjured and none of them of any religion at all. His
                    notes were demanded by the Vice-Chancellor, but on mature deliberation it has
                    been thought proper to punish him by a mortifying neglect….<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the facsimile of the
                            letter in John Fletcher Hurst, <hi rend="italic">The History of
                                Methodism</hi>, II.604-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That ‘mortifying neglect’ began at once. Charles Wesley records that ‘we [John
                    Wesley, Charles Wesley, Messrs. Piers and Meriton] walked back in form, the
                    little band of us four; for of the rest durst none join himself to us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. CWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Methodists, then and later, could see no proper warrant for anyone to have taken
                    offence at such a sermon; after all, Wesley had simply preached the gospel and
                    applied it ‘close and home’. Thomas Jackson’s later comment on it is
                    typical:</p>
                <quote>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> contains a beautiful and
                    forcible description of spiritual religion, with the manner by which it is
                    acquired by individuals and then spreads from one to another until it shall
                    cover the earth. The concluding application to the heads of colleges and halls,
                    to the fellows and tutors and to the body of undergraduates, assumes their
                    general and wide departure from the true Christian character, and [their]
                    abandonment to formality, worldliness, levity, and sloth. It contains nothing
                    sarcastic and irritating, nothing that was designed to give unnecessary pain or
                    offence; but is marked throughout by seriousness, fidelity, and tender
                        affection.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Rev. Charles Wesley</hi> (1841),
                            I.403.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <pb n="115"/>John Wesley himself was much more of a realist and also more aware
                    of his own intention:</p>
                <quote>I preached, I suppose the last time, at <placeName>St. Mary’s</placeName>. Be
                    it so. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully delivered my own
                    soul.</quote>
                <quote>The Beadle came to me afterwards and told me the Vice-Chancellor had sent him
                    for my notes. I sent them without delay, not without admiring the wise
                    providence of God. Perhaps few men of note would have given a sermon of mine the
                    reading if I had put it into their hands; but by this means it came to be read,
                    probably more than once, by every man of eminence in the University.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">JWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That he never regretted the affair or its consequences would appear from a
                    complacent recollection of it in 1781 in ‘A Short History of the People called
                    Methodists’:</p>
                <quote>Friday, August 24, St. Bartholomew’s Day, I preached for the last time before
                    the University of Oxford. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully
                    delivered my own soul. And I am well pleased that it should be the very day on
                    which, in the last century,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, the Great Ejectment in
                            1662.</p>
                    </note> near two thousand burning and shining lights were put
                    out at one stroke. Yet what a wide difference is there between their case and
                    mine! They were turned out of house and home, and all that they had; whereas I
                    am only hindered from preaching, without any other loss; and that in a kind of
                    honourable manner; it being determined that when my next turn to preach came
                    they would pay another person to preach for me. And so they did twice or thrice,
                    even to the time that I resigned my fellowship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">§30. See Vol. 9 of this edn. and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 420.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>What would have been most obvious to his Methodist readers was the heroic stature
                    of their leader who had preached ‘plain truth’ to academic people to their face
                    and at the cost of rejection by them. What clearer proof could there be of his
                    fidelity to the gospel under all circumstances and of his total commitment in
                    his ministry among them? It was no small matter for a tenured don to have
                    forsaken his privileged status in a class-conscious English society in exchange
                    for ‘The Foundery’, ‘The New Room’, and a career among the masses. They knew,
                    all too well, how rudely the Methodists had been treated, to the point of savage
                    persecution, condoned by magistrates and clergy alike in the years between 1739
                    and 1746; they could still foresee dangerous days ahead. <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> as published was an evangelical proclamation;
                    it was also an act of defiance.</p>
                <p>These ‘prefixed’ sermons, therefore, serve a particular junction in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> as a bloc: they proclaim the Wesleyan message in
                    prophetic terms, and they signify Wesley’s transference of his allegiance from
                    the <pb n="116"/>Academy to his new vocation as a preacher of ‘plain truth for
                    plain people’. Together they dispel any impression of inconsistency. His message
                    in St. Mary’s had been the same as it was now in Moorfields. Thus, these sermons
                    could serve as a multifaceted introductory quartet to the larger endeavour of
                        <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi>.</p>
                <p>The edited text of <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi> is based upon the
                    first edition of 1738. For a stemma illustrating its publishing history through
                    its thirty-one editions in Wesley’s lifetime, together with substantive variant
                    readings, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                    10.</p>
                <p>The text for <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi> is based upon its first
                    edition, 1741. For a stemma and table of variant readings through the
                    twenty-eight extant editions during Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix.
                    See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 50.</p>
                <p>The first edition of <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> followed
                    here, was published shortly after the sermon itself was preached in 1742. For a
                    stemma and variant readings from the fifty-two extant editions in Charles
                    Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 59.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> was also published shortly after
                    its delivery in 1744 and ran through at least fifteen editions in Wesley’s
                    lifetime. For a stemma of these editions and a list of variant readings, see
                    Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 92.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="131"/>
            <head>The Almost Christian</head>
            <head type="subhead">Sermon preached at St. Mary’s, Oxford,<lb/>before the
                University,<lb/>on July 25, 1741<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The half-title in the first edition of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, Vol. I (1746), and a footnote in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> I.15, record the date as June 18, 1738—an
                        obvious misremembrance, since Wesley was in Germany then; cf.
                    JWJ.</p>
                </note>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Acts 26:28</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <!--Consider renaming this attribute value; look at Guidelines
                for ideas.-->
                <p>And many there are who go thus far: ever since the Christian religion was in the
                    world there have been many in every age and nation who were ‘almost persuaded to
                    be Christians’. But seeing it avails nothing before God to go <hi rend="italic">only thus far</hi>, it highly imports us to consider,</p>
                <p>First, what is implied in being <hi rend="italic">almost</hi>,</p>
                <p>Secondly, what in being <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi> a Christian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See ‘Intro. Com.’,
                            p. 111 above; half-title from <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I (1746). The
                            distinction between ‘almost’ and ‘altogether’ Christians was by now a
                            commonplace. Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Sermons of Mr. Henry Smith,
                                Gathered into One Volume</hi> (1657), pp.420-23; William Sheppard,
                                <hi rend="italic">Sincerity and Hypocrisy; or, the Sincere Christian
                                and Hypocrite in their Lively Colours, Standing One by the
                                Other</hi> (1658); William Allen, ‘Dedicatory Epistle’, <hi rend="italic">The Glass of Justification</hi>, p. 20, speaks of a
                            ‘negative Christian’; in 1661 Matthew Mead preached a series of seven
                            sermons at St. Sepulchre’s, Holborn, on <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian Discovered</hi>; John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Precepts and Practical Rules for a Truly Christian Life</hi>
                            (1678), p.2; John Norris has extended references to ‘those who serve God
                            by halves, … the almost Christians’, in <hi rend="italic">Christian
                                Prudence</hi> (1710), pp. 16-20, and in <hi rend="italic">Practical
                                Discourses</hi>, IV (1728), ‘Concerning Practical Atheism’, pp.
                            100-24; James Knight, <hi rend="italic">Eight Sermons</hi> (1721),
                            p.274, speaks of ‘lukewarm spirits’; and William Bates, Sermon X, in <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, p.383. Throughout the Wesley corpus one
                            finds references to ‘the almost Christian’, ‘half-Christians’, ‘the good
                            sort of men’, ‘saints of the world’ (cf. No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.5 and n.).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <div type="subsection" n="1">
                    <p n="1">I. (I). 1. Now in the being ‘almost a Christian’ is implied, first,
                        heathen honesty<hi rend="bold">.</hi>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Wesley here understands ‘honesty’, as his
                                audience would have, in its classical Latin sense of honour (as in
                                Plautus, Cicero, Quintilian) denoting that form of self-disciplined
                                conduct approved of by Aristotle in his <hi rend="italic">Nicomachean Ethics</hi> (I.5; III.8; IV.3), a shared source
                                which Wesley knew very well.</p>
                        </note> No one, I suppose, will make
                        any question of this, especially since by heathen honesty here I mean, not
                        that which is recommended in the writings of their philosophers only, <pb n="132"/>but such as the common heathens expected of one another, and
                        many of them actually practised. By the rules of this they were taught that
                        they ought not to be unjust; not to take away their neighbour’s goods,
                        either by robbery or theft; not to oppress the poor, neither to use
                        extortion toward any; not to cheat or overreach either the poor or rich in
                        whatsoever commerce they had with them; to defraud no man of his right, and
                        if it were possible to owe no man anything.</p>
                    <p n="2">2. Again, the common heathens allowed that some regard was to be paid
                        to truth as well as to justice. And accordingly they not only had him in
                        abomination who was forsworn, who called God to witness to a lie, but him
                        also who was known to be a slanderer of his neighbour, who falsely accused
                        any man. And indeed little better did they esteem wilful liars of any sort,
                        accounting them the disgrace of humankind, and the pests of society.</p>
                    <p n="3">3. Yet again, there was a sort of love and assistance which they
                        expected one from another. They expected whatever assistance anyone could
                        give another without prejudice to himself. And this they extended, not only
                        to those little offices of humanity which are performed without any expense
                        or labour, but likewise to the feeding the hungry if they had food to spare,
                        the clothing the naked with their own superfluous raiment, and in general
                        the giving to any that needed such things as they needed not themselves.
                        Thus far (in the lowest account of it) heathen honesty went, the first thing
                        implied in the being ‘almost a Christian’.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <div type="subsection" n="2">
                        <p n="4">(II). 4. A second thing implied in the being ‘almost a Christian’
                            is the having a form of godliness<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
                            <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                                <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:5.
                                    For references to Wesley’s distinction between the ‘form’ and
                                    the ‘power’ of godliness, see the <hi rend="italic">General
                                        Rules</hi> (in <hi rend="italic">The Nature, Design, and
                                        General Rules of the United Societies</hi>, 1743, <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 73, Vol. 9 of this edn.),
                                    §2; Nos. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>,
                                    III.11; and 150, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’, II.2; <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Original Sin</hi>, 1757, pp. 229-30; see
                                    also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Matt. 13:28.</p>
                            </note> of
                            that godliness which is prescribed in the gospel of Christ—the having
                            the <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> of a real Christian. Accordingly the
                            ‘almost Christian’ does nothing which the gospel forbids. He taketh not
                            the name of God in vain<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
                            <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See Exod.
                                20:7.</p>
                            </note> he blesseth and curseth not<hi rend="bold">,</hi>
                            <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:14.</p>
                            </note> he sweareth not
                            at all, but his communication is ‘Yea, yea,’ ‘nay, nay.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                                    5:34, 37.</p>
                            </note> He profanes not the day of the Lord, nor
                            suffers it to be profaned, even by the stranger that is within his
                                gates.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 20:10.</p>
                            </note> He not only avoids all actual
                            adultery, <pb n="133"/>fornication, and uncleanness, but every word or
                            look that either directly or indirectly tends thereto: nay, and all idle
                            words, abstaining both from all detraction, backbiting, talebearing,
                            evil-speaking, and from ‘all foolish talking and jesting’ (εὐτραπελία),
                            a kind of virtue in the heathen moralist’s account.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s translation of
                                    εὐτραπελία follows the AV of Eph. 5:4, where εὐτραπελία is
                                    disparaged. For the ‘heathen moralist’, however, cf. Aristotle,
                                        <hi rend="italic">Nicomachean Ethics</hi>, II.7 (1108<hi rend="italic">a</hi>), who had indeed reckoned it as a
                                    virtue: ‘In the matter of “pleasantness” (παιδία) the mean is
                                    “wit” and the middle way is “wittiness” (εὐτραπελία); excess
                                    here is buffoonery…and its deficiency is boorishness.’ Wesley
                                    could presume that his audience understood this discrepancy
                                    between the κοινή of the New Testament and the classical usage
                                    of ‘the heathen moralist’. Cf. Irène Simon, <hi rend="italic">Three Restoration Divines</hi>, I. 316.</p>
                            </note> Briefly,
                            from all conversation that is not ‘good to the use of edifying’, and
                            that consequently ‘grieves the Holy Spirit of God, whereby we are sealed
                            to the day of redemption’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:29-30.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="5">5. He abstains from ‘wine wherein is excess’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:18.</p>
                            </note>
                            from revellings and gluttony. He avoids, as much as in him lies, all
                            strife and contention, continually endeavouring to live peaceably with
                            all men.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:18.</p>
                            </note> And if he suffer
                            wrong, he avengeth not himself, neither returns evil for evil. He is no
                            railer, no brawler, no scoffer, either at the faults or infirmities of
                            his neighbour. He does not willingly wrong, hurt, or grieve any man; but
                            in all things acts and speaks by that plain rule, ‘Whatsoever thou
                            wouldst not he should do unto thee, that do not thou to another.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                                <p rend="footnote text">This
                                    particular form of the Golden Rule is ascribed in the Talmud
                                        (<hi rend="italic">Sabb</hi>. xxxi.1) to Hillel: ‘What is
                                    hateful to you, do not to your neighbour; that is the whole
                                    Torah, while the rest is the commentary thereof; go and learn
                                    it.’ See also Tobit 4:15: ‘And what thou hatest, do to no man.’
                                    Cf. Nos. 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount, X’, §§22, 24; and 150,
                                    ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’, I.10. It is not clear how Wesley had come
                                    by this form of the ‘Rule’.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="6">6. And in doing good he does not confine himself to cheap and easy
                            offices of kindness, but labours and suffers for the profit of many,
                            that by all means he may help some. In spite of toil or pain,
                            ‘whatsoever his hand findeth to do, he doth it with his might,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                                    Eccles. 9:10.</p>
                            </note> whether it be for his friends or for
                            his enemies, for the evil or for the good. For, being ‘not slothful in’
                            this or in any ‘business’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:11.</p>
                            </note> ‘as he hath
                            opportunity he doth good’, all manner of good, ‘to all men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                                    6:10. Note the similarity here with the second of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi>.</p>
                            </note> and to their
                            souls as well as their bodies. He reproves the wicked, instructs the
                            ignorant, confirms the wavering, quickens the good, and comforts the
                            afflicted. He labours to awaken those that sleep,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Steepest’</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                            to lead those whom God hath already awakened to <pb n="134"/>the
                            fountain opened for sin and for uncleanness, that they may wash therein
                            and be clean; and to stir up those who are saved through faith to adorn
                            the gospel of Christ in all things.</p>
                        <p n="7">7. He that hath the form of godliness uses also the means of grace;
                            yea, all of them, and at all opportunities. He constantly frequents the
                            house of God; and that not as the manner of some is, who come into the
                            presence of the Most High either loaded with gold and costly apparel, or
                            in all the gaudy vanity of dress, and either by their unseasonable
                            civilities to each other or the impertinent gaiety of their behaviour
                            disclaim all pretensions to the form as well as to the power of
                            godliness. Would to God there were none, even among ourselves, who fall
                            under the same condemnation: who come into his house, it may be, gazing
                            about, or with all the signs of the most listless, careless
                            indifference, though sometimes they may <hi rend="italic">seem</hi> to
                            use a prayer to God for his blessing on what they are entering upon; who
                            during that awful service are either asleep or reclined in the most
                            convenient posture for it; or, as though they supposed God was asleep,
                            talking with one another, or looking round, as utterly void of
                                employment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                                <p rend="footnote text">An echo of frequent criticisms in the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi> and other newspapers of
                                    indecorous behaviour in churches. E.g., in No. 460, Aug. 18,
                                    1712, Richard Steele comments on ‘the ceremonies, bows,
                                    curtsies, whisperings, smiles, winks, nods, with other familiar
                                    arts of salutation, which take up in our churches so much time
                                    that might be better employed’; he goes on to speak of gossips
                                    who could ‘give a particular account how two or three hundred
                                    people were dressed’ but no inkling of the sermon. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi>, No. 140, May 2,
                                1710.</p>
                            </note> Neither let these be accused of the form of
                            godliness. No: he who has even this behaves with seriousness and
                            attention in every part of that solemn service. More especially when he
                            approaches the table of the Lord it is not with a light or careless
                            behaviour, but with an air, gesture, and deportment which speaks nothing
                            else but ‘God be merciful to me, a sinner!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            18:13.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="8">8. To this if we add the constant use of family prayer by those who
                            are masters of families, and the setting times apart for private
                            addresses to God, with a daily seriousness of behaviour—he who uniformly
                            practises this outward religion has the form of godliness. There needs
                            but one thing more in order to his being ‘almost a Christian’, and that
                            is, sincerity.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="subsection" n="3">
                        <p n="9">(III).9. By sincerity I mean a real, inward principle of religion
                            from whence these outward actions flow.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                                <p rend="footnote text">‘Sincerity’ was a shibboleth in
                                    eighteenth-century religion, especially among the
                                    latitudinarians. C. F. Allison, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of
                                        Moralism</hi>, p. 144, believes that Edward Fowler
                                    (1632-1714), Bishop of Gloucester, was the first to make
                                    sincerity a prerequisite to justification, in his <hi rend="italic">The Design of Christianity</hi> (1671). Samuel
                                    Johnson, in the <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> (1755),
                                    defined sincerity as ‘honesty of intention’ and quotes John
                                    Rogers (1679-1729), <hi rend="italic">The Necessity of Divine
                                        Revelation and the Truth of the Christian Religion</hi>
                                    (1727): ‘Jesus Christ has purchased for us terms of
                                    reconciliation, who will accept of sincerity instead of
                                    perfection; but then this sincerity implies our honest
                                    endeavours to do our utmost.’ Lecky, <hi rend="italic">A History
                                        of England in the Eighteenth Century</hi>, I.312-13, cites
                                    Benjamin Hoadly (1676-1761) as affirming that ‘sincerity is the
                                    one necessary requirement for the Christian profession.’ See
                                    also William Bates, <hi rend="italic">Whole Works</hi> (1st
                                    edn., 1700; 1815), II.63; and William Reeves, <hi rend="italic">Fourteen Sermons Preached on Several Occasions</hi> (1729),
                                    p. 251.</p>
                                <p rend="footnote text">The early Wesley had
                                    commented on the prime importance of sincerity in a letter to
                                    his mother, July 29, 1725, and to Ann Granville, Oct. 3, 1731;
                                    the late Wesley makes almost the same point in a letter to
                                    Arthur Keene, Dec. 25, 1787. In between, see the references in
                                    the <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi> of 1746 (May 13), and in the
                                    following sermons: Nos. 6, ‘The Righteousness of Faith’, III.5;
                                    9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’, IV.1; 12, ‘The
                                    Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §11; 18, ‘The Marks of the New
                                    Birth’, II.2; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of
                                    God’, II.10; 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount, X’, §9; 137, ‘On
                                    Corrupting the Word of God’, proem.</p>
                            </note> And indeed if we
                            have <pb n="135"/>not this we have not heathen honesty; no, not so much
                            of it as will answer the demand of a heathen, Epicurean poet. Even this
                            poor wretch, in his sober intervals, is able to testify:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>
                                <hi rend="italic">Oderunt peccare boni virtutis amore;</hi>
                            </l>
                            <l>
                                <hi rend="italic">Oderunt peccare mali formidine poenae.</hi>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <hi rend="endnote_reference">
                            <note place="end">
                                <p>Good men avoid sin from the love of virtue; wicked men avoid sin
                                    from the fear of punishment. [Cf. Horace, <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I.xvi.52-53: <lg>
                                        <l>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Oderunt peccare boni virtutis
                                                amore;</hi>
                                        </l>
                                        <l>
                                            <hi rend="italic">Tu nihil admittes in te formidine
                                                poenae.</hi>
                                        </l>
                                    </lg>
                                </p>
                                <p rend="endnote text">Here Wesley has garbled the second line for
                                    the sake of the contrast between <hi rend="italic">oderunt
                                        peccare boni</hi> and <hi rend="italic">oderunt peccare
                                        mali</hi>. The notion that Horace was an Epicurean was an
                                    eighteenth-century commonplace, and found support in Horace’s
                                    jesting reference to himself as an Epicurean in <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I.iv.16. There are frequent
                                    quotations from Horace in Wesley’s sermons, usually prefaced by
                                    epithets as, e.g., ‘the poor heathen’ (Nos. 28, ‘Sermon on the
                                    Mount, VIII’, §18); ‘your brother heathen’ (56, ‘God’s
                                    Approbation of His Works’, II.1); ‘the old Roman’ (78,
                                    ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, I.4); ‘the old heathen poet’ (102, ‘Of
                                    Former Times’, §8); ‘the heathen poet’ (129, ‘Heavenly Treasure
                                    in Earthen Vessels’, II.1).]</p>
                            </note>
                        </hi>
                        <p>So that if a man only abstains from doing evil in order to avoid
                            punishment,</p>
                        <l>
                            <hi rend="italic">Non pasces in cruce corvos</hi>
                            <hi rend="endnote_reference">
                                <note place="end">
                                    <p rend="endnote text">Thou shalt not be hanged [Horace, <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I.xvi.48].</p>
                                </note>
                            </hi>
                        </l>
                        <p>saith the pagan—there, ‘thou hast thy reward’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Horace, <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I.xvi.47: ‘<hi rend="italic">habes pretium, loris non ureris</hi>’ (‘You have your
                                    reward; you are not being flogged’). Cf. Matt. 6:2, 5,
                                16.</p>
                            </note> But even he will not allow such a harmless man as
                            this to be so much as a <hi rend="italic">good</hi>
                            <pb n="136"/>
                            <hi rend="italic">heathen</hi>. If then any man from the
                            same motive (viz. to avoid punishment, to avoid the loss of his friends,
                            or his gain, or his reputation) should not only abstain from doing evil
                            but also do ever so much good—yea, and use all the means of grace—yet we
                            could not with any propriety say, this man is even ‘almost a Christian’.
                            If he has no better principle in his heart he is only a hypocrite
                            altogether.</p>
                        <p n="10">10. Sincerity therefore is necessarily implied in the being
                            ‘almost a Christian’: a real design to serve God, a hearty desire to do
                            his will. It is necessarily implied that a man have a sincere view of
                            pleasing God in all things: in all his conversation, in all his actions;
                            in all he does or leaves undone. This design, if any man be ‘almost a
                            Christian’, runs through the whole tenor of his life. This is the moving
                            principle both in his doing good, his abstaining from evil, and his
                            using the ordinances of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Note that, on this basis, a person obeying
                                    Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi> would be no better
                                    than an ‘almost Christian’.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="11">11. But here it will probably be inquired, Is it possible that any
                            man living should go so far as this and nevertheless be <hi rend="italic">only</hi> ‘almost a Christian’? What more than this
                            can be implied in the being ‘a Christian altogether’? I answer, first,
                            that it is possible to go thus 20 far, and yet be but ‘almost a
                            Christian’, I learn not only from the oracles of God, but also from the
                            sure testimony of experience.</p>
                        <p n="12">12. Brethren, ‘great is my boldness toward you in this
                                behalf.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:4.</p>
                            </note> And ‘forgive me
                            this wrong’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                                <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 12:13.</p>
                            </note> if I declare my
                            own folly upon the housetop, for yours and the gospel’s sake. Suffer me
                            then to speak freely of myself, even as of another man. I am content to
                            be abased so ye may be exalted,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 11:7.</p>
                            </note> and to be
                            yet more vile for the glory of my Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                                <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Sam. 6:21-22. See also JWJ,
                                    Apr. 2, 1739: ‘I submitted to be more vile, and proclaimed in
                                    the highways the glad tidings of salvation….’</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                        <p n="13">13. I did go thus far for many years, as many of this place can
                            testify: using diligence to eschew all evil, and to have a conscience
                            void of offence;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Acts 24:16.</p>
                            </note> redeeming the
                                time,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Col. 4:5.</p>
                            </note> buying up every
                            opportunity of doing all good to all men;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:10.</p>
                            </note>
                            constantly and carefully using all the public and all the private means
                            of grace; endeavouring after a steady seriousness of behaviour at all
                            times and in all places. And God is my record, before whom I stand,
                            doing all this in sincerity; having a real design to serve God, a hearty
                            desire to do his will in all things, to please him who had <pb n="137"/>called me to ‘fight the good fight’, and to ‘lay hold of eternal
                                life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                                <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:12.</p>
                            </note> Yet my own
                            conscience beareth me witness in the Holy Ghost that all this time I was
                            but ‘almost a Christian’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 81, ‘In What Sense we are to Leave
                                    the World‘, §23, where Wesley (in 1784) recalls that it had
                                    ‘pleased God’ to convert him from an ‘almost’ to an ‘altogether
                                    Christian’ in 1725. But see also JWJ, Jan. 4, 1739, and his
                                    letter to brother Charles, June 27, 1766, and cf. Benham, pp.
                                    34-40. Note also that all editions of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Plain Account of Christian Perfection</hi> refer to 1725 as
                                    the beginning of his conscious quest for perfection. The fact is
                                    that Wesley wavered from time to time about what it means to
                                    confess oneself ‘a Christian’.</p>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="2">
                    <p>II. If it be inquired, ‘What more than this is implied in the being
                        “altogether a Christian”?’ I answer:</p>
                    <p n="1">(I). 1. First, the love of God. For thus saith his Word: ‘Thou shalt
                        love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with
                        all thy mind, and with all thy strength.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Mark 12:30.</p>
                        </note> Such a love of God
                        is this as engrosses the whole heart, as takes up all the affections, as
                        fills the entire capacity of the soul, and employs the utmost extent of all
                        its faculties. He that thus loves the Lord his God, his spirit continually
                        ‘rejoiceth in God his Saviour’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:47.</p>
                        </note> ‘His delight is in
                        the Lord,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 1:2.</p>
                        </note>
                        <hi rend="italic">his</hi> Lord and his all, to whom ‘in everything he
                        giveth thanks’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 5:18.</p>
                        </note> All <hi rend="italic">his</hi> ‘desire is unto God, and to the remembrance of
                        his name’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 26:8.</p>
                        </note> His heart is ever crying out, ‘Whom have
                        I in heaven but thee? and there is none upon earth that I desire beside
                            thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 73:25.</p>
                        </note> Indeed, what can he desire beside God? Not
                        the world, or the things of the world. For he is ‘crucified to the world,
                        and the world crucified to him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:14.</p>
                        </note> He is crucified to
                        the desire of the flesh, the desire of the eye, and the pride of life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                            <p rend="footnote text">I.e., to all
                                    <hi rend="italic">sin</hi> (see 1 John 2:16), since Wesley had
                                long since agreed with Augustine that <hi rend="italic">autem tria
                                    genera vitiorium…OMNIA peccata concludunt</hi> (‘indeed, <hi rend="italic">all</hi> sins may be included within these three
                                classes of vice’); cf. <hi rend="italic">Enarratio in Psalmum</hi>,
                                VIII.13, in Migne, <hi rend="italic">PL</hi>, Vol. 36, col. 115. He
                                would reiterate this tirelessly; see No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                                Kingdom’, II.2 and n.</p>
                        </note> Yea, he is dead to pride of every
                        kind: for love ‘is not puffed up’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                            <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:4.</p>
                        </note> but he that
                        dwelling in love ‘dwelleth in God, and God in him’, is less than nothing in
                        his own eyes.</p>
                    <p n="2">(II). 2. The second thing implied in the being ‘altogether a Christian’
                        is the love of our neighbour. For thus said our Lord in the following words:
                        ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 22:39, etc.</p>
                        </note> If any man
                        ask, ‘Who is my neighbour?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Luke 10:29.</p>
                        </note> we reply, ‘Every man in
                            <pb n="138"/>the world; every child of his who is “the Father of the
                        spirits of all flesh”.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:9; also No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                                Kingdom’, I.8 and n.</p>
                        </note> Nor may we in any wise except our
                        enemies, or the enemies of God and their own souls. But every Christian
                        loveth these also as himself; yea, ‘as Christ loved us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 5:2.</p>
                        </note>
                        He that would more fully understand what manner of love this is may consider
                        St. Paul’s description of it. It is ‘long-suffering and kind. It envieth
                        not. It is not rash or hasty in judging. It is not puffed up,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                                13:4.</p>
                        </note> but maketh him that loves, the least, the servant
                        of all. Love ‘doth not behave itself unseemly’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            13:5.</p>
                        </note> but ‘becometh all things to all men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            9:22.</p>
                        </note> She ‘seeketh not her own’, but only the good of others,
                        that they may be saved. Love ‘is not provoked’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            13:5.</p>
                        </note> It casteth out wrath, which he who hath is wanting in
                        love. It ‘thinketh no evil’. It ‘rejoiceth not in iniquity, but rejoiceth in
                        the truth’. It ‘covereth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all
                        things, endureth all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:5-7.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="subsection" n="3">
                    <p n="3">(III). 3. There is yet one thing more that may be separately
                        considered, though it cannot actually be separate from the preceding, which
                        is implied in the being ‘altogether a Christian’, and that is the ground of
                        all, even faith. Very excellent things are spoken of this throughout the
                        oracles of God. ‘Everyone’, saith the beloved disciple, ‘that believeth, is
                        born of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:1.</p>
                        </note> ‘To as many as
                        received him gave he power to become the sons of God, even to them that
                        believe on his name.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 1:12.</p>
                        </note> And, ‘This is the
                        victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                            <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:4.</p>
                        </note>
                        Yea, our Lord himself declares, ‘He that believeth in the Son hath
                        everlasting life;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John 3:36.</p>
                        </note> and ‘cometh not into
                        condemnation, but is passed from death unto life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John 5:24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p n="4">4. But here let no man deceive his own soul. It is diligently to be
                        noted, the ‘faith which bringeth not forth repentance’ and love, and all
                        good works, is not that ‘right living faith’ which is here spoken of, ‘but a
                        dead and devilish one…. For even the devils believe that Christ was born of
                        a virgin, that he wrought all kind of miracles, declaring himself very God;
                        that for our sakes he suffered a most painful death, to redeem us from death
                        everlasting; that he rose again the third day; that he ascended into <pb n="139"/>heaven and sitteth at the right hand of the Father, and at the
                        end of the world shall come again to judge both the quick and the dead.
                        These articles of our faith the devils believe, and so they believe all that
                        is written in the Old and New Testament. And yet for all this faith, they be
                        but devils. They remain still in their 5 damnable estate, lacking the very
                        true Christian faith.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                            <note place="end">
                                <p rend="endnote text">Homily on the Salvation of Man [Pt. III, in
                                    a slight revision of Wesley’s own earlier extract therefrom in
                                        <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Salvation, Faith, and Good
                                        Works</hi>, §13, for which see Vol. 12 of this
                                edn.]</p>
                            </note>
                        </hi>
                    </p>
                    <p n="5">5. ‘The right and true Christian faith is’ (to go on in the words of
                        our own Church) ‘not only to believe that Holy Scripture and the articles of
                        our faith are true, but also to have a sure trust and confidence to be saved
                        from everlasting damnation by Christ’—it is a ‘sure trust and confidence’
                        which a man hath in God ‘that by the merits of Christ his sins <hi rend="italic">are</hi> forgiven, and he reconciled to the favour of
                        God’—‘whereof doth follow a loving heart to obey his commandments.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley,
                                    T<hi rend="italic">he Doctrine of Salvation, Faith, and Good
                                    Works</hi>, §14; cf. also the Homily on the Salvation of Man,
                                Pt. III.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p n="6">6. Now whosoever has this faith which ‘purifies the heart’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                                15:9; Jas. 4:8.</p>
                        </note> by the power of God who dwelleth therein,
                        from pride, anger, desire, ‘from all unrighteousness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                            <p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:9.</p>
                        </note>
                        ‘from all filthiness of flesh and spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                        </note> which fills it
                        with love stronger than death both to God and to all mankind—love that doth
                        the works of God, glorying to spend and to be spent for all men, and that
                        endureth with joy, not only the reproach of Christ, the being mocked,
                        despised, and hated of all men, but whatsoever the wisdom of God permits the
                        malice of men or devils to inflict; whosoever has this faith, thus ‘working
                        by love’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:6, Wesley’s favourite text for his teachings on faith
                                and good works (<hi rend="italic">fides caritatem formata</hi>), the
                                linch-pin by which he joined his double doctrine of ‘faith alone’
                                and ‘holy living’. Cf. Nos. 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’,
                                III.3; 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I‘, I.8; 19, ‘The Great
                                Privilege of those that are Born of God’, III.1; 25, ‘Sermon on the
                                Mount, V’, III.9; 35, ‘The Law Established through Faith, I’, II.3;
                                39, ‘Catholic Spirit’, I.14; 47, ‘Heaviness through Manifold
                                Temptations’, II.3, IV.5; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, III.6;
                                65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.14; 66, ‘The Signs of
                                the Times’, II.8; 79, ‘On Dissipation’, §16; 90, ‘An Israelite
                                Indeed’, II.4, II.11; 91, ‘On Charity’, III.11; 106, ‘On Faith, Heb.
                                11:6’, II.3; 107, ‘On God‘s Vineyard’, II.8; 109, ‘<hi rend="italic">The Trouble and Rest of Good Men’</hi>, I.3; 114, <hi rend="italic">On the Death of John Fletcher</hi>, I.3; 146, ‘The
                                One Thing Needful‘, III.3. Wesley records having preached from this
                                text fifteen times: twice in 1741, once in 1742 and 1747, twice in
                                1750, once in 1755, four times in 1760, three times in 1761, and
                                once in 1787.</p>
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jeremy Taylor, ‘<hi rend="italic">Fides Formata</hi>; Or, Faith Working by Love’, in
                                    <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1844), II.19-28. For Luther’s
                                denunciation of the distinction between ‘formed’ and ‘unformed’
                                faith, see his <hi rend="italic">Commentary on Galatians</hi>, 3:11.
                                See also W. P. Stephens, <hi rend="italic">The Holy Spirit in the
                                    Theology of Martin Bucer</hi> (London, Cambridge University
                                Press, 1970), pp. 51-68, for an analysis of the issues between <hi rend="italic">iustitia simplex</hi>, <hi rend="italic">iustitia
                                    duplex</hi>, etc.</p>
                        </note> is not <hi rend="italic">almost</hi> only, but <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi> a
                        Christian.</p>
                    <p n="7">
                        <pb n="140"/>7. But who are the living witnesses of these things? I
                        beseech you, brethren, as in the presence of that God before whom ‘hell and
                        destruction are without a covering: how much more the hearts of the children
                        of men!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                                Prov. 15:11.</p>
                        </note>—that each of you would ask his own heart,
                        ‘Am I of that number? Do I so far practise justice, mercy, and truth, as
                        even the rules of heathen honesty require? If so, have I the very <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> of a Christian? The form of godliness? Do I
                        abstain from evil, from whatsoever is forbidden in the written Word of God?
                        Do I, whatever good my hand findeth to do, do it with my might?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Eccles.
                                9:10.</p>
                        </note> Do I seriously use all the ordinances of God at all
                        opportunities? And is all this done with a sincere design and desire to
                        please God in all things?’</p>
                    <p n="8">8. Are not many of you conscious that you never came thus far? That you
                        have not been even ‘almost a Christian’? That you have not come up to the
                        standard of heathen honesty? At least, not to the form of Christian
                        godliness? Much less hath God seen sincerity in you, a real design of
                        pleasing him in all things. You never so much as intended to devote all your
                        words and works, your business, studies, diversions to his glory. You never
                        even designed or desired that whatsoever you did should be done ‘in the name
                        of the Lord Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:17.</p>
                        </note> and as such should be a
                        ‘spiritual sacrifice, acceptable to God through Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                        2:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p n="9">9. But supposing you had, do good designs and good desires make a
                        Christian? By no means, unless they are brought to good effect. ‘Hell is
                        paved’, saith one, ‘with good intentions.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                            <p rend="footnote text">This proverb was, of course, a
                                commonplace in Wesley’s time; cf. Richard Whitlock, <hi rend="italic">Ζωοτορία</hi> (1654); George Herbert, <hi rend="italic">Jacula Prudentum</hi> (1651); and John Ray, <hi rend="italic">English Proverbs</hi> (1670); it has a blurred
                                history. St. Francis de Sales attributes it to St. Bernard of
                                Clairvaux, in a letter to the Barrone de Chantal (Nov. 21, 1604) and
                                in another letter to the Mother Superior of the Visitations in Lyons
                                (Apr. 17, 1616); cf. Elisabeth Stopp, tr., <hi rend="italic">St.
                                    Francis de Sales; Selected Letters</hi> (London, Faber and
                                Faber, 1960), Letters 8, 92. The proverb itself has not yet been
                                located in St. Bernard’s published works. Cf. JWJ, July10, 1736. See
                                also No. 125, ‘On a Single Eye’, III.5, where Wesley cites St.
                                Chrysostom as saying that ‘Hell is paved with the skulls of
                                Christian priests.’</p>
                        </note> The great question of all, then,
                        still remains. Is the love of God shed abroad in your heart? Can you cry
                        out, ‘My God and my all’? Do <pb n="141"/>you desire nothing but him? Are
                        you happy in God? Is he your glory, your delight, your crown of rejoicing?
                        And is this commandment written in your heart, ‘that he who loveth God love
                        his brother also’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                            <p rend="footnote text">1 John 4:21.</p>
                        </note> Do you then love your
                        neighbour as yourself? Do you love every man, even your enemies, even the
                        enemies of God, as your own soul? As Christ loved you? Yea, dost thou
                        believe that Christ loved <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, and gave himself for
                        thee? Hast thou faith in his blood? Believest thou the Lamb of God hath
                        taken away <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> sins,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                            <p rend="footnote text">See John 1:29.</p>
                        </note> and cast them
                        as a stone into the depth of the sea? That he hath blotted out the
                        handwriting that was against <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, taking it out of
                        the way, nailing it to his cross? Hast <hi rend="italic">thou</hi> indeed
                        redemption through his blood, even the remission of <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> sins?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                            <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:7; Col. 1:14.</p>
                        </note> And doth
                        his Spirit bear witness with <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> spirit, that thou
                        art a child of God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                            <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p n="10">10. The God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who now standeth in
                        the midst of us, knoweth that if any man die without this faith and this
                        love, good it were for him that he had never been born.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 14:21.</p>
                        </note>
                        Awake, then, thou that sleepest, and call upon thy God: call in the day when
                        he may be found. Let him not rest till he ‘make his goodness to pass before
                        thee, till he proclaim unto thee the name of the Lord’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod.
                            33:19.</p>
                        </note>—‘the Lord, the Lord God, merciful and gracious,
                        long-suffering, and abundant in goodness and truth; keeping mercy for
                        thousands, forgiving iniquity, and transgression, and sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Exod.
                                34:6-7.</p>
                        </note> Let no man persuade thee by vain words to rest
                        short of this prize of thy high calling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:14.</p>
                        </note> But cry unto him
                        day and night who ‘while we were without strength died for the
                            ungodly’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:6.</p>
                        </note> until thou knowest in whom
                        thou hast believed, and canst say, ‘My Lord and my God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John 20:28.</p>
                        </note>
                        Remember ‘always to pray and not to faint’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:1.</p>
                        </note> till thou also
                        canst lift up thy hand unto heaven and declare to him that liveth for ever
                        and ever, ‘Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that I love
                            thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John 21:17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p n="11">11. May we all thus experience what it is to be not almost only, but
                        altogether Christians! Being justified freely by his grace, through the
                        redemption that is in Jesus, knowing we have peace with God through Jesus
                        Christ, rejoicing in hope of the glory of God, and having the love of God
                        shed abroad in our hearts by the Holy Ghost given unto us!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                            <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 5:1, 2,
                            5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>