<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 71: Of Good Angels</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon071</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 71: Of Good Angels</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume III: Sermons III,
                                71-114</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1986-11-01">1986-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="3"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="4"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="15"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p n="">Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="03:003"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 71-72]</hi>
                </head>
                <p n="">These twin essays in angelology were written as a single exercise in January
                    1783, and then published in four successive instalments with texts but no titles
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Arminian Magazine</hi>, 1783 (Vol. VI, January through
                    April), under the rubric, ‘Original Sermons by the Rev. John Wesley, M. A.,
                    Sermons XIII and XIV’. The paired sermons, with their present titles, were then
                    published in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, VI.103-45, and not published again in
                    Wesley’s lifetime.</p>
                <p n="">He must have thought that he needed to say something about the place and role of
                    angels in ‘the great chain of being’ which, along with the Christian Platonists,
                    he conceived of as the general structure of creation (see No. 56, ‘God’s
                    Approbation of His Works’, I.14 and n.). This would also help explain his
                    placement of these sermons here, after his delineations of the limits of
                    knowledge and reason. But angelology was not one of his prime interests; this is
                    suggested by the fact that he had preached from Heb. 1:14 only three times
                    before (in 1752, 1758, and 1782) and from Eph. 6:12 only once (in 1759); his
                    other references to angels are few and scattered in his writings as a whole.</p>
                <p n="">Wesley’s ideas here, with a single puzzling exception (see No. 72, ‘Of Evil
                    Angels’, I.3), are unsurprisingly conventional. One finds much the same
                    viewpoints in Anglican theology in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries,
                    usually in connection with a doctrine of Providence or other comments on ‘the
                    ways of God to men’. However, there are two identifiable sources closer than
                    others to Wesley’s basic arguments here; only their practical applications are
                    clearly different. One of these is Bishop George Bull, <hi rend="italic">Some
                        Important Points of Primitive Christianity</hi>, especially Sermons 11 and
                    12. Note that Wesley has reversed Bull’s order. This would follow his other main
                    source, Thomas Crane’s second chapter, ‘Of Good and Bad Angels’, in <hi rend="italic">Isagoge ad Dei Providentiam</hi>. And, of course, the great
                    cosmic vision of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> stands in Wesley’s further
                    background here. It is interesting that Wesley could not have known Milton’s
                    chapter IX, ‘Of the Special Government of Angels’, in his posthumous <hi rend="italic">De Doctrina Christiana</hi>, since that was not published
                    until 1825. But there is nothing in this part <pb n="03:004"/>of Milton’s
                    ‘doctrine’ from which Wesley would have dissented. And, on a crucial point, that
                    it was a majority of the angels who fell and enlisted under Satan’s banner,
                    Milton’s scenario in <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> is clearly decisive
                    here.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Of Good Angels</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p n="">Hebrews 1:14</p>
            </epigraph>
            <p n="">
                <hi rend="italic">Are they not all ministering spirits, sent forth to minister unto
                    them that shall be heirs of salvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Many of the ancient heathens had (probably from tradition) some notion
                    of good and evil angels. They had some conception of a superior order of beings
                    between men and God, whom the Greeks generally termed demons (‘knowing
                        ones’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            doubtful definition; cf. δαίμων in Liddell and Scott, and Arndt and
                            Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicons</hi>.</p>
                    </note> and
                    the Romans, <hi rend="italic">genii</hi>. Some of these they supposed to be kind
                    and benevolent, delighting in doing good; others to be malicious and cruel,
                    delighting in doing evil. But their conceptions both of one and the other were
                    crude, imperfect, and confused, being only fragments of truth, partly delivered
                    down by their forefathers, and partly borrowed from the inspired writings.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Of the former, the benevolent kind, seems to have been the celebrated
                    demon of Socrates, concerning which so many and so various conjectures have been
                    made in succeeding ages. ‘This gives me notice’, said he, ‘every morning, of any
                    evil which will befall me that day.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of Plato’s <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>,
                            31, 40.</p>
                    </note> A late writer, indeed (I suppose one that hardly
                    believes the existence of either angel or spirit), has published a dissertation
                    wherein he labours to prove that the <pb n="03:005"/>demon of Socrates was only
                    his reason.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John Gilbert Cooper, <hi rend="italic">The Life of Socrates</hi> (1750);
                            his discussion of Socrates’s ‘familiar’ is in III.81-96, but to a quite
                            different point than Wesley’s. Cooper is concerned to deny that Socrates
                            had, or claimed to have, supernatural powers (p. 89). Instead, his
                            ‘familiar’ was ‘nothing more than that inward feeling inseparable from
                            the hearts of all good and wise men which…gives [them] an almost
                            prophetic sensation of what ought to be done, before the slower
                            faculties of the mind can prove the moral rectitude of conduct’. Thus,
                            it was much more a certain ‘prescience’ than <hi rend="italic">reason</hi> in Wesley’s sense, and Cooper goes on to speak of it
                            thus. For other comments on Socrates’s ‘demon’, see Adam Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 144 n.: ‘a tingling in the ears’; A.
                            E. Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Socrates</hi> (New York, Doubleday Anchor
                            Books, 1953), p. 44 n.: ‘supernatural sign’; Xenophon, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, trans. by Sarah
                            Fielding), pp 511-12: ‘an uncommon strength of judgment’. For other
                            references to Socrates in the <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, cf. No.
                            70, ‘The Case of Reason Impartially Considered’, II.6 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    But it was not the manner of Socrates to speak in such obscure and ambiguous
                    terms. If he had meant his reason he would doubtless have said so. But this
                    could not be his meaning. For it was impossible his reason should give him
                    notice every morning of every evil which would befall him that day. It does not
                    lie within the province of reason to give such notice of future contingencies.
                    Neither does this odd interpretation in any wise agree with the inference which
                    he himself draws from it. ‘My demon’, says he, ‘did not give me notice this
                    morning of any evil that was to befall me today. Therefore I cannot regard as
                    any evil my being condemned to die.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Plato, <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>,
                        40.</p>
                    </note> Undoubtedly it was some spiritual being, probably one of
                    these ministering spirits.</p>
                <p n="3">3. An ancient poet, one who lived several ages before Socrates, speaks more
                    determinately on this subject. Hesiod does not scruple to say:</p>
                <l>Millions of spiritual creatures walk the earth Unseen.</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Actually, this is Milton’s paraphrase of Hesiod; cf. No.
                        70, ‘The Case of Reason Impartially Considered’, II.1 and n.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">Hence, it is probable, arose the numerous tales about the exploits of their
                    demigods, <hi rend="italic">minorum gentium</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf Hesiod, <hi rend="italic">Works and Days</hi>, ll. 155-73: ἡμίθεοί (i.e., demigods). In his
                                [<hi rend="italic">Tusculan</hi>] <hi rend="italic">Disputations,</hi> I.xiii.29, Cicero uses the phrase, <hi rend="italic">majorum gentium</hi>, to denote ‘the superior deities’
                                (<hi rend="italic">dii consentes</hi>). <hi rend="italic">Minorum
                                gentium</hi> would thus, by inference, denote ‘lesser deities’.
                            However, no such usage is recorded in Lewis and Short, <hi rend="italic">A Latin Dictionary</hi>. The oft-cited instance in Cicero’s <hi rend="italic">Epistolae ad Familiares</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Letters to Friends</hi>), IX.xxi.2, clearly does not
                        apply.</p>
                    </note> Hence their satyrs, fauns, nymphs of every kind, wherewith
                    they supposed both the sea and land to be filled. But how empty, childish,
                    unsatisfactory, are all <pb n="03:006"/>the accounts they give of them—as,
                    indeed, accounts that depend upon broken, uncertain tradition can hardly fail to
                    be!</p>
                <p n="4">4. Revelation only is able to supply this defect; this only gives us a
                    clear, rational, consistent account of those whom our eyes have not seen, nor
                    our ears heard:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 64:4; 1 Cor. 2:9.</p>
                    </note> of both good and evil angels. It
                    is my design to speak at present only of the former, of whom we have a full,
                    though brief, account in these words: ‘Are they not all ministering spirits,
                    sent forth to minister unto them that shall be heirs of salvation?’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. The question is, according to the manner of the Apostle, equivalent
                    to a strong affirmation. And hence we learn, first, that with regard to their
                    essence or nature they are all spirits: not material or corporeal beings; not
                    clogged with flesh and blood<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, III.5 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> like us, but having bodies, if any, not gross and earthly
                    like ours, but of a finer substance, resembling fire or flame more than any
                    other of these lower elements. And is not something like this intimated in those
                    words of the Psalmist, ‘Who maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers a flame
                    of fire!’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Ps. 104:4 [AV; Wesley uses ‘spirits’ here as does AV; BCP,
                                ‘winds’].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> As spirits he has endued them with
                    understanding, will, or affections (which are indeed the same thing, as the
                    affections are only the will exerting itself various ways), and liberty. And are
                    not these—understanding, will, and liberty—essential to, if not the essence of,
                    a spirit?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No.
                            60, ‘The General Deliverance’, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. But who of the children of men can comprehend what is the <hi rend="italic">understanding</hi> of an angel? Who can comprehend how far
                    their <hi rend="italic">sight</hi> extends? Analogous to sight in men, though
                    not the same—but thus we are constrained to speak through the poverty of human
                    language! Probably not only over one hemisphere of the earth, yea, or</p>
                <l>Tenfold the length of their terrene,</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, vi.78; see
                        No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §17 and n.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">or even of the solar system; but so far as to take in at one view the whole
                    extent of the creation. And we cannot conceive any defect in their perception,
                    neither any error in their understanding. But in what manner do they use their
                    understanding? We must in no <pb n="03:007"/>wise imagine that they creep from
                    one truth to another by that slow method which we call reasoning. Undoubtedly
                    they see at one glance whatever truth is presented to their understanding;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For Wesley’s
                            speculation that angelic knowledge is intuitive, cf. No. 10, ‘The
                            Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p>
                    </note> and that with all the
                    certainty and clearness that we mortals see the most self-evident axiom. Who
                    then can conceive the extent of their <hi rend="italic">knowledge</hi>? Not only
                    of the nature, attributes, and works of God (whether of creation or providence),
                    but of the circumstances, actions, words, tempers, yea, and thoughts of men? For
                    although God only ‘knows the hearts of all men’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 1:24.</p>
                    </note> unto
                    whom ‘known are all his works’, together with the changes they undergo, ‘from
                    the beginning of the world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 15:18.</p>
                    </note> yet we cannot doubt but his
                    angels know the hearts of those to whom they more immediately minister. Much
                    less can we doubt of their knowing the thoughts that are in our hearts at any
                    particular time. What should hinder their seeing them as they arise? Not the
                    thin veil of flesh and blood! Can these intercept the view of a spirit? Nay,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Walls within walls no more its passage bar,</l>
                    <l>Than unopposing space of liquid air.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Mark Le Pla, <hi rend="italic">A Paraphrase on the Song
                            of the Three Children</hi> (1724), st. 25, ll. 7-8, ‘O ye Lightnings’;
                        cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>
                        (1744), II.121.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">Far more easily, then, and far more perfectly than we can read a man’s thoughts
                    in his face, do these sagacious beings read our thoughts, just as they rise in
                    our hearts, inasmuch as they see their kindred spirit more clearly than we see
                    the body. If this seem strange to any who had not adverted to it before, let him
                    only consider. Suppose my spirit was out of the body, could not an angel see my
                    thoughts? Even without my uttering any words (if words are used in the world of
                    spirits)? And cannot that ministering spirit see them just as well now that I am
                    in the body? It seems therefore to be an unquestionable truth (although perhaps
                    not commonly observed) that angels know not only the words and actions, but also
                    the thoughts, of those to whom they minister. And indeed without this knowledge
                    they would be very ill qualified to perform various parts of their ministry.</p>
                <p n="3">3. And what an inconceivable degree of <hi rend="italic">wisdom</hi> must
                    they have acquired by the use of their amazing faculties, over and above that
                        <pb n="03:008"/>with which they were originally endued, in the course of
                    more than six thousand years. (That they have existed so long we are assured;
                    for they ‘sang together’ ‘when the foundations of the earth were laid’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 38:6, 7.
                            Wesley’s comment that the foundations of the world were laid more than
                            six thousand years before would mean that he was using Archbishop
                            Ussher’s date of 4004 B.C., a figure already commonplace because of its
                            use as a fixture as a marginal note in many edits. of the AV; cf. Robert
                            K. Merton, <hi rend="italic">On the Shoulders of Giants</hi> (New York,
                            A Harbinger Book, Harcourt, Brace and World, Inc., 1965), p. 80 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note>) How immensely must their wisdom have increased during so
                    long a period, not only by surveying the hearts and ways of men in their
                    successive generations, but by observing the works of God—his works of creation,
                    his works of providence, his works of grace! And above all by ‘continually
                    beholding the face of their Father which is in heaven’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 18:10 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>). The early Wesley makes the same point on
                            the wisdom of angels; see No. 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’,
                        II.2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. What measures of <hi rend="italic">holiness</hi>, as well as wisdom,
                    have they derived from this inexhaustible ocean!</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>A boundless, fathomless abyss,</l>
                    <l>Without a bottom or a shore!</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Probably Isaac Watts; cf. No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §18 and
                        n.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">Are they not hence, by way of eminence, styled ‘the holy angels’? What goodness,
                    what philanthropy, what love to man, have they drawn from those rivers that are
                    at his right hand! Such as we cannot conceive to be exceeded by any but that of
                    God our Saviour. And they are still drinking in more love from this ‘fountain of
                    living water’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer. 2:13; 17:13; cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on John 4:10,
                            14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Such is the knowledge and wisdom of the angels of God, as we learn from
                    his own oracles. Such are their holiness and goodness! And how astonishing is
                    their <hi rend="italic">strength</hi>! Even a fallen angel is styled by an
                    inspired writer, ‘the prince of the power of the air’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:2.</p>
                    </note> How
                    terrible a proof did he give of this power in suddenly raising the whirlwind
                    which ‘smote the four corners of the house’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 1:19.</p>
                    </note> and destroyed all the
                    children of Job at once! That this was his work we may easily learn from the
                    command to ‘save his life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 2:6.</p>
                    </note> But he gave a far more terrible
                    proof of his strength (if we suppose that ‘messenger of the Lord’ to have been
                    an evil angel, as is not at all improbable) when he smote with death a hundred,
                    fourscore and five thousand Assyrians in one night, nay, <pb n="03:009"/>
                    possibly in one hour, if not one moment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Kgs. 19:35; ‘the angel of the Lord’—i.e.,
                            lit., ‘the messenger of the Lord’.</p>
                    </note> Yet a strength abundantly
                    greater than this must have been exerted by that angel (whether he was an angel
                    of light or of darkness, which is not determined by the text) who ‘smote’ in one
                    hour ‘all the first-born of Egypt, both of man and beast’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 12:12.</p>
                    </note>
                    For considering the extent of the land of Egypt, the immense populousness
                    thereof, and the innumerable cattle fed in their houses and grazing in their
                    fruitful fields, the men and beasts who were slain in that night must have
                    amounted to several millions! And if this be supposed to have been an evil
                    angel, must not a good angel be as strong, yea, stronger than him? For surely
                    any good angel must have more power than even an ‘archangel ruined’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, i.593; and see No. 72, ‘Of Evil
                            Angels’, I.3, where a longer passage is quoted.</p>
                    </note> And what
                    power must the ‘four angels’ in the Revelation have, who were appointed to ‘keep
                    the four winds of heaven’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 7:1.</p>
                    </note> There seems therefore no
                    extravagance in supposing that, if God were pleased to permit, any of the angels
                    of light could heave the earth and all the planets out of their orbits; yea,
                    that he ‘could arm himself with all these elements’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A paraphrase from Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, vi.220-23.</p>
                    </note> and crush
                    the whole frame of nature. Indeed we do not know how to set any bounds to the
                    strength of these first-born children of God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. And although none but their great Creator is omnipresent; although none
                    beside him can ask, ‘Do not I fill heaven and earth?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 23:24.</p>
                    </note>; yet
                    undoubtedly he has given an immense sphere of action (though not unbounded) to
                    created spirits. ‘The prince of the kingdom of Persia’ (mentioned Daniel 10:13),
                    though probably an evil angel, seems to have had a sphere of action, both of
                    knowledge and power, as extensive as that vast empire. And the same, if not
                    greater, we may reasonably ascribe to the good angel whom he withstood for one
                    and twenty days.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Dan. 10:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. The angels of God have great power, in particular over the human body;
                    power either to cause or remove pain and diseases; either to kill or to heal.
                    They perfectly well understand whereof we are made; they know all the springs of
                    this curious machine;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s body-soul dualism, in the tradition of
                            Descartes, regarded the human body as a ‘curious machine’, as also in
                            No. 51, <hi rend="italic">The Good Steward</hi>, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    and can doubtless, by God’s permission, touch any of them so as <pb n="03:010"/>either to stop or restore its motion. Of this power, even in an evil angel, we
                    have a clear instance in the case of Job, whom he ‘smote with sore boils’ all
                    over, ‘from the crown’ of the head ‘to the sole of the foot’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 2:7.</p>
                    </note> And in
                    that instant undoubtedly he would have killed him if God had not ‘saved his
                        life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job
                            2:6.</p>
                    </note> And on the other hand, of the power of angels to heal we
                    have a remarkable instance in the case of Daniel. ‘There remained no strength in
                    me (said the prophet), neither was there breath in me. Then one came and touched
                    me, and said, Peace be unto thee: be strong, yea, be strong. And when he had
                    spoken unto me, I was strengthened.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Dan. 10:] ver. 17, etc [espec. ver.
                                18].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> On the other hand, when they are commissioned
                    from above, may they not put a period to human life? There is nothing improbable
                    in what Dr. Parnell supposes the angel to say to the hermit concerning the death
                    of the child:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>To all but thee in fits he seemed to go:</l>
                    <l>And ’twas my ministry to deal the blow.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Thomas Parnell, ‘The Hermit’, 230-31. Wesley had
                        included an extract of this in <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and
                            Sacred Poems</hi> (1744), I.275-76. Other quotations from this same poem
                        are in No. 80, ‘On Friendship with the World’, §28 and n. The idea of the
                        inscrutable purposes of God in cases of untimely death appears in a letter
                        to Mrs. Betty Bradburn, Feb. 28, 1782, and in JWJ, Sept. 25, 1789: ‘[Mr.
                        Henderson] could not save the life of his only son, who was probably taken
                        to bring his father to God.’</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">From this great truth the heathen poets probably derived their imagination that
                    Iris used to be sent down from heaven to discharge souls out of their
                        bodies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Iris
                            was the goddess of the rainbow, daughter of Light (Electra) and Wonder
                            (Thaumas). In the <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> she is mentioned
                            frequently as a ‘swift-footed messenger’, especially from Zeus or Hera
                            to the lesser gods and to men; she disappears from the <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> where her role and function are taken by Hermes. This
                            allusion to her ‘discharging souls out of their bodies’ has no explicit
                            textual warrant; it may be a curious inference from <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi>, xxiii.161-262 (the story of the funeral pyre of the
                            Trojan heroes and of Iris’s assistance in kindling the fire).</p>
                    </note>
                    And perhaps the sudden death of many of the children of God may be owing to the
                    ministry of an angel.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="">II. So perfectly are the angels of God qualified for their high office. It
                    remains to inquire how they discharge their office. How do they minister to the
                    heirs of salvation?</p>
                <p n="1">1. I will not say that they do not minister at all to those who <pb n="03:011"/>through their obstinate impenitence and unbelief disinherit
                    themselves of the kingdom. This world is a world of mercy, wherein God pours
                    down many mercies even on the evil and the unthankful. And many of these, it is
                    probable, are conveyed even to them by the ministry of angels; especially so
                    long as they have any thought of God, or any fear of God before their eyes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:18.</p>
                    </note> But it is their favourite employ, their peculiar office, to
                    minister to the heirs of salvation; to those who are ‘now saved by faith’, or at
                    least seeking God in sincerity.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Is it not their first care to minister to our souls? But we must not
                    expect this will be done ‘with observation’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 17:20.</p>
                    </note>—in such a manner as
                    that we may clearly distinguish their working from the workings of our own
                    minds. We have no more reason to look for this than for their appearing in a
                    visible shape. Without this they can in a thousand ways apply to our
                    understanding. They may assist us in our search after truth, remove many doubts
                    and difficulties, throw light on what was before dark and obscure, and confirm
                    us in the truth that is after godliness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 1:1.</p>
                    </note> They may warn us of evil
                    in disguise, and place what is good in a clear, strong light. They may gently
                    move our will to embrace what is good, and fly from that which is evil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            12:9.</p>
                    </note> They may many times quicken our dull affections,
                    increase our holy hope or filial fear, and assist us more ardently to love <hi rend="italic">him</hi> who has first loved <hi rend="italic">us</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John
                            4:19.</p>
                    </note> Yea, they may be sent of God to answer that whole
                    prayer put into our mouths by pious Bishop Ken:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>O may thy angels while I sleep,</l>
                    <l>Around my bed their vigils keep;</l>
                    <l>Their love angelical instil;</l>
                    <l>Stop every avenue of ill.</l>
                    <l> May they celestial joys rehearse,</l>
                    <l>And thought to thought with me converse!</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Thomas Ken, ‘An Evening Hymn’, in <hi rend="italic">A
                            Manual of Prayers</hi> (1709), st. 10; repeated, along with st. 11, in
                        No. 132, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §12. See also Wesley’s letter to Hester Ann
                        Roe, Dec. 9, 1781. In 1684, Ken had been consecrated Bishop of Bath and
                        Wells. In 1689 he was deposed as a Nonjuror but refused the offer of
                        reinstatement after the death of his replacement Benjamin Kidder in 1703.
                        For another reference of Wesley’s to Ken, see No. 102, ‘Of Former Times’,
                        §11.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">
                    <pb n="03:012"/>Although the manner of this we shall not be able to explain while
                    we dwell in the body.</p>
                <p n="3">3. May they not minister also to us with respect to our bodies, in a
                    thousand ways which we do not now understand? They may prevent our falling into
                    many dangers which we are not sensible of; and may deliver us out of many
                    others, though we know not whence our deliverance comes. How many times have we
                    been strangely and unaccountably preserved in sudden and dangerous falls? And it
                    is well if we did not impute that preservation to chance,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 69, ‘The Imperfection
                            of Human Knowledge’, II.1 and n.</p>
                    </note> or to our own wisdom or
                    strength. Not so; it was God gave his angels charge over us, and in their hands
                    they bore us up.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 91:11-12; Matt. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> Indeed men of the world will
                    always impute such deliverances to accident or to second causes. To these
                    possibly some of them might have imputed Daniel’s preservation in the lion’s
                    den. But himself ascribes it to the true cause: ‘My God has sent his angel, and
                    shut the mouths of the lions.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Dan. 6:22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. When a violent disease, supposed to be incurable, is totally and
                    suddenly removed, it is by no means improbable that this is effected by the
                    ministry of an angel. And perhaps it is owing to the same cause that a remedy is
                    unaccountably suggested either to the sick person, or some attending upon him,
                    by which he is entirely cured.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’,
                    II.2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. It seems, what are usually called divine dreams may be frequently
                    ascribed to angels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 124, ‘Human Life a Dream’, §4 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> We have a remarkable instance of this kind related by one that
                    will hardly be thought an enthusiast; for he was a heathen, a philosopher, and
                    an emperor. I mean Marcus Antoninus. ‘In his <hi rend="italic">Meditations</hi>
                    he solemnly thanks God for revealing to him, when he was at Cajeta, in a dream,
                    what totally cured the bloody flux, which none of his physicians were able to
                        heal.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The
                            quotation here has not been located. Its source, however, and one that
                            Wesley had read, was the so-called ‘Meditations’ of Marcus Aurelius,
                            i.17(8); the text is ὧς μὴ πτύειν αἵμα καὶμὴ ἰλιγγιάν—i.e., spitting up
                            blood and a spell of vertigo. ‘Cajeta’ would be the present-day
                            Gaeta.</p>
                    </note> And why may we not suppose that God gave him this
                    notice by the ministry of an angel?</p>
                <p n="6">6. And how often does God deliver us from evil men by the <pb n="03:013"/>ministry of his angels, overturning whatever their rage, or malice, or
                    subtlety had plotted against us! These are about their bed, and about their
                    path, and privy to all their dark designs;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See. Ps. 139:2 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> and many of
                    them undoubtedly they bring to nought by means that we think not of. Sometimes
                    they blast their favourite schemes in the beginning; sometimes when they are
                    just ripe for execution. And this they can do by a thousand means that we are
                    not aware of. They can check them in their mid-career, by bereaving them of
                    courage or strength; by striking faintness through their loins, or turning their
                    wisdom into foolishness. Sometimes they bring to light the hidden things of
                        darkness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> and show us the traps that are laid for our feet.
                    In these and various other ways they hew the snares of the ungodly in
                        pieces.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 129:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Another grand branch of their ministry is to counterwork evil angels;
                    who are continually going about, not only as roaring lions, seeking whom they
                    may devour;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Pet. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> but more dangerously still, as angels of
                        light,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Cor. 11:14.</p>
                    </note> seeking whom they may deceive. And how great is
                    the number of these! Are they not as the stars of heaven for multitude?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 1:10;
                            10:22; 28:62.</p>
                    </note> How great is their rage, envy, malice, revenge!
                    Such as the wickedest men on earth never felt. How great is their subtlety!
                    Matured by the experience of above six thousand years. How great is their
                    strength! Only inferior to that of the angels of God. The strongest of the sons
                    of men are but as grasshoppers before them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Num. 13:33.</p>
                    </note> And what an
                    advantage have they over us by that single circumstance, that they are
                    invisible! As we have not strength to repel their force, so we have not skill to
                    decline it But the merciful Lord hath not given us up to the will of our
                    enemies. ‘His eyes’, that is his holy angels, ‘run to and fro over all the
                        earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Chr. 16:9; Zech. 4:10.</p>
                    </note> And if our eyes were opened we
                    should see, ‘they are more that are for us than they that are against us. We
                    should see’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Kgs. 6:16-17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lg>
                    <l>A convoy attends,</l>
                    <l> A minist’ring host of invisible friends.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Funeral Hymns</hi>,
                        1746 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 115), p. 23 (Hymn 15, st. 7 in <hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, VI.211); see also No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, II.4.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">
                    <pb n="03:014"/>And whenever those assault us in soul or in body, these are able,
                    willing, ready to defend us; who are at least equally strong, equally wise, and
                    equally vigilant And who can hurt us while we have armies of angels and the God
                    of angels on our side?</p>
                <p n="8">8. And we may make one general observation: whatever assistance God gives
                    to men by men, the same—and frequently in a higher degree—he gives to them by
                        angels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’, III.1.</p>
                    </note> Does he administer to
                    us, by men, light when we are in darkness, joy when we are in heaviness,
                    deliverance when we are in danger, ease and health when we are sick or in pain?
                    It cannot be doubted but he frequently conveys the same blessings by the
                    ministry of angels; not so sensibly, indeed, but full as effectually, though the
                    messengers are not seen. Does he frequently deliver us by means of men from the
                    violence or subtlety of our enemies? Many times he works the same deliverance by
                    these invisible agents. These shut the mouths of the human lions, so that they
                    have no power to hurt us. And frequently they join with our human friends
                    (although neither they nor we are sensible of it) giving them wisdom, courage,
                    or strength, without which all their labour for us would be unsuccessful. Thus
                    do they secretly minister in numberless instances to the heirs of salvation;
                    while we hear only the voices of men, and see none but men round about us.</p>
                <p n="9">9. But does not the Scripture teach, ‘The help which is done upon earth,
                    God doth it himself’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 74:13 (BCP; cf. AV here); see also No. 67,
                            ‘On Divine Providence’, §29, for a comment on God’s ‘immediate
                            power’.</p>
                    </note> Most certainly he does. And he is able to do it by
                    his own immediate power; he has no need of using any instruments at all, either
                    in heaven or earth. He wants not either angels or men to fulfil the whole
                    counsel of his will. But it is not his pleasure so to work. He never did; and we
                    may reasonably suppose he never will. He has always wrought by such instruments
                    as he pleases: but still it is God himself that doth the work. Whatever help
                    therefore we have, either by angels or men, is as much the work of God as if he
                    were to put forth his almighty arm and work without any means at all. But he has
                    used them from the beginning of the world: in all ages he has used the ministry
                    both of men and angels. And hereby especially is seen ‘the manifold wisdom of
                    God in the Church’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 3:10 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> Meantime the same glory redounds to him as if he
                    used no instruments at all.</p>
                <p n="10">
                    <pb n="03:015"/>10. The grand reason why God is pleased to assist men by
                    men, rather than immediately by himself, is undoubtedly to endear us to each
                    other by these mutual good offices, in order to increase our happiness both in
                    time and eternity. And is it not for the same reason that God is pleased to give
                    his angels charge over us? Namely, that he may endear us and them to each other;
                    that, by the increase of our love and gratitude to them, we may find a
                    proportionable increase of happiness when we meet in our Father’s kingdom. In
                    the meantime, though we may not worship them (worship is due only to our common
                    Creator), yet we may ‘esteem them very highly in love, for their works’
                        sake’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Thess. 5:13.</p>
                    </note> And we may imitate them in all holiness; suiting
                    our lives to the prayer our Lord himself has taught us; labouring to do his will
                    on earth as angels do it in heaven.</p>
                <p n="">I cannot conclude this discourse better than in that admirable collect of our
                    Church:</p>
                <quote>‘O everlasting God, who hast ordained and constituted the services of angels
                    and men in a wonderful manner; [mercifully] grant that as thy holy angels always
                    do thee service in heaven, so by thy appointment they may succour and defend us
                    on earth, through Jesus Christ our Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The Collect for the Feast of St. Michael and
                            All Angels, Sept. 29; the Prayer Book text reads, ‘wonderful order’
                            rather than ‘wonderful manner’. Bishop Bull concludes his Sermon 12 with
                            ‘The Preface and Sanctus’ in the Order for Holy Communion in place of a
                            conventional ascription. For Wesley’s use of ascriptions, cf. No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, III.9 and
                    n.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>