<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 72: Of Evil Angels</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon072</idno>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 72: Of Evil Angels</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume III: Sermons III,
                                71-114</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1986-11-01">1986-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="3"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="3" to="4"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="16" to="29"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a
                combination of OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these
                docx into XML using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched
                them up manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="03:003"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 71-72]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>These twin essays in angelology were written as a single exercise in January
                    1783, and then published in four successive instalments with texts but no titles
                    in the <hi rend="italic">Arminian Magazine</hi>, 1783 (Vol. VI, January through
                    April), under the rubric, ‘Original Sermons by the Rev. John Wesley, M. A.,
                    Sermons XIII and XIV’. The paired sermons, with their present titles, were then
                    published in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, VI.103-45, and not published again in
                    Wesley’s lifetime.</p>
                <p>He must have thought that he needed to say something about the place and role of
                    angels in ‘the great chain of being’ which, along with the Christian Platonists,
                    he conceived of as the general structure of creation (see No. 56, ‘God’s
                    Approbation of His Works’, I.14 and n.). This would also help explain his
                    placement of these sermons here, after his delineations of the limits of
                    knowledge and reason. But angelology was not one of his prime interests; this is
                    suggested by the fact that he had preached from Heb. 1:14 only three times
                    before (in 1752, 1758, and 1782) and from Eph. 6:12 only once (in 1759); his
                    other references to angels are few and scattered in his writings as a whole.</p>
                <p>Wesley’s ideas here, with a single puzzling exception (see No. 72, ‘Of Evil
                    Angels’, I.3), are unsurprisingly conventional. One finds much the same
                    viewpoints in Anglican theology in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries,
                    usually in connection with a doctrine of Providence or other comments on ‘the
                    ways of God to men’. However, there are two identifiable sources closer than
                    others to Wesley’s basic arguments here; only their practical applications are
                    clearly different. One of these is Bishop George Bull, <hi rend="italic">Some
                        Important Points of Primitive Christianity</hi>, especially Sermons 11 and
                    12. Note that Wesley has reversed Bull’s order. This would follow his other main
                    source, Thomas Crane’s second chapter, ‘Of Good and Bad Angels’, in <hi rend="italic">Isagoge ad Dei Providentiam</hi>. And, of course, the great
                    cosmic vision of <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> stands in Wesley’s further
                    background here. It is interesting that Wesley could not have known Milton’s
                    chapter IX, ‘Of the Special Government of Angels’, in his posthumous <hi rend="italic">De Doctrina Christiana</hi>, since that was not published
                    until 1825. But there is nothing in this part <pb n="03:004"/>of Milton’s
                    ‘doctrine’ from which Wesley would have dissented. And, on a crucial point, that
                    it was a majority of the angels who fell and enlisted under Satan’s banner,
                    Milton’s scenario in <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi> is clearly decisive
                    here.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="03:016"/>
            <head>Of Evil Angels</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Ephesians 6:12</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">We wrestle not against flesh and blood, but against
                        principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the darkness of this
                        world, against wicked spirits</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Translated thus in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">in heavenly places.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. It has been frequently observed that there are no gaps or chasms in the
                    creation of God, but that all the parts of it are admirably connected together,
                    to make up one universal whole. Accordingly there is one chain of beings,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For other
                            references to this favourite notion of Wesley’s, cf. No. 56, ‘God’s
                            Approbation of His Works’, I.14 and n.</p>
                    </note> from the lowest to the
                    highest point, from an unorganized particle of earth or water to Michael the
                    archangel. And the scale of creatures does not advance <hi rend="italic">per
                        saltum</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The ‘fixity of species’ and their continuous gradation was a basic
                            supposition of Aristotelian biology which Wesley still took for granted;
                            cf. <hi rend="italic">Historia Animalium</hi>, VIII.588<hi rend="italic">a-b</hi>.</p>
                    </note> by leaps, but by smooth and gentle degrees;
                    although it is true, these are frequently imperceptible to our imperfect
                    faculties. We cannot accurately trace many of the intermediate links of this
                    amazing chain, which are abundantly too fine to be discerned either by our
                    senses or understanding.</p>
                <p n="2">2. We can only observe, in a gross and general manner, rising one above
                    another, first, inorganical earth, then minerals and vegetables in their several
                    orders; afterwards insects, reptiles, fishes, birds, beasts, men, and angels. Of
                    angels indeed we know nothing with any certainty but by revelation. The accounts
                    which are left by the wisest of the ancients, or given by the modern heathens,
                    being no better than silly, self-inconsistent fables, too gross to be imposed
                    even upon children. But by divine revelation we are informed that they were all
                    created holy and happy; yet they did not all continue as they were created—some
                    kept, but some left, their first estate. The former of these are now good
                    angels; the latter, evil angels. Of the former I have spoken in a <pb n="03:017"/>preceding discourse; I purpose now to speak of the latter. And highly
                    necessary it is that we should well understand what God has revealed concerning
                    them, that they may gain no advantage over us by our ignorance, that we may know
                    how to wrestle against them effectually. For ‘we wrestle not against flesh and
                    blood, but against principalities, against powers, against the rulers of the
                    darkness of this world, against wicked spirits in heavenly places.’</p>
                <p n="3">3. This single passage seems to contain the whole Scripture doctrine
                    concerning evil angels. I apprehend the plain meaning of it, literally
                    translated, is this: ‘Our wrestling’, the wrestling of real Christians, ‘is not’
                    only, or chiefly, ‘against flesh and blood’—weak men or fleshly appetites and
                    passions—‘but against principalities, against powers’—the mighty <hi rend="italic">princes</hi> of all the infernal legions,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jackson emended the original
                            ‘legions’ to ‘regions’, and may have had a textual warrant, since he had
                            before him Wesley’s annotated copy of <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>,
                            Vol. VI, now missing.</p>
                    </note> with their combined forces: and great
                    is their <hi rend="italic">power</hi>, as is also the power of the legions which
                    they command—‘against the rulers of the world’ (this is the literal meaning of
                    the word). Perhaps these principalities and powers remain chiefly in the citadel
                    of their kingdom. But there are other evil spirits that range abroad, to whom
                    the provinces of the world are committed. ‘Of the darkness’—chiefly the
                    spiritual darkness—‘of this age’—which prevails during this present state of
                    things—‘against wicked spirits’—eminently such, who mortally hate and
                    continually oppose holiness, and labour to infuse unbelief, pride, evil desire,
                    malice, anger, hatred, envy, or revenge—‘in heavenly places’—which were once
                    their abode, and which they still aspire after.</p>
                <p>In prosecuting this important subject, I will endeavour to explain, first, the
                    nature and properties of evil angels; and, secondly, their employment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. With regard to the first, we cannot doubt but all the angels of God
                    were originally of the same <hi rend="italic">nature</hi>. Unquestionably they
                    were the highest order of created beings. They were spirits, pure, ethereal
                    creatures, simple and incorruptible; if not wholly immaterial, yet certainly not
                    encumbered with gross, earthly flesh and blood. As spirits they were endued with
                    understanding, with affections, and with liberty, or a power of
                    self-determination; so <pb n="03:018"/>that it lay in themselves either to
                    continue in their allegiance to God or to rebel against him.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And their original <hi rend="italic">properties</hi> were doubtless the
                    same with those of the holy angels. There is no absurdity in supposing Satan,
                    their chief, otherwise styled ‘Lucifer, son of the morning’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 14:12.</p>
                    </note> to have
                    been at least ‘one of the first, if not the first Archangel’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, v.659-60.</p>
                    </note> Like the other sons of the
                    morning, they had a height and depth of understanding quite incomprehensible to
                    us. In consequence of this they had such knowledge and wisdom that the wisest of
                    the children of men (had men then existed) would have been mere idiots in
                    comparison of them. Their strength was equal to their knowledge, such as it
                    cannot enter into our heart to conceive; neither can we conceive to how wide a
                    sphere of action either their strength or their knowledge extended. Their number
                    God alone can tell: doubtless it was only less than infinite. And a third part
                    of these stars of heaven the arch-rebel drew after him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 12:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. We do not exactly know (because it is not revealed in the oracles of
                    God) either what was the occasion of their apostasy, or what effect it
                    immediately produced upon them. Some have not improbably supposed that when God
                    ‘published the decree’ (mentioned Psalm 2:6-7) concerning the kingdom of his
                    only-begotten Son to be over all creatures, these first-born of creatures gave
                    place to pride, comparing themselves to him (possibly intimated by the very name
                    of Satan, Lucifer, or Michael, which means, ‘Who is like God?’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> (1783) reads ‘Satan, Lucess, or Michael…’, obviously a
                            printer’s error. In the errata to <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> and in his
                            personal copy Wesley altered this to ‘Satan, successor of Michael’. For
                                <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> (1788) he altered it yet again to the
                            reading here preferred. This preference presupposes Wesley’s
                            disagreement with traditional angelology, in which Satan and Lucifer are
                            allied, and Michael has no such successor—cf. Rev. 12:7-9 and Isa.
                            14:12-20 (AV); see also J. B. Russell, <hi rend="italic">Satan, the
                                Early Christian Tradition</hi> (Cornell Univ. Press, 1981), pp. 67,
                            131, 194. The problem of Wesley’s first alteration, however, still
                            remains as an unaccountable anomaly.</p>
                    </note> It may be, Satan, then
                    first giving way to temptation, said in his heart, ‘I too will have my throne.
                    “I will sit upon the sides of the north! I will be like the Most High.”’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        14:13-14.</p>
                    </note> But how did the mighty then fall!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Sam. 1:19, 25, 27. Cf.
                            Charles Wesley’s hymn on Gen. 1:27<hi rend="italic">, Short Hymns on
                                Select Passages of the Holy Scriptures</hi>: ‘How are the mighty
                            fallen!’ (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, IX.2).</p>
                    </note> What an
                    amazing loss did they sustain! If we allow of them all, what our poet supposes
                    concerning their chief in particular:</p>
                <pb n="03:019"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>His form had not yet lost</l>
                    <l>All its original brightness, nor appeared</l>
                    <l>Less than archangel ruined, and the excess</l>
                    <l>Of glory obscured;</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                        i.591-94; and see No. 71, ‘Of Good Angels’, I.5 and n.</p>
                </note>
                <p>If we suppose their outward form was not entirely changed (though it must have
                    been in a great degree, because the evil disposition of the mind must dim the
                    lustre of the visage), yet what an astonishing change was wrought within when
                    angels became devils, when the holiest of all the creatures of God became the
                    most unholy!</p>
                <p n="4">4. From the time that they shook off their allegiance to God they shook off
                    all goodness, and contracted all those tempers which are most hateful to him,
                    and most opposite to his nature. And ever since they are full of pride,
                    arrogance, haughtiness, exalting themselves above measure; and although so
                    deeply depraved through their inmost frame, yet admiring their own perfections.
                    They are full of envy, if not against God himself (and even that is not
                    impossible, seeing they formerly aspired after his throne), yet against all
                    their fellow-creatures; against the angels of God, who now enjoy the heaven from
                    which they fell; and much more against those worms of the earth who are now
                    called to ‘inherit the kingdom’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 6:9, etc.</p>
                    </note> They are full of
                    cruelty, of rage, against all the children of men, whom they long to inspire
                    with the same wickedness with themselves, and to involve in the same misery.</p>
                <p n="5">5. In the prosecution of this infernal design they are diligent in the
                    highest degree. To find out the most effectual means of putting it into
                    execution, they apply to this end the whole force of their angelical
                    understanding. And they second it with their whole strength, so far as God is
                    pleased to permit. But it is well for mankind that God hath set them their
                    bounds which they cannot pass. He hath said to the fiercest and strongest of the
                    apostate spirits, ‘Hitherto shalt thou come, and no farther.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 38:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    Otherwise how easily and how quickly might one of them overturn the whole frame
                    of nature! How soon would they involve all in one common ruin, or at least
                    destroy man from the face of the earth!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 6:7.</p>
                    </note> And they are indefatigable
                    in their bad work: they never are faint or weary. Indeed it seems no spirits are
                    capable of weariness but those that inhabit flesh and blood.</p>
                <p n="6">
                    <pb n="03:020"/>6. One circumstance more we may learn from the Scripture
                    concerning the evil angels. They do not wander at large, but are all united
                    under one common head. It is he that is styled by our blessed Lord, ‘the prince
                    of this world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 12:31; 14:30; 16:11.</p>
                    </note> yea, the Apostle does not scruple
                    to call him ‘the god of this world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:4.</p>
                    </note> He is frequently styled
                    ‘Satan’, the adversary, being the great adversary both of God and man. He is
                    termed, ‘the devil’; by way of eminence, ‘Apollyon’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 9:11; see also Matthew
                            Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>; Matthew Henry, <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>; and Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, on the meaning of the name (from ἀπολλύειν, to
                            destroy). Wesley says: ‘Both Abaddon and Apollyon signify a destroyer.
                            By this he [Apollyon] is distinguished from the dragon, whose proper
                            name is Satan.’ But he would also have had in mind ‘the foul fiend’ in
                            Bunyan’s <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim’s Progress</hi> who assaults
                            Christian on his way through the Valley of Humiliation.</p>
                    </note> or
                    the destroyer; ‘the old serpent’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 12:9; 20:2.</p>
                    </note> from his beguiling Eve
                    under that form; and ‘the angel of the bottomless pit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 9:11.</p>
                    </note> We have
                    reason to believe that the other evil angels are under his command; that they
                    are ranged by him according to their several orders, that they are appointed to
                    their several stations, and have from time to time their several works and
                    offices assigned them. And undoubtedly they are connected (though we know not
                    how; certainly not by love) both to him and to each other.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="0">II. But what is the employment of evil angels? This is the second point to
                    be considered.</p>
                <p n="1">1. They are (remember! so far as God permits) κοσμοκράτορες,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:12,
                            and the references in the intertestamental literature in Arndt and
                            Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>. For Wesley’s
                            satanocratic views, cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §10 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> ‘governors of the world’! So that there may be more ground
                    than we are apt to imagine for that strange expression of Satan when he had
                    ‘showed’ our Lord ‘all the kingdoms of the world, and the glory of them’: ‘All
                    these things will I give thee, if thou wilt fall down and worship me.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt.
                                4:8-9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> It is a little more particularly expressed in
                    the fourth chapter of St. Luke. ‘The devil showed unto him all the kingdoms of
                    the world in a moment of time.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 4:5.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="03:021"/>(Such an astonishing measure of power is still left in the
                    prince of darkness!) ‘And the devil said, All this power will I give thee, and
                    the glory of them: for that is delivered unto me; and to whomsoever I will, I
                    give it.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Luke 4:] ver. 5, 6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> They are ‘the rulers of the
                    darkness of this age’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:12 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> (so the words are literally translated), of the
                    present state of things, during which ‘the whole world lieth in the wicked
                        one.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            5:19 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> He is the element of the
                    children of men only, those who fear God being excepted. He and his angels, in
                    connection with, and in subordination to him, dispose all the ignorance, all the
                    error, all the folly, and particularly all the wickedness of men, in such a
                    manner as may most hinder the kingdom of God, and most advance the kingdom of
                    darkness.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘But has every man a particular evil angel as well as a good one
                    attending him?’ This has been an exceeding ancient opinion both among the
                    Christians and the Jews before them. But it is generally doubted whether it can
                    be sufficiently proved from Scripture. Indeed it would not be improbable that
                    there is a particular evil angel with every man, if we were assured there is a
                    good one. But this cannot be inferred from those words of our Lord concerning
                    little children, ‘In heaven their angels do continually see the face of their
                    Father which is in heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 18:10.</p>
                    </note> This only proves that
                    there are angels who are appointed to take care of little children. It does not
                    prove that a particular angel is allotted to every child. Neither is it proved
                    by the words of Rhoda, who hearing the voice of Peter said, ‘It is his
                        angel.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            12:15.</p>
                    </note> We cannot infer any more from this, even suppose ‘his
                    angel’ means his guardian angel, than that Rhoda believed the doctrine of
                    guardian angels, which was then common among the Jews. But still it will remain
                    a disputable point (seeing revelation determines nothing concerning it) whether
                    every man is attended either by a particular good or a particular evil
                    angel.</p>
                <p n="3">3. But whether or no particular men are attended by particular evil
                    spirits, we know that Satan and all his angels are continually warring against
                    us, and watching over every child of man. They are ever watching to see whose
                    outward or inward circumstances, whose prosperity or adversity, whose health or
                    sickness, whose <pb n="03:022"/>friends or enemies, whose youth or age, whose
                    knowledge or ignorance, whose business or idleness, whose joy or sorrow, may lay
                    them open to temptation. And they are perpetually ready to make the utmost
                    advantage of every circumstance. These skilful wrestlers espy the smallest slip
                    we make, and avail themselves of it immediately; as they also are ‘about our
                    bed, and about our path, and spy out all our ways’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 139:2
                        (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Indeed each of them ‘walketh about as a roaring lion,
                    seeking whom he may devour’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> or whom he may ‘beguile
                    through his subtlety, as the serpent beguiled Eve’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 11:3.</p>
                    </note>
                    Yea, and in order to do this the more effectually they transform themselves into
                    angels of light. Thus</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>With rage that never ends</l>
                    <l>Their hellish arts they try:</l>
                    <l>Legions of dire, malicious fiends,</l>
                    <l>And spirits enthroned on high.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘Hymns for the Watch-night’, No. 8, st.
                        7, ll. 5-8, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1749), II.130
                            (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, V.272). See also, No. 83, ‘On
                        Patience’, §2, where the first four lines of this stanza appear.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="4">4. It is by these instruments chiefly that the ‘foolish hearts’ of those
                    that know not God ‘are darkened’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 1:21.</p>
                    </note> yea, they frequently
                    darken in a measure the hearts of them that do know God. ‘The god of this world
                    knows’ how to ‘blind our hearts,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:4.</p>
                    </note> to spread a cloud over
                    our understanding, and to obscure the light of those truths which at other times
                    shine as bright as the noonday sun. By this means he assaults our faith, our
                    evidence of things unseen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 11:1.</p>
                    </note> He endeavours to weaken
                    that hope full of immortality<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 3:4. For Wesley’s other uses of this text,
                            cf. Nos. 74, ‘Of the Church’, §9; 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’, I.11,
                            II.12; and 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, I.3.</p>
                    </note>
                    to which God had begotten us,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 1:3.</p>
                    </note> and thereby to lessen,
                    if he cannot destroy, our joy in God our Saviour. But above all he strives to
                    damp our love of God, as he knows this is the spring of all our religion, and
                    that as this rises or falls the work of God flourishes or decays in the
                    soul.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Next to the love of God there is nothing which Satan so cordially abhors
                    as the love of our neighbour. He uses therefore <pb n="03:023"/>every possible
                    means to prevent or destroy this; to excite either private or public suspicions,
                    animosities, resentment, quarrels; to destroy the peace of families or of
                    nations, and to banish unity and concord from the earth. And this indeed is the
                    triumph of his art; to embitter the poor, miserable children of men against each
                    other, and at length urge them to do his own work, to plunge one another into
                    the pit of destruction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 55:23 (AV).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. This enemy of all righteousness is equally diligent to hinder every good
                    word and work. If he cannot prevail upon us to do evil he will, if possible,
                    prevent our doing good. He is peculiarly diligent to hinder the work of God from
                    spreading in the hearts of men. What pains does he take to prevent or obstruct
                    the general work of God! And how many are his devices to stop its progress in
                    particular souls!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 42, ‘Satan’s Devices’, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>.</p>
                    </note> To hinder their continuing or growing in
                    grace, in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 3:18.</p>
                    </note> To
                    lessen, if not destroy, that ‘love, joy, peace’; that ‘long-suffering,
                    gentleness, goodness’; that ‘fidelity, meekness, temperance’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22-23 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> which our Lord works by his
                    loving Spirit in them that believe, and wherein the very essence of religion
                    consists.</p>
                <p n="7">7. To effect these ends he is continually labouring with all his skill and
                    power to infuse evil thoughts of every kind into the hearts of men. And
                    certainly it is as easy for a spirit to speak to our heart as for a man to speak
                    to our ears. But sometimes it is exceeding difficult to distinguish these from
                    our own thoughts, those which he injects so exactly resembling those which
                    naturally arise in our own minds. Sometimes indeed we may distinguish one from
                    the other by this circumstance: the thoughts which naturally arise in our minds
                    are generally, if not always, occasioned by, or at least connected with, some
                    inward or outward circumstance that went before. But those that are
                    preternaturally suggested have frequently no relation to or connection (at least
                    none that we are able to discern) with anything which preceded. On the contrary
                    they shoot in as it were across, and thereby show that they are of a different
                        growth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. He likewise labours to awaken evil passions or tempers in our souls. He
                    endeavours to inspire those passions and tempers <pb n="03:024"/>which are
                    directly opposite to ‘the fruit of the Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22; Eph. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> He strives to
                    instil unbelief, atheism, ill-will, bitterness, hatred, malice, envy—opposite to
                    faith and love; fear, sorrow, anxiety, worldly care—opposite to peace and joy;
                    impatience, ill nature, anger, resentment—opposite to long-suffering,
                    gentleness, meekness; fraud, guile, dissimulation—contrary to fidelity; love of
                    the world, inordinate affection, foolish desires—opposite to the love of God.
                    One sort of evil desires he may probably raise or inflame by touching the
                    springs of this animal machine,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 51, <hi rend="italic">The Good
                            Steward</hi>, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> endeavouring thus by means of the
                    body to disturb or sully the soul.</p>
                <p n="9">9. And in general we may observe that as no good is done, or spoken, or
                    thought by any man without the assistance of God, working together <hi rend="italic">in</hi> and <hi rend="italic">with</hi> those that believe in
                    him; so there is no evil done, or spoke[n], or thought, without the assistance
                    of the devil, ‘who worketh with energy’, with strong though secret power, ‘in
                    the children of unbelief’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:2.</p>
                    </note> Thus he ‘entered
                        into’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            22:3.</p>
                    </note> Judas, and confirmed him in the design of betraying his
                    Master. Thus he ‘put it into the heart’ of Ananias and Sapphira ‘to lie unto the
                    Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 5:3.</p>
                    </note> And in like manner he has a share in all the
                    actions and words and designs of evil men. As the children of God ‘are workers
                    together with God’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 6:1.</p>
                    </note> in every good thought,
                    or word, or action; so the children of the devil are workers together with him
                    in every evil thought, or word, or work. So that as all good tempers, and
                    remotely all good words and actions, are the fruit of the good Spirit; in like
                    manner all evil tempers, with all the words and works which spring from them,
                    are the fruit of the evil spirit; insomuch that all the ‘works of the
                        flesh’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                            5:19.</p>
                    </note> of our evil nature, are likewise the ‘works of the
                        devil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 3:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. On this account, because he is continually inciting men to evil, he is
                    emphatically called, ‘the tempter’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 4:3; 1 Thess. 3:5.</p>
                    </note> Nor is it only
                    with regard to his own children that he is thus employed. He is continually
                    tempting the children of God also, and those that are labouring so to be:</p>
                <pb n="03:025"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>A constant watch he keeps;</l>
                    <l>He eyes them night and day:</l>
                    <l>He never slumbers, never sleeps,</l>
                    <l>Lest he should lose his prey.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                            Poems</hi> (1749), II.119, No. 2 of ‘Hymns for the Watch-night’ (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, V.261):</p>
                    <p rend="Verse">A constant watch he keeps,</p>
                    <p rend="Verse">He eyes me night and day,</p>
                    <p rend="Verse">And never slumbers, never sleeps,</p>
                    <p rend="Verse">Lest he should lose his prey.</p>
                    <p rend="footnote text">See also No. 132, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §10, where
                        Wesley again quotes this quatrain.</p>
                </note>
                <p n="">Indeed the holiest of men, as long as they remain upon earth, are not exempt
                    from his temptations. They cannot expect it; seeing ‘it is enough for the
                    disciple to be as his Master.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 10:25.</p>
                    </note> And we know he was
                    tempted to evil till he said, ‘Father, into thy hands I commend my spirit.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        23:46.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. For such is the malice of the wicked one that he will torment whom he
                    cannot destroy. If he cannot entice men to sin he will (so far as he is
                    permitted) put them to pain. There is no doubt but he is the occasion, directly
                    or indirectly, of many of the pains of mankind; which those who can no otherwise
                    account for them lightly pass over as ‘nervous’. And innumerable ‘accidents’, as
                    they are called, are undoubtedly owing to his agency, such as the unaccountable
                    fright or falling of horses, the overturning of carriages, the breaking or
                    dislocating of bones; the hurt done by the falling or burning of houses, by
                    storms of wind, snow, rain, or hail, by lightning or earthquakes. But to all
                    these, and a thousand more, this subtle spirit can give the appearance of
                    ‘accidents’, for fear the sufferers, if they knew the real agent, should call
                    for help on one that is stronger than him.</p>
                <p n="12">12. There is little reason to doubt but many diseases likewise, both of
                    the acute and chronical kind, are either occasioned or increased by diabolical
                    agency; particularly those that begin in an instant, without any discernible
                    cause; as well as those that continue, and perhaps gradually increase, in spite
                    of all the power of medicine. Here indeed ‘vain men’ that ‘would be wise’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job
                        11:12.</p>
                    </note> again call in the nerves to their assistance. But is not
                    this explaining <hi rend="italic">ignotum per ignotius</hi>—a thing unknown by
                    what is more <pb n="03:026"/>unknown?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A Latin tag long since a commonplace; cf. Chaucer,
                            ‘The Canon’s Yeoman’s Tale’, l. 904, <hi rend="italic">Canterbury
                                Tales</hi> (1687), p. 109. See Wesley’s letter to William Law, Jan.
                            6, 1756: ‘<hi rend="italic">ignotum per aeque ignotum</hi>’; and also
                                <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. I, V.9 (11:147 in this
                            edn.).</p>
                    </note> For what do we know of the nerves themselves? Not even
                    whether they are solid or hollow!</p>
                <p n="13">13. Many years ago I was asking an experienced physician, and one
                    particularly eminent for curing lunacy, ‘Sir, have you not seen reason to
                    believe that some lunatics are really demoniacs?’ He answered: ‘Sir, I have been
                    often inclined to think that most lunatics are demoniacs. Nor is there any
                    weight in that objection that they are frequently cured by medicine. For so
                    might any other disease occasioned by an evil spirit, if God did not suffer him
                    to repeat the stroke by which that disease is occasioned.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Probably Thomas Deacon
                            (1698-1753), a physician and schismatic non-juring bishop, much
                            interested in demoniacal possession and exorcisms. In No. 132, ‘On
                            Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §8, Wesley speaks of ‘one of the most eminent
                            physicians I ever knew, particularly in cases of insanity, Dr. Deacon’.
                            He had known Deacon first at Oxford, and in his diary records a visit
                            with Deacon in Manchester on May 17, 1733 (and occasional visits
                            thereafter). See also <hi rend="italic">The Principles of a Methodist
                                Farther Considered</hi>, IV.7, and Wesley’s letter to Thomas
                            Stedman, Aug. 13, 1774. The same idea had already been suggested by
                            Joseph Mede, Discourse VI, on John 10:20, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            p. 29.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="14">14. This thought opens to us a wider scene. Who can tell how many of those
                    diseases which we impute altogether to natural causes may be really
                    preternatural? What disorder is there in the human frame which an evil angel may
                    not inflict? Cannot he smite us, as he did Job, and that in a moment, with boils
                    from the crown of the head to the sole of the foot?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 2:7.</p>
                    </note> Cannot he
                    with equal ease inflict any other either external or internal malady? Could not
                    he in a moment, by divine permission, cast the strongest man down to the ground,
                    and make him ‘wallow foaming’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:20.</p>
                    </note> with all the symptoms either
                    of an epilepsy or apoplexy? In like manner, it is easy for him to smite any one
                    man, or everyone in a city or nation, with a malignant fever, or with the plague
                    itself, so that vain would be the help of man.</p>
                <p n="15">15. But that malice blinds the eyes of the wise,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 16:19.</p>
                    </note> one
                    would imagine so intelligent a being would not stoop so low as it seems the
                    devil sometimes does to torment the poor children of men! For to him we may
                    reasonably impute many little inconveniences which we suffer. ‘I believe’ (said
                    that excellent man, the Marquis de Renty, when the bench on which he sat snapped
                    in sunder <pb n="03:027"/>without any visible cause), ‘that Satan had a hand in
                    it, making me to fall untowardly.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Saint-Jure, <hi rend="italic">Life</hi>, p. 96:
                            ‘He told her [the Prioress of the Carmelites of Dijon] that being led
                            into his Chapel of Citry, and set down upon a bench, by reason of his
                            sickness, the bench broke, without any appearance at all to him that
                            such a thing could happen, and that he believed, the evil spirit had
                            broken it, to move him to impatience, making him to fall untowardly:
                            “But by the mercy of God, I was no more moved thereat”, said he, “than
                            you see me now, although the pains that surprised me were very sharp.”’
                            Cf. also, Wesley, <hi rend="italic">An Extract of the Life of M. de
                                Renty</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 43), London, 1741,
                            p. 21 (iv. 4).</p>
                    </note> I know not whether he may not have a hand in
                    that unaccountable horror with which many have been seized in the dead of night,
                    even to such a degree that all their bones have shook. Perhaps he has a hand
                    also in those terrifying dreams<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 124, ‘Human Life a Dream’, §4 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> which many have, even while they are in perfect health.</p>
                <p n="">It may be observed in all these instances we usually say ‘the devil’, as if
                    there was one only; because these spirits, innumerable as they are, do all act
                    in concert, and because we know not whether one or more are concerned in this or
                    that work of darkness.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="0">[III.] It remains only to draw a few plain inferences from the doctrine
                    which has been delivered.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And first, as a general preservative against all the rage, the power,
                    and subtlety of your great adversary, ‘put on the panoply’, the whole armour,
                    ‘of God,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 6:11.</p>
                    </note> universal holiness. See that ‘the mind be in you
                    which was also in Christ Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> and that ye ‘walk as
                    Christ also walked’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:6.</p>
                    </note> that ye have a
                    conscience void of offence toward God and toward men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 24:16.</p>
                    </note> So
                    shall ye ‘be able to withstand’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:13.</p>
                    </note> all the force and all the
                    stratagems of the enemy. So shall ye be able to ‘withstand in the evil
                        day’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid</hi>.</p>
                    </note> in the day of sore temptation.
                    And ‘having done all, to stand’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>—to remain
                    in the posture of victory and triumph.</p>
                <p n="2">2. To his ‘fiery darts’, his evil suggestions of every kind, blasphemous or
                    unclean, though numberless as the stars of heaven, oppose ‘the shield of
                        faith’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            6:16.</p>
                    </note> a consciousness of the love of Christ Jesus will
                    effectually quench them all.</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Jesus hath died for <hi rend="italic">you</hi>!</l>
                    <l>What can your faith withstand?</l>
                    <l>Believe, hold fast your shield! and who</l>
                    <l>Shall pluck you from his hand?</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Charles Wesley, ‘The Whole Armour of God’, <hi rend="italic">in Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1749), I.237 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, V.42). Orig., second line reads, ‘What
                        can his love withstand?’</p>
                </note>
                <p n="3">
                    <pb n="03:028"/>3. If he inject doubts whether you are a child of God, or
                    fears lest you should not endure to the end, ‘Take to you for a helmet the hope
                    of salvation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> Hold fast that glad word, ‘Blessed be the
                    God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his abundant mercy
                    hath begotten us again unto a living hope of an inheritance incorruptible,
                    undefiled, and that fadeth not away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:3-4.</p>
                    </note> You will never be
                    overthrown, you will never be staggered by your adversary, if you ‘hold fast the
                    beginning of this confidence steadfast unto the end.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 3:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Whenever the ‘roaring lion, walking about and seeking whom he may
                        devour’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Pet. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> assaults you with all his malice, and rage, and
                    strength, ‘resist’ him, ‘steadfast in the faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> Then is
                    the time, having cried to the Strong for strength,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See No. 48, ‘Self-denial’,
                            III.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> to ‘stir up the gift of God that is in
                        you;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                            Tim. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> to summon all your faith, and hope, and love; to
                    turn the attack in the name of the Lord, and in the power of his might;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        6:10.</p>
                    </note> and ‘he will’ soon ‘flee from you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 4:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. But ‘there is no temptation’, says one, ‘greater than the being without
                        temptation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Miguel de Molinos, <hi rend="italic">The Spiritual Guide Which
                                Disentangles the Soul</hi> (1688), I.63. Wesley extracted this for
                            the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, XXXVIII.262: ‘Finally thou
                            art to know, that the greatest temptation is to be without
                            temptation.’</p>
                    </note> When therefore this is the case, when Satan
                    seems to be withdrawn, then beware lest he hurt you more as a crooked serpent
                    than he could do as a roaring lion. Then take care you are not lulled into a
                    pleasing slumber, ‘lest he should beguile you as he did Eve’, even in innocence,
                    and insensibly draw you ‘from your simplicity toward Christ’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 11:3.</p>
                    </note>
                    from seeking all your happiness in him.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Lastly, if he ‘transform himself into an angel of light’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            11:14.</p>
                    </note> then are you in the greatest danger of all. Then have
                    you need to beware, lest you also fall where many mightier have been slain: then
                    have you the greatest need to ‘watch and pray, that ye enter not into
                        temptation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:41.</p>
                    </note> And if you continue so to do, the God whom you
                    love and serve will deliver you. ‘The anointing of the <pb n="03:029"/>Holy One
                    shall abide with you, and teach you of all things.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:20, 27 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> Your eye will pierce through
                        snares:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Job 40:24.</p>
                    </note> you shall know what that ‘holy, and acceptable,
                    and perfect will of God is’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:1, 2.</p>
                    </note> and shall hold on your
                    way till you ‘grow up in all things into him that is our head, even Christ
                        Jesus.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 4:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <p n="">January 7, 1783<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Date as added in <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>