<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 1: Salvation by Faith</title>
                <title type="subtitle">A Sermon preached at St. Mary’s, Oxford, before the
                    University, on <date when="1738-06-11">June 11, 1738</date>
                </title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-21</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon001</idno>                            
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 1: Salvation by Faith</title>
                            <date when="1738-06-11"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="130"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:109"/>
            <introduction>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 1-4]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As we have seen, these first four sermons in this first volume of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> were ‘prefixed’ to the other eight on the advice of
                    friends, and also as proof of the consistency of Wesley’s new preaching, whether
                    before the University of Oxford or to the masses in Moorfields. But they also
                    serve another function, unavowed but crucial: they mark out the successive
                    stages of Wesley’s alienation from any further career as a reformer within the
                    university, as he made the radical shift in his commitment to the Revival as his
                    new vocation.</p>
                <p>Along with other ordained Oxford M.A.s, the brothers Wesley were subject to
                    occasional appointment as preachers in the <hi rend="italic">rota</hi> of
                    university services on Sundays and saints’ days (most of them in the Church of
                    St. Mary the Virgin, but others in St. Peter’s in the East and certain college
                        chapels).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Oxford University Statutes, tr. by G. R. M. Ward (1845), Vol. I, ‘The
                            Laudian Statutes’ (1636), Title XVI, chs. 1-7.</p>
                    </note> Attendance
                    upon these services was a stated obligation of ‘all doctors, masters, graduates,
                    and scholars’, who were enjoined to ‘be present at them from their beginning to
                    their end…’; no one was ‘permitted to wander abroad to another church, or
                    churches, under pain of chastisement…’, etc. (ch. 10). Even though these
                    injunctions were often honoured in the breach, such occasions were still
                    splendid sounding boards for eloquent preachers with earnest messages.</p>
                <p>John Wesley’s first ‘university sermon’ had been delivered in St. Mary’s on
                    November 15, 1730, ‘On Gen. 1:27’ (see No. 141, Vol. IV); a second on July 23,
                    1732 (‘A Consecration Sermon’, not extant); a third on January 1, 1733 (‘The
                    Circumcision of the Heart’; see No. 17 below). This last may be reckoned as a
                    landmark in the development of Wesley’s theology, and must also have made a
                    favourable general impression, for in the next two and a half years he was
                    invited to deliver <pb n="110"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">six</hi> more university
                    sermons: March 26, 1733 (Easter); April 1, 1733 (Low Sunday); May 13, 1733
                    (Whitsunday); February 10, 1734; June 11, 1734 (St. Barnabas’s); September 21,
                    1735 (St. Matthew’s). This is out of all proportion to any typical rotation, and
                    even if Wesley was serving as substitute for other appointed preachers, that
                    would have required the approval of the Vice-Chancellor (cf. <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>, XVI, ch. 6). The least that this can mean is that John
                    Wesley was more widely appreciated at Oxford as a preacher than the popular
                    stereotypes have suggested.</p>
                <p>This fact sheds some light on the arrangement by the university officials for
                    Wesley to preach again in Oxford soon after his return from Georgia (probably in
                    expectation of his resumption of his duties there); the new appointment was set
                    for the Festival of St. Barnabas, June 11, 1738. By that time, of course, Wesley
                    had undergone the radical change of heart and mind described in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for May 24, about which his Oxford colleagues
                    would have known nothing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Intro., above, p.4; see also Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Wesley</hi>, I.141-95, for a careful analysis of the
                            theological developments involved in this ‘conversion’; JWJ, Feb. 7-May
                            28, sheds light on Wesley’s mood as he revised his sermon for this
                            crucial new occasion.</p>
                    </note> Meanwhile, he had already tested his
                    ‘new gospel’ (‘salvation by faith alone’) in several churches in and near
                    London, and his presentation of it had almost invariably stirred up more offence
                    than conversions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, Feb. 5 (Milbank, Westminster); Feb. 12 (St. Andrew’s,
                            Holborn); Feb. 26 (thrice in London, the first, in St. Lawrence Jewry,
                            being the most blessed ‘because it gave the most offence’); Mar. 6
                            (after being counselled by Böhler to ‘preach faith <hi rend="italic">till</hi> you have it; and then, <hi rend="italic">because</hi> you
                            have it, you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> preach faith’); Mar. 17, 26,
                            and 27; Apr. 2, 25, 26; May 7, 9, 14, and 21 (this last being also the
                            day of Charles Wesley’s experience of assurance).</p>
                    </note> In most of
                    these instances, as he records with a trace of self-righteousness, he had been
                    thenceforth barred from this pulpit and that. The Aldersgate experience had not
                    produced a new doctrine, but a new resolution to make the most of his
                    opportunities to expound the one to which he had already come.</p>
                <p>He was by now very well aware of the controversial character of his message, and
                    he could not have expected a sympathetic hearing at Oxford. ‘Salvation by Faith’
                    was, however, the first public occasion after his ‘Aldersgate’ experience for a
                    positive evangelical manifesto. It is worth noting that its Moravian substance
                    is qualified by echoes from the Edwardian <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, as in
                    the claim that salvation involved a power not to commit sin (<hi rend="italic">posse non peccare</hi>). There is also an obvious Anglican nuance in the
                    definition of saving faith presented here.</p>
                <p>When his turn as university preacher came round again (<date when="1741-07-25">July 25, 1741</date>), the Revival was in full swing and Wesley had found
                    in its <pb n="111"/>leadership an alternative career. He had not only begun to
                    shift his loyalties from Oxford to his own Societies; he had also become one of
                    Oxford’s harsher critics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This may be seen in the Latin and English versions
                            of a sermon on Isa. 1:21 which he had first prepared in 1739, probably
                            in connection with his exercises for the B.D. degree which, as Fellow of
                            Lincoln College, he was expected to take in due course (see below, Nos.
                            150, 151).</p>
                    </note> John Gambold had already advised him that he would
                    face a hostile audience, but Wesley was in no mood to mollify them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, June 18,
                            1741: ‘All here [Gambold had said of the Oxford community] are so
                            prejudiced that they will mind nothing you say.’ Wesley’s reaction: ‘I
                            know that. However, I am to deliver my own soul, whether they will hear
                            or whether they will forbear’ (one of Wesley’s standard formulae of
                            alienation). A fortnight later even Wesley and Gambold had come to a
                            parting of their ways (cf. JWJ, July 2). Earlier, he had finally got
                            round to reading ‘that celebrated book, Martin Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Comment on the Epistle to the Galatians</hi>’; his
                            negative reaction to it was intemperate (see JWJ, June 15).</p>
                    </note>
                    Indeed, the whole <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> record for June and July
                    reflects a mounting tension, as if Wesley was aware of the crisis. On June 28 he
                    preached ‘at Charles Square [London], to the largest congregation that, I
                    believe, was ever seen there, on “Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian”
                    [cf. Acts 26:28]’. This was the sermon that, revised and with its new
                    ‘application’ explicitly aimed at Oxford, he delivered on the festival day of
                    St. James the Apostle, July 25.</p>
                <p>Its theme—the radical difference between nominal and real Christianity—was
                    already a familiar one in Puritan preaching;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, proem and n.</p>
                    </note> it was, however, already
                    conventional to ignore the text’s plain reference to Agrippa’s being almost
                    persuaded to become a Christian rather than to his already being a nominal one.
                    Wesley draws out the distinctions between the two stages of Christian experience
                    (‘almost’ and ‘altogether’). Part I paints a vivid picture of the high-minded
                    hypocrite (the ‘almost Christian’) and concludes with Wesley’s confession ‘that
                    this had been his own state in all his days at Oxford’ (I.13). Part II
                    delineates the ‘altogether Christian’ according to his new conceptions, and
                    openly expresses doubt that there are many such in Oxford even now (II.7-9).
                    There are no records of this sermon’s reception on this occasion, but it would
                    not have been lost on his Methodist readers that their leader had bearded the
                    Anglican establishment in one of its citadels and had survived.</p>
                <p>In the following year Charles Wesley came up for an appointment as preacher in
                    St. Mary’s on <date when="1742-04-04">April 4, 1742</date>. His evangelical
                    conversion had preceded his brother’s, either on <date when="1738-05-03">May 3,
                        1738</date> (when ‘it pleased God to open his <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> so
                    that he saw clearly what was the nature of [saving] <pb n="112"/>faith…’) or on
                        <date when="1738-05-19">May 19</date> (when he ‘had found rest to his
                        soul’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            both CWJ and JWJ for these dates and experiences.</p>
                    </note> In any
                    case, Charles was more exuberant in temperament and rhetoric than his elder
                        brother.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            above, p. 2, n. 6: ‘…in connection I beat you; but in strong, pointed
                            sentences you beat me.’</p>
                    </note> He had already preached a sermon on
                    justification ‘before the university [July 1739] with great boldness…’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">CWJ, Sunday, July
                            1, 1739; this is followed (on Monday) by a note that the Vice-Chancellor
                            and ‘all were against [that] sermon as liable to be misunderstood’. Had
                            this been Charles’s reinforcing sequel to John’s <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>?</p>
                    </note> His bidding prayer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the
                            unpublished MS of a sermon on Rom. 3:27-28.</p>
                    </note> indicates that
                    this preaching service had been held in Christ Church Cathedral rather than St.
                    Mary’s. On June 30, 1740, he reports having spent a week in Oxford ‘preaching
                    repentance’ but also in discovering that ‘learned Gallio cared for none of these
                        things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 18:17 for this analogy between a Roman proconsul’s and Oxford’s
                            indifference.</p>
                    </note> Now, he was scheduled to preach in St. Mary’s
                    itself—for the first and last time.</p>
                <p>Charles’s message, with a barrage of invidious questions for its climax, fell
                    largely on deaf ears; this is reported by a visitor who was in the audience:
                    Thomas Salmon, a popular historian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The times of the day the University go to this
                            church are ten in the morning and two in the afternoon, on Sundays and
                            holidays, the sermon usually lasting about half an hour. But when I
                            happened to be at Oxford, in 1742, Mr. Wesley, the Methodist, of Christ
                            Church, entertained his audience two hours, having insulted and abused
                            all degrees from the highest to the lowest, was in a manner hissed out
                            of the pulpit by the lads;’ Thomas Salmon, <hi rend="italic">A
                                Foreigner’s Companion through the Universities of Cambridge and
                                Oxford</hi> (1748), p. 25, and quoted in CWJ, Apr. 15,
                        1750.</p>
                    </note> Charles Wesley’s denial of Salmon’s report appears in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for April 15, 1750, and is emphatic;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘And it would
                            have been high time for them to do so, if the historian [Salmon] said
                            true. But, unfortunately for him, I measured the time by my watch and it
                            was within the hour; I abused neither high nor low, as my sermon in
                            print will prove; neither was I hissed out of the pulpit or treated with
                            the least incivility, either by young or old….’</p>
                    </note> he may have
                    been right about the time, since the sermon as printed can be read aloud in
                    thirty minutes. On the other hand, Charles’s accusations must surely have
                    aroused resentment in his auditory, and Salmon would have been a competent judge
                    of that. In any case this sermon would have persuaded any Methodist reader of
                    Charles’s wholehearted identification with his brother’s cause and theirs. <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> is then a lively evangelical
                    statement, a personal identification with the Revival and a valedictory to
                    Oxford.</p>
                <p>By August 1744 the Revival was gaining momentum, the network (‘connexion’) of the
                    Methodist Societies had extended over into Wales <pb n="113"/>and had come under
                    serious persecution by English mobs, the first ‘conference’ had just been held
                    (June 25-29), and John Wesley had found his true mission in life. Even so, his
                    turn as university preacher came up yet again for August 24 (another festival,
                    this one for St. Bartholomew). This, of course, was an anniversary of the
                    notorious Massacre of Paris (in 1572) and, again, of the Great Ejectment of the
                    Nonconformists in England in 1662, in which both of Wesley’s grandfathers had
                    suffered. Benjamin Kennicott’s explanation of Wesley’s appointment was that ‘as
                    no clergyman [could] avoid his turn, so the university can refuse none;
                    otherwise Mr. Wesley would not have preached.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">At this time, Kennicott was an undergraduate
                            at Wadham College, but he was destined to set Old Testament studies in
                            England upon a new level with his great <hi rend="italic">Vetus
                                Testamentum cum Variis Lectionibus</hi> (Vol. 1, 1776; Vol. 2,
                            1780). His account of Wesley’s sermon appeared in <hi rend="italic">WMM</hi>, 1866, 47-48.</p>
                    </note> Actually, though, that rule was
                    flexible; there was ample precedent for substitutions. One must wonder,
                    therefore, how the appointment came about. Was it a gesture of academic freedom?
                    Did Wesley have a stronger base in Oxford than would appear from the record?
                    There is no indication that he had claimed his turn as by right, but it would
                    never have crossed his mind to avoid it. Thus, the stage was set for a
                    confrontation—and another valedictory.</p>
                <p>Parts I-III of <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> constitute a
                    positive account of Wesley’s conception of the ‘order of salvation’ (Part I), an
                    interesting missiological perspective (Part II), and an early statement of
                    Wesley’s eschatological ideas (Part III)—the sum of these parts is evangelical
                    and Anglican. The mood changes in Part IV where he comes to his ‘plain and
                    practical application’. Here the judgment is passed, with scant charity, that
                    Oxford’s hypocrisies are an intolerable offence to God and a general hindrance
                    to the Christian mission. Kennicott’s uncharitable suspicion was that this final
                    salvo ‘was what [Wesley] had been preparing for all along…’:</p>
                <quote>[In the conclusion] he fired his address with so much zeal and unbounded
                    satire as quite spoiled what otherwise might have been turned to great
                    advantage…. I liked some of his freedom: such as calling the generality of young
                    townsmen ‘a generation of triflers’…. But considering how many shining lights
                    are here that are the glory of the Christian cause, his sacred censure was much
                    too flaming and strong and his charity much too weak…. Having summed up the
                    measure of our iniquities, he concluded with a lifted up eye in this most solemn
                    form, ‘It is time for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, Lord, to lay to <hi rend="italic">thine</hi> hand’—words full of such presumption and seeming
                    imprecation that they gave an universal shock…. Had these things been omitted
                    and his censures moderated, I think his discourse, as to style and delivery,
                    would have been uncommonly pleasing to others as well as to myself. He is
                    allowed to be a man of great parts, and that by the excellent Dean <pb n="114"/>of Christ Church;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John Conybeare, who succeeded Joseph Butler as
                            Bishop of Bristol, and author of <hi rend="italic">Defence of Revealed
                                Religion…</hi> (1732), one of the eighteenth century’s more famous
                            replies to Tindal and other deists.</p>
                    </note> for the day he preached
                    the dean generously said of him, ‘John Wesley will always be thought a man of
                    sound sense, though an enthusiast!’ However, the Vice-Chancellor<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Walter Hodges,
                            Provost of Oriel.</p>
                    </note> sent for the sermon, and I hear that the
                    heads of college intend to shew their resentment.</quote>
                <p>Another eyewitness report of the same event was recorded by William Blackstone,
                    already a Fellow of All Souls and on his way to the fame he would earn as author
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Laws of England</hi> (1765-69). In
                    a letter to a family friend (Aug. 28) the young Blackstone reports on Wesley’s
                    sermon, which seems to have become the talk of the town:</p>
                <quote>We were last Friday [Aug. 24] entertained at St. Mary’s by a curious sermon
                    from Wesley the Methodist. Among other equally modest particulars, he informed
                    us, 1st, that there was not one Christian among all the Heads of Houses; 2ndly,
                    that pride, gluttony, avarice, luxury, sensuality and drunkenness were general
                    characteristics of all Fellows of Colleges, who were useless to a proverbial
                    uselessness. Lastly, that the younger part of the University were a generation
                    of triflers, all of them perjured and none of them of any religion at all. His
                    notes were demanded by the Vice-Chancellor, but on mature deliberation it has
                    been thought proper to punish him by a mortifying neglect….<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the facsimile of the
                            letter in John Fletcher Hurst, <hi rend="italic">The History of
                                Methodism</hi>, II.604-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That ‘mortifying neglect’ began at once. Charles Wesley records that ‘we [John
                    Wesley, Charles Wesley, Messrs. Piers and Meriton] walked back in form, the
                    little band of us four; for of the rest durst none join himself to us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. CWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Methodists, then and later, could see no proper warrant for anyone to have taken
                    offence at such a sermon; after all, Wesley had simply preached the gospel and
                    applied it ‘close and home’. Thomas Jackson’s later comment on it is
                    typical:</p>
                <quote>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> contains a beautiful and
                    forcible description of spiritual religion, with the manner by which it is
                    acquired by individuals and then spreads from one to another until it shall
                    cover the earth. The concluding application to the heads of colleges and halls,
                    to the fellows and tutors and to the body of undergraduates, assumes their
                    general and wide departure from the true Christian character, and [their]
                    abandonment to formality, worldliness, levity, and sloth. It contains nothing
                    sarcastic and irritating, nothing that was designed to give unnecessary pain or
                    offence; but is marked throughout by seriousness, fidelity, and tender
                        affection.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Rev. Charles Wesley</hi> (1841),
                            I.403.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <pb n="115"/>John Wesley himself was much more of a realist and also more aware
                    of his own intention:</p>
                <quote>I preached, I suppose the last time, at <placeName>St. Mary’s</placeName>. Be
                    it so. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully delivered my own
                    soul.</quote>
                <quote>The Beadle came to me afterwards and told me the Vice-Chancellor had sent him
                    for my notes. I sent them without delay, not without admiring the wise
                    providence of God. Perhaps few men of note would have given a sermon of mine the
                    reading if I had put it into their hands; but by this means it came to be read,
                    probably more than once, by every man of eminence in the University.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">JWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That he never regretted the affair or its consequences would appear from a
                    complacent recollection of it in 1781 in ‘A Short History of the People called
                    Methodists’:</p>
                <quote>Friday, August 24, St. Bartholomew’s Day, I preached for the last time before
                    the University of Oxford. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully
                    delivered my own soul. And I am well pleased that it should be the very day on
                    which, in the last century,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, the Great Ejectment in
                            1662.</p>
                    </note> near two thousand burning and shining lights were put
                    out at one stroke. Yet what a wide difference is there between their case and
                    mine! They were turned out of house and home, and all that they had; whereas I
                    am only hindered from preaching, without any other loss; and that in a kind of
                    honourable manner; it being determined that when my next turn to preach came
                    they would pay another person to preach for me. And so they did twice or thrice,
                    even to the time that I resigned my fellowship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">§30. See Vol. 9 of this edn. and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 420.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>What would have been most obvious to his Methodist readers was the heroic stature
                    of their leader who had preached ‘plain truth’ to academic people to their face
                    and at the cost of rejection by them. What clearer proof could there be of his
                    fidelity to the gospel under all circumstances and of his total commitment in
                    his ministry among them? It was no small matter for a tenured don to have
                    forsaken his privileged status in a class-conscious English society in exchange
                    for ‘The Foundery’, ‘The New Room’, and a career among the masses. They knew,
                    all too well, how rudely the Methodists had been treated, to the point of savage
                    persecution, condoned by magistrates and clergy alike in the years between 1739
                    and 1746; they could still foresee dangerous days ahead. <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> as published was an evangelical proclamation;
                    it was also an act of defiance.</p>
                <p>These ‘prefixed’ sermons, therefore, serve a particular junction in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> as a bloc: they proclaim the Wesleyan message in
                    prophetic terms, and they signify Wesley’s transference of his allegiance from
                    the <pb n="116"/>Academy to his new vocation as a preacher of ‘plain truth for
                    plain people’. Together they dispel any impression of inconsistency. His message
                    in St. Mary’s had been the same as it was now in Moorfields. Thus, these sermons
                    could serve as a multifaceted introductory quartet to the larger endeavour of
                        <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi>.</p>
                <p>The edited text of <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi> is based upon the
                    first edition of 1738. For a stemma illustrating its publishing history through
                    its thirty-one editions in Wesley’s lifetime, together with substantive variant
                    readings, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                    10.</p>
                <p>The text for <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi> is based upon its first
                    edition, 1741. For a stemma and table of variant readings through the
                    twenty-eight extant editions during Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix.
                    See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 50.</p>
                <p>The first edition of <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> followed
                    here, was published shortly after the sermon itself was preached in 1742. For a
                    stemma and variant readings from the fifty-two extant editions in Charles
                    Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 59.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> was also published shortly after
                    its delivery in 1744 and ran through at least fifteen editions in Wesley’s
                    lifetime. For a stemma of these editions and a list of variant readings, see
                    Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 92.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Salvation by Faith</head>
            <head type="subhead">Sermon preached at St. Mary’s, Oxford,<lb/>before the
                University,<lb/>on <date when="1738-06-11">June 11, 1738</date>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The half-title in the first
                        edition of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, Vol. I (1746), and a footnote in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> I.15, record the date as June 18, 1738—an
                        obvious misremembrance, since Wesley was in Germany then; cf.
                    JWJ.</p>
                </note>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Ephesians 2:8</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">By grace ye are saved through faith.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">One of Wesley’s favourite texts. In No. 16, ‘The
                            Means of Grace’, II.6, he speaks of its theme as ‘that great foundation
                            of the whole Christian building’; cf. John Telford, <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Rev. Charles Wesley</hi> (London, Wesleyan
                            Methodist Book Room, 1900), pp. 76, 79-80, and also John Hampson’s
                            comment (<hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, I.199) that Wesley’s definition
                            of faith here, based upon the <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, remained
                            constant thereafter.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. All the blessings which God hath bestowed upon man are of his mere
                    grace, bounty, or favour: his free, undeserved favour, favour altogether
                    undeserved, man having no claim to the least of his mercies.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gen 32:10.</p>
                    </note> It
                    was free grace that ‘formed man of the dust of the ground, and breathed into him
                    a living soul’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> and stamped on that soul the image of
                        God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This
                            metaphor from Gen. 1:27 is the basic one in Wesley’s anthropology; it
                            first appears in the MS sermon on the Genesis text (see below, No. 141,
                            ‘The Image of God’, dated 1730) and is often repeated throughout the
                            corpus. Cf. Nos. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>,
                            I.2; 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, I.1-2; 6, ‘The Righteousness of
                            Faith’, II.9; 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §16; 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, III.2; 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our Righteousness</hi>, I.2; 22, ‘Sermon on
                            the Mount, II’, II.6; 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, III.5;
                            45, ‘The New Birth’, I.1; 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.6; 60, ‘The
                            General Deliverance’, I.1, 2, III.11, 12; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s
                            Coming’, I.7; 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, II.1; 128, ‘The
                            Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, I.2; 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in
                            Earthen Vessels’, §2, I.1; 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’, II.2; 139, ‘On the
                            Sabbath’, I.2; 146, ‘The One Thing Needful’, I.2, III.1; cf. also his
                            letter to Richard Morgan, Jan. 15, 1734, and to William Dodd, Mar. 12,
                            1756. See also <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi> (1784), IV. 54-55.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">The phrase denotes for Wesley the human capacity
                            for knowing and responding to God’s prevenient, justifying, and
                            sanctifying activities and, in this respect, is equivalent to his other
                            phrase about our ‘spiritual sensorium’ (cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.). The restoration of our corrupted and disabled
                            ‘image’ to its pristine capacity is, indeed, the goal of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">ordo salutis</hi>.</p>
                    </note> and ‘put all things
                    under <pb n="118"/>his feet’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 8:6; a rare quotation of a psalm from the AV.
                            See also 1 Cor. 15:27; Eph. 1:22.</p>
                    </note> The same free grace
                    continues to us, at this day, life, and breath, and all things.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        17:25.</p>
                    </note> For there is nothing we are, or have, or do, which can
                    deserve the least thing at God’s hand. ‘All our works thou, O God, hast wrought
                    in us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            26:12.</p>
                    </note> These therefore are so many more instances of free
                    mercy: and whatever righteousness may be found in man, this also is the gift of
                    God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Wherewithal then shall a sinful man atone for any the least of his sins?
                    With his own works? No. Were they ever so many or holy, they are not his own,
                    but God’s. But indeed they are all unholy and sinful themselves, so that every
                    one of them needs a fresh atonement. Only corrupt fruit grows on a corrupt
                        tree.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 7:17, 18; 12:33.</p>
                    </note> And his heart is altogether corrupt
                    and abominable, being ‘come short of the glory of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:23.</p>
                    </note> the
                    glorious righteousness at first impressed on his soul, after the image of his
                    great Creator. Therefore having nothing, neither righteousness nor works, to
                    plead, his ‘mouth is utterly stopped before God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:19.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. If then sinful man find favour with God, it is ‘grace upon grace’ (χάριν
                    ἀντὶ χάριτος).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 1:16. Orig. Χάρις ἀντι Χάριτος, in the early editions; the Greek
                            parenthesis was omitted from later separate editions (beginning in
                            1743), and from all the collected editions of the sermons.</p>
                    </note> If
                    God vouchsafe still to pour fresh blessings upon us—yea, the greatest of all
                    blessings, salvation—what can we say to these things but ‘Thanks be unto God for
                    his unspeakable gift!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 9:15.</p>
                    </note> And thus it is. Herein ‘God
                    commendeth his love toward us, in that, while we were yet sinners, Christ
                        died’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            5:8.</p>
                    </note> to save us. ‘By grace’, then, ‘are ye saved through
                        faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 2:8.</p>
                    </note> Grace is the source, faith the condition, of
                    salvation.</p>
                <p>Now, that we fall not short of the grace of God, it concerns us carefully to
                    inquire:</p>
                <p>I. What faith it is through which we are saved.</p>
                <p>II. What is the salvation which is through faith.</p>
                <p>III. How we may answer some objections.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>
                    <pb n="119"/>I. What faith it is through which we are saved.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And, first, it is not barely the faith of a heathen. Now God requireth
                    of a heathen to believe ‘that God is, and that he is a rewarder of them that
                    diligently seek him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:6.</p>
                    </note> and that he is to be
                    sought by ‘glorifying him as God by giving him thanks for all things’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            2:20.</p>
                    </note> and by a careful practice of moral virtue, of justice,
                    mercy, and truth, toward their fellow-creatures. A Greek or Roman, therefore,
                    yea, a Scythian or Indian, was without excuse if he did not believe thus much:
                    the being and attributes of God, a future state of reward and punishment, and
                    the obligatory nature of moral virtue. For this is barely the faith of a
                        heathen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For
                            other uses of this phrase and for Wesley‘s denials of the efficacy of
                            natural religion, see Nos. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>; 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’; 54, ‘On
                            Eternity’, §17; 69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, III.2; 74,
                            ‘Of the Church’, §11; 106, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, I.3, II.2. See also
                            his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Acts 17:28, and <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi> II.276. For Susanna Wesley’s comments on this topic,
                            see John Newton, <hi rend="italic">Susanna Wesley and the Puritan
                                Tradition in Methodism</hi> (London, Epworth Press, 1968), p. 149.
                            Cf. also South, Sermon XIX, on Rom. 1:20, ‘Sinners Inexcusable from
                            Natural Religion Only’, §IV, in <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, I.313
                            ff.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Nor, secondly, is it the faith of a devil,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This phrase was familiar from
                            the Homily ‘Of Salvation’, Pt. III, <hi rend="italic">Certain Sermons or
                                Homilies Appointed to be Read in Churches…</hi> (Oxford, Oxford
                            University Press, 1840),p. 26 (hereafter cited as <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>). For other instances of Wesley’s insistence that
                            orthodoxy may be no better than ‘the faith of a devil’, cf. Nos. 7, ‘The
                            Way to the Kingdom’, I.6; and 150, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’, I.9; see also
                            his letter to Richard Tompson, July 25, 1755.</p>
                    </note> though this
                    goes much farther than that of a heathen. For the devil believes, not only that
                    there is a wise and powerful God, gracious to reward and just to punish, but
                    also that Jesus is the Son of God, the Christ, the Saviour of the world. So we
                    find him declaring in express terms: ‘I know thee who thou art, the Holy One of
                        God.’<note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Luke 4:34.</p>
                    </note> Nor can
                    we doubt but that unhappy spirit believes all those words which came out of the
                    mouth of the Holy One; yea, and whatsoever else was written by those holy men of
                    old, of two of whom he was compelled to give that glorious testimony, ‘These men
                    are the servants of the most high God, who show unto you the way of
                        salvation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 16:17.</p>
                    </note> Thus much then the great enemy of God and
                    man believes, and trembles in believing, that ‘God was made manifest in the
                        flesh;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Tim. 3:16.</p>
                    </note> that he will ‘tread all enemies under his
                        feet’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Cor. 15:25.</p>
                    </note> and <pb n="120"/>that ‘all Scripture was given by
                    inspiration of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 3:16.</p>
                    </note> Thus far goeth the
                    faith of a devil.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Thirdly, the faith through which we are saved, in that sense of the word
                    which will hereafter be explained, is not barely that which the apostles
                    themselves had while Christ was yet upon earth;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An allusion to the doctrines of Robert
                            Sandeman and John Glas, that faith in the apostolic <hi rend="italic">kerygma</hi> in itself was salvific. Cf. No. 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, II.3.</p>
                    </note> though they
                    so believed on him as to ‘leave all and follow him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 10:28,
                        etc.</p>
                    </note> although they had then power to work miracles, ‘to heal all
                    manner of sickness, and all manner of disease’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:1.</p>
                    </note> yea, they had then
                    ‘power and authority over all devils’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 9:1.</p>
                    </note> and which is beyond all
                    this, were sent by their Master to ‘preach the kingdom of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 9:2; the
                            text of 1746 ends here.</p>
                    </note> Yet after their return from doing all
                    these mighty works their Lord himself terms them, ‘a faithless generation’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        9:41.</p>
                    </note> He tells them ‘they could not cast out a devil, because of
                    their unbelief.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 9:40; Mark 6:6.</p>
                    </note> And when long after, supposing they
                    had some already, they said unto him, ‘Increase our faith,’ he tells them
                    plainly that of this faith they had none at all, no, not as a grain of mustard
                    seed: ‘The Lord said, If ye had faith as a grain of mustard seed, ye might say
                    unto this sycamine tree, Be thou plucked up by the roots, and be thou planted in
                    the sea; and it should obey you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 17:5-6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. What faith is it then through which we are saved? It may be answered:
                    first, in general, it is a faith in Christ—Christ, and God through Christ, are
                    the proper object<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the text of 1771 (and several later edns., but
                            not that of 1787) ‘object’ is altered to ‘objects’. The 1771 edition is
                            notorious for its careless printing and, in any case, it would have
                            seemed natural to a printer to use a plural object after a plural verb.
                            It is scarcely probable that Wesley would have meant ‘objects’ in this
                            context since the theological connotation would have been di-theistic.
                            ‘Object’, then, is more probably Wesley’s own usage.</p>
                    </note> of it.
                    Herein therefore it is sufficiently, absolutely, distinguished from the faith
                    either of ancient or modern heathens. And from the faith of a devil it is fully
                    distinguished by this—it is not barely a speculative, rational thing, a cold,
                    lifeless assent, a train of ideas in the head; but also a disposition of the
                    heart. For thus saith the Scripture, ‘With the heart man believeth unto
                    righteousness.’ And, ‘If thou shalt confess with thy mouth the Lord Jesus, and
                    shalt believe with thy <hi rend="italic">heart</hi> that God hath raised him
                    from the dead, thou shalt be saved.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 10:9, 10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">
                    <pb n="121"/>5. And herein does it differ from that faith which the
                    apostles themselves had while our Lord was on earth, that it acknowledges the
                    necessity and merit of his death, and the power of his resurrection. It
                    acknowledges his death as the only sufficient means of redeeming man from death
                    eternal, and his resurrection as the restoration of us all to life and
                    immortality; inasmuch as he ‘was delivered for our sins, and rose again for our
                        justification’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:25.</p>
                    </note> Christian faith is then
                    not only an assent to the whole gospel of Christ, but also a full reliance on
                    the blood of Christ, a trust in the merits of his life, death, and
                        resurrection;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This is close to the definition of ‘lively faith’
                            in the Homily ‘Of Faith’, Pt. I (<hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p.
                            30). The crucial distinction, in both places, is between faith as
                            ‘assent’ and faith as ‘trust’. See also <hi rend="italic">An Earnest
                                Appeal</hi>, §59 (11: 68-69 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note> a recumbency
                    upon him as our atonement and our life, as <hi rend="italic">given for us</hi>,
                    and <hi rend="italic">living in us</hi>. It is a sure confidence which a man
                    hath in God, that through the merits of Christ <hi rend="italic">his</hi> sins
                    are forgiven, and <hi rend="italic">he</hi> reconciled to the favour of God; and
                    in consequence hereof<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The first edition here reads: ‘It is a confidence
                            in the goodness of God, through the Son of his love, living, dying, and
                            interceding for us. It is an acceptance of him in all his offices, as
                            our Prophet, our Priest, and our King.’ No copy of the 2nd edition
                            survives, but the 3rd (1740) turns back again to the language of the
                            Homily ‘Of Salvation’, Pt. III (<hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, pp.
                            26-27).</p>
                    </note> a closing with him<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Closing with Christ’ was a favourite Puritan
                            metaphor. Cf. Ralph Erskine, <hi rend="italic">Law-Death, Gospel-Life:
                                Or, the Death of Legal Righteousness, the Life of
                                Gospel-Holiness</hi> (Edinburgh, 1724); also Matthew Mead, <hi rend="italic">Ἐν ὀλίγῳ Χριστιανός, the Almost Christian
                                Discovered</hi> (1661). Similar usages may be seen in William Allen,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Glass of Justification</hi> (1658), p. 26;
                            Richard Alleine, <hi rend="italic">Vindiciae Pietatis</hi> (1676), p.
                            176; William Guthrie, <hi rend="italic">The Christian’s Great
                                Interest</hi> (1766), pp. 103, 118-19; Thomas Ridgeley, <hi rend="italic">A Body of Divinity</hi> (1733), p. 551. See also
                            George Whitefield’s letter to Dr. Doddridge in Seymour,
                        I.202.</p>
                    </note> and cleaving to him as our ‘wisdom, righteousness,
                    sanctification, and redemption’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 1:30. The edition of 1771 omits the phrase
                            following the scriptural quotation.</p>
                    </note> or, in one word, our
                    salvation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>II. What salvation it is which is through this faith is the second thing to be
                    considered.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And, first, whatsoever else it imply, it is a present salvation. It is
                    something attainable, yea, actually attained on earth, by those who are
                    partakers of this faith. For thus saith the Apostle to the believers at Ephesus,
                    and in them to the believers of all ages, not, ‘Ye <hi rend="italic">shall
                        be</hi>’ (though that also is true), but ‘Ye <hi rend="italic">are</hi>
                    saved through faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Ye are saved (to comprise all in one word) from sin. This is <pb n="122"/>the salvation which is through faith. This is that great salvation foretold by
                    the angel before God brought his first-begotten into the world: ‘Thou shalt call
                    his name Jesus, for he shall save his people from their sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 1:21.</p>
                    </note> And
                    neither here nor in other parts of Holy Writ is there any limitation or
                    restriction. All his people, or as it is elsewhere expressed, all that believe
                    in him, he will save from all their sins:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 10:43, etc.</p>
                    </note> from original
                    and actual, past and present sin, of the flesh and of the spirit. Through faith
                    that is in him they are saved both from the guilt and from the power of it.</p>
                <p n="3">3. First, from the guilt of all past sin. For whereas ‘all the world is
                    guilty before God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:19.</p>
                    </note> insomuch that should he
                    ‘be extreme to mark what is done amiss, there is none that could abide it’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 130:3
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> and whereas ‘by the law is only the knowledge of sin’,
                    but no deliverance from it, so that ‘by fulfilling the deeds of the law no flesh
                    can be justified in his sight’; now ‘the righteousness of God, which is by faith
                    of Jesus Christ‘, ‘is manifested unto all that believe’. Now they are ‘justified
                    freely by his grace through the redemption that is in Jesus Christ. Him God hath
                    set forth to be a propitiation through faith in his blood, to declare his
                    righteousness for (or by) the remission of the sins that are past.‘<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            3:20-25.</p>
                    </note> Now hath Christ ‘taken away the curse of the law,
                    being made a curse for us‘.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 3:13.</p>
                    </note> He hath ‘blotted out the
                    handwriting that was against us, taking it out of the way, nailing it to his
                        cross’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Col. 2:14.</p>
                    </note> ‘There is therefore no condemnation now to them
                    which believe in Christ Jesus.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And being saved from guilt, they are saved from fear. Not indeed from a
                    filial fear of offending, but from all servile fear, from that ‘fear which hath
                        torment’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:18.</p>
                    </note> from fear of punishment, from fear of the
                    wrath of God, whom they now no longer regard as a severe master, but as an
                    indulgent Father. ‘They have not received again the spirit of bondage, but the
                    Spirit of adoption, whereby they cry, Abba, Father: the Spirit itself also
                    bearing witness with their spirit, that they are the children of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:15-16.</p>
                    </note> They are also saved from the fear, though not from
                    the possibility, of falling away<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 2:3. In opposition to all notions of
                            final perseverance Wesley stresses the risks of faith and the dangers of
                            lapsing, even from peak experiences of faith. Cf. Nos. 21, ‘Sermon on
                            the Mount, I’, II.4; 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, I.9; 61, ‘The
                            Mystery of Iniquity’, §30; 76, ‘On Perfection’, proem; 86, <hi rend="italic">A Call to Backsliders</hi>, I.2(3). For the earliest
                            instances of its use see Nos. 133, ‘Death and Deliverance’ (Oct 1,
                            1725), ¶16; and 149, ‘On Love’ (Feb. 20, 1737), §1.See also <hi rend="italic">Predestination Calmly Considered</hi>, §74; <hi rend="italic">Serious Thoughts Upon the Perseverance of the
                                Saints</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 192, Vol. 12 of
                            this edn.); JWJ, May 6, 1742; May 6, 1785; and Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on this text as well as on Heb.
                        6:6.</p>
                    </note> from the grace of God, and coming short of the <pb n="123"/>great and precious promises. They are ‘sealed with the Holy Spirit of promise,
                    which is the earnest of their inheritance’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:13. This sentence is omitted from the
                            edition of 1771.</p>
                    </note> Thus have they ‘peace with God through our
                    Lord Jesus Christ…. They rejoice in hope of the glory of God…. And the love of
                    God is shed abroad in their hearts through the Holy Ghost which is given unto
                        them.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 5:1, 2, 5.</p>
                    </note> And hereby they are ‘persuaded’ (though
                    perhaps not all at all times, nor with the same fullness of persuasion) ‘that
                    neither death, nor life, nor things present, nor things to come, nor height, nor
                    depth, nor any other creature, shall be able to separate them from the love of
                    God, which is in Christ Jesus our Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:38-39.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Again, through this faith they are saved from the power of sin as well
                    as from the guilt of it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In most separate editions the following passage is
                            added: ‘Indeed “the infection of nature doth remain: which hath in
                            itself the nature of sin” [cf. Art. IX, ‘Of Original or Birth Sin’ in
                            The Thirty-nine Articles of Religion; for minor variants, see Appendix,
                            ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV]. For it is “a coming short of the glory of
                            God” [cf. Rom. 3:23]. And St. John accordingly declares, not only that
                            “if a man say he hath not sinned he maketh God a liar” [cf. 1 John
                            1:10], but also, “If we say we have no sin” now remaining “we deceive
                            ourselves” [1 John 1:8]. Many infirmities likewise do remain, whereby we
                            are daily subject to what are called sins of infirmity. And doubtless
                            they are in some sense sins, as being “transgressions of the perfect
                            law” [cf. 1 John 3:4]. And with regard to these it may be said of us all
                            our lives that “in many things we offend all” [Jas. 3:2]. But this
                            notwithstanding, the same Apostle declares….’</p>
                    </note> So the Apostle
                    declares, ‘Ye know that he was manifested to take away our sins, and in him is
                    no sin. Whosoever abideth in him sinneth not.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[1 John] chap. 3, ver.
                            5-6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Again, ‘Little children, let no man deceive you….
                    He that committeth sin is of the devil.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:7-8.</p>
                    </note> ‘Whosoever believeth
                    is born of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:1.</p>
                    </note> And, ‘Whosoever is born of God doth not commit
                    sin; for his seed remaineth in him: and he cannot sin, because he is born of
                        God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:9.</p>
                    </note> Once more, ‘We know that whosoever is born of God
                    sinneth not; but he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, and that wicked one
                    toucheth him not.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Chap. 5, ver. 18.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="6">
                    <pb n="124"/>6. He that is by faith born of God sinneth not,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., ‘sinneth
                            not’, deliberately or intentionally. It is a crucial point for Wesley to
                            distinguish between ‘sins properly so called’ (intentional violations of
                            known laws of God) and indeliberate ‘sins’ of various sorts. Cf. below,
                            No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi> (intro.).</p>
                    </note>
                    (1), by any habitual sin, for all habitual sin is sin reigning; but sin cannot
                    reign in any that believeth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For other references to ‘sin remaining but not
                            reigning’, cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, I.6
                            and n.</p>
                    </note> Nor, (2), by any wilful sin; for his will, while he
                    abideth in the faith, is utterly set against all sin, and abhorreth it as deadly
                    poison. Nor, (3), by any sinful desire; for he continually desireth the holy and
                    perfect will of God;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> and any unholy desire<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">All editions
                            except <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771) read, ‘and any tendency to an
                            unholy desire’.</p>
                    </note> he by the grace of God stifleth in the birth.
                    Nor, (4), doth he sin by infirmities, whether in act, word, or thought; for his
                    infirmities have no concurrence of his will; and without this they are not
                    properly sins. Thus, ‘He that is born of God doth not commit sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9. The
                                <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1746) and the editions stemming from
                            it omit here a passage present in most single editions: ‘<hi rend="italic">hath sin in him</hi>, but’.</p>
                    </note> And though he
                    cannot say he <hi rend="italic">hath not sinned</hi>, yet now ‘<hi rend="italic">he sinneth not</hi>’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. This then is the salvation which is through faith, even in the present
                    world: a salvation from sin and the consequences of sin, both often expressed in
                    the word ‘justification’, which, taken in the largest sense, implies a
                    deliverance from guilt and punishment, by the atonement of Christ actually
                    applied to the soul of the sinner now believing on him, and a deliverance from
                    the power of sin,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771) alters ‘the
                            whole body of sin’ to ‘the power of sin’.</p>
                    </note> through Christ
                    ‘formed in his heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:19; the first and other early editions
                            have ‘Christ gradually “formed in the heart”’.</p>
                    </note> So that he who
                    is thus justified or saved by faith is indeed ‘born again’. He is ‘born again of
                    the Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 3:3, 5, etc. See also Nos. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, III.2 and n.; and 45, ‘The New Birth’.</p>
                    </note>
                    unto a new ‘life which is hid with Christ in God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:3. All editions
                            except the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771) add here: ‘He is a new
                            creature: old things are passed away; all things in him are become new’
                            (2 Cor. 5:17).</p>
                    </note> And as a ‘newborn babe he gladly receives the
                    ἄδολον, the sincere milk of the word, and grows thereby’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 2:2.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘going on in the might of the Lord his God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘from faith to
                        faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            1:17.</p>
                    </note> ‘from grace to grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 1:16.</p>
                    </note> ‘until at length he
                    comes unto a <pb n="125"/>perfect man, unto the measure of the stature of the
                    fullness of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>III. The first usual objection to this is,</p>
                <p n="1">1. That to preach salvation or justification by faith only is to preach
                    against holiness and good works. To which a short answer might be given: it
                    would be so if we spake, as some do, of a faith which was separate from these.
                    But we speak of a faith which is not so, but necessarily productive of all good
                    works and all holiness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The first edition reads: ‘But we speak of a faith
                            which is necessarily inclusive of all good works and all holiness.’ See
                            Appendix ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, for full details of variants. Notice
                            the emphatic correlation here between ‘faith alone’ and ‘good works’,
                            and this within days after ‘Aldersgate’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. But it may be of use to consider it more at large: especially since it
                    is no new objection, but as old as St. Paul’s time, for even then it was asked,
                    ‘Do we not make void the law through faith?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:31. See also the later sermons
                            (Nos. 35, 36) on ‘The Law Established through Faith’, Discourses I and
                            II, both on this text and, together, expounding the same conjunction of
                            saving faith and good works as its fruitage.</p>
                    </note> We answer,
                    first, all who preach not faith do manifestly make void the law, either directly
                    and grossly, by limitations and comments that eat out all the spirit of the
                    text; or indirectly, by not pointing out the only means whereby it is possible
                    to perform it. Whereas, secondly, ‘We establish the law’, both by showing its
                    full extent and spiritual meaning, and by calling all to that living way whereby
                    ‘the righteousness of the law may be fulfilled in them’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.8:4.</p>
                    </note> These,
                    while they trust in the blood of Christ alone, use all the ordinances which he
                    hath appointed, do all the ‘good works which he had before prepared that they
                    should walk therein’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> and enjoy and manifest
                    all holy and heavenly tempers, even the same ‘mind that was in Christ
                        Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. But does not preaching this faith lead men into pride? We answer,
                    accidentally it may. Therefore ought every believer to be earnestly cautioned
                    (in the words of the great Apostle): ‘Because of unbelief the first branches
                    were broken off, and thou standest by faith. Be not high-minded, but fear. If
                    God spared not the natural branches, take heed lest he spare not thee. Behold
                    therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them which fell, severity; but
                    toward thee, goodness, if thou continue in his <pb n="126"/>goodness: otherwise
                    thou also shalt be cut off.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 11:20-22.</p>
                    </note> And while he
                    continues therein, he will remember those words of St. Paul, foreseeing and
                    answering this very objection: ‘Where is boasting, then? It is excluded. By what
                    law? Of works? Nay; but by the law of faith.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 3:27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> If a man
                    were justified by his works, he would have whereof to glory. But there is no
                    glorying for him ‘that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the
                        ungodly’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 4:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> To the same effect are
                    the words both preceding and following the text: ‘God, who is rich in mercy,
                    …even when we were dead in sins, hath quickened us together with Christ (by
                    grace ye are saved), …that he might show the exceeding riches of his grace in
                    his kindness toward us through Christ Jesus. For by grace ye are saved through
                    faith: and that not of yourselves.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Eph. 2:4-5, 7-8.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Of
                    yourselves cometh neither your faith nor your salvation. ‘It is the gift of
                        God,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            2:8.</p>
                    </note> the free, undeserved gift—the faith through which ye are
                    saved, as well as the salvation which he of his own good pleasure, his mere
                    favour, annexes thereto. That ye believe is one instance of his grace; that
                    believing, ye are saved, another. ‘Not of works, lest any man should
                        boast.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:9.</p>
                    </note> For all our works, all our righteousness, which
                    were before our believing, merited nothing of God but condemnation, so far were
                    they from deserving faith, which therefore, whenever given, is not ‘of works’.
                    Neither is salvation of the works we do when we believe. For ‘it is’ then ‘God
                    that worketh in us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 12:6; Eph. 3:20; Phil. 2:13.</p>
                    </note>
                    And, therefore, that he giveth us a reward for what he himself worketh only
                    commendeth the riches of his mercy, but leaveth us nothing whereof to
                        glory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, I.1-4, III.6-7, where the
                            identical point is made once again, much later (1785). For Wesley’s
                            other uses of the <hi rend="italic">in se est</hi> theme, cf. above,
                            Intro., pp. 72-73.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. However, may not the speaking thus of the mercy of God, as saving or
                    justifying freely by faith only, encourage men in sin? Indeed it may and will;
                    many will ‘continue in sin, that grace may abound’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:1.</p>
                    </note> But
                    their blood is upon their own head. The goodness of God ought to lead them to
                        repentance,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 2:4.</p>
                    </note> and so it will those <pb n="127"/>who are sincere of heart. When they know there is yet forgiveness
                    with him, they will cry aloud that he would blot out their sins also through
                    faith which is in Jesus. And if they earnestly cry and faint not, if they seek
                    him in all the means he hath appointed, if they refuse to be comforted till he
                    come, he ‘will come, and will not tarry’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:37.</p>
                    </note> And he can do much
                    work in a short time. Many are the examples in the Acts of the Apostles of God’s
                    working this faith in men’s hearts as quick as lightning falling from heaven. So
                    in the same hour that Paul and Silas began to preach the gaoler <hi rend="italic">repented</hi>, <hi rend="italic">believed</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">was baptized</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 16:30-34.</p>
                    </note>—as were three
                    thousand by St. Peter on the day of Pentecost, who all repented and believed at
                    his first preaching.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 2:37-41.</p>
                    </note> And, blessed be God,
                    there are now many living proofs that he is still thus ‘mighty to save’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        63:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Yet to the same truth, placed in another view, a quite contrary
                    objection is made: ‘If a man cannot be saved by all that he can do, this will
                    drive men to despair.’ True, to despair of being saved by their own works, their
                    own merits or righteousness. And so it ought; for none can trust in the merits
                    of Christ till he has utterly renounced his own. He that ‘goeth about to
                    establish his own righteousness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:3.</p>
                    </note> cannot receive the
                    righteousness of God. The righteousness which is of faith cannot be given him
                    while he trusteth in that which is of the law.</p>
                <p n="6">6. But this, it is said, is an uncomfortable doctrine. The devil spoke like
                    himself, that is, without either truth or shame, when he dared to suggest to men
                    that it is such. ‘Tis the only comfortable one, ‘tis ‘very full of
                        comfort’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:4. Cf. Art. XI, ‘that we are justified by faith only is a
                            most wholesome doctrine and very full of comfort’, in Thirty-nine
                            Articles of Religion. See also the Homily ‘Of Faith’, Pt. III, in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, pp. 37-40.</p>
                    </note> to all
                    self-destroyed, self-condemned sinners. That ‘whosoever believeth on him shall
                    not be ashamed’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 9:33.</p>
                    </note> that ‘the same Lord over all
                    is rich unto all that call upon him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 10:12.</p>
                    </note>—here is comfort, high as
                    heaven, stronger than death! What! Mercy for all? For Zaccheus, a public robber?
                    For Mary Magdalene, a common harlot? Methinks I hear one say, ‘Then I, even I,
                    may hope for mercy!’ And so thou mayst, thou afflicted one, whom none hath
                    comforted! God will not cast out thy prayer. Nay, perhaps he may say the next
                    hour, ‘Be of good cheer, thy sins are forgiven thee;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 9:2.</p>
                    </note> so
                    forgiven that they shall <pb n="128"/>reign over thee no more; yea, and that
                    ‘the Holy Spirit shall bear witness with thy spirit that thou art a child of
                        God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note> O glad tidings! Tidings of great joy, which are
                    sent unto all people.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 2:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘Ho, everyone that
                    thirsteth, come ye to the waters; come ye and buy without money, and without
                        price.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 55:1.</p>
                    </note> Whatsoever your sins be, ‘though red, like
                        crimson’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 1:18.</p>
                    </note> though ‘more than the hairs of your
                        head’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 40:12.</p>
                    </note> ‘return ye unto the Lord, and he will have mercy
                    upon you, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                    55:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. When no more objections occur, then we are simply told that salvation by
                    faith only ought not to be preached as the first doctrine, or at least not to be
                    preached to all. But what saith the Holy Ghost? ‘Other foundation can no man lay
                    than that which is laid, even Jesus Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 3:11.</p>
                    </note> So, then, ‘that
                    whosoever believeth on him shall be saved’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:16; Mark 16:16.</p>
                    </note> is and
                    must be the foundation of all our preaching; that is, must be preached first.
                    ‘Well, but not to all.’ To whom then are we not to preach it? Whom shall we
                    except? The poor? Nay, they have a peculiar right to have the gospel preached
                    unto them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 11:5; Luke 7:22.</p>
                    </note> The unlearned? No. God hath revealed
                    these tidings unto unlearned and ignorant men<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 4:13.</p>
                    </note> from the beginning.
                    The young? By no means. ‘Suffer these’ in any wise ‘to come unto Christ, and
                    forbid them not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 10:14.</p>
                    </note> The sinners? Least of
                    all. He ‘came not to call the righteous, but sinners to repentance’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark
                        2:17.</p>
                    </note> Why then, if any, we are to except the rich, the learned,
                    the reputable, the moral men. And ‘tis true, they too often except themselves
                    from hearing; yet we must speak the words of our Lord. For thus the tenor of our
                    commission runs: ‘Go and preach the gospel to every creature.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 16:15.</p>
                    </note> If
                    any man wrest it or any part of it to his destruction, he must bear his own
                        burden.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 6:5.</p>
                    </note> But still, ‘as the Lord liveth, whatsoever the
                    Lord saith unto us, that we will speak.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Kgs. 22:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. At this time more especially will we speak, that ‘by grace ye are saved
                    through faith:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:8.</p>
                    </note> because never was the
                    maintaining this doctrine more seasonable than it is at this day. Nothing but
                    this can effectually prevent the increase of the Romish delusion among us. ‘Tis
                    endless to attack one by one all the errors of that <pb n="129"/>Church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Orig., ‘that
                            apostate Church’, revised in <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1746) and
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771).</p>
                    </note> But salvation by
                    faith strikes at the root, and all fall at once where this is established. It
                    was this doctrine (which our Church justly calls ‘the strong rock and foundation
                    of the Christian religion’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. ‘Of Salvation’, Pt. II, in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p. 22.</p>
                    </note>) that first drove popery out of
                    these kingdoms, and ‘tis this alone can keep it out. Nothing but this can give a
                    check to that immorality which hath overspread the land as a flood. Can you
                    empty the great deep drop by drop? Then you may reform us by dissuasives from
                    particular vices. But let ‘the righteousness which is of God by faith’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil.
                        3:9.</p>
                    </note> be brought in, and so shall its proud waves be stayed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Job
                            38:11.</p>
                    </note> Nothing but this can stop the mouths of those who
                    ‘glory in their shame’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:19.</p>
                    </note> ‘and openly deny the
                    Lord that bought them’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> They can talk as
                    sublimely of the law as he that hath it written by God in his heart. To hear
                    them speak on this head might incline one to think they were not far from the
                    kingdom of God. But take them out of the law into the gospel; begin with the
                    righteousness of faith, with ‘Christ, the end of the law to everyone that
                        believeth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:4.</p>
                    </note> and those who but now
                    appeared almost if not altogether Christians<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>.</p>
                    </note> stand confessed the sons of
                        perdition,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 17:12; 2 Thess. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> as far from life and salvation
                    (God be merciful unto them!) as the depth of hell from the height of heaven.</p>
                <p n="9">9. For this reason the adversary so rages whenever ‘salvation by faith’ is
                    declared to the world. For this reason did he stir up earth and hell to destroy
                    those who first preached it. And for the same reason, knowing that faith alone
                    could overturn the foundations of his kingdom, did he call forth all his forces,
                    and employ all his arts of lies and calumny, to affright that glorious champion
                    of the Lord of Hosts, Martin Luther, from reviving it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘that glorious champion of
                            the Lord of Hosts…’ was dropped from the text in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I (1746). For an earlier evaluation of Luther, cf. JWJ,
                            June 15-16, 1741; see also No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.9 and n. for other references to
                        Luther.</p>
                    </note> Nor can we wonder thereat. For as that man of God
                    observes, ‘How would it enrage a proud strong man armed to be stopped and set at
                    nought by a little child, coming against him with a reed in his hand!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Not yet located
                            in Luther’s own words. But cf. Samuel Clarke, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Marrow of Ecclesiastical Historie</hi> (1650), p. 97, which Wesley
                            had read.</p>
                    </note>—especially when he knew that little child would
                    surely overthrow him and tread him under foot. ‘Even so, Lord Jesus!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                            22:20.</p>
                    </note> Thus hath thy strength been ever ‘made perfect in
                        weakness’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 12:9.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="130"/>Go forth then, thou little child that believest in him, and his
                    ‘right hand shall teach thee terrible things’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 45:4.</p>
                    </note> Though thou art
                    helpless and weak as an infant of days, the strong man shall not be able to
                    stand before thee. Thou shalt prevail over him, and subdue him, and overthrow
                    him, and trample him under thy feet. Thou shalt march on under the great Captain
                    of thy salvation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘conquering and to
                        conquer’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 6:2.</p>
                    </note> until all thine enemies are destroyed, and ‘death
                    is swallowed up in victory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 15:54.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
                <p>Now thanks be to God which giveth us the victory through our Lord Jesus
                        Christ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 15:57.</p>
                    </note> to whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghost, be
                    blessing and glory, and wisdom, and thanksgiving, and honour, and power, and
                    might, for ever and ever. Amen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.7:12. This use of a concluding ascription would
                            seem conventional enough, especially in such a sermon, <hi rend="italic">ad aulam</hi>. It is, however, quite rare for Wesley: only nine of
                            his collected sermons carry such ascriptions: Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>; 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of
                            Adoption’; 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’; 29, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, IX’; 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’; 63, ‘The General
                            Spread of the Gospel’; 71, ‘Of Good Angels’ (a collect); 85, ‘On Working
                            Out Our Own Salvation’ (where the benediction serves as an ascription);
                            107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’ (where Wesley uses the Preface to the Sanctus
                            as an ascription). Note that neither No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, nor No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, appears in this list. Nine of the early
                            ‘uncollected’ sermons have formal ascriptions: Nos. 133, ‘Death and
                            Deliverance’; 134, ‘Seek First the Kingdom’; 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’;
                            136, ‘On Mourning for the Dead’; 137, ‘On Corrupting the Word of God‘;
                            140, ‘The Promise of Understanding’; 141, ‘The Image of God’; 146, ‘The
                            One Thing Needful’; and 150, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>