<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 53: On the Death of George Whitefield</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 53: On the Death of George Whitefield</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="325" to="346"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:325"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>On its face, this is scarcely more than a heartfelt tribute from one great
                    evangelist to another, a eulogy for a brother minister fallen before his time in
                    a splendid career. Certainly, it was thus intended and thus may be read But if
                    one notices a certain formality in its tone or any lack of fervency, an
                    understanding of its peculiar circumstances could be helpful. Actually, this
                    sermon was the epilogue to a complex history of friendly rivalry and open
                    conflict that would have been vivid in the memories of its first hearers and
                    readers. This history has yet to be explored in sufficient depth, despite the
                    massive but partisan biographical studies of Seymour, <hi rend="italic">Countess
                        of Huntingdon</hi>, and Tyerman’s twin ‘Lives’ of John Wesley (3 vols.) and
                    George Whitefield (2 vols.). But it was a more decisive influence in the course
                    of the Evangelical Revival than has been fully realized.</p>
                <p>Its occasion was not only solemn; it was downright awkward, and called for all
                    the diplomacy and aplomb that Wesley could muster. Three months before (August
                    7-10, 1770), Wesley and his ‘Conference’ had issued a public warning to all
                    Methodists who ‘had leaned too much toward Calvinism’. This had given huge
                    offence to Whitefield’s closest friends and sponsors—the Countess of Huntingdon
                    and her ‘Connexion’. Even so, they had dutifully complied with Whitefield’s
                    expressed desire that Wesley be invited to preach his funeral sermon; and Wesley
                    had accepted. Behind this lies a fascinating story, some parts of which bear
                    directly upon an understanding of the sermon itself.</p>
                <p>George Whitefield, close on his eighteenth birthday, had come up to Oxford in
                    1732 from his lowly origins in Gloucester to become a humble ‘servitor’ at
                    Pembroke College, across St. Aldate’s Street from lordly Christ Church. He soon
                    heard about ‘the Methodists’ and admired them at a distance, but was not
                    admitted to ‘the Holy Club’ until the winter of 1735. Thus, he was too young to
                    be included in the Georgia expedition (and he was also not yet ordained).
                    Instead, he spent a year of informal ministry in and around Gloucester and
                    Bristol, experienced his ‘new birth’ long before the Wesleys, and was ordained
                    deacon by Bishop Martin Benson in Gloucester Cathedral, June 20, 1736.
                    Personally <pb n="02:326"/>diffident and self-deprecating, he discovered an
                    extraordinary talent for dramatic preaching, and quickly became the most popular
                    preacher in England, with nine published sermons to his credit (one on ‘New
                    Birth’, another on ‘The Almost Christian’, and a third on ‘Justification by
                    Faith’), all before his twenty-third birthday, and still only a deacon.
                    Moreover, he owed none of this success to the Wesleys, whom he had quickly
                    eclipsed in fame and notoriety.</p>
                <p>Nevertheless, he was interested in their Georgia mission and at their belated
                    invitation decided to join them. The venture was, however, delayed, for various
                    reasons, until February 1738. Indeed, he was in Deal harbour, ready to sail
                    westward on February 7, his exuberantly hopeful departure making a poignant
                    contrast to the dispirited homecoming of John Wesley. Wesley wrote Whitefield a
                    hasty note, advising him to abandon his mission and return to London; see
                    Tyerman, Life of Rev. George Whitefield (1876-77), I.114-16. Whitefield ignored
                    this, of course, and thereafter was greatly vindicated by his almost instant
                    success in Georgia. The colonists responded eagerly to his eloquence, and even
                    William Stephens found his preaching impressive:</p>
                <quote>May 21, 1738. Mr. Whitefield officiated this day at the church and made a
                    sermon very engaging to the most thronged congregation I had ever seen
                    there.</quote>
                <quote>May 28th. Mr. Whitefield manifests great ability in the ministry and his
                    sermons today were very moving.</quote>
                <quote>July 2nd. Mr. Whitefield gains more and more on the affections of the people,
                    by his labour and assiduity in the performance of divine offices [as a deacon!]
                    to which an open and easy deportment without show of austerity or singularity of
                    behaviour in conversation contribute not a little…. [Obviously, Stephens is here
                    contrasting Whitefield with his predecessor.]</quote>
                <p>By temperament, however, Whitefield was indisposed toward a settled ministry, and
                    was back in England before the year was out, preaching and raising money for
                    both his ‘Charity Schools’ and a projected ‘Orphans’ House’ in Georgia. On
                    January 14, 1739, he was ordained priest in Christ Church Cathedral, Oxford, by
                    Bishop Benson, who was acting for Bishop Secker and also for Bishop Gibson of
                    London, who had agreed with the Georgia Trustees that Whitefield should return
                    to Savannah as rector. For this unusual ordination, Lady Huntingdon and some of
                    her noble friends (e.g., the Duchess of Marlborough) had come as lay sponsors.
                    Shortly thereafter, Whitefield began to preach in the fields of Kingswood
                    (February 17) and was promptly threatened with excommunication by the Chancellor
                    of the diocese (February 20). Disregarding this, he went from success to success
                    in his new irregular <pb n="02:327"/>ministry—and even managed to involve a
                    reluctant John Wesley in it.</p>
                <p>Five months later, he was on his way back to America with a collection of £2,530
                    for his cherished Orphanage (on a five hundred acre tract of land donated by the
                    Georgia Trustees). In the course of the next thirty years he raised more than
                    £3,000 for this project. Moreover, he added five more evangelistic missions to
                    America and, despite his untimely death at fifty-five, he had left a permanent
                    mark on American Christianity as a part of the first ‘Great Awakening’. It was a
                    career more spectacular than Wesley’s in almost all respects, save only that he
                    left no organization to carry on his work and also that his message left a scant
                    residue of original ideas. But, as a popular spokesman for the prevailing
                    Puritan piety, he had no peer in his time.</p>
                <p>In his doctrine, predestination was more presupposed than argued out, but he
                    asserted it so vigorously that Wesley came to regard it not only as a denial of
                    ‘free-will’ but as an encouragement to the relaxation of Christian <hi
                        rend="italic">discipline</hi>. This is what Stephens had noticed in
                    Georgia—and had approved. Moreover, Whitefield’s <hi rend="italic"
                    >Journals</hi>, published in 1738-39, were candid beyond prudence and had made
                    him an easy target for his critics. They pounced on his unguarded expressions of
                    ‘enthusiasms’ (claims to ‘direct inspiration’) and on his equally unguarded
                    invectives against the Establishment (cf. his comment that ‘Archbishop Tillotson
                    knew no more about true Christianity than Mahomet’). When ‘Methodism’ was
                    attacked (as by Bishop Gibson), it was Whitefield who was more often in view
                    than the brothers Wesley—somewhat to their exasperation.</p>
                <p>Although his first protests against Whitefield’s ‘overemphasis’ had been private,
                    Wesley felt divinely led (in 1740) to preach <hi rend="italic">and publish</hi>
                    a harsh attack upon the doctrine and all its partisans, in a sermon called <hi
                        rend="italic">Free Grace</hi> (see No. 110). This caused an irreparable
                    breach between what became ‘two sorts of Methodists’. Wesley and Whitefield both
                    sought reconciliation, short of compromise—and Whitefield never lost his
                    personal admiration for Wesley and for his mission. But Seymour’s insight on
                    this point is shrewd: ‘Mr. Wesley and Mr. Whitefield interchanged letters not
                    very frequently, and they preached occasionally in each other’s pulpits; but
                    there was no cordial intercourse—no hearty cooperation. Such a wound as had been
                    made in their friendship always leaves a scar…. Nevertheless, they did justice
                    to each other’s intentions and virtues…’ (Seymour, <hi rend="italic">Countess of
                        Huntingdon</hi>, I.474).</p>
                <p>Wesley reports two important approaches to reconciliation in 1766—in January (see
                    JWJ for the 31st) and August (17 and 24), on <pb n="02:328"/>the eve of
                    Whitefield’s departure for America, from which he never returned. The latter is
                    especially illuminating:</p>
                <quote>It was at the earnest request of the Countess of Huntingdon, whose heart God
                    has turned again, that I came hither [to meet Whitefield in London]; and if no
                    other good result from it but our firm union with Mr. Whitefield, it is abundant
                    recompense for my labour. My brother and I conferred with him every day, and we
                    resolved…by the grace of God, to go on hand in hand through honour and
                    dishonour.</quote>
                <p>They would not meet again on earth.</p>
                <p>But tensions between Wesley and the Calvinists continued:</p>
                <quote>Many were not a little surprised in the evening [of Aug. 25] at seeing me in
                    the Countess of Huntingdon’s chapel. The congregation was not only large but
                    serious, and I fully delivered my own soul. So I am in no concern whether I
                    preach there again or no.</quote>
                <p>He never did.</p>
                <p>Whitefield’s seventh mission to America ended in Newburyport, Massachusetts, on
                    September 30, 1770. His untimely death and the extraordinary outpouring of grief
                    and honour that followed are lovingly recounted in John Gillies, <hi
                        rend="italic">Memoirs of the Life of the Rev. G. Whitefield, M.A.</hi>, in
                    his collected edition of Whitefield’s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771-72),
                    VII.269-346.</p>
                <quote>The melancholy news of Mr. Whitefield’s death reached London on Monday, Nov.
                    5, 1770, by the <hi rend="italic">Boston Gazette</hi> and by three letters from
                    different persons at Boston, to his friend Mr. Keen, who also by the same post
                    received two of [Whitefield’s] own handwriting, written in health (one seven and
                    the other five days before his death). Mr. Keen had the melancholy event
                    notified the same night at the Tabernacle [Moorfields] and the next night at
                    Tottenham Court Chapel. His next step was to consider of the proper person to
                    preach the funeral sermon; and recollecting he had often said to Mr. Whitefield,
                    ‘If you should die abroad, whom shall we get to preach your funeral sermon? Must
                    it be your old friend, the Rev. Mr. John Wesley?’ And having received constantly
                    for answer, ‘He is the man’, Mr. Keen accordingly waited on the Rev. Mr. Wesley
                    on the Saturday following [Nov. 10] and engaged him to preach it on the Lord’s
                    day, Nov. 18, which he did to a very large, crowded, and mournful auditory, many
                    hundreds going away who could not possibly get in (p. 276).</quote>
                <p>Wesley’s record of this is in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for November
                    10:</p>
                <quote>I returned to London and had the melancholy news of Mr. Whitefield’s death
                    confirmed by his executors, who desired me to preach his funeral sermon on
                    Sunday the 18th. In order to write this, I retired to Lewisham on Monday, and on
                    Sunday following went to the chapel in Tottenham Court Road…. It was an awful
                    season. All were still as night; most appeared to be deeply affected; and an
                    impression was made on many which one would hope will not speedily be
                    effaced.</quote>
                <quote>The time appointed for my beginning at the Tabernacle [in Upper Moorfields,
                    three hundred yards from the Foundery] was half-hour after five, but it was
                    quite filled at three, so I began at four…. Oh that all may hear the voice of
                    him with whom are the <pb n="02:329"/>issues of life and death; and who so
                    loudly, by this unexpected stroke, calls all his children to love one another.
                    (See also <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for November 23.)</quote>
                <p>The untypically fulsome title-page of this sermon suggests Wesley’s sense that it
                    was, in some sense or other, the official memorial. There were, however, dozens
                    of others both in America and England by closer friends and colleagues than
                    Wesley; see Gillies’s <hi rend="italic">Extracts</hi> from ‘Some of the Funeral
                    Sermons Preached on the Occasion of [Whitefield’s] Death’, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Memoirs</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, VII.292-346. What is obvious
                    is that Wesley was ‘thoroughly sensible how difficult it [was for him] to speak
                    on so delicate a subject [under those circumstances]; what prudence is
                    required…to say neither too little nor too much’ (II.3). The bulk of the sermon
                    is a summary of Whitefield’s early career drawn chiefly from his <hi
                        rend="italic">Journals</hi>, to which are added excerpts from <hi
                        rend="italic">The Boston Gazette</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The London
                        Evening Post</hi>. The conclusion is a moving tribute to one whose talents
                    for dramatic oratory were clearly greater than his own. The only inlet for
                    controversy would come in Wesley’s claim that the essence of Whitefield’s gospel
                    could be ‘summed up in two words, “the new birth” and “justification by faith”’.
                    His offer to edit and publish Whitefield’s writings (see below, I.17) was quite
                    sincere but quietly ignored. That assignment went to Dr. John Gillies.</p>
                <p>One of Whitefield’s most ardent admirers, William Romaine, had already been
                    outraged by the anti-Calvinist ‘Minute’ and was further offended by what he
                    regarded as Wesley’s presumption. In the ensuing issue of <hi rend="italic">The
                        Gospel Magazine</hi> (January 1771) he attacked both the sermon and the
                    preacher. His objection to the sermon was its <hi rend="italic">text</hi>: ‘How
                    improper to apply the words of a mad prophet [Balaam] to so holy a man as Mr.
                    Whitefield!’ But his main complaint was Wesley’s falsification, as he saw it, of
                    Whitefield’s essential teaching. ‘On the contrary, the grand fundamental
                    doctrines which [Whitefield] everywhere preached were the everlasting covenant
                    between the Father and the Son and absolute predestination flowing therefrom.’
                    Wesley’s cool reply to this may be seen in his open letter to <hi rend="italic"
                        >Lloyd’s Evening Post</hi>, March 1, 1771.</p>
                <p>This, and much more, lay behind what must have been, for Wesley, one of his most
                    difficult ‘occasions’. It was a labour of love, an exercise in honest candour,
                    an unaccustomed venture in diplomacy. The sermon went through five editions in
                    two years and was not thereafter reprinted in Wesley’s lifetime; he omitted it
                    from <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I-VIII (1787-88). For this publishing history
                    and a list of variant readings, see Appendix, Vol. 4; see also <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bibliog</hi>, No. 324.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:330"/>
            <head>On the Death of George Whitefield</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Numbers 23:10</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Let me die the death of the righteous, and let my last end be
                        like his!</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <p>1. ‘Let my last end be like his!’ How many of you join in this wish? Perhaps
                    there are few of you who do not, even in this numerous congregation. And Oh!
                    that this wish may rest upon your minds! That it may not die away till your
                    souls also are lodged ‘where the wicked cease from troubling, and where the
                    weary are at rest’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 3:17; the text and an echo of Wesley’s
                            early sermon, No. 109, <hi rend="italic">The Trouble and Rest of Good
                                Men</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p>2. An elaborate exposition of the text will not be expected on this occasion. It
                    would detain you too long from the sadly-pleasing thought of your beloved
                    brother, friend, and pastor; yea, and father too; for how many are here whom he
                    hath ‘begotten in the Lord’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 4:15.</p></note> Will it not then be
                    more suitable to your inclinations, as well as to this solemnity, directly to
                    speak of this man of God whom you have so often heard speaking in this
                    place?—‘the end of whose conversation’ ye know, ‘Jesus Christ, the same
                    yesterday, today, and for ever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:7-8.</p></note></p>
                <p>And may we not,</p>
                <p>First, observe a few particulars of his life and death;</p>
                <p>Secondly, take some view of his character; and,</p>
                <p>Thirdly, inquire how we may improve this awful providence, his sudden removal
                    from us.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>I. 1. We may, in the first place, observe a few particulars of his life and
                    death. He was born at Gloucester in December 1714,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Dec. 16.</p></note> and put to a
                    grammar-school there when about twelve years old.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">St. Mary de Crypt.<hi
                                rend="bold color(FF0000)">t</hi></p></note> When he was seventeen he
                    began to be seriously religious, and served God to the best of his knowledge.
                    About eighteen he <pb n="02:331"/>removed to the university, and was admitted at
                    Pembroke College in Oxford. And about a year after he became acquainted with the
                    Methodists (so called), whom from that time he loved as his own soul.</p>
                <p>2. By them he was convinced that we ‘must be born again’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">John 3:7.</p></note> or outward
                    religion will profit us nothing. He joined with them in fasting on Wednesdays
                    and Fridays, in visiting the sick and the prisoners, and in gathering up the
                    very fragments of time, that no moment might be lost; and he changed the course
                    of his studies, reading chiefly such books as entered into the heart of
                    religion, and led directly to an experimental knowledge of Jesus Christ and him
                        crucified.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Cor. 2:2.</p></note></p>
                <p>3. He was soon tried as with fire. Not only his reputation was lost, and some of
                    his dearest friends forsook him, but he was exercised with inward trials, and
                    those of the severest kind. Many nights he lay sleepless upon his bed, many days
                    prostrate on the ground. But after he had groaned several months under ‘the
                    spirit of bondage’, God was pleased to remove the heavy load by giving him ‘the
                    spirit of adoption’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p></note> enabling him, through a
                    living faith, to lay hold on ‘the Son of his love’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">A paraphrase of ὁ υἱός μου ὁ
                            ἀγαπητός (as in Matt. 3:17; 17:5; and 2 Pet. 1:17: ‘my beloved
                            son’).</p></note></p>
                <p>4. However, it was thought needful for the recovery of his health, which was much
                    impaired, that he should go into the country. He accordingly went to Gloucester,
                    where God enabled him to awaken several young persons. These soon formed
                    themselves into a little society, and were some of the first-fruits of his
                    labour. Shortly after he began to read twice or thrice a week to some poor
                    people in the town, and every day to read to and pray with the prisoners in the
                    county gaol.</p>
                <p>5. Being now about twenty-one years of age, he was solicited to enter into holy
                    orders. Of this he was greatly afraid, being deeply sensible of his own
                    insufficiency. But the bishop himself sending for him, and telling him, ‘Though
                    I had purposed to ordain none under three and twenty, yet I will ordain <hi
                        rend="italic">you</hi> whenever you come;’ and several other providential
                    circumstances concurring, he submitted, and was ordained on Trinity Sunday,
                        1736.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">June
                            20th.</p></note> The next Sunday he preached to a crowded auditory in
                    the church wherein <pb n="02:332"/>he was baptized. The week following he
                    returned to Oxford and took his bachelor’s degree. And he was now fully
                    employed; the care of the prisoners and the poor lying chiefly on him.</p>
                <p>6. But it was not long before he was invited to London to serve the cure of a
                    friend going into the country.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Thomas Broughton (1712-77), curate of the Tower of
                            London. He had been active in the Holy Club.</p></note> He continued
                    there two months, lodging in the Tower, reading prayers in the chapel twice a
                    week, catechizing and preaching once, besides daily visiting the soldiers in the
                    barracks and the infirmary. He also read prayers every evening at Wapping Chapel
                    and preached at Ludgate prison every Tuesday. While he was here letters came
                    from his friends in Georgia which made him long to go and help them. But not
                    seeing his call clear, at the appointed time he returned to his little charge at
                    Oxford; where several youths met daily at his room to ‘build up each other in
                    their most holy faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Jude 20.</p></note></p>
                <p>7. But he was quickly called from hence again to supply the cure of Dummer in
                        Hampshire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >As curate to Charles Kinchin (1711-42), another Oxford
                        Methodist.</p></note> Here he read prayers twice a day, early in the morning
                    and in the evening after the people came from work. He also daily catechized the
                    children, and visited from house to house. He now divided the day into three
                    parts, allotting eight hours for sleep and meals, eight for study and
                    retirement, and eight for reading prayers, catechizing, and visiting the people.
                    Is there a more excellent way for a servant of Christ and his church? If not,
                    who will ‘go and do likewise’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 10:37.</p></note></p>
                <p>8. Yet his mind still ran on going abroad. And being now fully convinced he was
                    called of God thereto, he set all things in order, and in January 1737 went down
                    to take leave of his friends in Gloucester. It was in this journey that God
                    began to bless his ministry in an uncommon manner. Wherever he preached, amazing
                    multitudes of hearers flocked together, in Gloucester, in Stonehouse,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Revd. Sampson
                            Harris was the incumbent of St. Cyril’s parish church in Stonehouse,
                            Gloucestershire. Whitefield preached in his pulpit and then in the
                            churchyard to overflowing crowds.</p></note> in Bath, in Bristol; so
                    that the heat of the churches was scarce supportable. And the impressions made
                    on the minds of many were no less extraordinary. After his return to London,
                    while he was detained by General Oglethorpe<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="16"><p rend="footnote text">A retrospective reference to James Edward
                            Oglethorpe (1696-1785), one of the chief promoters and defenders of the
                            Georgia colony; Oglethorpe’s promotion to brigadier-general did not come
                            until 1743.</p></note> from week to <hi n="02:333"/> week and from month
                    to month, it pleased God to bless his word still more. And he was indefatigable
                    in his labour: generally on Sunday he preached four times, to exceeding large
                    auditories; besides reading prayers twice or thrice, and walking to and fro,
                        often<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >‘Often’ is inserted only in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                        1771.</p></note> ten or twelve miles.</p>
                <p>9. On December 28 [1737] he left London. It was on the 29th that he first
                    preached without notes. December 30 he went on board;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">The <hi rend="italic"
                                >Whitaker</hi>, from Purfleet.</p></note> but it was above a month
                    before they cleared the land. One happy effect of their very slow passage he
                    mentions in April following: ‘Blessed be God, we now live very comfortably in
                    the great cabin. We talk of little else but God and Christ. […] And scarce a
                    word is heard among us when together but what has reference to our fall in the
                    first, and our new birth in the Second Adam.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19"
                        n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">George Whitefield’s
                                Journals</hi>, ed., Iain Murray (London, Banner of Truth Trust,
                            1960), p. 149.</p></note> It seems likewise to have been a peculiar
                    providence that he should spend a little time at Gibraltar, where both citizens
                    and soldiers, high and low, young and old, acknowledged the day of their
                    visitation.</p>
                <p>10. From Sunday, May 7, 1738, till the latter end of August following, he ‘made
                    full proof of his ministry’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 4:5.</p></note> in Georgia, particularly
                    at Savannah. He read prayers and expounded twice a day, and visited the sick
                    daily. On Sunday he expounded at five in the morning; at ten read prayers and
                    preached, and at three in the afternoon; and at seven in the evening expounded
                    the Church catechism. How much easier is it for our brethren in the ministry,
                    either in England, Scotland, or Ireland, to find fault with such a labourer in
                    our Lord’s vineyard than to tread in his steps!</p>
                <p>11. It was now that he observed the deplorable condition of many children here;
                    and that God put into his heart the first thought of founding an orphan-house,
                    for which he determined to raise contributions in England, if God should give
                    him a safe return thither. In December following he did return to London, and on
                    Sunday, January the 14th, 1739, he was ordained priest at Christ Church, Oxford.
                    The next day he came to London again; and on Sunday 21st preached twice. But
                    though the churches were large, and crowded exceedingly, yet many hundred stood
                    in <hi n="02:334"/> the churchyard, and hundreds more returned home. This put
                    him upon the first thought of preaching in the open air. But when he mentioned
                    it to some of his friends, they judged it to be mere madness. So he did not
                    carry it into execution till after he had left London. It was on Wednesday,
                    February 21, that finding all the church doors to be shut in Bristol (beside
                    that no church was able to contain one half of the congregation) at three in the
                    afternoon he went to Kingswood and preached abroad, to near two thousand people.
                    On Friday he preached there to four or five thousand; and on Sunday to (it was
                    supposed) ten thousand. The number continually increased all the time he stayed
                    at Bristol. And a flame of holy love was kindled, which will not easily be put
                    out. The same was afterwards kindled in various parts of Wales, of
                    Gloucestershire, and Worcestershire. Indeed wherever he went God abundantly
                    confirmed the word of his messenger.</p>
                <p>12. On Sunday, April 29, he preached the first time in Moorfields, and on
                    Kennington Common.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A then open tract of public ground on ‘the Surrey
                            side of the Thames’ across from Pimlico and just beyond the celebrated
                            Vauxhall ‘pleasure gardens’. Cf. Earl of Egmont, <hi rend="italic">Diary
                                of Viscount Percival, Afterwards First Earl of Egmont</hi> (London,
                            Historical Manuscripts Commission, 1920-23), III.64, 67-69, for an
                            eyewitness account of Whitefield’s open air preaching on Woolwich Common
                            (June 5, 1739) and on Charlton Green (June 8).</p></note> And the
                    thousands of hearers were as quiet as they could have been in a church. Being
                    again detained in England from month to month, he made little excursions into
                    several counties, and received the contributions of willing multitudes for an
                    orphan-house in Georgia. The embargo which was now laid on the shipping<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Because of the
                            tense situation in the West Indies, which led to open war (Oct. 19,
                            1739); it was ‘the prelude to a struggle for dominion, lasting nearly a
                            quarter of a century, between England and the Bourbon powers’; cf. Basil
                            Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Whig Supremacy</hi>, p. 203; see also,
                            pp. 197-200, 220-21.</p></note> gave him leisure for more journeys
                    through various parts of England, for which many will have reason to bless God
                    to all eternity. At length, on August 14, he embarked. But he did not land in
                    Pennsylvania till October 30. Afterwards he went through Pennsylvania, the
                    Jerseys, New York, Maryland, Virginia, North and South Carolina, preaching all
                    along to immense congregations, with full as great effect as in England. On
                    January 10, 1740, he arrived at Savannah.</p>
                <p>13. January 29 he added three desolate orphans to near twenty which he had in his
                    house before. The next day he laid out the ground for the house, about ten miles
                    from Savannah. February <pb n="02:335"/>11 he took in four orphans more, and set
                    out for Frederica<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                            rend="footnote text">On St. Simon’s Island, where Charles Wesley had
                            served briefly as minister. Cf. CWJ, Mar. 9-May 13, 1736.</p></note> in
                    order to fetch the orphans that were in the southern parts of the colony. In his
                    return he fixed a school, both for children and grown persons, at Darien,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">A settlement of
                            Scottish Highlanders at the mouth of the Altamaha River, seventy-three
                            miles southwest of Savannah. Cf. JWJ, Dec. 2, 1737.</p></note> and took
                    four orphans thence. March 25 he laid the first stone of the orphan-house, to
                    which, with great propriety, he gave the name of ‘Bethesda’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">See John 5:2.</p></note>—a
                    work for which the children yet unborn shall praise the Lord. He had now about
                    forty orphans, so that there were near an hundred mouths to be fed daily. But he
                    was ‘careful for nothing’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:6.</p></note> casting his care on him who
                    ‘feedeth the young ravens that call upon him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                        n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 147:9 (BCP).</p></note></p>
                <p>14. In April he made another tour through Pennsylvania, the Jerseys, and New
                    York. Incredible multitudes flocked to hear, among whom were abundance of
                    Negroes. In all places the greater part of the hearers were affected to an
                    amazing degree. Many were deeply convinced of their lost state; many truly
                    converted to God. In some places thousands cried out aloud; many as in the
                    agonies of death; most were drowned in tears; some turned pale as death; others
                    were wringing their hands; others lying on the ground; others sinking into the
                    arms of their friends; almost all lifting up their eyes, and calling for
                    mercy.</p>
                <p>15. He returned to Savannah June 5. The next evening during the public service
                    the whole congregation, young and old, were dissolved in tears. After service
                    several of the parishioners, and all his family, particularly the little
                    children, returned home crying along the street, and some could not help praying
                    aloud. The groans and cries of the children continued all night, and great part
                    of the next day.</p>
                <p>16. In August he set out again, and through various provinces came to Boston.
                    While he was here and in the neighbouring places he was extremely weak in body.
                    Yet the multitudes of hearers were so great, and the effects wrought on them so
                    astonishing, as the oldest men then alive in the town had never seen before. The
                    same power attended his preaching at New York; particularly on Sunday, November
                    2, almost as soon as he began, crying, weeping, and wailing were to be heard on
                    every <hi n="02:336"/> side. Many sunk down to the ground, cut to the heart; and
                    many were filled with divine consolation. Toward the close of his journey he
                    made this reflection: ‘It is the seventy-fifth day since I arrived at Rhode
                    Island, exceeding weak in body. Yet God has enabled me to preach an hundred and
                    seventy-five times in public, beside exhorting frequently in private. Never did
                    God vouchsafe me greater comforts. Never did I perform my journeys with less
                    fatigue, or see such a continuance of the divine presence in the congregations
                    to whom I preached.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Whitefield, <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, p.
                            499 (Dec. 1, 1740).</p></note> In December he returned to Savannah, and
                    in the March following arrived in England.</p>
                <p>17. You may easily observe that the preceding account is chiefly extracted from
                    his own <hi rend="italic">Journals</hi>, which, for their artless and unaffected
                    simplicity, may vie with any writings of the kind. And how exact a specimen is
                    this of his labours both in Europe and America for the honour of his beloved
                    Master during the thirty years that followed! As well as of the uninterrupted
                    shower of blessings wherewith God was pleased to succeed his labours! Is it not
                    much to be lamented that anything should have prevented his continuing this
                    account till at least near the time when he was called by his Lord to enjoy the
                    fruit of his labours? If he has left any papers of this kind, and his friends
                    account me worthy of the honour, it would be my glory and joy to methodize,
                    transcribe, and prepare them for the public view.</p>
                <p>18. A particular account of the last scene of his life is thus given by a
                    gentleman of Boston:</p>
                <quote>After being about a month with us in Boston and its vicinity, and preaching
                    every day, he went to Old York,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Then in ‘New Hampshire’; now York Village,
                            Maine.</p></note> preached on Thursday, September 27, there; proceeded
                    to Portsmouth and preached there on Friday. On Saturday morning he set out for
                    Boston; but before he came to Newbury,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Newburyport, Mass.</p></note> where he had
                    engaged to preach the next morning, he was importuned to preach by the way. The
                    house not being large enough to contain the people, he preached in an open
                    field. But having been infirm for several weeks, this so exhausted his strength
                    that when he came to Newbury he could not get out of the ferry-boat without the
                    help of two men. In the evening, however, he recovered his spirits and appeared
                    with his usual cheerfulness. He went to his chamber at nine, his fixed time,
                    which no company could divert him from; and slept better than he had done for
                    some weeks before. He rose at four in the morning, September 30, and went into
                    his closet; and his companion observed he was unusually long in private. He left
                    his <pb n="02:337"/>closet, returned to his companion, threw himself on the bed,
                    and lay about ten minutes. Then he fell upon his knees, and prayed most
                    fervently to God that if it was consistent with his will he might that day
                    finish his Master’s work. He then desired his man to call Mr. Parsons,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Jonathan Parsons
                            (1705-76), minister of the Old South Church of Newburyport.</p></note>
                    the clergyman at whose house he was; but in a minute, before Mr. Parsons could
                    reach him, died without a sigh or groan. On the news of his death, six gentlemen
                    set out for Newbury in order to bring his remains hither, but he could not be
                    moved, so that his precious ashes must remain at Newbury. Hundreds would have
                    gone from this town to attend his funeral had they not expected he would have
                    been interred here…. May this stroke be sanctified to the church of God in
                    general, and to this province in particular!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                        n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Presumably from one of those ‘three letters
                            from different persons at Boston’ which Robert Keen would have brought
                            to Wesley, along with his copy of the <hi rend="italic">Boston
                                Gazette</hi>—see above, p. 328.</p></note></quote>
            </div>
            <div><p>II. 1. We are, in the second place, to take some view of his character. A little
                    sketch of this was soon after published in the <hi rend="italic">Boston
                        Gazette</hi>, an extract of which is subjoined:</p>
                <quote>Little can be said of him but what every friend to vital Christianity who has
                    sat under his ministry will attest. In his public labours he has for many years
                    astonished the world with his eloquence and devotion. With what divine pathos
                    did he persuade the impenitent sinner to embrace the practice of piety and
                    virtue! Filled with the spirit of grace, he spoke from the heart, and with a
                    fervency of zeal perhaps unequalled since the days of the apostles, adorned the
                    truths he delivered with the most graceful charms of rhetoric and oratory. From
                    the pulpit he was unrivalled in the command of an ever-crowded auditory. Nor was
                    he less agreeable and instructive in his private conversation: happy in a
                    remarkable ease of address, willing to communicate, studious to edify. May the
                    rising generation catch a spark of that flame which shone with such
                    distinguished lustre in the spirit and practice of this faithful servant of the
                    most high God!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Abridged from an editorial in <hi rend="italic">The Massachusetts
                                Gazette, and Boston Post-Boy and The Advertizer</hi>, No. 684 (Mon.
                            Oct. 1, 1770), p. 3. The news itself had been reported in the same paper
                            the day before.</p></note></quote>
                <p>2. A more particular, and equally just character of him, has appeared in one of
                    the English papers. It may not be disagreeable to you to add the substance of
                    this likewise:</p>
                <quote>The character of this truly pious person must be deeply impressed on the
                    heart of every friend to vital religion. In spite of a tender and delicate
                    constitution he continued to the last day of his life preaching with a frequency
                    and a fervour that seemed to exceed the natural strength of the most robust.
                    Being called to the exercise of his function at an early age, when most young
                    men are only beginning to qualify themselves for it, he had not time to make a
                    very considerable progress in the learned languages. But this defect was amply
                        <pb n="02:338"/>supplied by a lively and fertile genius, by fervent zeal,
                    and by a forcible and most persuasive delivery. And though in the pulpit he
                    often found it needful by ‘the terrors of the Lord to persuade men’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            5:11.</p></note> he had nothing gloomy in his nature, being singularly
                    cheerful, as well as charitable and tender-hearted. He was as ready to relieve
                    the bodily as the spiritual necessities of those that applied to him. It ought
                    also to be observed that he constantly enforced upon his audience every moral
                    duty, particularly industry in their several callings, and obedience to their
                    superiors. He endeavoured by the most extraordinary efforts of preaching in
                    different places, and even in the open fields, to rouse the lower class of
                    people from the last degree of inattention and ignorance to a sense of religion.
                    For this and his other labours the name of George Whitefield will long be
                    remembered with esteem and veneration.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">An abridgement from <hi rend="italic">The
                                London Evening Post</hi> for Nov. 10, 1770 (No. 1607), p. 4. Sugden
                            cites it as from <hi rend="italic">The London Chronicle</hi> for Nov. 6,
                            but that paper carried only an announcement of Whitefield’s death
                            without the eulogy quoted here. The <hi rend="italic">Post</hi>’s
                            encomium was then reprinted in <hi rend="italic">The Scots Magazine</hi>
                            (Dec. 1770, XXXII.574-75), as from a ‘Lond[on]
                    pap[er]’.</p></note></quote>
                <p>3. That both these accounts are just and impartial will readily be allowed; that
                    is, as far as they go. But they go little farther than the <hi rend="italic"
                        >outside</hi> of his character. They show you the <hi rend="italic"
                        >preacher</hi>, but not the <hi rend="italic">man</hi>, the <hi
                        rend="italic">Christian</hi>, the <hi rend="italic">saint</hi> of God. May I
                    be permitted to add a little on this head from a personal knowledge of near
                    forty years? Indeed, I am thoroughly sensible how difficult it is to speak on so
                    delicate a subject, what prudence is required to avoid both extremes, to say
                    neither too little nor too much. Nay, I know it is impossible to speak at all,
                    to say either less or more, without incurring from some the former, from others
                    the latter censure. Some will seriously think that too little is said, and
                    others that it is too much. But without attending to this I will speak just what
                    I know, before him to whom we are all to give an account.</p>
                <p>4. Mention has already been made of his unparalleled <hi rend="italic">zeal</hi>,
                    his indefatigable <hi rend="italic">activity</hi>, his <hi rend="italic"
                        >tender-heartedness</hi> to the afflicted, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >charitableness</hi> toward the poor. But should we not likewise mention his
                    deep <hi rend="italic">gratitude</hi> to all whom God had used as instruments of
                    good to him? Of whom he did not cease to speak in the most respectful manner,
                    even to his dying day? Should we not mention that he had a heart susceptible of
                    the most generous and the most tender <hi rend="italic">friendship</hi>? I have
                    frequently thought that this, of all others, was the distinguishing part of his
                    character. How few have we known of so kind a temper, of such large and flowing
                    affections! Was it not principally by this that the hearts of others were so
                    strangely drawn and knit to him? Can anything but love <pb n="02:339"/>beget
                    love? This shone in his very countenance, and continually breathed in all his
                    words, whether in public or private. Was it not this, which, quick and
                    penetrating as lightning, flew from heart to heart? Which gave that life to his
                    sermons, his conversations, his letters? Ye are witnesses.</p>
                <p>5. But away with the vile misconstruction of men of corrupt minds, who know of no
                    love but what is ‘earthly and sensual’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 3:15.</p></note> Be it remembered at
                    the same time that he was endued with the most nice and unblemished <hi
                        rend="italic">modesty</hi>. His office called him to converse very
                    frequently and largely with women as well as men; and those of every age and
                    condition. But his whole behaviour toward them was a practical comment on that
                    advice of St. Paul to Timothy, ‘Entreat the elder women as mothers, the younger
                    as sisters, with all purity.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 5:1-2.</p></note></p>
                <p>6. Meantime, how suitable to the friendliness of his spirit was the <hi
                        rend="italic">frankness</hi> and <hi rend="italic">openness</hi> of his
                    conversation! Although it was as far removed from rudeness on the one hand as
                    from guile and disguise on the other. Was not this frankness at once a fruit and
                    a proof of his <hi rend="italic">courage</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >intrepidity</hi>? Armed with these, he feared not the faces of men, but
                    ‘used great plainness of speech’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 3:12.</p></note> to persons of every
                    rank and condition, high and low, rich and poor; endeavouring only ‘by
                    manifestation of the truth’ to ‘commend himself to every man’s conscience in the
                    sight of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 2 Cor. 4:2.</p></note></p>
                <p>7. Neither was he afraid of labour or pain, any more than of ‘what man could do
                    unto him’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 13:6.</p></note> being equally</p>
                <l><hi rend="italic">Patient</hi></l> in bearing ill and doing well.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Samuel Wesley, Jun.,
                        ‘The Battle of the Sexes’, st. xxxv, l. 8, in <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>
                        (1736), p. 38; cf. John Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and
                            Sacred Poems</hi> (1744), III.33. See also, No. 83, ‘On Patience’, §7;
                        his letters to Richard Morgan, Dec. 17, 1733, and Penelope Newman, Aug. 12,
                        1744. Cf. Wesley’s obituary of Robert Swindells, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Minutes</hi>, July 29, 1783.</p></note>
                <p>And this appeared in the <hi rend="italic">steadiness</hi> wherewith he pursued
                    whatever he undertook for his Master’s sake. Witness one instance for all, the
                    orphan-house in Georgia, which he began and perfected in spite of all
                    discouragements. Indeed, in whatever concerned himself he was pliant and
                    flexible. In this case he was ‘easy to be entreated’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:17.</p></note> easy to
                    be either convinced or persuaded. But he was immovable in the things of God, or
                    wherever his <hi n="02:340"/> conscience was concerned. None could persuade, any
                    more than affright him, to vary in the least point from that <hi rend="italic"
                        >integrity</hi> which was inseparable from his whole character, and
                    regulated ail his words and actions. Herein he did</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Stand as an iron pillar strong,</l>
                    <l>And steadfast as a wall of brass.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">John and
                            Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1739), p.
                            203 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.180). Cf. Wesley’s letter to
                            the Countess of Huntingdon, Sept. 16, 1773.</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p>8. If it be inquired what was the foundation of this integrity, or of his
                    sincerity, courage, patience, and every other valuable and amiable quality, it
                    is easy to give the answer. It was not the excellence of his natural temper; not
                    the strength of his understanding. It was not the force of education; no, nor
                    the advice of his friends. It was no other than faith in a bleeding Lord: ‘faith
                    of the operation of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Col. 2:12.</p></note> It was ‘a lively hope’ of ‘an
                    inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            1:3-4.</p></note> It was ‘the love of God shed abroad in his heart by
                    the Holy Ghost which was given unto him’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46"
                        n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:5.</p></note> filling his soul
                    with tender, disinterested love to every child of man. From this source arose
                    that torrent of <hi rend="italic">eloquence</hi> which frequently bore down all
                    before it; from this that astonishing force of <hi rend="italic"
                    >persuasion</hi>, which the most hardened sinners could not resist. This it was
                    which often made his ‘head as waters’ and his ‘eyes a fountain of tears’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer.
                        9:1.</p></note> This it was which enabled him to pour out his soul in <hi
                        rend="italic">prayer</hi> in a manner peculiar to himself, with such
                    fullness and ease united together, with such strength and variety both of
                    sentiment and expression.</p>
                <p>9. I may close this head with observing what an honour it pleased God to put upon
                    his faithful servant by allowing him to declare his everlasting gospel in so
                    many various countries, to such numbers of people, and with so great an effect
                    on so many of their precious souls! Have we read or heard of any person since
                    the apostles who testified the gospel of the grace of God through so widely
                    extended a space, through so large a part of the habitable world? Have we read
                    or heard of any person who called so many thousands, so many myriads of sinners
                    to repentance? Above all, have we read or heard of any who has been a blessed
                    instrument in his hand of bringing so many sinners ‘from <pb n="02:341"
                    />darkness to light, and from the power of Satan unto God’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 26:18. On this same day
                            (Nov. 18) Henry Venn was also preaching a similar sermon in the Countess
                            of Huntingdon’s Chapel in Bath (on the text, Isa. 8:18) and agreed with
                            Wesley on this point especially: ‘The greatness and intenseness of his
                            labours…[and] their compass exceeds anything that others can pretend to’
                            (see John Gillies, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, in Whitefield’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi>, VII.332). Tyerman, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Whitefield</hi>, II.619-28, lists seventeen memorial sermons
                            preached and seven as published. At least six other published sermons
                            are in MA. All of them stress the extraordinary impact of Whitefield’s
                            preaching. Augustus Toplady went so far as to declare Whitefield ‘the
                            Apostle of the English empire, …the prince of [all English] preachers’
                            (‘A Concise Character of the Late Rev. Mr. Whitefield’, <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi> [1837], p. 494).</p></note> It is true,
                    were we to talk thus to the gay world we should be judged to ‘speak as
                        barbarians’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 Cor. 14:11.</p></note> But <hi rend="italic">you</hi> understand
                    the language of the country to which you are going, and whither our dear friend
                    is gone a little before us.</p></div>
            <div>
                <p>III. But how shall we improve this awful providence? This is the third thing
                    which we have to consider. And the answer to this important question is easy
                    (may God write it in all our hearts!): by keeping close to the <hi rend="italic"
                        >grand doctrines</hi> which he delivered, and by drinking into his <hi
                        rend="italic">spirit</hi>.</p>
                <p>1. And, first, let us keep close to the grand scriptural doctrines which he
                    everywhere delivered. There are many doctrines of a less essential nature, with
                    regard to which even the sincere children of God (such is the present weakness
                    of human understanding!) are and have been divided for many ages. In these we
                    may think and let think;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6 and
                        n.</p></note> we may ‘agree to disagree’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51"
                        n="51"><p rend="footnote text">In his letter to his brother Charles, Aug.
                            19, 1785, Wesley wrote, ‘We can (as Mr. Whitefield used to say) agree to
                            disagree.’ See also an earlier letter to Charles on Nov. 3, 1775. Cf.
                            Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi>, i.433: ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >Discors concordia</hi>’ (‘agreeing to differ’). St. Bernard of
                            Clairvaux had already phrased the same notion in his letter to Cardinal
                            Hugh of Ostia: ‘It became a matter of discord. But why do I say discord?
                            It was rather a matter of concord, for all the brethren were found to
                            agree completely in disagreeing’ (<hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> [1953],
                            p. 443).</p></note> But meantime let us hold fast the essentials of ‘the
                    faith which was once delivered to the saints’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                        n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Jude 3.</p></note> and which this champion of
                    God so strongly insisted on at all times and in all places.</p>
                <p>2. His fundamental point was: give God all the glory of whatever is good in man.
                    And in the business of salvation, set Christ as high and man as low as possible.
                    With this point he and his friends at Oxford, the original Methodists<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Wesley makes
                            frequent autobiographical references to the Holy Club or ‘the young
                            gentlemen at Oxford’. Cf. Nos. 63, ‘The General Spread of the Gospel’,
                            §13; 79, ‘On Dissipation’, §20; see also 89, ‘The More Excellent Way’,
                            VI.4; 112, <hi rend="italic">On Laying the Foundation of the New
                                Chapel</hi>, I.2, II.15.</p></note> (so called), set out. <pb
                        n="02:342"/>Their grand principle was: there is <hi rend="italic">no
                        power</hi> (by nature) and <hi rend="italic">no merit</hi> in man. They
                    insisted, all power to think, speak, or act right is in and from the Spirit of
                    Christ; and all merit is (not in man, how high soever in grace, but merely) in
                    the blood of Christ. So he and they taught: there is no power in man, till it is
                    given him from above, to do one good work, to speak one good word, or to form
                    one good desire. For it is not enough to say all men are <hi rend="italic">sick
                        of sin</hi>. No, we are all ‘<hi rend="italic">dead</hi> in trespasses and
                        sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            2:1.</p></note> It follows that all the children of men are ‘by nature
                    children of wrath’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:3.</p></note> We are all ‘guilty before
                        God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            3:19.</p></note> liable to death, temporal and eternal.</p>
                <p>3. And we are all helpless, both with regard to the power and to the guilt of
                    sin. For, ‘Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">Job 14:4.</p></note> None less
                    than the Almighty. Who can raise those that are <hi rend="italic">dead</hi>,
                    spiritually dead in sin? None but he who raised us from the dust of the earth.
                    But on what consideration will he do this? ‘Not for works of righteousness that
                    we have done.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Titus 3:5.</p></note> ‘The dead cannot praise thee, O Lord!’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Pss. 88:10;
                            115:17.</p></note> Nor do anything for the sake of which they should be
                    raised to life. Whatever therefore God does, he does it merely for the sake of
                    his well-beloved Son: ‘He was wounded for our transgressions, he was bruised for
                    our iniquities.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Isa. 53:5.</p></note> ‘He himself bore all our sins in his own body
                    upon the tree.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Pet. 2:24.</p></note> ‘He was delivered for our offences, and rose
                    again for our justification.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:25.</p></note> Here then is the sole <hi
                        rend="italic">meritorious cause</hi> of every blessing we do or can enjoy;
                    in particular of our pardon and acceptance with God, of our full and free
                        justification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text">But this conflict between ‘meritorious’ and
                            ‘formal’ causes in justification was one of the controverted issues
                            between Wesley and the Calvinists (including Whitefield). See
                            Whitefield’s Sermon XIV, ‘The Lord Our Righteousness’, in <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi>, V.216-34; and Sermon XV, <hi rend="italic"
                                >ibid.</hi>, pp. 235-50; and cf. Wesley’s No. 20, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Lord our Righteousness</hi>.</p></note> But by what means do we
                    become interested in what Christ has done and suffered? ‘Not by works, lest any
                    man should boast;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:9.</p></note> but by faith alone. ‘We
                    conclude’, says the apostle, ‘that a man is justified by faith, without the
                    works of the law.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:28.</p></note> And ‘to as many as’ thus
                    ‘receive him giveth he power to become the sons of God: even to those that
                    believe in his name, who are born, not of the will of man, but of God.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                            1:12-13.</p></note></p>
                <p><pb n="02:343"/>4. And ‘except a man be thus born again he cannot see the kingdom
                    of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 3:3.</p></note> But all who are thus ‘born of the Spirit’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                        3:5.</p></note> have ‘the kingdom of God within’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 17:21.</p></note>
                    them. Christ sets up his kingdom in their hearts—‘righteousness, peace, and joy
                    in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p></note> That ‘mind is in them which
                    was in Christ Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p></note> enabling them to ‘walk as
                    Christ also walked’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:6.</p></note> His indwelling Spirit
                    makes them both holy in heart and ‘holy in all manner of conversation’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        1:15.</p></note> But still, seeing all this is a free gift through the
                    righteousness and blood of Christ, there is eternally the same reason to
                    remember, ‘he that glorieth, let him glory in the Lord.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 1:31; 2 Cor.
                        10:17.</p></note></p>
                <p>5. You are not ignorant that these are the fundamental doctrines which he
                    everywhere insisted on. And may they not be summed up, as it were, in two
                        words—<hi rend="italic">the new birth</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >justification by faith</hi>? These let us insist upon with all boldness, at
                    all times, and in all places; in public (those of us who are called thereto)
                    and, at all opportunities, in private. Keep close to these good, old,
                    unfashionable doctrines, how many soever contradict and blaspheme. Go on, my
                    brethren, ‘in the name of the Lord, and in the power of his might’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            6:10.</p></note> with all care and diligence ‘keep that safe which is
                    committed to your trust;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:20.</p></note> knowing that ‘heaven
                    and earth shall pass away; but’ this truth ‘shall not pass away’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 24:35,
                            etc.</p></note></p>
                <p>6. But will it be sufficient to keep close to his <hi rend="italic"
                        >doctrines</hi>, how pure soever they are? Is there not a point of still
                    greater importance than this, namely, to drink into his <hi rend="italic"
                        >spirit</hi>? Herein to ‘be a follower of’ him, ‘even as’ he was ‘of
                        Christ’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Cor. 11:1.</p></note> Without this the purity of our doctrines would
                    only increase our condemnation. This, therefore, is the principal thing, to copy
                    after his spirit. And allowing that in some points we must be content to <hi
                        rend="italic">admire</hi> what we cannot <hi rend="italic">imitate</hi>; yet
                    in many others we may, through the same free grace, be partakers of the same
                    blessing. Conscious then of your own wants, and of his bounteous love who
                    ‘giveth liberally and upbraideth not’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:5.</p></note> cry to him that worketh
                    all in all for a measure of the same precious faith; of the same zeal and
                    activity, the same tender-heartedness, charitableness, bowels of mercies.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">See Col.
                            3:12.</p></note> Wrestle <pb n="02:344"/>with God for some degree of the
                    same grateful, friendly, affectionate temper; of the same openness, simplicity,
                    and godly sincerity, ‘love without dissimulation’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:9.</p></note> Wrestle
                    on, till the power from on high works in you the same steady courage and
                    patience; and above all, because it is the crown of all, the same invariable
                    integrity.</p>
                <p>7. Is there any other fruit of the grace of God with which he was eminently
                    endowed, and the want of which among the children of God he frequently and
                    passionately lamented? There is one, that is, <hi rend="italic">catholic
                        love</hi>: that sincere and tender affection which is due to all those who,
                    we have reason to believe, are children of God by faith; in other words, all
                    those in every persuasion who ‘fear God and work righteousness’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 15:2
                            (AV); Eccles. 12:13.</p></note> He longed to see all who had ‘tasted of
                    the good word’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Heb. 6:5.</p></note> of a truly <hi rend="italic">catholic
                        spirit</hi>—a word little understood, and still less experienced, by many
                    who have it frequently in their mouth. Who is he that answers this character?
                    Who is a man of a ‘catholic spirit’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’. Also Richard Baxter,
                                <hi rend="italic">The True Catholick and Catholick Church
                                Described</hi>.</p></note> One who loves as friends, as brethren in
                    the Lord, as joint partakers of the present kingdom of heaven, and fellow-heirs
                    of his eternal kingdom, all, of whatever opinion, mode of worship, or
                    congregation, who believe in the Lord Jesus; who love God and man; who,
                    rejoicing to please and fearing to offend God, are careful to abstain from evil,
                    and zealous of good works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p></note> He is a man of a truly
                    catholic spirit who bears all these continually upon his heart; who having an
                    unspeakable tenderness for their persons, and an earnest desire of their
                    welfare, does not cease to commend them to God in prayer, as well as to plead
                    their cause before men; who speaks comfortably to them, and labours by all his
                    words to strengthen their hands in God. He assists them to the uttermost of his
                    power in all things, spiritual and temporal. He is ready ‘to spend and to be
                        spent’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 12:15.</p></note> for them; yea, to ‘lay down his life for his
                        brethren’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. John 15:13; 1 John 3:16.</p></note></p>
                <p>8. How amiable a character is this! How desirable to every child of God! But why
                    is it then so rarely found? How is it that there are so few instances of it?
                    Indeed, supposing we have tasted of the love of God, how can any of us rest till
                    it is our own! Why, there is <pb n="02:345"/>a delicate device whereby Satan
                    persuades thousands<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 42, ‘Satan’s Devices’; cf. also
                            Whitefield’s Sermon XLVIII, ‘Satan’s Devices’, in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Works</hi>, VI.241-56.</p></note> that they may stop short of it,
                    and yet be guiltless. It is well if many here present are not in this ‘snare of
                    the devil, taken captive at his will’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 2:26.</p></note> ‘O yes’, says one, ‘I
                    have all this love for those I believe to be children of God. But I will never
                    believe he is a child of God who belongs to that <hi rend="italic">vile
                        congregation</hi>! Can he, do you think, be a child of God who holds such
                        <hi rend="italic">detestable opinions</hi>? Or he that joins in such
                    senseless and superstitious, if not idolatrous worship?’ So we justify ourselves
                    in one sin by adding a second to it! We excuse the want of love in ourselves by
                    laying the blame on others. To colour our own devilish temper we pronounce our
                    brethren children of the devil. O beware of this! And if you are already taken
                    in the snare, escape out of it as soon as possible. Go and learn that truly
                    catholic love which ‘is not rash or hasty’ in judging; that love which ‘thinketh
                    no evil’, which ‘believeth and hopeth all things’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:4, 5,
                        7.</p></note> which makes all the allowances for others that we desire
                    others should make for us. Then we shall take knowledge of the grace of God
                    which is in every man, whatever be his opinion or mode of worship. Then will all
                    that fear God be near and dear unto us ‘in the bowels of Jesus Christ’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            1:8.</p></note></p>
                <p>9. Was not this the spirit of our dear friend? And why should it not be ours? O
                    thou God of love, how long shall thy people be a by-word among the heathen?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 44:14
                            (AV).</p></note> How long shall they laugh us to scorn, and say, ‘See
                    how <hi rend="italic">these</hi> Christians love one another!’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text">Tertullian, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Apology</hi>, ch. 39, §7; see No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’,
                            III.18 and n.</p></note> When wilt thou roll away our reproach?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">See Josh.
                            5:9.</p></note> ‘Shall the sword devour for ever? How long will it be
                    ere thou bid thy people return from following each other?’ Now at least ‘let all
                    the people stand still, and pursue after’ their brethren ‘no more’!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Sam. 2:26,
                            28.</p></note> But whatever others do, let all of us, my brethren, hear
                    the voice of him that ‘being dead, yet speaketh’!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:4.</p></note> Suppose
                    ye hear him say: ‘Now at least “be ye followers of me as I was of Christ!”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            11:1.</p></note> Let brother “no more lift up sword” against brother,
                    neither “know ye war any more”!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 2:4; Mic. 4:3.</p></note> Rather “put ye
                    on, as the elect of God, bowels of mercies, humbleness of mind, brotherly
                    kindness, gentleness, long-suffering, forbearing one another in love.”<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col.
                            3:12-13.</p></note> Let the time past <pb n="02:346"/>suffice for
                    strife, envy, contention, for “biting and devouring one another”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            5:15.</p></note> Blessed be God that ye have not long ago been “consumed
                    one of another”!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p
                            rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> From
                    henceforth hold ye “the unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace”.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        4:3.</p></note></p>
                <p>10. O God, with thee no word<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p
                            rend="footnote text">All published edns. read ‘word’; but is this a
                            printer’s misreading of ‘work’?</p></note> is impossible: thou dost
                    whatsoever pleaseth thee! O that thou wouldst cause the mantle of thy prophet,
                    whom thou hast taken up, now to fall upon us that remain! ‘Where is the Lord God
                    of Elijah?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="footnote text">2
                            Kgs. 2:14.</p></note> ‘Let’ his ‘spirit rest upon’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">2 Kgs. 2:9, 15.</p></note>
                    these thy servants! Show thou art the God that ‘answerest by fire’!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Kgs.
                            18:24.</p></note> Let the fire of thy love fall on every heart! And
                    because we love thee, let us love one another with a ‘love stronger than
                        death’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. S. of S. 8:6.</p></note> ‘Take away from us all anger, and wrath,
                    and bitterness; all clamour, and evil-speaking.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:31.</p></note>
                    Let thy Spirit so rest upon us that from this hour we may ‘be kind to each
                    other, tender-hearted; forgiving one another, even as God for Christ’s sake hath
                    forgiven us’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Eph. 4:32.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>An HYMN</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>I</l>
                    <l>Servant of God, well done!</l>
                    <l>Thy glorious warfare’s past,</l>
                    <l>The battle’s fought, the race is won,</l>
                    <l>And thou art crowned at last;</l>
                    <l>Of all thy heart’s desire</l>
                    <l>Triumphantly possessed,</l>
                    <l>Lodged by the ministerial choir</l>
                    <l>In thy Redeemer’s breast.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>II</l>
                    <l>In condescending love</l>
                    <l>Thy ceaseless prayer He heard,</l>
                    <l>And bade thee suddenly remove</l>
                    <l>To thy complete reward:</l>
                    <l>Ready to bring the peace,</l>
                    <l>Thy beauteous feet were shod,</l>
                    <l>When mercy signed thy soul’s release</l>
                    <l>And caught thee up to God.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>III</l>
                    <l>With saints enthroned on high</l>
                    <l>Thou dost thy Lord proclaim,</l>
                    <l>And still to God salvation cry,</l>
                    <l>Salvation to the Lamb!</l>
                    <l>O happy, happy soul!</l>
                    <l>In ecstasies of praise,</l>
                    <l>Long as eternal ages roll,</l>
                    <l>Thou seest thy Saviour’s face.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg>
                    <l>IV</l>
                    <l>Redeemed from earth and pain,</l>
                    <l>Ah! when shall we ascend,</l>
                    <l>And all in Jesus’ presence reign</l>
                    <l>With our translated friend!</l>
                    <l>Come, Lord, and quickly come !</l>
                    <l>And when in thee complete,</l>
                    <l>Receive thy longing servants home,</l>
                    <l>To triumph—at thy feet!</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p rend="footnote text">By Charles
                            Wesley (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, VI.316-17); this hymn, almost
                            certainly included in the sermon as delivered, would have served as the
                            rhetorical equivalent of an ascription.</p></note>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
