<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 73: Of Hell</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon073</idno>                        
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 73: Of Hell</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume III: Sermons III,
                                71-114</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1986-11-01">1986-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="3"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="31"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="44"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="03:030"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>This is a sermon on yet another topic about which Wesley had previously written
                    very little and which, apparently, had not bulked large in his oral preaching
                    save as it mirrored the conventional eschatological ideas of the day. As early
                    as 1731, in Oxford, he had preached from Mark 9:48; he had used the same text
                    again in 1770. Still later, in 1788, he would produce another sermon on hell and
                    heaven (see No. 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’). In all of these his views of hell and
                    perdition were wholly conventional; already he had, as a matter of course,
                    included the phrase, ‘descended into hell’ in the text of the Apostles’ Creed in
                    his revision of the Order of Morning Prayer in <hi rend="italic">The Sunday
                        Service</hi> (1784), and he would never have approved its omission by the
                    American Methodists (1786 and thereafter). When Wesley’s references to hell
                    (here and elsewhere) are compared to a classical Puritan statement like Jonathan
                    Edwards’s famous ‘Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God’ (first preached in 1741
                    and then published as Sermon XV in <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Various
                        Subjects</hi>, 1765), Wesley’s emphases seem low-keyed. But when compared to
                    a more direct source (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, Isaac Watts, Discourses XII
                    and XIII on Mark 9:46, in <hi rend="italic">The World to Come…</hi> [1745], in
                        <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.705-52), the resemblances are striking. If
                    anything, Wesley’s tone is more severe than Watts’s.</p>
                <p>‘Of Hell’ was finished on October 10, 1788, at Newport on the Isle of Wight; it
                    was, therefore, written on the road during a regular preaching mission (cf. JWJ,
                    October 7-11). One may guess that it was written expressly for inclusion in the
                        <hi rend="italic">Arminian Magazine</hi> since it promptly appeared there,
                    without a title but numbered as ‘Sermon XII’ in the ensuing issues (Vol. V,
                    1782, November and December, pp. 565-69, 623-32)—i.e., <hi rend="italic">before</hi> the twin sermons on angels. In <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, VI,
                    he reversed this order and placed ‘Of Hell’ after the other two (i.e., pp.
                    147-69). It was reprinted separately in 1789 and 1790, with a different title,
                    ‘The Eternity of Hell Torments’. What is more distinctive than the doctrines in
                    this sermon are Wesley’s applications of them, and his obvious efforts to update
                    them with illustrations both from the traditional sources and contemporary ones
                    as well.</p>
                <p><pb n="03:031"/>Wesley had already included an eschatological discourse on 2 Pet.
                    3:10-13, by James Knight, in his own collected <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>
                    (1773), XX.290-321; cf. Knight, <hi rend="italic">A Discourse on the
                        Conflagration and Renovation of the World</hi> (1736). A copy of Wesley’s
                    extract is still extant—in the Methodist Archives in the John Rylands Library,
                    Manchester—in a hand closely resembling Wesley’s own (but probably by John
                    Jones). It had the following quaint superscript that would date from somewhere
                    toward the end of the nineteenth century:</p>
                <quote>The celebrated John Wesley gave this to a Mr. Whitney who gave it to Ann
                    Livingston of Deptford, who, after giving it to Mrs. Eleanor Smith, she in her
                    turn, gave it to John Overton of Rose Cottage, Kings Road, Chelsea.</quote>
            </introduction>
            <head>Of Hell</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Mark 9:48</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Every truth which is revealed in the oracles of God is undoubtedly of
                    great importance. Yet it may be allowed that some of those which are revealed
                    therein are of greater importance than others, as being more immediately
                    conducive to the grand end of all, the eternal salvation of men. And we may
                    judge of their importance even from this circumstance, that they are not
                    mentioned once only in the sacred writings, but are repeated over and over. A
                    remarkable instance of this we have with regard to the awful truth which is now
                    before us. Our blessed Lord, who uses no superfluous words, who makes no ‘vain
                        repetitions’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:7.</p></note> repeats it over and over in the same chapter, and
                    as it were in the same breath. So verse 43, 44: ‘If thy hand offend thee’, if a
                    thing or person as useful as a hand be an occasion of sin, and there is no other
                    way to shun that sin, ‘cut it off. It is better for thee to enter into life
                    maimed, than having two hands to go into hell; into <pb n="03:032"/>unquenchable
                    fire, where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.’ So again, verse
                    45,46: ‘If thy foot offend thee, cut it off. It is better for thee to enter halt
                    into life, than having two feet to be cast into hell; into unquenchable fire,
                    where their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.’ And yet again, verse
                    47, 48: ‘If thine eye’, a person or thing as dear as thine eye, ‘offend thee’,
                    hinder thy running the race which is set before thee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:1.</p></note> ‘pluck
                    it out: it is better for thee to enter into the kingdom of God with one eye,
                    than having two eyes to be cast into hell-fire; where their worm dieth not, and
                    the fire is not quenched.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. And let it not be thought that the consideration of these terrible
                    truths is proper only for enormous sinners. How is this supposition consistent
                    with what our Lord speaks to those who were then doubtless the holiest men upon
                    earth? ‘When innumerable multitudes were gathered together, he said to his
                    disciples’ (the apostles) ‘first of all, I say unto you, my friends, Fear not
                    them that can kill the body, and after that have no more that they can do. But I
                    say unto you, Fear him who after he hath killed hath power to cast into hell;
                    yea, I say unto you, Fear him!’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Luke 12:1, 4-5.</p></note></hi> Yea, fear him
                    under this very notion, of having power to cast into hell; that is, in effect,
                    fear lest he should cast you into the place of torment.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 16:28.</p></note> And this
                    very fear, even in the children of God, is one excellent means of preserving
                    them from it.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It behoves therefore not only the outcasts of men but even ‘you, his
                    friends’, you that fear and love God, deeply to consider what is revealed in the
                    oracles of God concerning the future state of punishment. How widely distant is
                    this from the most elaborate accounts which are given by the heathen authors!
                    Their accounts are (in many particulars at least) childish, fanciful, and
                    self-inconsistent. So that it is no wonder they did not believe themselves, but
                    only related the tales of the vulgar. So Virgil strongly intimates, when, after
                    the laboured account he had given of the shades beneath, he sends him that had
                    related it out at the ivory gate, through which (as he tells us) only <hi rend="italic">dreams</hi> pass; thereby giving us to know that all the
                    preceding account is no more than a <pb n="03:033"/>dream.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, vi.893-98:</p><p rend="Verse">Sunt geminae Somni
                            portae; quarum altera, fertur</p><p rend="Verse">Cornea, qua veris
                            facilis datur exitus umbris,</p><p rend="Verse">Altera candenti perfecta
                            nitens elephanto,</p><p rend="Verse">Sed falsa ad caelum mittunt
                            insomnia Manes.</p><p rend="Verse">His ubi tum natum Anchises unaque
                            Sibyllam</p><p rend="Verse">Prosequitur dictis portaque emittit
                            eburna.</p><p rend="footnote text">Dryden’s translation (which Wesley
                            had in mind) stresses the image of ‘the ivory gate’:</p><p rend="Verse">Two gates the silent house of Sleep adorn;</p><p rend="Verse">Of
                            polish’d iv’ry this, that of transparent horn:</p><p rend="Verse">True
                            visions thro’ transparent horn arise;</p><p rend="Verse">Thro’ polish’d
                            iv’ry pass deluding lies,</p><p rend="Verse">Of various things
                            discoursing as he pass’d,</p><p rend="Verse">Anchises hither bends his
                            steps at last</p><p rend="Verse">Then, thro’ the gate of iv’ry, he
                            dismiss’d</p><p rend="Verse">His valiant offspring and divining
                            guest.</p><p rend="footnote text">Virgil’s source was Homer, <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>, xix.562-67; cf. also No. 132, ‘On Faith,
                            Heb. 11:1’, §16.</p></note> This he only insinuates; but his brother
                    poet, Juvenal, speaks out flat and plain:</p>
                <lg><l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Esse aliquos manes, et subterranea regna, …</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Nec pueri credunt, nisi qui nondum aere
                    lavantur</hi></l></lg><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Juvenal, <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi>, ii. 149,152:
                        ‘There are [stories about] the Manes [ghosts and infernal deities] and the
                        underworld…that children do not believe except those too young to be allowed
                        in the public baths.’ The Latin quotation, with a slightly different
                        translation, is repeated in No. 132, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §17. Hesiod also
                        speaks of ‘spiritual creatures’ which Milton then versifies; see No. 70,
                        ‘The Case of Reason Impartially Considered’, II.1 and n.</p></note>—
                    <p>‘Even our children do not believe a word of the tales concerning another
                    world.’</p>
                <p n="4">4. Here, on the contrary, all is worthy of God the Creator, the Governor of
                    mankind. All is awful and solemn, suitable to his wisdom and justice by whom
                    ‘Tophet was ordained of old’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 30:33.</p></note> although originally
                    ‘prepared’, not for the children of men, but ‘for the devil and his
                        angels’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            25:41.</p></note></p>
                <p>The punishment of those who in spite of all the warnings of God resolve to have
                    their portion with the devil and his angels<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> will,
                    according to the ancient and not improper division, be either <hi rend="italic">poena damni</hi>, what they lose, or <hi rend="italic">poena sensus</hi>,
                    what they feel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. one of Wesley’s favourite essays, Thomas Boston, <hi rend="italic">Human Nature in Its Fourfold State</hi> (1720), State IV, Head VI,
                            pp 424 ff. The idea, however, comes from a familiar scholastic
                            distinction between the punishment of bereavement and deprivation (<hi rend="italic">poena damni</hi>), i.e., of what had been valued in
                            this life, and the active punishment of the bodily senses (<hi rend="italic">poena afflictiva seu sensus</hi>). Cf. Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologia</hi>, Appendix I, Q. 2, Art. 1
                            [Respondeo], and cf. R. J. Deferrari (ed), <hi rend="italic">A Lexicon
                                of St. Thomas</hi> (1948), 844, for definitions and citations from
                            Thomas. The idea, of course, runs back to patristic eschatology, cf. the
                            article on ‘Hölle’, in <hi rend="italic">Lexikon für Theologie und
                                Kirche</hi>.</p></note> After <pb n="03:034"/>considering these
                    separately I shall touch on a few additional circumstances, and conclude with
                    two or three inferences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, let us consider <hi rend="italic">the poena damni</hi>,
                    the punishment of loss. This commences in that very moment wherein the soul is
                    separated from the body; in that instant the soul loses all those pleasures, the
                    enjoyment of which depends on the outward senses. The smell, the taste, the
                    touch delight no more; the organs that ministered to them are spoiled, and the
                    objects that used to gratify them are removed far away. In the dreary regions of
                    the dead all these things are forgotten; or, if remembered, are only remembered
                    with pain, seeing they are gone for ever. All the pleasures of the imagination
                    are at an end.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">For more instances of this phrase, ‘pleasures of the imagination’, see
                            No. 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, II.10 and n.</p></note>
                    There is no grandeur in the infernal region; there is nothing beautiful in those
                    dark abodes, no light but that of livid flames. And nothing new, but one
                    unvaried scene of horror upon horror. There is no music but that of groans and
                    shrieks, of weeping, wailing, and gnashing of teeth;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 8:12;
                        13:42.</p></note> of curses and blasphemies against God, or cutting
                    reproaches of one another. Nor is there anything to gratify the sense of honour:
                    no, they are the heirs of shame and everlasting contempt.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Dan. 12:2.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. Thus are they totally separated from all the <hi rend="italic">things</hi> they were fond of in the present world. At the same instant
                    will commence another loss—that of all the <hi rend="italic">persons</hi> whom
                    they loved. They are torn away from their nearest and dearest relations, their
                    wives, husbands, parents, children, and (what to some will be worse than all
                    this) the friend which was as their own soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Sam. 18:1, 3; 20:17; and No. 47,
                            ‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’, III.4.</p></note> All the
                    pleasure they ever enjoyed in these is lost, gone, vanished away. For there is
                    no friendship in hell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">The thesis of J.-P. Sartre, <hi rend="italic">Huis
                                Clos</hi> (Paris, Gallimard, 1947); translated by Stuart Gilbert as
                                <hi rend="italic">No Exit</hi> (New York, Knopf, 1948).</p></note>
                    Even the poet who affirms (though I know not on what authority),</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Devil with devil damned</l>
                    <l>Firm concord holds;</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                        ii.496-97.</p>
                </note>
                <p><pb n="03:035"/>does not affirm that there is any concord among the human fiends
                    that inhabit the great abyss.</p>
                <p n="3">3. But they will then be sensible of a greater loss than that of all they
                    enjoyed on earth. They have lost their place in Abraham’s bosom,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        16:22.</p></note> in the paradise of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">Rev. 2:7.</p></note> Hitherto indeed it hath
                    not entered into their hearts to conceive what holy souls enjoy in the garden of
                        God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Ezek.
                            28:13; 31:8, 9.</p></note> in the society of angels, and of the wisest
                    and best men that have lived from the beginning of the world (not to mention the
                    immense increase of knowledge which they will then undoubtedly receive). But
                    they will then fully understand the value of what they have vilely cast
                    away.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But as happy as the souls in paradise are, they are preparing for far
                    greater happiness. For paradise is only the porch of heaven; and it is there the
                    spirits of just men are made perfect.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:23. In Wesley’s eschatology, paradise
                            was regarded as only ‘the ante-chamber of heaven’(cf. Nos. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, II.4; and 115, ‘Dives and
                            Lazarus’, I.3 and n.); he sharply distinguished this from what he
                            understood of the Roman Catholic doctrine of purgatory.</p></note> It is
                    in heaven only that there is the fullness of joy, the pleasures that are at
                    God’s right hand for evermore.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 16:11 (AV).</p></note> The loss of this by
                    those unhappy spirits will be the completion of their misery. They will then
                    know and feel that God alone is the centre of all created spirits; and
                    consequently that a spirit made for God can have no rest out of him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, I.i; cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Steepest’</hi>, II.5 and n.</p></note> It seems
                    that the Apostle had this in his view when he spoke of those ‘who shall be
                    punished with everlasting destruction from the presence of the Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">2 Thess.
                        1:9.</p></note> Banishment from the presence of the Lord is the very essence
                    of destruction to a spirit that was made for God. And if that banishment lasts
                    for ever, it is ‘everlasting destruction’.</p>
                <p>Such is the loss sustained by those miserable creatures on whom that awful
                    sentence will be pronounced, ‘Depart from me, ye cursed!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:41.</p></note> What
                    an unspeakable curse, if there were no other! But alas! This is far from being
                    the whole; for to the punishment of <hi rend="italic">loss</hi> will be added
                    the punishment of <hi rend="italic">sense</hi>. What they lose implies
                    unspeakable misery, which yet is inferior to what they feel. This it is which
                    our Lord expresses in those emphatical words, ‘where their worm dieth not, and
                    the fire is not quenched’.</p>
            </div>
            <pb n="03:036"/>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. From the time that sentence was pronounced upon man, ‘Dust thou art,
                    and unto dust thou shalt return,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 3:19.</p></note> it was the custom of all
                    nations, so far as we can learn, to commit dust to dust: it seemed natural to
                    restore the bodies of the dead to the general mother earth. But in process of
                    time another method obtained, chiefly among the rich and great, of burning the
                    bodies of their relations, and frequently in a grand magnificent manner. For
                    which purpose they erected huge funeral piles, with immense labour and expense.
                    By either of these methods the body of man was soon restored to its parent dust.
                    Either the worm or the fire soon consumed the well-wrought frame; after which
                    the worm itself quickly died, and the fire was entirely quenched. But there is
                    likewise a worm that belongs to the future state; and that is a worm that never
                    dieth. And there is a fire hotter than that of the funeral pile; and it is a
                    fire that will never be quenched.</p>
                <p n="2">2. The first thing intended by the worm that never dieth seems to be a
                    guilty conscience, including self-condemnation, sorrow, shame, remorse, and a
                    sense of the wrath of God. May not we have some conception of this by what is
                    sometimes felt even in the present world? Is it not of this chiefly that Solomon
                    speaks when he says, ‘The spirit of a man may bear his infirmities’, his
                    infirmities or griefs of any other kind, ‘but a wounded spirit who can
                        bear?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Prov. 18:14.</p></note> Who can bear the anguish of an awakened
                    conscience, penetrated with a sense of guilt, and the arrows of the Almighty
                    sticking in the soul, and drinking up the spirit!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">See Job 6:4.</p></note> How
                    many of the stout-hearted have sunk under it, and chose strangling rather than
                        life!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Job 7:15.</p></note> And yet what are these wounds, what is all this
                    anguish of a soul while in this present world, in comparison of those they must
                    suffer when their souls are wholly awakened to feel the wrath of an offended
                    God! Add to these all unholy passions, fear, horror, rage; evil desires, desires
                    that can never be satisfied. Add all unholy tempers, envy, jealousy, malice, and
                    revenge; all of which will incessantly gnaw the soul, as the vulture was
                    supposed to do the liver of Tityus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Homer, <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi>,
                            xi.576-81. Tityus was ‘a son of Earth’ whose body covered ‘nine acres’
                            and who was punished for his assault upon Leto by having two vultures to
                            tear away at his liver. This is to be distinguished from the more
                            familiar Promethean myth in Hesiod’s <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi>
                            where, for stealing fire from heaven and giving it to man, Prometheus is
                            punished by being chained to a rock where an eagle gnawed away at his
                            liver even as it was also continually renewed. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Theogony</hi>, 559-86 for the story of the ‘crime’ and 521-25 for
                            the ‘punishment’; cf. also No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important
                                Question</hi>, III.10. In No. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great
                                Assize</hi>, III.2, Wesley defines pride, malice, revenge, rage,
                            horror, despair as the ‘dogs of hell’.</p></note> To these if we <pb n="03:037"/>add hatred of God and all his creatures—all these united
                    together may serve to give us some little, imperfect idea of the worm that never
                    dieth.</p>
                <p n="3">3. We may observe a remarkable difference in the manner wherein our Lord
                    speaks concerning the two parts of the future punishment. He says, ‘Where <hi rend="italic">their</hi> worm dieth not’ of the one; ‘where <hi rend="italic">the</hi> fire is not quenched’ of the other. This cannot be by
                    chance. What then is the reason for this variation of the expression?</p>
                <p>Does it not seem to be this? ‘The fire’ will be the same, essentially the same,
                    to all that are tormented therein—only perhaps more intense to some than others,
                    according to their degree of guilt. But ‘their worm’ will not, cannot be the
                    same. It will be infinitely varied according to the various kinds as well as
                    degrees of wickedness. This variety will arise partly from the just judgment of
                    God, ‘rewarding every man according to his works’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 16:27.</p></note>
                    For we cannot doubt but this rule will take place no less in hell than in
                    heaven. As in heaven ‘every man will receive his own reward’, incommunicably his
                    own, according to ‘his own labours’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:8.</p></note> incommunicably his, that is,
                    the whole tenor of his tempers, thoughts, words, and actions;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">The phrase, ‘incommunicably
                            his own, according to “his own labours”’, is omitted in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> (1788) and subsequent edns.</p></note> so
                    undoubtedly every man in fact will receive his own bad reward, according to his
                    own bad labour. And this likewise will be incommunicably <hi rend="italic">his
                        own</hi>, even as his labour was. Variety of punishment will likewise arise
                    from the very nature of the thing. As they that bring most holiness to heaven
                    will find most happiness there, so on the other hand it is not only true that
                    the more wickedness a man brings to hell the more misery he will find there; but
                    that this misery will be infinitely varied according to the various kinds of his
                    wickedness. It was therefore proper to say ‘the fire’ in general, but ‘their
                    worm’ in particular.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But it has been questioned by some whether there be any fire in
                    hell—that is, any material fire. Nay, if there be any fire it is unquestionably
                    material. For what is immaterial fire? The same as immaterial water or earth!
                    Both the one and the other is absolute nonsense, a contradiction in terms.
                    Either therefore we must affirm it to be material, or we deny its existence. But
                    if we <pb n="03:038"/>granted them there is no fire at all there, what would
                    they gain thereby? Seeing this is allowed on all hands, that it is either fire
                    or something worse. And consider this: does not our Lord speak <hi rend="italic">as if</hi> it were real fire? No one can deny or doubt of this. Is it
                    possible then to suppose that the God of truth would speak in this manner if it
                    were not so? Does he design to fright his poor creatures? What, with scarecrows?
                    With vain shadows of things that have no being? O let not anyone think so!
                    Impute not such folly to the Most High!</p>
                <p n="5">5. But others aver ‘It is not possible that fire should burn always. For by
                    the immutable law of nature it consumes whatever is thrown into it. And by the
                    same law, as soon as it has consumed its fuel, it is itself consumed; it goes
                    out.’</p>
                <p>It is most true that in the present constitution of things, during the present
                    laws of nature, the element of fire does dissolve and consume whatever is thrown
                    into it. But here is the mistake: the present laws of nature are not
                        immutable.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">An echo of Malebranche’s ‘occasionalism’, which Wesley found more
                            congenial for apologetic purposes than the Newtonian world-view of
                            ‘[physical] laws’. Cf. Wesley’s letter to ‘John Smith’, June 25, 1746,
                            §7; see also Malebranche’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise Concerning the
                                Search After Truth</hi> (1964), VI.ii.3.</p></note> When the heavens
                    and the earth shall flee away,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 24:35, etc.</p></note> the present scene
                    will be totally changed; and with the present constitution of things, the
                    present laws of nature will cease. After this great change nothing will be
                    dissolved, nothing will be consumed any more. Therefore if it were true that
                    fire consumes all things now, it would not follow that it would do the same
                    after the whole frame of nature has undergone that vast, universal change.</p>
                <p n="6">6. I say, ‘If it were true that fire consumes <hi rend="italic">all
                        things</hi> now.’ But indeed it is not true. Has it not pleased God to give
                    us already some proof of what will be hereafter? Is not the <hi rend="italic">linum asbestum</hi>, the incombustible flax, known in most parts of
                        Europe?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> has a two-column article
                            on asbestos and Wesley has more than two pages on it in the <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi> (1777), II.319-21. See also Peter Sterry,
                                <hi rend="italic">Free Grace Exalted</hi> (1670), p. 12: ‘They say
                            of the Romans of old that they had a sort of linen that would not be
                            burnt in the fire, and after they had burned their dead as was their
                            custom, they took up the bones and wrapt them in that linen and therein
                            burnt them to ashes unmixed from the common ashes.’ See also No. 54, ‘On
                            Eternity’, §7 and n.</p></note> If you take a towel or handkerchief made
                    of this (one of which may now be seen in the British Museum<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">In the <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, an experiment with the
                            attempted burning of ‘a handkerchief of [asbestos]’ is reported. The
                            reference to the British Museum applies to the Sir Hans Sloane
                            Collection which, in Wesley’s time, was in the great buildings on Great
                            Russell Street. In 1826 this collection (with the ‘towel or
                            handkerchief’ to which Wesley refers) was transferred to the new Museum
                            of Natural History on West Cromwell Road.</p></note>) you may throw it
                    into the hottest <pb n="03:039"/>fire, and when it is taken out again it will be
                    observed, upon the nicest experiment, not to have lost one grain of its weight.
                    Here therefore is a substance before our eyes, which even in the present
                    constitution of things (as if it were an emblem of things to come) may remain in
                    fire without being consumed.</p>
                <p n="7">7. Many writers have spoken of other bodily torments added to the being
                    cast into the lake of fire. One of these, even pious Kempis, supposes that
                    misers, for instance, have melted gold poured down their throats; and he
                    supposes many other particular torments to be suited to men’s particular
                        sins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">A
                            puzzle; no such reference appears in Kempis, although there is a passage
                            where it would have been relevant; cf. <hi rend="italic">Imitation</hi>,
                            i.24 (see Wesley’s translation, <hi rend="italic">The Christian’s
                                Pattern</hi>, 1735, pp. 56-61). Nor has any other likely source been
                            located. For other references to Kempis, see No. 55, <hi rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>, §1 and n.</p></note> Nay, our great poet
                    himself supposes the inhabitants of hell to undergo variety of tortures; not to
                    continue always in the lake of fire, but to be frequently ‘by harpy-footed
                    furies haled’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, ii.596.</p></note> into
                    regions of ice, and then back again through ‘extremes by change more
                        fierce’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, 599.</p></note> But I find no word, no
                    tittle of this, not the least hint of it, in all the Bible. And surely this is
                    too awful a subject to admit of such play of imagination. Let us keep to the
                    written Word. It is torment enough to dwell with everlasting burnings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        33:14.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8">8. This is strongly illustrated by a fabulous story, taken from one of the
                    eastern writers, concerning a Turkish king who, after he had been guilty of all
                    manner of wickedness, once did a good thing; for seeing a poor man falling into
                    a pit, wherein he must have inevitably perished, and kicking him from it, he
                    saved his life. The story adds that when for his enormous wickedness he was cast
                    into hell, that foot wherewith he had saved the man’s life was permitted to lie
                    out of the flames.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">π; source not identified.</p></note> But allowing
                    this to be a real case, what a poor comfort would it be! What if both feet were
                    permitted to lie out of the flames, yea, and both hands, how little would it
                    avail! Nay, if all the body were taken out, and placed where no fire touched it,
                    and only one hand or one foot kept in a burning fiery furnace, would the man
                    meantime be much at ease? Nay, quite the contrary. Is it not common to say to a
                    child, ‘Put <pb n="003:040"/>your finger into that candle: can you bear it even
                    for one minute? How then will you bear hell-fire!’ Surely it would be torment
                    enough to have the flesh burnt off from only one finger. What then will it be to
                    have the whole body plunged into a lake of fire burning with brimstone!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        19:20.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="0">III. It remains now only to consider two or three circumstances attending
                    the never-dying worm and the unquenchable fire.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And first consider the company wherewith everyone is surrounded in that
                    place of torment. It is not uncommon to hear even condemned criminals in our
                    public prisons say, ‘O! I wish I was hanged out of the way, rather than to be
                    plagued with these wretches that are round about me.’ But what are the most
                    abandoned wretches upon earth, compared to the inhabitants of hell? None of
                    these are as yet perfectly wicked, emptied of every spark of good; certainly not
                    till this life is at an end; probably not till the day of judgment. Nor can any
                    of these exert without control their whole wickedness on their fellow-creatures.
                    Sometimes they are restrained by good men; sometimes even by bad. So even the
                    torturers in the Roman Inquisition are restrained by those that employ them when
                    they suppose the sufferer cannot endure any more. They then order the
                    executioners to forbear; because it is contrary to the rules of the house that a
                    man should die upon the rack.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s knowledge of the Inquisition, apart from
                            the common store of anti-Roman lore from which this detail probably
                            comes, was largely based on Michael Geddes, <hi rend="italic">A View of
                                the Inquisition of Portugal; with a list of the Prisoners which came
                                out of the Inquisitions of Lisbon, in an Act of Faith</hi> (1682),
                            in <hi rend="italic">Miscellaneous Tracts</hi> (1730), I.385-443; and
                            Samuel Chandler, <hi rend="italic">The History of Persecution</hi>
                            (1736). See also Nos. 82, ‘On Temptation’, II.2; and 91, ‘On Charity’,
                            III.10.</p></note> And very frequently, when there is no human help,
                    they are restrained by God, who hath set them their bounds which they cannot
                    pass, and saith, ‘Hitherto shall ye come, and no farther.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 38:11.</p></note> Yea,
                    so mercifully hath God ordained that the very extremity of pain causes a
                    suspension of it. The sufferer faints away, and so (for a time at least) sinks
                    into insensibility. But the inhabitants of hell are perfectly wicked, having no
                    spark of goodness remaining. And they are restrained by none from exerting to
                    the uttermost their total wickedness. Not by men; none will be restrained from
                    evil by his companions in damnation. And not by God; for he hath forgotten them,
                    hath <pb n="03:041"/>delivered them over to the tormentors.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 18:34.</p></note>
                    And the devils need not fear, like their instruments upon earth, lest they
                    should expire under the torture. They can die no more: they are strong to
                    sustain whatever the united malice, skill, and strength of angels can inflict
                    upon them. And their angelic tormentors have time sufficient to vary their
                    torments a thousand ways. How infinitely may they vary one single
                    torment—horrible appearances! Whereby, there is no doubt, an evil spirit, if
                    permitted, could terrify the stoutest man upon earth to death.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Consider, secondly, that all these torments of body and soul are without
                    intermission. They have no respite from pain; but ‘the smoke of their torment
                    ascendeth up day and night.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 14:11.</p></note> Day and night! That is
                    speaking according to the constitution of the present world, wherein God has
                    wisely and graciously ordained that day and night should succeed each other, so
                    that in every four and twenty hours there comes a</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Daily sabbath, made to rest</l>
                    <l>Toiling man and weary beast.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Mark Le Pla, <hi rend="italic">A Paraphrase on the Song
                            of the Three Children,</hi> st. 21, ll. 7-8 (cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi> [1744],
                        II.119).</p>
                </note>
                <lg>
                    <l>Hence we seldom undergo much labour, or suffer much pain, before</l>
                    <l>Tired nature’s kind restorer, balmy sleep,</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Edward Young, <hi rend="italic">Night Thoughts</hi>,
                        i.1 (Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>
                        [1744], II.229); ‘Tired Nature’s sweet restorer, balmy sleep!’</p>
                </note>
                <p>steals upon us by insensible degrees, and brings an interval of ease. But
                    although the damned have uninterrupted night, it brings no interruption of their
                    pain. No sleep accompanies that darkness: whatever either ancient or modern
                    poets, either Homer or Milton, dream, there is no sleep either in hell or
                        heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            No. 51, <hi rend="italic">The Good Steward</hi>, II.10 and n.</p></note>
                    And be their suffering ever so extreme, be their pain ever so intense, there is
                    no possibility of their fainting away—no, not for a moment.</p>
                <p>Again. The inhabitants of earth are frequently diverted from attending to what is
                    afflictive by the cheerful light of the sun, the vicissitudes of the seasons,
                    ‘the busy hum of men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">L’Allegro</hi>, l. 118.
                            Cf. Wesley’s Preface to <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1746), §5, where
                            he speaks of ‘the busy ways of men’.</p></note> and a <pb n="03:042"/>thousand objects that roll around them with endless variety. But the
                    inhabitants of hell have nothing to divert them from their torments even for a
                    moment:</p>
                <l>Total eclipse: no sun, no moon!</l><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">George Frederick Handel, <hi rend="italic">Samson, An
                            Oratorio</hi> (1742):</p><p rend="Verse">Total eclipse: No sun, no
                        moon,</p><p rend="Verse">All dark amidst the blaze of noon!</p><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi rend="italic">Samson Agonistes</hi>,
                        ll. 80-81.</p></note>— <p n="">no change of seasons or of companions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">See above, I.2:
                            ‘no friendship in hell’.</p></note> There is no business, but one
                    uninterrupted scene of horror, to which they must be all attention. They have no
                    interval of inattention or stupidity: they are all eye, all ear, all sense.
                    Every instant of their duration it may be said of their whole frame that they
                    are</p>
                <lg><l>…tremblingly alive all o’er,</l>
                    <l>And smart and agonize at every pore.</l></lg><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Pope, <hi rend="italic">Essay on
                            Man</hi>, i.197-98.</p></note>
                <p n="3">3. And of this duration <hi rend="italic">there is no end</hi>! What a
                    thought is this! Nothing but eternity is the term of their torment! And who can
                    count the drops of rain, or the sands of the sea, or the days of eternity? Every
                    suffering is softened if there is any hope, though distant, of deliverance from
                    it. But here,</p>
                <l>Hope never comes, that comes to all</l><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                        i.66-67; see also No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>,
                        II.7.</p></note>
                <p>the inhabitants of the upper world! What, sufferings never do end!</p>
                <lg><l>Never! Where sinks the soul at that dread sound!</l>
                    <l>Into a gulf how dark, and how profound!</l></lg><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Last
                            Day</hi>, iii.156-57; see No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §15 and n.</p></note>
                <p>Suppose millions of days, of years, of ages elapsed; still we are only on the
                    threshold of eternity! Neither the pain of body nor of soul is any nearer at an
                    end than it was millions of ages ago. When they are once cast into τὸ πῦρ τὸ
                        ἄσβεστον<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:43.</p></note> (how emphatical!),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 72, ‘Of Evil Angels’,
                            II.10.</p></note> ‘the fire, the unquenchable’, all is concluded: ‘their
                    worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:44, 46, 48. Cf. No. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great Assize</hi>, III.1, where endless torment is
                            also affirmed.</p></note></p>
                <p><pb n="03:043"/>Such is the account which the Judge of all<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:23.</p></note> gives
                    of the punishment which he has ordained for impenitent sinners. And what a
                    counterbalance may the consideration of this be to the violence of any
                    temptation! In particular to the fear of man, the very use to which it is
                    applied by our Lord himself. ‘Be not afraid of them that kill the body, and
                    after that have no more that they can do: but fear him who after he hath killed
                    hath power to cast into hell.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Luke 12:4-5.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p>What a guard may these considerations be against any temptation from
                    pleasure! Will you lose, for any of these poor, earthly pleasures which perish
                    in the using (to say nothing of the present substantial pleasures of religion),
                    the pleasures of paradise, such ‘as eye hath not seen, nor ear heard, neither
                    hath it entered into our hearts to conceive’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 2:9.</p></note> Yea, the pleasures
                    of heaven, the society of angels, and of the spirits of just men made
                        perfect,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:23.</p></note> the conversing face to face with God your
                    Father, your Saviour, your Sanctifier, and the drinking of those rivers of
                        pleasure<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 36:8.</p></note> that are at God’s right hand for evermore?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 16:11
                            (AV).</p></note></p>
                <p>Are you tempted by pain either of body or mind? O compare present things
                    with future. What is the pain of body which you do or may endure, to that of
                    lying in a lake of fire burning with brimstone?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Rev. 19:20.</p></note> What is any pain of
                    mind, any fear, anguish, sorrow, compared to ‘the worm that never dieth’? <hi rend="italic">That never dieth</hi>! This is the sting of all! As for our
                    pains on earth, blessed be God, they are not eternal. There are some intervals
                    to relieve, and there is some period to finish them. When we ask a friend that
                    is sick how he does, ‘I am in pain now,’ says he, ‘but I hope to be easy soon.’
                    This is a sweet mitigation of the present uneasiness. But how dreadful would his
                    case be if he should answer: ‘I am all over pain, and I shall never be eased of
                    it. I lie under exquisite torment of body and horror of soul; and I shall feel
                    it for ever.’ Such is the case of the damned sinners in hell. Suffer any pain,
                    then, rather than come into that place of torment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 16:28.</p></note></p>
                <p>I conclude with one more reflection, taken from Dr. Watts:</p>
                <quote><pb n="03:044"/>It demands our highest gratitude that we who have long ago
                    deserved this misery are not yet plunged into it, while there are thousands who
                    have been adjudged to this place of punishment before they had continued so long
                    in sin as many of us have done. What an instance is it of divine goodness that
                    we are not under this fiery vengeance! Have we not seen many sinners, on our
                    right and left, cut off in their sins? And what but the tender mercy of God hath
                    spared us week after week, month after month, and given us space for repentance?
                    What shall we render unto the Lord for all his patience and long-suffering, even
                    to this day? How often have we incurred the sentence of condemnation by our
                    repeated rebellion against God? And yet we are still alive in his presence, and
                    are hearing the words of hope and salvation. O let us look back and shudder at
                    the thoughts of that dreadful precipice, on the edge of which we have so long
                    wandered! Let us fly for refuge to the hope that is set before us, and give a
                    thousand thanks to the divine mercy that we are not plunged into this
                        perdition.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">An abridgement and paraphrase of Watts’s longer and more graceful
                            ‘Reflection V’, in his Discourse XII, ‘The Nature of the Punishments in
                            Hell’ (on Mark 9:46), in <hi rend="italic">The World to Come…</hi>; see
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.724.</p></note></quote>
            </div>
            <p>Newport, Isle of Wight, <date when="1782-10-10">Oct. 10, 1782</date><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Place and date as in
                            <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>.</p></note></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>