<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 5: Justification by Faith</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-23</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon005</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 5: Justification by Faith</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="181" to="199"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="181"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>There was no mistaking the minatory tone and spirit of the ‘prefixed’ university
                    sermons; they measure Wesley’s move from pious don to itinerant evangelist. In
                    ‘Justification by Faith’, however, we come to his first fully positive
                    exposition of his ‘new’ soteriology—‘faith alone’, ‘the article by which the
                    Church stands or falls’ (see No. 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our
                        Righteousness</hi>, §4 and n.). Wesley’s claim (in his letters to William
                    Law, May 14 and 20, 1738; see <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> I [Vol. 25 of this
                    edn.], pp. 540-50, for Wesley’s letters and Law’s replies) that he had never <hi rend="italic">heard</hi> of the doctrine of <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi>
                    is scarcely credible, since a wide-ranging controversy on this very point had
                    been raging in the Church of England between Puritans and Anglicans since the
                    latter half of the sixteenth century (cf. proem, §2). In 1739 Wesley had
                    extracted and published Robert Barnes’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise on
                        Justification by Faith Only, According to the Doctrine of the Eleventh
                        Article of the Church of England</hi>, from Barnes’s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, 1573 (cf. above, p. 37); he had long known the Articles
                    (specifically IX-XIV) and the Homilies (specifically the first five of the
                    Edwardian set, 1547). What is credible is that his preoccupations with ‘holy
                    living’ and ‘the means of grace’ before 1738 had obscured the priority of
                    justifying faith as antecedent to, and the ground of, ‘the faith that works by
                    love’. In Holy Communion he had prayed, countless times, for ‘grace so to follow
                    [the] good example…[of God’s] servants departed this life in [true] faith and
                    fear…for Jesus Christ’s sake, our <hi rend="italic">only</hi> Mediator and
                    Advocate’; now he is prepared to explain how Christ’s mediation and advocacy
                    effect the pardon of a repentant sinner. The explanation is ‘plain’ enough for
                    ‘plain people’, but III.3 and IV.6 give evidence that this essay was also
                    addressed to the theological community at large.</p>
                <p>The first record in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> of an oral sermon on
                    justification from this text is for May 28, 1738 (at the chapel in Long Acre,
                    London). Later entries suggest that Wesley preached from Rom. 4:5 at least eight
                    more times before June 8, 1742, when he preached at Epworth (probably from his
                    father’s tombstone): ‘At eight I largely enforced at Epworth the great truth (so
                    little understood in what is called a <pb n="182"/>Christian country), “Unto him
                    that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth the ungodly, his faith is
                    counted to him for righteousness.”’ This written sermon was first published in
                    1746, and it stands as the earliest full summary of Wesley’s soteriology in the
                    basic form in which it will continue. In this sense, it is a landmark sermon to
                    which all subsequent ones may be compared. It was not reprinted separately
                    during Wesley’s lifetime, in common with many others first published in
                    Wesley’s<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> SOSO</hi>, for whose publishing
                    history and variant readings see the Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, in Vol. 4 of
                    this edn. It has been noted earlier that items which were printed separately
                    before being collected into one of the volumes of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>
                    are italicized in the notes and in Appendix C, and for these only are separate
                    stemmata given in the Appendix, along with a few which were reprinted separately
                    after originally appearing in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>.<anchor xml:id="bookmark0"/>
                    <anchor xml:id="bookmark1"/>
                    <anchor xml:id="bookmark2"/>
                </p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Justification by Faith</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 4:5</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">To him that worketh not, but believeth on him that justifieth
                        the ungodly, his faith is counted to him for righteousness.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. How a sinner may be justified before God, the Lord and Judge of all, is
                    a question of no common importance to every child of man. It contains the
                    foundation of all our hope, inasmuch as while we are at enmity with God there
                    can be no true peace, no solid joy, either in time or in eternity. What peace
                    can there be while our own heart condemns us? And much more he that ‘is greater
                    than our heart, and knoweth all things’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:20.</p>
                    </note> What solid joy, either
                    in this world or that to come, while ‘the wrath of God abideth on us’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                        3:36.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And yet how little hath this important question been understood! What
                    confused notions have many had concerning it! Indeed not only confused, but
                    often utterly false, contrary to the truth as light to darkness; notions
                    absolutely inconsistent with <pb n="183"/>the oracles of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., the Holy Scriptures taken
                            as a whole; cf. Rom. 3:2, Heb. 5:12, 1 Pet. 4:11, and Acts 7:38. See
                            also the agreement here between Matthew Poole and Matthew Henry, but
                            notice that Poole (on Heb. 5:11) adds the ‘ancient creeds’ in which he
                            sees ‘God’s oracles in the Scriptures’ as being ‘summed up’. This
                            metaphor of the Scriptures as ‘oracles’ is a favourite with Wesley, a
                            basic presupposition in his hermeneutics (it is also one of the premises
                            of his early practice of bibliomancy); it appears in at least fifteen
                            other sermons and more times than that in his other writings.</p>
                    </note>
                    and with the whole analogy of faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The general and true sense of Scripture (both the
                            truths revealed in Scripture and solid inferences drawn from them, as in
                            the creeds and biblically-grounded theology); cf. John Gerhard, who had
                            summed up their consensus in his <hi rend="italic">Loci Theologici</hi>
                            (1621), I.55, and II.424: ‘All the interpretation of Scripture should be
                            according to the analogy of faith…’ (i.e., the general and essential
                            truth of Scripture taken as a whole). See also Francis Turrentin, <hi rend="italic">Institutio Theologiae Elencticae</hi> (1686), Eng. tr.
                            J. Beardslee (1981), I.xii.6-7; II.xix.2-6; and add the summary analyses
                            of Lutheran views in Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Theology of the
                                Evangelical Lutheran Church</hi> (Philadelphia, Lutheran Publication
                            Society, 1889, 3rd edn. rev.; Minneapolis, Minn., Augsburg Publishing
                            House, 1961), pp. 70, 76; and Heinrich Heppe, <hi rend="italic">Reformed
                                Dogmatics</hi> (London, George Allen and Unwin, 1950), pp.
                            30-31.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">In his comment on Rom. 12:6 (in <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>) Wesley connects ‘the analogy of faith’
                            with ‘the oracles of God’ and cites 1 Pet. 4:11 as his authority. He
                            then sums up its particulars: ‘that grand scheme of doctrine which is
                            delivered [in the Scriptures], touching original sin, justification by
                            faith, and present inward salvation’. He then stipulates that ‘any
                            question should be determined by this rule; every doubtful Scripture
                            interpreted according to the grand truths which run through the
                            whole.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For other usages of this phrase, see
                            Nos. 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, §6 and n.; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s
                            Coming’, III.5 and n.; 64, ‘The New Creation’, §2; 115, ‘Dives and
                            Lazarus’, III.7; 122, ‘Causes of the Inefficacy of Christianity’, §6;
                            135, ‘On Guardian Angels’, III.1. See also Susanna’s letter to John,
                            Aug. 18, 1725, where she concludes a long paragraph on the Calvinist
                            doctrine of predestination: ‘This is the sum of what I believe
                            concerning predestination, which I think is agreeable to the analogy of
                            faith’ (see <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, I, Vol. 25 of this edn., p.
                            180).</p>
                    </note> And hence, erring concerning the very foundation, they
                    could not possibly build thereon; at least, not ‘gold, silver, or precious
                    stones’, which would endure when ‘tried as by fire’, but only ‘hay and
                        stubble’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Cor. 3:12, 13.</p>
                    </note> neither acceptable to God nor profitable to
                    man.</p>
                <p n="3">3. In order to do justice, as far as in me lies, to the vast importance of
                    the subject, to save those that seek the truth in sincerity from ‘vain
                        jangling’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Tim. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> and ‘strife of words’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:4.</p>
                    </note> to
                    clear the confusedness of thought into which so many have already been led
                    thereby, and to give them true and just conceptions of this great mystery of
                        godliness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Tim. 3:16.</p>
                    </note> I shall endeavour to show,</p>
                <p>First, what is the general ground of this whole doctrine of justification;</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="184"/>Secondly, what justification is; </p>
                <p>Thirdly, who they are that are justified; and, </p>
                <p>Fourthly, on what terms they are justified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>I. I am first to show what is the general ground of this whole doctrine of
                    justification.</p>
                <p n="1">1. In the image of God was man made;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 1:27; 9:6. See Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.; and141, ‘The Image of God’, on
                            Gen. 1:27.</p>
                    </note> holy as he that created him is holy, merciful as
                    the author of all is merciful, perfect as his Father in heaven is perfect.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            5:48.</p>
                    </note> As God is love, so man dwelling in love dwelt in God,
                    and God in him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 4:16.</p>
                    </note> God made him to be ‘an image of his own
                        eternity’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 2:23.</p>
                    </note> an incorruptible picture of the God of glory. He
                    was accordingly pure, as God is pure, from every spot of sin. He knew not evil
                    in any kind or degree, but was inwardly and outwardly sinless and undefiled. He
                    ‘loved the Lord his God with all his heart, and with all his mind, and soul, and
                        strength’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. To man thus upright and perfect God gave a perfect law, to which he
                    required full and perfect obedience. He required full obedience in every point,
                    and this to be performed without any intermission from the moment man became a
                    living soul till the time of his trial should be ended. No allowance was made
                    for any falling short. As, indeed, there was no need of any, man being
                    altogether equal to the task assigned, and thoroughly furnished for every good
                    word and work.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 3:17; 2 Thess. 2:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. To the entire law of love which was written in his heart (against which,
                    perhaps, he could not sin directly) it seemed good to the sovereign wisdom of
                    God to superadd one positive law: ‘Thou shalt not eat of the fruit of the tree
                    that groweth in the midst of the garden;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 3:3.</p>
                    </note> annexing that
                    penalty thereto, ‘In the day thou eatest thereof, thou shalt surely die.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                        2:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Such then was the state of man in paradise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A similar (and even more
                            detailed) account of human perfection in man’s first creation had
                            already been expounded in No.141, ‘The Image of God’ (Gen.1:27). In both
                            sermons Wesley takes the perfection of the paradisaical state as normal
                            and normative for human existence. Its restoration is the goal of ‘the
                            order of salvation’; indeed, salvation is defined as the restoration of
                            the image of God; see No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>,
                            §1 and n.; also No. 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, III.5 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> By the free, <pb n="185"/>unmerited love of God he was
                    holy and happy;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Holiness and happiness had long been linked in the Anglican (catholic)
                            tradition as reciprocals (as in John Norris, Richard Lucas, John
                            Tillotson, and William Tilly). Here, in a staunchly Protestant
                            exposition of ‘faith alone’, Wesley finds it easy and natural to
                            presuppose the integrity of God’s design for humanity (happiness) and
                            his demand upon it (holiness). This linkage—‘holy <hi rend="italic">and</hi> happy’—is one of Wesley’s most consistent themes, early,
                            middle, and late, with nuances very much worth noting, for if holiness
                            is active love toward God and neighbour, then happiness is one’s
                            enjoyment and security in such love. Cf. above, p. 35.</p>
                    </note> he
                    knew, loved, enjoyed God, which is (in substance) life everlasting. And in this
                    life of love he was to continue for ever if he continued to obey God in all
                    things. But if he disobeyed him in any he was to forfeit all. ‘In that day (said
                    God) thou shalt surely die.’</p>
                <p n="5">5. Man did disobey God; he ‘ate of the tree of which God commanded him,
                    saying, Thou shalt not eat of it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 3:17.</p>
                    </note> And in that day he was
                    condemned by the righteous judgment of God. Then also the sentence whereof he
                    was warned before began to take place upon him. For the moment he tasted that
                    fruit he died. His soul died, was separated from God; separate from whom the
                    soul has no more life than the body has when separate from the soul. His body
                    likewise became corruptible and mortal, so that death then took hold on this
                    also. And being already dead in spirit, dead to God, dead in sin, he hastened on
                    to death everlasting, to the destruction both of body and soul in the fire never
                    to be quenched.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Mark 9:43. For Wesley’s interesting explanation as to how Adam’s
                            body <hi rend="italic">became</hi> corruptible and mortal, see No. 141,
                            ‘The Image of God’, II.1; it represents his concern to apply his
                            understanding of current advances in medical knowledge to exegetical and
                            soteriological problems.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Thus ‘by one man sin entered into the world, and death by sin. And so
                    death passed upon all men,’ as being contained in him who was the common father
                    and representative of us all. Thus ‘through the offence of one’ all are dead,
                    dead to God, dead in sin, dwelling in a corruptible, mortal body, shortly to be
                    dissolved, and under the sentence of death eternal. For as ‘by one man’s
                    disobedience all were made sinners’, so by that offence of one ‘judgment came
                    upon all men to condemnation.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 5:12, etc.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. In this state we were, even all mankind, when ‘God so loved the world
                    that he gave his only begotten Son, to the end we might not perish but have
                    everlasting life.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:16.</p>
                    </note> In the fullness of time
                    he <pb n="186"/>was made man, another common head of mankind, a second general
                    parent and representative of the whole human race.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo here of the
                            Christological views of Hugo Grotius of Christ as the ‘Federal Head’ of
                            the whole body of humanity; cf. his <hi rend="italic">De Veritate
                                Religionis Christianae</hi> (1642; though Wesley probably knew it in
                            Le Clerc’s revision of 1709), Bks. II and III. In Charles Wesley’s hymn
                            (see No. 125 in <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Hymns</hi>, Vol. 7 in
                            this edn.), it appears applied to the Pauline analogy between the First
                            and Second Adams:</p>
                        <p rend="Verse">Adam, descended from above,</p>
                        <p rend="Verse">Federal head of all mankind.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">The
                            metaphor is developed at greater length in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of Original Sin</hi> (1757), Sect. VI, pp. 366-68, against
                            John Taylor’s denial of the orthodox interpretations. In his conclusion
                            Wesley quotes James Hervey approvingly: ‘That as Adam was the first
                            general representative of mankind, so Christ was the second and
                            last….’Cf. Isa. 53:4-6.</p>
                    </note> And as such it was that ‘he bore our
                    griefs’, the Lord ‘laying upon him the iniquities of us all’. Then ‘was he
                    wounded for our transgressions, and bruised for our iniquities.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            53:4-6.</p>
                    </note> ‘He made his soul an offering for sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        53:10.</p>
                    </note> He poured out his blood for the transgressors. He ‘bare
                    our sins in his own body on the tree’, that ‘by his stripes we might be
                        healed’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Pet. 2:24; Isa. 53:5.</p>
                    </note> And ‘by that one oblation of himself
                    once offered’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion, Prayer of Consecration; note Wesley’s ‘that one
                            oblation…’ in place of ‘his one oblation of himself’.</p>
                    </note> he
                    ‘hath redeemed me and all mankind’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Catechism.</p>
                    </note>
                    having thereby ‘made a full, perfect, and sufficient sacrifice and satisfaction
                    for the sins of the whole world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Communion, Prayer of
                            Consecration; note Wesley’s omission of the term
                    ‘oblation’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. In consideration of this, that the Son of God hath ‘tasted death for
                    every man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 2:9.</p>
                    </note> God hath now ‘reconciled the world to himself, not
                    imputing to them their former trespasses’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> And thus, ‘as by
                    the offence of one judgment came upon all men to condemnation, even so by the
                    righteousness of one the free gift came upon all men unto justification.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        5:18.</p>
                    </note> So that for the sake of his well-beloved Son, of what he
                    hath done and suffered for us, God now vouchsafes on one only condition (which
                    himself also enables us to perform) both to remit the punishment due to our
                    sins, to reinstate us in his favour, and to restore our dead souls to spiritual
                    life, as the earnest of life eternal.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our
                                Righteousness</hi>, II.8, for a cross-reference to this
                        passage.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">
                    <pb n="187"/>9. This therefore is the general ground of the whole doctrine
                    of justification. By the sin of the first Adam, who was not only the father but
                    likewise the representative of us all, we all ‘fell short of the favour of
                        God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 3:23.</p>
                    </note> we all became ‘children of wrath’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        2:3.</p>
                    </note> or, as the Apostle expresses it, ‘Judgment came upon all men
                    to condemnation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:18.</p>
                    </note> Even so by the sacrifice for
                    sin made by the second Adam, as the representative of us all, God is so far
                    reconciled to all the world that he hath given them a new covenant. The plain
                    condition whereof being once fulfilled, ‘there is no more condemnation for
                        us’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:1.</p>
                    </note> but we are ‘justified freely by his grace through
                    the redemption that is in Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. But what is it to be ‘justified’? What is ‘justification’? This was
                    the second thing which I proposed to show. And it is evident from what has been
                    already observed that it is not the being made actually just and righteous. This
                    is <hi rend="italic">sanctification</hi>; which is indeed in some degree the
                    immediate <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi> of justification, but nevertheless is a
                    distinct gift of God, and of a totally different nature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The relation between
                            justification and sanctification—and the problem of their order of
                            precedence—was an old bone of contention between Puritans and Anglicans.
                            Lutherans and Calvinists, as a rule, understood justification (in the
                            forensic sense of pardon and acquittal) as antecedent to sanctification
                            (in the sense of ‘renovation’); cf. Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal
                                Theology</hi>, Pt. III, ch. iii, §48 (pp. 486 ff.). Anglicans, like
                            Jeremy Taylor, insisted that some evidence of sanctification (e.g.,
                            repentance and ‘works meet for repentance’) should precede
                            justification. Wesley stressed the difference between the two
                            (justification as ‘what God does <hi rend="italic">for</hi> us’;
                            sanctification as ‘what he works <hi rend="italic">in</hi> us’; cf.
                            No.45, ‘The New Birth’, §1) and, after 1738, insists on the priority of
                            justification in the order of salvation (cf. No. 19, ‘The Great
                            Privilege of those that are Born of God’, I.1 and n.). But see the
                            Minute of 1770 for an interesting recurrence of the holy living theme
                                (<hi rend="italic">secundum merita operum</hi>), and also the
                            comment on the contrast between Lutherans, Catholics, and Methodists on
                            this issue in No. 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.5.</p>
                    </note> The one
                    implies what God <hi rend="italic">does for us</hi> through his Son; the other
                    what he <hi rend="italic">works in us</hi> by his Spirit. So that although some
                    rare instances may be found wherein the term ‘justified’ or ‘justification’ is
                    used in so wide a sense as to include sanctification also, yet in general use
                    they are sufficiently distinguished from each other both by St. Paul and the
                    other inspired writers.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Neither is that far-fetched conceit that justification is the clearing
                    us from accusation, particularly that of Satan, easily <pb n="188"/>provable
                    from any clear text of Holy Writ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">It has been supposed (e.g., by Sugden) that this is
                            the Origenistic soteriology (and that of other Eastern Fathers; e.g.,
                            Athanasius, Gregory of Nyssa). It is, of course, a misreading of Origen;
                            cf. Gustaf Aulén, <hi rend="italic">Christus Victor</hi> (London, SPCK,
                            1945), pp. 54, 63-71.</p>
                    </note> In the whole scriptural account of this
                    matter, as above laid down, neither that accuser nor his accusation appears to
                    be at all taken in. It cannot indeed be denied that he is the ‘accuser of
                        men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rev. 12:10.</p>
                    </note> emphatically so called. But it does in no wise
                    appear that the great Apostle hath any reference to this, more or less, in all
                    that he hath written touching justification either to the Romans or the
                    Galatians.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It is also far easier to take for granted than to prove from any clear
                    Scripture testimony that justification is the clearing us from the accusation
                    brought against us by <hi rend="italic">the law</hi>. At least, if this forced,
                    unnatural way of speaking mean either more or less than this, that whereas we
                    have transgressed the law of God and thereby deserved the damnation of hell, God
                    does not inflict on those who are justified the punishment which they had
                        deserved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This was typical Reformation teaching, as in John Gerhard, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, VII.4-5: ‘The Law accuses the sinner
                            before the judgment-seat of God…’; cf. Martin Chemnitz, <hi rend="italic">Loci Theologici</hi>, II.250, where it is argued that
                            ‘the conscience of the sinner [is] accused by the divine Law before the
                            tribunal of God….’ Note the mild tone of Wesley’s rejection of this
                            tradition.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Least of all does justification imply that God is <hi rend="italic">deceived</hi> in those whom he justifies; that he thinks them to be what in
                    fact they are not, that he accounts them to be otherwise than they are. It does
                    by no means imply that God judges concerning us contrary to the real nature of
                    things, that he esteems us better than we really are, or believes us righteous
                    when we are unrighteous.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A mild distortion of the typical Puritan doctrine
                            of forensic justification in which Christ’s imputed righteousness allows
                            the Father justly to pardon the elect and therefore regard them as if
                            they were righteous. The ruling metaphor, in that view, is a forensic
                            one: ‘the heavenly tribunal’. Cf. Calvin, <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi>, III.12; see also John Davenant, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on Justification</hi> (1631), I.227-36, and George
                            Downham [Downame], <hi rend="italic">A Treatise of Justification</hi>
                            (1639), pp. 15-45. For a larger survey of the Puritan thesis that
                            imputation is the formal cause of justification (in Davenant, Downham,
                            Joseph Hall, James Ussher, John Donne, Lancelot Andrewes, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>), cf. Allison, <hi rend="italic">The Rise
                                of Moralism</hi>, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Surely
                    no. The judgment of the all-wise God is always according to truth. Neither can
                    it ever consist with his unerring wisdom to think that I am innocent, to judge
                    that I am righteous or holy, because another is so. He can no more in this
                    manner confound me with Christ than with David or Abraham. Let any man to whom
                    God hath given understanding weigh this <pb n="189"/>without prejudice, and he
                    cannot but perceive that such a notion of justification is neither reconcilable
                    to reason nor Scripture.</p>
                <p n="5">5. The plain scriptural notion of justification is pardon,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The fulcrum of
                            Wesley’s evangelical soteriology. No such definition of justification
                            appears anywhere in the early Wesley. The idea is normative after
                            1738—but see No. 86, <hi rend="italic">A Call to Backsliders</hi>,
                            II.2(3), where Wesley speaks of those who ‘had been sanctified in the
                            first degree…’, i.e., before ‘remission of sins’. For the early Wesley,
                            see, e.g., his letter to his mother, Feb. 28, 1730, where he accepts
                            Jeremy Taylor’s correlation of ‘pardon of sins in the gospel [with]
                            sanctification’. Contrast this with Nos. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of
                            those that are Born of God’ (1748), §2; and 43, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Scripture Way of Salvation</hi> (1765), I.3. It was in this sense
                            that Wesley could maintain, in a letter to John Newton, May 14, 1765: ‘I
                            think on justification just as I have done any time these seven and
                            twenty years—and just as Mr. Calvin does. In this respect I do not
                            differ from him an hair’s breadth.’ Earlier (Apr. 24, 1765), he wrote to
                            Dr. Erskine, ‘In…justification by faith I have not wavered a moment for
                            these seven and twenty years.’ Later (May 23, 1768), he would reassure
                            the Revd. Mr. Plenderlieth: ‘Since I believed justification by faith,
                            which I have done upwards of thirty years, I have constantly maintained
                            that we are pardoned and accepted wholly and solely for the sake of what
                            Christ hath both <hi rend="italic">done and suffered</hi> for us.’ Cf.
                            also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Rom. 3:24; 5:18, and <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, 1746.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">If the
                            difference between Wesley and Calvin were only a hair’s breadth, that
                            hair’s breadth was crucial—and the Calvinists always recognized it as
                            such. In the <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi>, III. xx. 5, Calvin
                            asserts expressly that ‘in justification, faith is <hi rend="italic">merely passive</hi>…’; whereas Wesley understood justifying faith
                            as ‘active’ in some sense (prompted, as it is, by the Spirit’s
                            prevenient activity). In this, he was nearer to Richard Lucas (<hi rend="italic">Enquiry</hi>, III.33), John Goodwin (<hi rend="italic">Imputatio Fidei; Or a Treatise of Justification</hi> [1642], p.77),
                            or even to Thomas Cockman (<hi rend="italic">Salvation by Jesus Christ
                                Alone…in two sermons preached before the University of Oxford,
                                January 2 and 6, 1732</hi>) than to Calvin, Davenant, or Bunyan.
                            There is also his letter to Charles (July 31, 1747), which outlines ‘<hi rend="italic">a genesis problematica</hi> on justifying faith’, with
                            its first formal question, ‘Is justifying faith a sense of pardon?’—and
                            the formal answer, ‘<hi rend="italic">Negatur</hi>’! The ensuing
                            explanation would seem to contradict the central thesis of
                            ‘Justification by Faith’ and the claim to consensus with Calvin. A
                            closer look, however, suggests a somewhat imprecise elision of
                            justification as pardon with the ‘<hi rend="italic">sense of
                            pardon</hi>’ here defined as ‘a distinct, explicit assurance that my
                            sins are forgiven’. Thus, for all of these variants, <hi rend="italic">justification as pardon</hi> continues as Wesley’s baseline
                            definition.</p>
                    </note> the forgiveness of sins. It is that act of God
                    the Father whereby, for the sake of the propitiation made by the blood of his
                    Son, he ‘showeth forth his righteousness (or mercy) by the remission of the sins
                    that are past’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:25.</p>
                    </note> This is the easy, natural account of it given
                    by St. Paul throughout his whole Epistle. So he explains it himself, more
                    particularly in this and in the following chapter. Thus in the next verses but
                    one to the text, ‘Blessed are they (saith he) whose iniquities are forgiven, and
                    whose sins are covered. Blessed is the man to whom the Lord will not impute
                        sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            4:7, 8; cf. Ps. 32:1, 2.</p>
                    </note> To him that is justified or forgiven
                    God ‘will not impute sin’ to his condemnation. He will not condemn him on that
                    account either in this world or in that which is to come. His sins, all his past
                    sins, <pb n="190"/>in thought, word, and deed, ‘are covered’, are blotted out;
                    shall not be remembered or mentioned against him, any more than if they had not
                    been. God will not inflict on that sinner what he deserved to suffer, because
                    the Son of his love hath suffered for him. And from the time we are ‘accepted
                    through the Beloved’, ‘reconciled to God through his blood’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 1:6, 7; Rom. 5:9,
                            10.</p>
                    </note> he loves and blesses and watches over us for good, even
                    as if we had never sinned.</p>
                <p n="6">Indeed the Apostle in one place seems to extend the meaning of the word
                    much farther, where he says: ‘Not the hearers of the law, but the doers of the
                    law shall be justified.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:13.</p>
                    </note> Here he appears to refer our
                    justification to the sentence of the great day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., to our ‘final justification’ (<hi rend="italic">iustitia duplex</hi>); this, then, is an echo of
                            Wesley’s doctrine of a ‘double justification’, already rejected by the
                            Lutherans (cf. Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Theology</hi>, Pt.
                            III, ch. iii, §42, and, more specifically, pp. 430 ff.).</p>
                    </note> And
                    so our Lord himself unquestionably doth when he says, ‘By thy words thou shalt
                    be justified;’ proving thereby that ‘for every idle word men shall speak they
                    shall give an account in the day of judgment.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:36, 37.</p>
                    </note> But perhaps we
                    can hardly produce another instance of St. Paul’s using the word in that distant
                    sense. In the general tenor of his writings it is evident he doth not; and least
                    of all in the text before us, which undeniably speaks, not of those who have
                    already ‘finished their course’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> but of those who are now
                    just setting out, just beginning ‘to run the race which is set before
                        them’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 12:1. Another echo of the idea of ‘double justification’, which
                            Wesley will argue for in the next sermon, ‘The Righteousness of Faith’
                            (see I.7 and n.).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. But this is the third thing which was to be considered, namely, who
                    are they that are justified? And the Apostle tells us expressly, the ungodly:
                    he, that is, God, ‘justifieth the ungodly’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> the ungodly of every
                    kind and degree, and none but the ungodly. As ‘they that are righteous need no
                        repentance,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 5:32; 15:7; etc.</p>
                    </note> so they need no forgiveness. It is
                    only sinners that have any occasion for pardon: it is sin alone which admits of
                    being forgiven. Forgiveness therefore has an immediate reference to sin and (in
                    this respect) to nothing else. It is our ‘unrighteousness’ to which the
                    pardoning God is ‘merciful’; it is our ‘iniquity’ which he ‘remembereth no
                        more’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 8:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">
                    <pb n="191"/>2. This seems not to be at all considered by those who so
                    vehemently contend that man must be sanctified, that is, holy, before he can be
                    justified; especially by such of them as affirm that universal holiness or
                    obedience must precede justification<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An unsympathetic reference to the typical
                            assumption by those in the ‘holy living’ tradition that ‘repentance and
                            works meet for repentance’ (Acts 26:20) were normal antecedents to
                            justification—and certainly to anything like ‘final justification’
                            (since the doctrine of ‘double justification’ had come to them from
                            Erasmus, Bucer, and others). Jeremy Taylor had spoken for many in
                            espousing this view in a letter to Bishop John Warner of Rochester
                            (Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, II. 678-80; see also <hi rend="italic">Unum Necessarium</hi>, ch. ix, ‘The Effect of
                            Repentance’, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 598 ff.); he had
                            expounded it at greater length in <hi rend="italic">The Rule and
                                Exercises of Holy Living</hi> (1650), <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            I.399-515. Bishop Thomas Barlow of Lincoln had accused George Bull of
                            such a teaching in the <hi rend="italic">Harmonia Apostolica</hi>
                            (1669), despite Robert Nelson’s denials of any such intention on Bull’s
                            part; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Life of Bull</hi> (1713), pp. 90, 181,
                            211. Despite Nelson’s protestations, Wesley had joined Barlow in
                            denouncing both Bull and Tillotson as having taught such a doctrine of
                            works-righteousness (cf. Nos. 150, 151, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’). Thomas
                            Tully thought he had found such a heresy in Richard Baxter’s <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms on Justification</hi>, and had roundly
                            condemned it in <hi rend="italic">Justificatio Paulina</hi> (1674). The
                            point is that here Wesley has reversed his earlier stand and now is
                            stressing the primacy of justification in the <hi rend="italic">ordo
                                salutis</hi> even as Baxter had sought to do in his <hi rend="italic">Aphorisms</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Confession</hi>.
                            Even John Turner in his Boyle Lecture of 1708, ‘The Wisdom of God in the
                            Redemption of Man’, <hi rend="italic">Sermons at the Boyle Lectures</hi>
                            (1739), II.359, had asserted that universal or perfect obedience to the
                            Law is impossible to fallen man. What everybody was trying to avoid was
                            the Council of Trent’s bald identification of justification as ‘inherent
                            and infused righteousness’ (cf. Sessions VI, ch. vii). Thus, Wesley here
                            is concerned to set down his new doctrine as clearly and firmly as
                            possible.</p>
                    </note> (unless they mean that justification at the last
                    day which is wholly out of the present question); so far from it, that the very
                    supposition is not only flatly impossible (for where there is no love of God
                    there is no holiness, and there is no love of God but from a sense of his loving
                    us) but also grossly, intrinsically absurd, contradictory to itself. For it is
                    not a <hi rend="italic">saint</hi> but a <hi rend="italic">sinner</hi> that is
                        <hi rend="italic">forgiven</hi>, and under the notion of a sinner. God <hi rend="italic">justifieth</hi> not the godly, but the <hi rend="italic">ungodly</hi>; not those that are holy already, but the unholy. Upon what
                    condition he doth this will be considered quickly; but whatever it is, it cannot
                    be holiness. To assert this is to say the Lamb of God takes away only those sins
                    which were taken away before.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of the <hi rend="italic">Agnus Dei</hi> and
                            1 John 2:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Does then the good Shepherd seek and save only those that are found
                    already? No. He seeks and saves that which is lost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 19:10.</p>
                    </note> He
                    pardons those who need his pardoning mercy. He saves from the guilt of sin (and
                    at the same time from the power) sinners of every kind, of every degree: men who
                    till then were altogether ungodly; in whom the love of the Father was not; and
                    consequently in <pb n="192"/>whom dwelt no good thing, no good or truly
                    Christian temper, but all such as were evil and abominable—pride, anger, love of
                    the world, the genuine fruits of that ‘carnal mind which is enmity against
                        God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. These ‘who are sick’, the ‘burden of whose sins is intolerable’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion,
                            General Confession.</p>
                    </note> are they that ‘need a physician’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            9:12.</p>
                    </note> these who are guilty, who groan under the wrath of God,
                    are they that need a pardon. These who are ‘condemned already’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                        3:18.</p>
                    </note> not only by God but also by their own conscience, as by a
                    thousand witnesses, of all their ungodliness, both in thought, and word, and
                    work, cry aloud for him that ‘justifieth the ungodly’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> ‘through
                    the redemption that is in Jesus’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note>—‘the ungodly and him that
                    worketh not’, that worketh not before he is justified anything that is good,
                    that is truly virtuous or holy, but only evil continually. For his heart is
                    necessarily, essentially evil, till the love of God is shed abroad therein.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        5:5.</p>
                    </note> And while the tree is corrupt so are the fruits, ‘for an
                    evil tree cannot bring forth good fruit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:18; Luke 6:43.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. If it be objected, ‘Nay, but a man, before he is justified, may feed the
                    hungry, or clothe the naked;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:37-38.</p>
                    </note> and these are good
                    works,’ the answer is easy. He <hi rend="italic">may</hi> do these, even before
                    he is justified. And these are in one sense ‘good works’; they are ‘good and
                    profitable to men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 3:8.</p>
                    </note> But it does not follow that
                    they are, strictly speaking, good in themselves, or good in the sight of God.
                    All truly ‘good works’ (to use the words of our Church) ‘follow after
                    justification’, and they are therefore ‘good and acceptable to God in Christ’,
                    because they ‘spring out of a true and living faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">The
                                Thirty-nine Articles</hi>, Art. XII, ‘Of Good Works’; also ‘Of the
                            True and Lively Faith’, Pts. I-III, in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>,
                            pp. 29-40, and ‘Of Good Works Annexed Unto Faith’, Pt. I, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 41-44.</p>
                    </note> By a parity of
                    reason all ‘works done before justification are not good’, in the Christian
                    sense, ‘forasmuch as they spring not of faith in Jesus Christ’ (though from some
                    kind of faith in God they may spring), ‘yea, rather for that they are not done
                    as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, we doubt not’ (how <pb n="193"/>strange soever it may appear to some) ‘but they have the nature of sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Thirty-nine Articles</hi>, Art. XIII, ‘Of Works
                            Before Justification’, and see <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of
                                Salvation, Faith, and Good Works</hi>, II.6 (p. 4 above). In the
                            homily, ‘Of Good Works’, <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p.43, Cranmer
                            cites St. Chrysostom’s <hi rend="italic">De Fide, Lege et Spiritu…</hi>:
                            ‘they which glister and shine in good works without faith in God be like
                            dead men which had goodly and precious tombs and yet it availeth them
                            nothing.’ Cf. Migne, <hi rend="italic">PG</hi>, 48:1081-83, where <hi rend="italic">De Lege</hi> comes under the rubric ‘Spuria’; even so,
                            the passage faithfully reflects St. Chrysostom’s views on the point.
                            Also, see No. 99, <hi rend="italic">The Reward of Righteousness</hi>,
                            I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Perhaps those who doubt of this have not duly considered the weighty
                    reason which is here assigned why no works done before justification can be
                    truly and properly good. The argument runs thus:</p>
                <p><!--How to number unnumbered paragraphs?-->No works are good which are not done
                    as God hath willed and commanded them to be done:</p>
                <p>But no works done before justification are done as God hath willed and commanded
                    them to be done:</p>
                <p>Therefore no works done before justification are good.</p>
                <p>The first proposition is self-evident. And the second, that no works done before
                    justification are done as God hath willed and commanded them to be done, will
                    appear equally plain and undeniable if we only consider God hath willed and
                    commanded that ‘all our works should be done in charity’ (ἐν ἀγάπῃ),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 16:14.
                            For Wesley’s preference for ‘love’ rather than ‘charity’ as a
                            translation of ἀγάπῃ, cf. No. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2
                            and n.</p>
                    </note> in love, in that love to God which produces love to
                    all mankind. But none of our works can be done in this love while the love of
                    the Father (of God as our Father) is not in us. And this love cannot be in us
                    till we receive the ‘Spirit of adoption, crying in our hearts, Abba,
                        Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> If therefore God doth not ‘justify the ungodly’,
                    and him that (in this sense) ‘worketh not’, then hath Christ died in vain; then,
                    notwithstanding his death, can no flesh living be justified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. But on what terms then is he justified who is altogether ‘ungodly’,
                    and till that time ‘worketh not’? On one alone, which is faith. He ‘believeth in
                    him that justifieth the ungodly’, and ‘he that believeth is not condemned’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                        3:18.</p>
                    </note> yea, he ‘is passed from death unto life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 5:24; cf. 1 John
                            3:14.</p>
                    </note> For ‘the righteousness (or mercy) of God is by faith of
                    Jesus Christ unto all and upon all them that believe; …whom God hath set forth
                    to be a propitiation through faith in his blood’, <pb n="194"/>that ‘he might be
                    just, and (consistently with his justice) the justifier of him which believeth
                    in Jesus…. Therefore we conclude that a man is justified by faith without the
                    deeds of the law’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:22, 25-26, 28.</p>
                    </note>—without previous
                    obedience to the moral law, which indeed he could not till now perform. That it
                    is the moral law, and that alone, which is here intended, appears evidently from
                    the words that follow: ‘Do we then make void the law through faith? God forbid!
                    Yea, we establish the law.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.3:31; see Nos. 34, ‘The Original, Nature,
                            Properties, and Use of the Law’, and 35, 36, ‘The Law Established
                            through Faith’, Discourses I and II, for a full exposition of Wesley’s
                            views on ‘Law and Gospel’.</p>
                    </note> What law do we establish by faith?
                    Not the ritual law; not the ceremonial law of Moses. In no wise; but the great,
                    unchangeable law of love, the holy love of God and of our neighbour.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Faith in general is a divine, supernatural ἔλεγχος, ‘evidence’ or
                    conviction ‘of things not seen’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:1. Cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, I.11 and n.</p>
                    </note> not discoverable by
                    our bodily senses as being either past, future, or spiritual.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Is there an echo here of St.
                            Augustine’s famous distinction between three orders of time (<hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, XI. xi-xxxi—<hi rend="italic">memoria</hi>, <hi rend="italic">expectatio</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">contuitus</hi>)? Wesley’s ‘spiritual’ is a rough
                            equivalent to St. Augustine’s ‘contuitive’. See No. 29, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, IX’, §28 and n.</p>
                    </note> Justifying faith implies, not only a
                    divine evidence or conviction that ‘God was in Christ, reconciling the world
                    unto himself’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> but a sure trust and confidence that Christ died
                    for <hi rend="italic">my</hi> sins, that he loved <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, and
                    gave himself for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:3 and Gal. 2:20. This is
                            Wesley’s definition of the ‘testimony’ or ‘witness of the Spirit’. See
                            Nos. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.7; 11, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Witness of the Spirit</hi>, II, II.2; 17, ‘The Circumcision of the
                            Heart’, II.5; 58, <hi rend="italic">On Predestination</hi>, §12; 106,
                            ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, I.12. There is also here an echo of ‘Aldersgate’,
                            JWJ, May 24, 1738. See also Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on 1
                            John 3:14.</p>
                    </note> And at what time soever a sinner thus believes, be
                    it in early childhood, in the strength of his years, or when he is old and
                    hoary-haired, God justifieth that ungodly one; God for the sake of his Son
                    pardoneth and absolveth him who had in him till then no good thing. Repentance
                    indeed God had given him before. But that repentance was neither more nor less
                    than a deep sense of the want of all good, and the presence of all evil. And
                    whatever good he hath or doth from that hour when he first believes in God
                    through Christ, faith does not <hi rend="italic">find</hi> but <hi rend="italic">bring</hi>. This is the fruit of faith. First the tree is good, and then
                    the fruit is good also.</p>
                <p n="3">
                    <pb n="195"/>3. I cannot describe the nature of this faith better than in
                    the words of our own Church: ‘The only instrument of salvation’ (whereof
                    justification is one branch) ‘is faith: that is […] a sure trust and confidence
                    […] that God both hath and will forgive our sins, that he hath accepted us again
                    into his favour, […] for the merits of Christ’s death and Passion…. But here we
                    must take heed that we do not halt with God through an inconstant, wavering
                    faith. […] Peter coming to Christ upon the water, because he fainted in faith,
                    was in danger of drowning. So we, if we begin to waver or doubt, it is to be
                    feared that we should sink as Peter did, not into the water but into the
                    bottomless pit of hell-fire.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Second Sermon on the Passion [<hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, pp. 382-83].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3.2">Therefore have ‘a sure and constant faith, not only that the death of
                    Christ is available for […] all the world, […] but […] that he hath made […] a
                    full and sufficient sacrifice for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, a perfect
                    cleansing of <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> sins, so that […] thou mayst say with
                    the Apostle, […] he loved <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, and gave himself for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note> For this is […] to make
                    Christ <hi rend="italic">thine own</hi>, and to apply his merits unto <hi rend="italic">thyself</hi>.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Sermon on the Sacrament, First Part [<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 399].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. By affirming that this faith is the term or <hi rend="italic">condition</hi> of justification I mean, first, that there is no
                    justification without it. ‘He that believeth not is condemned already;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                        3:18.</p>
                    </note> and so long as he believeth not that condemnation cannot be
                    removed, ‘but the wrath of God abideth on him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:36.</p>
                    </note> As ‘there is no other
                    name given under heaven than that of Jesus of Nazareth,’ no other merit whereby
                    a condemned sinner can ever be saved from the guilt of sin;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 4:10, 12.</p>
                    </note>
                    so there is no other way of obtaining a share in his merit than ‘by faith in his
                        name’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 3:16.</p>
                    </note> So that as long as we are without this faith we
                    are ‘strangers to the covenant of promise’, we are ‘aliens from the commonwealth
                    of Israel’, and ‘without God in the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> Whatsoever virtues (so
                    called) a man may have—I speak of those unto whom the gospel is preached; ‘for
                    what have I to do to judge them that are without?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                    5:12.</p>
                    </note>—whatsoever good works (so accounted) he may do, it profiteth
                    not: he is still a ‘child of wrath’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> still under the curse,
                    till he believes in Jesus.</p>
                <p n="5">
                    <pb n="196"/>5. Faith therefore is the <hi rend="italic">necessary</hi>
                    condition of justification. Yea, and the <hi rend="italic">only necessary</hi>
                    condition thereof. This is the second point carefully to be observed: that the
                    very moment God giveth faith (for ‘it is the gift of God’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:8; thus faith is not a
                            meritorious ‘work’.</p>
                    </note> to the ‘ungodly’, ‘that worketh not’,
                    that ‘faith is counted to him for righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> He
                    hath no righteousness at all antecedent to this, not so much as negative
                        righteousness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., Adam’s state before temptation and its
                            bearing on the problem of ‘original righteousness’; cf. St. Irenaeus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Against Heresies</hi>, III. xxii.v., and St.
                            Athanasius, <hi rend="italic">Contra Gentes</hi>, 3. The Lutheran
                            theologians had discussed <hi rend="italic">iustitia originalis</hi> and
                            had rejected any correlation of that with any <hi rend="italic">status
                                purorum naturalium</hi> (cf. Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal
                                Theology</hi>, pp. 230-31, and see his citations of Gerhard,
                            Calixtus, and Quenstedt). For the phrase, ‘negative righteousness’, cf.
                            William Allen, <hi rend="italic">The Glass of Justification</hi> (1658),
                            p. 20.</p>
                    </note> or innocence. But ‘faith is imputed to him for
                    righteousness’ the very moment that he believeth. Not that God (as was observed
                    before) thinketh him to be what he is not. But as ‘he made Christ to be sin for
                        us’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                            Cor. 5:21.</p>
                    </note> (that is, treated him as a sinner, punished him
                    for our sins), so he counteth us righteous from the time we believe in him (that
                    is, he doth not punish us for our sins, yea, treats us as though we were
                    guiltless and righteous).</p>
                <p n="6">6. Surely the difficulty of assenting to this proposition, that faith is
                    the <hi rend="italic">only condition</hi> of justification, must arise from not
                    understanding it. We mean thereby thus much: that it is the only thing without
                    which none is justified, the only thing that is immediately, indispensably,
                    absolutely requisite in order to pardon. As on the one hand, though a man should
                    have everything else, without faith, yet he cannot be justified; so on the
                    other, though he be supposed to want everything else, yet if he hath faith he
                    cannot but be justified. For suppose a sinner of any kind or degree, in a full
                    sense of his total ungodliness, of his utter inability to think, speak, or do
                    good, and his absolute meetness for hell-fire—suppose, I say, this sinner,
                    helpless and hopeless, casts himself wholly on the mercy of God in Christ (which
                    indeed he cannot do but by the grace of God)—who can doubt but he is forgiven in
                    that moment? Who will affirm that any more is <hi rend="italic">indispensably
                        required</hi> before that sinner can be justified?</p>
                <p n="6.2">Now if there ever was one such instance from the beginning of the world
                    (and have there not been, and are there not ten <pb n="197"/>thousand times ten
                        thousand?)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Dan. 7:10.</p>
                    </note> it plainly follows that faith is, in the above
                    sense, the sole condition of justification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s starkest assertion, in any of his
                            writings, of the <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi>, for here he excludes
                            even <hi rend="italic">repentance</hi>, which elsewhere he conjoins with
                            faith as the human components of justification. See, e.g., No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, II.6; <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, 1745; <hi rend="italic">Principles of a
                                Methodist Farther Explained</hi>, VI.4; and his <hi rend="italic">Letter to a Gentleman at Bristol</hi>, Jan. 6, 1758. See also
                            Wesley’s extracts of the lives of Henry and James Fraser in the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, L.98-99, and XLIX.299. For a
                            doctrine of <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi> nuanced rather differently
                            and yet still in the same tradition, cf. Joseph Mede, Discourse XXVI,
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1677), pp. 113-15, and also Cockman,
                                <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Jesus Christ
                    Alone…</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. It does not become poor, guilty, sinful worms, who receive whatsoever
                    blessings they enjoy (from the least drop of water that cools our tongue<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                            16:24.</p>
                    </note> to the immense riches of glory in eternity) of grace,
                    of mere favour, and not of debt, to ask of God the reasons of his conduct. It is
                    not meet for us to call him in question ‘who giveth account to none of his
                        ways’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Job 33:13.</p>
                    </note> to demand, ‘Why didst thou make faith the
                    condition, the only condition of justification? Wherefore didst thou decree, “He
                    that believeth”, and he only, “shall be saved”?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 16:16.</p>
                    </note> This is
                    the very point on which St. Paul so strongly insists in the ninth chapter of
                    this Epistle, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, that the terms of pardon and
                    acceptance must depend, not on us, but ‘on him that calleth us’; that there is
                    no ‘unrighteousness with God’ in fixing his own terms, not according to ours,
                    but his own good pleasure: who may justly say, ‘I will have mercy on whom I will
                    have mercy,’ namely, on him who believeth in Jesus. ‘So then it is not of him
                    that willeth, nor of him that runneth’, to choose the condition on which he
                    shall find acceptance, ‘but of God that showeth mercy,’ that accepteth none at
                    all but of his own free love, his unmerited goodness. ‘Therefore hath he mercy
                    on whom he will have mercy,’ <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, on those who believe
                    on the Son of his love; ‘and whom he will’, that is, those who believe not, ‘he
                    hardeneth’—leaves at last to the hardness of their hearts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 9:11, 14-16,
                        18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. One reason, however, we may humbly conceive, of God’s fixing this
                    condition of justification—‘If thou believest in the Lord Jesus Christ thou
                    shalt be saved’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 16:31.</p>
                    </note>—was to ‘hide pride from man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 33:17. This
                            is one of Calvin’s main points, in the <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi>, III, xii. 3-7, where (after quoting Augustine) he
                            identifies pride as the chief obstacle to faith. See also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, xiii. 2, 4.</p>
                    </note> Pride had already
                    destroyed the very angels of God, had <pb n="198"/>cast down a ‘third part of
                    the stars of heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 8:12; 12:4.</p>
                    </note> It was likewise in
                    great measure owing to this, when the tempter said, ‘Ye shall be as gods,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 3:5; see
                            also Nos. 141, ‘The Image of God’; and 45, ‘The New Birth’, I.4 and n.,
                            for further interpretations of the Fall.</p>
                    </note> that Adam fell from
                    his own steadfastness and brought sin and death into the world. It was therefore
                    an instance of wisdom worthy of God to appoint such a condition of
                    reconciliation for him and all his posterity as might effectually humble, might
                    abase them to the dust. And such is faith. It is peculiarly fitted for this end.
                    For he that cometh unto God by this faith must fix his eye singly on his own
                    wickedness, on his guilt and helplessness, without having the least regard to
                    any supposed good in himself, to any virtue or righteousness whatsoever. He must
                    come as a <hi rend="italic">mere sinner</hi> inwardly and outwardly,
                    self-destroyed and self-condemned, bringing nothing to God but ungodliness only,
                    pleading nothing of his own but sin and misery. Thus it is, and thus alone, when
                    his ‘mouth is stopped’, and he stands utterly ‘guilty before God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:19.</p>
                    </note> that he can ‘look unto Jesus’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> as
                    the whole and sole ‘propitiation for his sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:2;
                        4:10.</p>
                    </note> Thus only can he be ‘found in him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:9.</p>
                    </note> and
                    receive the ‘righteousness which is of God by faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                    3:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. Thou ungodly one who hearest or readest these words, thou vile,
                    helpless, miserable sinner, I charge thee before God, the judge of all, go
                    straight unto him with all thy ungodliness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the abrupt change here from exposition
                            to direct and sustained exhortation. Cf. Wesley’s letter to Joseph
                            Taylor, Feb. 14, 1787: ‘A sermon should be all application.’ Also, No.
                            20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our Righteousness</hi>, II.20. This,
                            then, is the carryover into a written sermon of a dominant feature of
                            Wesley’s oral preaching.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">This, of course, was
                            not original with Wesley; English preaching was strong on ‘application’.
                            Cf., e.g., John Selden, <hi rend="italic">Table Talk</hi> (1689), p. 92:
                            ‘Nothing is text but what was spoken in the Bible, and meant there for
                            person, and place; the rest is <hi rend="italic">application</hi>, which
                            a discreet man may do well; but ’tis his Scripture, not the Holy Ghost.’
                            See also Tillotson, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.560; Samuel
                            Annesley’s sermon ‘On Conscience’ in <hi rend="italic">The Morning
                                Exercise at Cripplegate</hi> (1661), p. 7; and Robert South’s sermon
                            on 1 Sam. 25:32, 33, preached at Christ Church, Oxford, Nov. 10, 1673,
                            which Wesley extracted for the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>,
                            XLIII.141-49.</p>
                    </note> Take heed thou destroy not thy own soul by
                    pleading thy righteousness, more or less. Go as altogether ungodly, guilty,
                    lost, destroyed, deserving and dropping into hell, and thou shalt then find
                    favour in his sight, and know that he justifieth the ungodly. As such thou <pb n="199"/>shalt be brought unto the ‘blood of sprinkling’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:24.</p>
                    </note>
                    as an undone, helpless, damned sinner. Thus ‘look unto Jesus’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:2.</p>
                    </note>
                    There is ‘the Lamb of God, who taketh away <hi rend="italic">thy</hi>
                        sins’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 1:29.</p>
                    </note> Plead thou no works, no righteousness of thine
                    own; no humility, contrition, sincerity! In no wise. That were, in very deed, to
                    deny the Lord that bought thee. No. Plead thou singly the blood of the
                        covenant,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 24:8; Heb. 10:29.</p>
                    </note> the ransom paid for thy proud,
                    stubborn, sinful soul. Who art thou that now seest and feelest both thine inward
                    and outward ungodliness? Thou art the man!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Sam. 12:7.</p>
                    </note> I want thee for my
                    Lord. I challenge <hi rend="italic">thee</hi> for a child of God by faith. The
                    Lord hath need of thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 21:3, etc.</p>
                    </note> Thou who feelest
                    thou art just fit for hell art just fit to advance his glory: the glory of his
                    free grace, justifying the ungodly and him that worketh not. O come quickly.
                    Believe in the Lord Jesus; and <hi rend="italic">thou</hi>, even <hi rend="italic">thou</hi>, art reconciled to God.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>