<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 46: The Wilderness State</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 46: The Wilderness State</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="221"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:202"/>
            <introduction>
                <p><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 46-47]</hi></p>
                <p>Like that of true love, the course of true <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> never did
                    run smooth (cf. Thomas Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">A Child of Light Walking in
                        Darkness</hi> (1636); abridged by Wesley in the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                        Library</hi> (1751), Vol. XI; and Hugh Binning, <hi rend="italic">Fellowship
                        With God</hi>, especially Sermon XIV). There is, therefore, a natural
                    progress in following a sermon on conversion with two further comments on the
                    peaks and valleys in a Christian pilgrim’s progress. That is the point to this
                    particular pair of sermons, Nos. 46, ‘The Wilderness State’, and 47, ‘Heaviness
                    through Manifold Temptations’. By 1760 Wesley knew, from long experience, how
                    regularly any stress on the <hi rend="italic">necessity</hi> of assurance would
                    raise the levels of religious anxiety amongst his hearers and disciples. Even
                    earlier, he had pondered Thomas à Kempis’s generalization (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Imitation</hi>, II. ix. 7): ‘I never found anyone so religious and devout
                    that he had not sometimes a withdrawing of grace or felt not some decrease of
                    zeal.’ He also remembered how quickly the euphoria of his own Aldersgate
                    experience had passed (cf. JWJ, May 26, 1738, ‘My soul continued in peace, but
                    yet in heaviness because of manifold temptations,’ and May 28, ‘I waked in
                    peace, but not in joy’).</p>
                <p>Thus, wary though he was of allegorizing, he found himself turning to the Old
                    Testament story of the sojourn of the Children of Israel in the wilderness of
                    Sinai as a metaphor for the anxieties and depressions that follow upon ‘the new
                    birth’. This allegory was already a familiar one among the Puritans. There was,
                    e.g., Samuel Mather’s <hi rend="italic">Figures or Types of the Old
                        Testament</hi> (Dublin, 1683); Mather had understood ‘wilderness’ to mean
                    ‘the wilderness of this world’ through which ‘Christ directs and conducts his
                    people in their travels…to the true Canaan’ (p. 170; cf. p. 192). Thus it was
                    clear to him that just ‘as the Ark of God had led [the Israelites] through the
                    Wilderness, so we are to follow the guidance of Christ through the world’ (p.
                    510). Mather had also cited (pp. 200-201) a quite different interpretation in
                    Jeremiah Burroughs (whom Wesley also knew) in <hi rend="italic">The Excellency
                        of </hi><pb n="02:203"/><hi rend="italic">Holy Courage in Evil Times</hi>
                    (1661), where ‘the wilderness state’ is understood as ‘an unregenerate
                    condition’ before conversion (cf. chs. 25-26 and Burroughs’s comments on Heb.
                    11:27). In Robert Gell’s <hi rend="italic">Remaines</hi>, I.16, the reference
                    had been transferred from the wilderness of Sinai to Jesus’ experience of ‘forty
                    days and nights’ in the wilderness of Judea. Wesley had followed Gell in this,
                    at least once, in Bristol (cf. JWJ, March 28, 1740): ‘From these words, “Then
                    was Jesus led by the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil,” I
                    took occasion to describe that wilderness state, that state of doubts and fears
                    and strong temptations which so many go through, though in different degrees,
                    after they have received remission of sins.’</p>
                <p>From none of these sources, however, could one have anticipated Wesley’s
                    uncommonly sharp distinction, now in 1760, between ‘the wilderness state’ as
                    ‘darkness’ (i.e., an actual ‘loss of faith’ and ‘a total loss of joy’; in
                    effect, a relapse from faith into unfaith that simply reverses the positive
                    processes of salvation) and ‘heaviness’ (religious depression) which is more or
                    less normal, and thus not a valid ground for prolonged anxiety or despair. But
                    this is the distinction which is expounded, along with its psychological
                    implications, in the two sermons here (and also, presumably, in his thirty-five
                    oral sermons on John 16:22). It had been summarized in the manuscript Minutes of
                    1744 (<hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 10) and then
                    commented on in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>: ‘This [John 16:22] gives
                    us no manner of authority to assert that all believers <hi rend="italic"
                        >must</hi> come into a state of darkness. They never <hi rend="italic"
                        >need</hi> lose either their peace or their love, or the witness that they
                    are the children of God. They can never lose these, but either through sin, or
                    ignorance, or vehement temptation, or bodily disorders.’ This same idea will be
                    repeated in letters to Mrs. Marston, August 11, 1770, and to Rebecca Yeoman,
                    February 5, 1772 (who is urged to read ‘The Wilderness State’ in ‘the fourth
                    volume, and examine yourself thereby’). Charles Wesley, however, had understood
                    ‘the wilderness state’ rather as Gell had done: ‘that [condition] into which the
                    believer is generally led by the Spirit to be tempted as soon as he is baptized
                    by the Holy Ghost’ (CWJ, August 26, 1739).</p>
                <p>It would be interesting to know how John Wesley understood his own episodes of
                    acute religious anxiety. By 1780 he could ‘not remember to have felt lowness of
                    spirits for one quarter of an hour since I was born’ (see No. 77, ‘Spiritual
                    Worship’, III.2). Actually, though, he has been through <hi rend="italic"
                        >many</hi> such episodes both early and late (as in his letter to
                    ‘Varanese’, February 6, 1736; or, in JWJ, January 4, 1739; or, again, in a
                    letter to Elizabeth Hardy, May 1758: ‘I felt the wrath of God abiding on me. I
                    was afraid of dropping into hell;’ and another to Mrs. <pb n="02:204"/>Ryan,
                    November 4, 1758). The most remarkable of these is mirrored in an outburst to
                    his brother Charles, June 26, 1766: ‘In one of [[my]] last [letters] [[I]] was
                    saying, [[I]] do not feel the wrath of God abiding on [[me]]…. [[I do not love
                    God. I never did]]…. [[I have no]] direct witness… [[I]] have no more fear than
                    love. Or if [[I have any fear, it is not that of falling]] into hell, but of
                    falling into nothing.’ (The words within double brackets are transcribed from
                    shorthand.) Was this a case of ‘heaviness’ or ‘darkness’, or what?</p>
                <p>‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’ is the linked sequel to ‘The Wilderness
                    State’, designed to help believers avoid any further slide from depression into
                    ‘darkness’ or sinful despair. Thus, it seeks to lay out ‘the wide and essential
                    difference between “darkness” and “heaviness”’. He had already done this in
                    sixteen oral sermons on 1 Pet. 1:6 between 1754 and 1757, which suggests that
                    the problem of religious anxiety had become more widespread and urgent in and
                    after the upswing in ‘professors of perfection’ in 1755. At any rate, this
                    particular pair of sermons seems to have been written expressly for <hi
                        rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV (1760). They were reprinted in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Works</hi> (1771), IV, and again in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV (1787),
                    but were not otherwise printed separately.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:205"/>
            <head>The Wilderness State</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>John 16:22</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ye now have sorrow; but I will see you again, and your heart
                        shall rejoice, and your joy no man taketh from you.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. After God had wrought a great deliverance for Israel by bringing them
                    out of the house of bondage,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Exod. 13:3.</p></note> they did not immediately
                    enter into the land which he had promised to their fathers, but ‘wandered out of
                    the way in the wilderness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 107:40 (BCP).</p></note> and were variously
                    tempted and distressed. In like manner after God has delivered them that fear
                    him from the bondage of sin and Satan; after they are ‘justified freely by his
                    grace, through the redemption that is in Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                        n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:24.</p></note> yet not many of them
                    immediately enter into ‘the rest’ which ‘remaineth for the people of God’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                        4:9.</p></note> The greater part of them wander more or less out of the good
                    way into which he hath brought them. They come as it were into a ‘waste and
                    howling desert’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Deut. 32:1</p></note> where they are variously tempted and
                    tormented. And this some, in allusion to the case of the Israelites, have termed
                    ‘a wilderness state’.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Certain it is that the condition wherein these are has a right to the
                    tenderest compassion. They labour under an evil and sore disease, though one
                    that is not commonly understood. And for this very reason it is the more
                    difficult for them to find a remedy. Being in darkness themselves, they cannot
                    be supposed to understand the nature of their own disorder; and few of their
                    brethren—nay, perhaps of their teachers—know either what their sickness is, or
                    how to heal it. So much the more need there is to inquire, first, what is the
                    nature of this disease; secondly, what is the cause; and thirdly, what is the
                    cure of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, what is the nature of this disease into which so many
                    fall after they have believed? Wherein does it properly <pb n="02:206"/>consist?
                    And what are the genuine symptoms of it? It properly consists in the loss of
                    that faith which God once wrought in their heart. They that are ‘in the
                    wilderness’ have not now that divine ‘evidence’, that satisfactory ‘conviction
                    of things not seen’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:1. See No. 3, ‘<hi rend="italic">Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest</hi>’, I.11 and n.</p></note> which they once
                    enjoyed. They have not now that inward demonstration of the Spirit which before
                    enabled each of them to say, ‘The life I live, I live by faith in the Son of
                    God, who loved <hi rend="italic">me</hi> and gave himself for <hi rend="italic"
                        >me</hi>.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 2:20.</p></note> The light of heaven does not now ‘shine in their
                        hearts’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                            Cor. 4:6.</p></note> neither do they ‘see him that is invisible’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                        11:27.</p></note> but darkness is again on the face of their souls, and
                    blindness on the eyes of their understanding. The Spirit no longer ‘witnesses
                    with their spirits that they are the children of God’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p></note>
                    neither does he continue as the Spirit of adoption, ‘crying in their hearts,
                    Abba, Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Gal. 4:6.</p></note> They have not now a sure trust in his love,
                    and a liberty of approaching him with holy boldness. ‘Though he slay me, yet
                    will I trust in him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Job 13:15.</p></note> is no more the language of
                    their heart. But they are shorn of their strength, and become weak and
                    feeble-minded, even as other men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. the story of Samson in Judg. 16:7, 11,
                        19.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. Hence, secondly, proceeds the loss of love, which cannot but rise or
                    fall at the same time, and in the same proportion, with true, living faith.
                    Accordingly they that are deprived of their faith are deprived of the love of
                    God also. They cannot now say, ‘Lord, thou knowest all things; thou knowest that
                    I love thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >John 21:17.</p></note> They are not now happy in God, as everyone is
                    that truly loves him. They do not delight in him as in time past, and ‘smell the
                    odour of his ointments’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 12:3.</p></note> Once all their ‘desire
                    was unto him, and to the remembrance of his name’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 26:8.</p></note> But
                    now even their desires are cold and dead, if not utterly extinguished. And as
                    their love of God is ‘waxed cold’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 24:12.</p></note> so is also their love
                    of their neighbour. They have not now that zeal for the souls of men, that
                    longing after their welfare, that fervent, restless, active desire of their
                    being reconciled to God. They do not feel those ‘bowels of mercies’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Col.
                        3:12.</p></note> for the sheep that are lost, that tender ‘compassion for
                    the ignorant, and them that are out of the way’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 5:2.</p></note> Once
                    they were <pb n="02:207"/>‘gentle toward all men’, meekly ‘instructing’ such as
                    ‘opposed’ the truth,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 2:24-25.</p></note> and ‘if any was
                    overtaken in a fault, restoring such an one in the spirit of meekness’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                        6:1.</p></note> But after a suspense perhaps of many days, anger begins to
                    regain its power. Yea, peevishness and impatience thrust sore at them, that they
                    may fall.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            118:13.</p></note> And it is well if they are not sometimes driven even
                    to ‘render evil for evil and railing for railing’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 3:9.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. In consequence of the loss of faith and love follows, thirdly, loss of
                    joy in the Holy Ghost. For if the loving consciousness of pardon be no more, the
                    joy resulting therefrom cannot remain. If the Spirit does not witness with our
                    spirit that we are the children of God, the joy that flowed from that inward
                    witness must also be at an end. And in like manner they who once ‘rejoiced with
                    joy unspeakable in hope of the glory’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:8.</p></note> of God, now they are
                    deprived of that ‘hope full of immortality’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 3:4.</p></note> are deprived of the joy
                    it occasioned; as also of that which resulted from a consciousness of ‘the love
                    of God’ then ‘shed abroad in their hearts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26"
                        n="26"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:5.</p></note> For the cause being
                    removed, so is the effect: the fountain being dammed up, those living waters
                    spring no more to refresh the thirsty soul.</p>
                <p n="4">4. With loss of faith and love and joy there is also joined, fourthly, the
                    loss of that peace which once passed all understanding. That sweet tranquillity
                    of mind, that composure of spirit, is gone. Painful doubt returns: doubt whether
                    we ever did, and perhaps whether we ever shall, believe. We begin to doubt
                    whether we ever did find in our hearts the real testimony of the Spirit. Whether
                    we did not rather deceive our own souls, and mistake the voice of nature for the
                    voice of God. Nay, and perhaps whether we shall ever hear his voice and find
                    favour in his sight. And these doubts are again joined with servile fear, with
                    that ‘fear’ which ‘hath torment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 4:18.</p></note> We fear the wrath of God,
                    even as before we believed; we fear lest we should be cast out of his presence;
                    and thence sink again into that fear of death from which we were before wholly
                    delivered.</p>
                <p n="5">5. But even this is not all. For loss of peace is accompanied with loss of
                    power. We know everyone who has peace with God through Jesus Christ has power
                    over all sin. But whenever he <pb n="02:208"/>loses the peace of God he loses
                    also the power over sin. While that peace remained, power also remained, even
                    over the besetting sin, whether it were the sin of his nature, his constitution,
                    the sin of his education, or that of his profession; yea, and over those evil
                    tempers and desires which till then he could not conquer. ‘Sin’ had then ‘no
                    more dominion over him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 6:14.</p></note> but he hath now no more
                    dominion over sin. He may struggle indeed, but he cannot overcome; the crown is
                    fallen from his head. His enemies again prevail over him, and more or less bring
                    him into bondage. The glory is departed from him,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 10:18.</p></note>
                    even the kingdom of God which was in his heart. He is dispossessed of
                    righteousness, as well as of peace and joy in the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 14:17.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Such is the nature of what many have termed, and not improperly,
                    ‘the wilderness state’. But the nature of it may be more fully understood by
                    inquiring, secondly, What are the causes of it? These indeed are various. But I
                    dare not rank among these the bare, arbitrary, sovereign will of God. He
                    rejoiceth ‘in the prosperity of his servants’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                        n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 35:27.</p></note> He delighteth not
                    to ‘afflict or grieve the children of men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32"
                        n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Lam. 3:33.</p></note> His invariable
                    ‘will is our sanctification’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 4:3.</p></note> attended with ‘peace
                    and joy in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p></note> These are his own free
                    gifts; and we are assured ‘the gifts of God are’ on his part ‘without
                        repentance.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 11:29.</p></note> He never repenteth of what he hath given, or
                    desires to withdraw them from us. Therefore he never <hi rend="italic"
                        >deserts</hi> us, as some speak: it is we only that <hi rend="italic"
                        >desert</hi> him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The reference here is twofold: to the mystical
                            theories (as in St. John of the Cross) of God’s withdrawal from the
                            believer in ‘the dark night of the soul’, and to Lutheran explanations
                            of religious depressions (<hi rend="italic">Anfechtungen</hi>) in terms
                            of the concept of the <hi rend="italic">Deus absconditus</hi> (God’s
                            withdrawals of himself).</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. [(I).] The most usual cause of inward darkness is <hi rend="italic"
                        >sin</hi> of one kind or another. This it is which generally occasions what
                    is often a complication of sin and misery. And, first, sin of <hi rend="italic"
                        >commission</hi>. This may frequently be observed to darken the soul in a
                    moment; especially if it be a known, a wilful, or presumptuous sin. If, for
                    instance, a person who is now walking in the clear light of God’s countenance
                    should be any way prevailed on to commit a single act of drunkenness or
                    uncleanness, it would be no wonder if in <pb n="02:209"/>that very hour he fell
                    into utter darkness. It is true, there have been some very rare cases wherein
                    God has prevented this by an extraordinary display of his pardoning mercy,
                    almost in the very instant. But in general such an abuse of the goodness of God,
                    so gross an insult on his love, occasions an immediate estrangement from God,
                    and a ‘darkness that may be felt’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 10:21.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. But it may be hoped this case is not very frequent; that there are not
                    many who so despise the riches of his goodness as, while they walk in his light,
                    so grossly and presumptuously to rebel against him. That light is much more
                    frequently lost by giving way to sins of <hi rend="italic">omission</hi>.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 14, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.14 and
                        n.</p></note> This indeed does not immediately quench the Spirit,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess.
                            5:19.</p></note> but gradually and slowly. The former may be compared to
                    pouring water upon a fire; the latter to withdrawing the fuel from it. And many
                    times will that loving Spirit reprove our neglect before he departs from us.
                    Many are the inward checks, the secret notices, he gives before his influences
                    are withdrawn. So that only a train of omissions wilfully persisted in can bring
                    us into utter darkness.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Perhaps no sin of omission more frequently occasions this than the
                    neglect of private prayer; the want whereof cannot be supplied by any other
                    ordinance whatever. Nothing can be more plain than that the life of God in the
                    soul does not continue, much less increase, unless we use all opportunities of
                    communing with God, and pouring out our hearts before him. If therefore we are
                    negligent of this, if we suffer business, company, or any avocation whatever, to
                    prevent these secret exercises of the soul (or which comes to the same thing, to
                    make us hurry them over in a slight and careless manner) that life will surely
                    decay. And if we long or frequently intermit them, it will gradually die
                    away.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Another sin of omission which frequently brings the soul of a believer
                    into darkness is the neglect of what was so strongly enjoined even under the
                    Jewish dispensation: ‘Thou shalt in any wise rebuke thy neighbour, and not
                    suffer sin upon him:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Lev. 19:17.</p></note> ‘Thou shalt not hate thy
                    brother in thy heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> Now if we
                    do ‘hate our brother in our heart’, if we do not ‘rebuke’ him when we see him in
                    a fault, but ‘suffer sin upon him’, this will soon bring leanness into our own
                    soul; seeing hereby we are ‘partakers of his sin’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 18:4.</p></note> By
                        <pb n="02:210"/>neglecting to reprove our neighbour we make his sin our own.
                    We become accountable for it to God: we saw his danger, and gave him no warning.
                    So ‘if he perish in his iniquity’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Josh. 22:20.</p></note> God may justly ‘require
                    his blood at our hands’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Sam. 4:11; Ezek. 3:18; 33:8.</p></note> No
                    wonder then if by thus grieving the Spirit we lose the light of his
                        countenance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. No. 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’.</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. A third cause of our losing this is the giving way to some kind of <hi
                        rend="italic">inward sin</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9, and n.</p></note> For example: we
                    know ‘everyone that is proud in heart is an abomination to the Lord;’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Prov.
                        16:5.</p></note> and that although this pride of heart should not appear in
                    the outward conversation. Now how easily may a soul filled with peace and joy
                    fall into this snare of the devil! How natural is it for him to imagine that he
                    has more grace, more wisdom or strength, than he really has! ‘To think more
                    highly of himself than he ought to think!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48"
                        n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:3.</p></note> How natural to
                    glory in something he has received as if he had not received it!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            4:7.</p></note> But seeing God continually ‘resisteth the proud, and
                    giveth grace’ only ‘to the humble’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:5.</p></note> this must certainly obscure,
                    if not wholly destroy, the light which before shone on his heart.</p>
                <p n="7">7. The same effect may be produced by giving place to anger, whatever the
                    provocation or occasion be; yea, though it were coloured over with the name of
                        <hi rend="italic">zeal</hi> for the truth, or for the glory of God. Indeed
                    all zeal which is any other than the flame of love is ‘earthly, animal,
                        devilish’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Jas. 3:15 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>). See No. 92, ‘On Zeal’, for
                            this point enlarged.</p></note> It is the flame of wrath. It is flat,
                    sinful anger, neither better nor worse. And nothing is a greater enemy to the
                    mild, gentle love of God than this. They never did, they never can, subsist
                    together in one breast. In the same proportion as this prevails, love and joy in
                    the Holy Ghost decrease. This is particularly observable in the case of <hi
                        rend="italic">offence</hi>, I mean, anger at any of our brethren, at any of
                    those who are united with us either by civil or religious ties. If we give way
                    to the spirit of offence but one hour we lose the sweet influences of the Holy
                    Spirit; so that instead of amending them we destroy ourselves, and become an
                    easy prey to any enemy that assaults us.</p>
                <p n="8">8. But suppose we are aware of this snare of the devil, we may be attacked
                    from another quarter. When fierceness and anger are asleep, and love alone is
                    waking, we may be no less endangered by <pb n="02:211"/><hi rend="italic"
                        >desire</hi>, which equally tends to darken the soul. This is the sure
                    effect of any ‘foolish desire’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:9 (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Notes</hi>).</p></note> any vain or inordinate affection. If we ‘set our
                    affection on things of the earth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:2.</p></note> on any person or thing
                    under the sun, if we desire anything but God and what tends to God, if we seek
                    happiness in any creature, the jealous God will surely contend with us; for he
                    can admit of no rival. And ‘if we ‘will’ not ‘hear’ his warning ‘voice’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 95:7;
                            Heb. 3:7, 15.</p></note> and return to him with our whole soul; if we
                    continue to grieve him with our idols, and running after other gods, we shall
                    soon be cold, barren, and dry, and ‘the god of this world’ will ‘blind’ and
                    darken ‘our hearts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:4.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. But this he frequently does, even when we do not give way to any
                    positive sin. It is enough, it gives him sufficient advantage, if we do not
                    ‘stir up the gift of God which is in us’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56"
                        n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 1:6.</p></note> if we do not
                    ‘agonize’ continually ‘to enter in at the strait gate’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 13:24 (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Notes</hi>).</p></note> if we do not earnestly ‘strive for the
                        mastery’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 2 Tim. 2:5.</p></note> and ‘take the kingdom of heaven by
                        violence’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Matt. 11:12 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p></note> There needs
                    no more than not to fight, and we are sure to be conquered. Let us only be
                    careless or ‘faint in our mind’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:3.</p></note> let us be easy and
                    indolent, and our natural darkness will soon return, and overspread our soul. It
                    is enough, therefore, if we give way to <hi rend="italic">spiritual sloth</hi>:
                    this will effectually darken the soul. It will as surely destroy the light of
                    God, if not so swiftly, as murder or adultery.</p>
                <p n="10">10. But it is well to be observed that the cause of our darkness
                    (whatsoever it be, whether omission or commission, whether inward or outward
                    sin) is not always nigh at hand. Sometimes the sin which occasioned the present
                    distress may lie at a considerable distance. It might be committed days or weeks
                    or months before. And that God now withdraws his light and peace on account of
                    what was done so long ago is not (as one might at first imagine) an instance of
                    his severity, but rather a proof of his long-suffering and tender mercy. He
                    waited all this time if haply we would see, acknowledge, and correct what was
                    amiss. And in default of this he at length shows his displeasure, if thus, at
                        last,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">Orig.,
                            ‘least’, altered in 1771 and 1787.</p></note> he may bring us to
                    repentance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1"><pb n="02:212"/>(II). 1. Another general cause of this darkness is <hi
                        rend="italic">ignorance</hi>; which is likewise of various kinds. If men
                    know not the Scriptures, if they imagine there are passages either in the Old or
                    New Testament which assert that all believers without exception <hi
                        rend="italic">must</hi> sometimes be in darkness, this ignorance will
                    naturally bring upon them the darkness which they expect. And how common a case
                    has this been among us! How few are there that do not expect it! And no wonder,
                    seeing they are taught to expect it; seeing their guides lead them into this
                    way. Not only the mystic writers of the Romish Church, but many of the most
                    spiritual and experimental in our own (very few of the last century excepted),
                    lay it down with all assurance as a plain, unquestionable Scripture doctrine,
                    and cite many texts to prove it.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Ignorance also of the work of God in the soul frequently occasions this
                    darkness. Men imagine (because so they have been taught, particularly by writers
                    of the Romish communion, whose plausible assertions too many Protestants have
                    received without due examination) that they are not always to walk in ‘luminous
                    faith’; that this is only a ‘lower dispensation’; that as they rise higher they
                    are to leave those ‘sensible comforts’, and to live by ‘naked faith’ (<hi
                        rend="italic">naked</hi> indeed, if it be stripped both of love and peace
                    and joy in the Holy Ghost!); that a state of light and joy is good, but a state
                    of ‘darkness’ and ‘dryness’ is better, that it is by these alone we can be
                    ‘purified’ from pride, love of the world, and inordinate self-love; and that
                    therefore we ought neither to expect nor desire to ‘walk in the light’
                        always.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            St. John of the Cross, <hi rend="italic">Ascent of Mount Carmel</hi>,
                            II.ii, in <hi rend="italic">Complete Works</hi> (1933), I.68 ff.; see
                            also <hi rend="italic">The Dark Night of the Soul</hi>, I.ix-x, <hi
                                rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, I.373-80.</p></note> Hence it is (though
                    other reasons may concur) that the main body of pious men in the Romish Church
                    generally walk in a dark uncomfortable way, and if ever they receive, soon lose
                    the light of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Jean Orcibal, ‘The Theological Originality of
                            John Wesley and Continental Spirituality’ (see above, Vol. 1, pp. 36,
                            75). Besides his conventional, lifelong anti-Roman prejudices, Wesley
                            was predisposed to take the gloom of the Jansenists and even of M. de
                            Renty as normative. Thus he ignored the lilting ‘folk-spirituality’ of
                            the Ursulines, the Oratorians, the Salesians (and eighteenth-century
                            Catholicism generally), so lovingly recounted by Henri Bremond in a
                            classic study, <hi rend="italic">A Literary History of Religious Thought
                                in France</hi> (French text, 1916; Eng. tr., London, SPCK, 1928,
                            1930), 2 vols.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">(III). 1. A third general cause of this darkness is <hi rend="italic"
                        >temptation</hi>. When the candle of the Lord first shines on our head,
                    temptation frequently flees away, and totally disappears. All is calm within:
                        <pb n="02:213"/>perhaps without, too, while God makes our enemies to be at
                    peace with us. It is then very natural to suppose that we shall not see war any
                    more. And there are instances wherein this calm has continued, not only for
                    weeks, but for months or years. But commonly it is otherwise: in a short time
                    ‘the winds blow, the rains descend, and the floods arise’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:25, 27.</p></note>
                    anew. They who ‘know not either the Son or the Father’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 8:19.</p></note> and
                    consequently hate his children, when God slackens the bridle which is in their
                    teeth, will show that hatred in various instances. As of old ‘he that was born
                    after the flesh persecuted him that was born after the Spirit, even so it is
                        now;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                            4:29.</p></note> the same cause still producing the same effect. The
                    evil which yet remains in the heart will then also move afresh; anger and many
                    other ‘roots of bitterness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:15.</p></note> will endeavour to spring
                    up. At the same time Satan will not be wanting to cast in his fiery darts;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            6:16.</p></note> and the soul will have to ‘wrestle’, not only with the
                    world, not only ‘with flesh and blood, but with principalities and powers, with
                    the rulers of the darkness of this world, with wicked spirits in high
                        places’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 6:12.</p></note> Now when so various assaults are made at once, and
                    perhaps with the utmost violence, it is not strange if it should occasion not
                    only heaviness, but even darkness in a weak believer. More especially if he was
                    not watching, if these assaults are made in an hour when he looked not for them;
                    if he expected nothing less, but had fondly told himself,</p>
                <l>The day of evil would return no more.</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi
                            rend="italic">Letters</hi>, 26:389 (line 8) in this edn., where these
                        exact words occur in a somewhat despairing letter of Oct. 7, 1749, though
                        without quotation marks. This letter, however, is known only through copies
                        of 1828 and 1831, when the elusive quotation was apparently not recognized
                        as such.</p></note>
                <p n="2">2. The force of those temptations which arise from within will be
                    exceedingly heightened if we before thought too highly of ourselves, as if we
                    had been cleansed from all sin. And how naturally do we imagine this during the
                    warmth of our first love! How ready are we to believe that God has ‘fulfilled’
                    in us the whole ‘work of faith with power’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71"
                        n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 1:11.</p></note> That because we
                        <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> no sin, we <hi rend="italic">have</hi> none in
                    us, but the soul is all love! And well may a sharp attack from an enemy whom we
                    supposed to be not only <hi n="02:214"/> conquered but slain, throw us into much
                    heaviness of soul, yea, sometimes into utter darkness; particularly when we <hi
                        rend="italic">reason</hi> with this enemy, instead of instantly calling upon
                    God, and casting ourselves upon him by simple faith who <hi rend="italic"
                        >alone</hi> ‘knoweth how to deliver’ his [own] ‘out of temptation’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet.
                            2:9.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>III. These are the usual causes of this second darkness. Inquire we, thirdly,
                    what is the cure of it?</p>
                <p n="1">1. To suppose that this is one and the same in all cases is a great and
                    fatal mistake; and yet extremely common even among many who pass for experienced
                    Christians; yea, perhaps take upon them to be ‘teachers in Israel’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:10
                                (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p></note> to be the guides of other
                    souls. Accordingly they know and use but one medicine, whatever be the cause of
                    the distemper. They begin immediately to apply the promises, to ‘preach the
                    gospel’, as they call it. To give comfort is the single point at which they aim,
                    in order to which they say many soft and tender things concerning the love of
                    God to poor, helpless sinners, and the efficacy of the blood of Christ. Now this
                    is ‘quackery’ indeed, and that of the worse sort, as it tends, if not to kill
                    men’s bodies, yet without the peculiar mercy of God to ‘destroy both’ their
                    ‘bodies and souls in hell’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 10:28. Cf. Samuel Johnson’s understanding
                            of ‘quackery’ in the particular sense of medical malpractice.</p></note>
                    It is hard to speak of these ‘daubers with untempered mortar’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ezek. 13:10, 11, 14, 15;
                            22:28.</p></note> these promisemongers, as they deserve. They well
                    deserve the title which has been ignorantly given to others: they are ‘spiritual
                        mountebanks’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">An ironic reference to Bishop George Lavington’s
                            application of this label to the Methodists, in <hi rend="italic">The
                                Enthusiasm of Methodists and Papists Compared</hi>, Pt. II, p. 147:
                            ‘Their mountebank’s infallible prescription must be swallowed…—though
                            they die for it.’ See also No. 35, ‘The Law Established through Faith,
                            I’, I.12 and n.</p></note> They do, in effect, make ‘the blood of the
                    covenant an unholy thing’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:29.</p></note> They vilely prostitute the
                    promises of God by thus applying them to all without distinction. Whereas indeed
                    the cure of spiritual, as of bodily diseases, must be as various as are the
                    causes of them. The first thing, therefore, is to find out the cause, and this
                    will naturally point out the cure.</p>
                <p n="2">2. For instance: is it sin which occasions darkness? What sin? Is it
                    outward sin of any kind? Does your conscience accuse you of committing any sin
                    whereby you grieve the Holy Spirit of God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78"
                        n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:30.</p></note>
                    <pb n="02:215"/>Is it on this account that he is departed from you, and that joy
                    and peace are departed with him? And how can you expect they should return till
                    you put away the accursed thing?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Josh. 7:13.</p></note> ‘Let the wicked forsake
                    his way;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                            55:7.</p></note> ‘cleanse your hands, ye sinners;’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 4:8.</p></note> ‘put away
                    the evil of your doings.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Isa. 1:16.</p></note> So shall your ‘light break
                    out of obscurity’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 58:10.</p></note> ‘the Lord will return
                    and abundantly pardon.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 55:7.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. If upon the closest search you can find no sin of commission which
                    causes the cloud upon your soul, inquire next if there be not some sin of
                    omission which separates between God and you. Do you ‘not suffer sin upon your
                        brother’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Lev. 19:17.</p></note> Do you reprove them that sin in your sight?
                    Do you walk in all the ordinances of God? In public, family, private prayer? If
                    not, if you habitually neglect any one of these known duties, how can you expect
                    that the light of his countenance should continue to shine upon you? Make haste
                    to ‘strengthen the things that remain’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Rev. 3:2.</p></note> then your soul shall live.
                    ‘Today, if ye will hear his voice’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 95:7; Heb. 3:7, 15; 4:7.</p></note> by his
                    grace supply what is lacking. When you ‘hear a voice behind you, saying, This is
                    the way; walk thou in it,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 30:21.</p></note> ‘harden not your
                        heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 95:8; Heb. 3:8, 15; 4:7.</p></note> Be no more ‘disobedient to the
                    heavenly calling’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 26:19.</p></note> Till the sin, whether of
                    omission or commission, be removed, all comfort is false and deceitful. It is
                    only skinning the wound over, which still festers and rankles beneath. Look for
                    no peace within till you are at peace with God; which cannot be without ‘finite
                    meet for repentance’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. But perhaps you are not conscious of even any <hi rend="italic">sin of
                        omission</hi> which impairs your peace and joy in the Holy Ghost.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        14:17.</p></note> Is there not : then some <hi rend="italic">inward
                    sin</hi>, which as a ‘root of bitterness springs up’ in your heart to ‘trouble
                        you’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 12:15. The following paragraph closely resembles both the forms and
                            substance of the Puritan schemes of self-examination; cf. Robert Bolton,
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (3rd edn., 1614), II.27: ‘a fruitless
                            and dangerous speculation of a man’s own worthiness—rather fasten it
                            upon your corruptions and infirmities, upon your many deficiencies in
                            religious duties and executions of your calling, wants and weaknesses in
                            prayer and inward devotion, dullness and uncheerfulness in religious
                            exercises.’ See also Joseph Alleine, ‘Letter IX’ in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Christian Letters</hi>, published by Wesley in 1767 (see <hi
                                rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 301; and Vol. 16 of this edn.); see
                            also ‘Letter XVI’ and ‘Letter XXI’.</p></note> Is not your dryness and
                    barrenness of soul occasioned by your heart’s ‘departing from the living
                        God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            3:12.</p></note> Has not ‘the foot of pride come against’ you?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            36:11.</p></note> Have you <pb n="02:216"/>not ‘thought’ of yourself
                    ‘more highly than you ought to think’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:3.</p></note> Have you not in any
                    respect ‘sacrificed to your own net, and burnt incense to your own drag’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Hab.
                            1:16.</p></note> Have you not ascribed your success in any undertaking
                    to your own courage, or strength, or wisdom? Have you not boasted of something
                    ‘you have received, as though you had not received it’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 4:7.</p></note>
                    Have you not gloried ‘in anything save the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            6:14.</p></note> Have you not sought after or desired the praise of men?
                    Have you not taken pleasure in it? If so, you see the way you are to take. If
                    you have fallen by pride, ‘humble yourself under the mighty hand of God, and he
                    will exalt you in due time.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 5:6.</p></note> Have you not forced him
                    to depart from you by giving place to anger? Have you not ‘fretted yourself
                    because of the ungodly’ or ‘been envious against the evil-doers’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 37:1
                            (BCP).</p></note> Have you not been offended at any of your brethren?
                    Looking at their (real or imagined) sin, so as to sin yourself against the great
                    law of love by estranging your heart from them? Then look unto the Lord, that
                    you may renew your strength, that all this sharpness and coldness may be done
                    away, that love and peace and joy may return together, and you may be invariably
                    ‘kind to each other, and tender-hearted; forgiving one another, even as God for
                    Christ’s sake hath forgiven you’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:32.</p></note> Have not you given way to
                    any foolish desire? To any kind or degree of inordinate affection? How then can
                    the love of God have place in your heart, till you put away your idols? ‘Be not
                    deceived; God is not mocked:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:7.</p></note> he will not dwell in a divided
                    heart. As long therefore as you cherish Delilah in your bosom he has no place
                    there. It is vain to hope for a recovery of his light till you pluck out the
                    right eye and cast it from you.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:29.</p></note> O let there be no longer
                    delay. Cry to him that he may enable you so to do! Bewail your own impotence and
                    helplessness; and the Lord being your helper, enter in at the strait gate:<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        7:13.</p></note> take the kingdom of heaven by violence!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 11:12.</p></note>
                    Cast out every idol from his sanctuary, and the glory of the Lord shall soon
                        appear.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Lev. 9:6.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. Perhaps it is this very thing, the want of striving, <hi rend="italic"
                        >spiritual sloth</hi>, which keeps your soul in darkness. You dwell at ease
                    in the land: there is no war in your coasts, and so you are quiet and <pb
                        n="02:217"/>unconcerned. You go on in the same even track of outward duties,
                    and are content there to abide. And do you wonder meantime that your soul is
                    dead? O stir yourself up before the Lord! Arise, and shake yourself from the
                    dust: wrestle with God for the mighty blessing.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text">See Gen.
                        32:25-26.</p></note> Pour out your soul unto God in prayer, and continue
                    therein with all perseverance.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Eph. 6:18.</p></note> Watch! Awake out of
                    sleep, and keep awake! Otherwise there is nothing to be expected but that you
                    will be alienated more and more from the light and life of God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. If upon the fullest and most impartial examination of yourself you
                    cannot discern that you at present give way either to spiritual sloth or any
                    other inward or outward sin,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See No. 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’, III.4
                            and n.</p></note> then call to mind the time that is past. Consider your
                    former tempers, words, and actions. Have these been right before the Lord?
                    ‘Commune with him in your chamber, and be still,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 4:4
                        (BCP).</p></note> and desire of him to try the ground of your heart, and
                    bring to your remembrance whatever has at any time offended the eyes of his
                        glory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Isa. 3:8.</p></note> If the guilt of any unrepented sin remain on your
                    soul it cannot be but you will remain in darkness, till, having been ‘renewed by
                        repentance’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:6. Another instance of ‘a second
                            repentance’; see intro. to Nos. 13 and 14 (<hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>).</p></note> you are again washed by faith in the
                    ‘fountain opened for sin and uncleanness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114"
                        n="114"><p rend="footnote text">Zech. 13:1.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. Entirely different will be the manner of the cure if the cause of the
                    disease be not sin, but <hi rend="italic">ignorance</hi>. It may be ignorance of
                    the meaning of Scripture; perhaps occasioned by ignorant commentators—ignorant
                    at least in this respect, however knowing or learned they may be in other
                    particulars. And in this case that ignorance must be removed before we can
                    remove the darkness arising from it. We must show the true meaning of those
                    texts which have been misunderstood. My design does not permit me to consider
                    all the passages of Scripture which have been pressed into this service. I shall
                    just mention two or three which are frequently brought to prove that all
                    believers must, sooner or later, ‘walk in darkness’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text">Isa. 59:9; John
                        8:12.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8">8. One of these is Isaiah 50:10: ‘Who is among you that feareth the Lord,
                    and obeyeth the voice of his servant, that walketh in <pb n="02:218"/>darkness
                    and hath no light? Let him trust in the name of the Lord, and stay upon his
                    God.’ But how does it appear either from the text or context that the person
                    here spoken of ever had light? One who is ‘convinced of sin’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 8:46.</p></note>
                    ‘feareth the Lord and obeyeth the voice of his servant’. And him we should
                    advise, though he was still dark of soul, and had never seen the light of God’s
                    countenance, yet to ‘trust in the name of the Lord, and stay upon his God.’ This
                    text therefore proves nothing less than that a believer in Christ ‘must
                    sometimes “walk in darkness”’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The intent of ‘nothing less than’ is to <hi
                                rend="italic">negate</hi> the predicate of the sentence and is
                            common eighteenth-century usage; in modern ears it can be taken in the
                            opposite sense. Wesley is here going against the interpretations of both
                            Henry, <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>, and Poole, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Annotations</hi>, who understand Isa. 50:10 in terms of what Wesley
                            will call ‘heaviness’ in the following sermon rather than ‘darkness’.
                            Poole makes a distinction between <hi rend="italic">sin</hi> and <hi
                                rend="italic">misery</hi> and supposes the prophet to be referring
                            to misery that may pass. Similarly, Henry comments that ‘they walk in
                            darkness when…their joy in God is interrupted, the testimony of the
                            Spirit is interrupted, and the light of God’s countenance
                        eclipsed.’</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. Another text which has been supposed to speak the same doctrine is Hosea
                    2:14: ‘I will allure her, and bring her into the wilderness, and speak
                    comfortably unto her.’ Hence it has been inferred that God will bring every
                    believer ‘into the wilderness’, into a state of deadness and darkness. But it is
                    certain the text speaks no such thing. For it does not appear that it speaks of
                    particular believers at all. It manifestly refers to the Jewish nation; and
                    perhaps to that only. But if it be applicable to particular persons, the plain
                    meaning of it is this: I will draw him by love; I will next convince him of sin,
                    and then comfort him by my pardoning mercy.</p>
                <p n="10">10. A third Scripture from whence the same inference has been drawn is
                    that above-recited: ‘Ye now have sorrow; but I will see you again, and your
                    heart shall rejoice, and your joy no man taketh from you.’ This has been
                    supposed to imply that God would after a time withdraw himself from all
                    believers; and that they could not, till after they had thus sorrowed, have the
                    joy which no man could take from them. But the whole context shows that our Lord
                    is here speaking personally to the apostles, and no others; and that he is
                    speaking concerning those particular events—his own death and resurrection. ‘A
                    little while’, says he, ‘and ye shall not see me;’ namely, while I am in the
                    grave. ‘And again a little while, and ye shall see me,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p rend="footnote text">John 16:16-17.</p></note>
                    when I am risen from <pb n="02:219"/>the dead. ‘Ye will weep and lament, and the
                    world will rejoice: but your sorrow shall be turned into joy…. Ye now have
                    sorrow,’ because I am about to be taken from your head; ‘but I will see you
                    again,’ after my resurrection, ‘and your heart shall rejoice. And your joy’,
                    which I will then give you, ‘no man taketh from you.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p rend="footnote text">John 16:20, 22.</p></note>
                    All this we know was literally fulfilled in the particular case of the apostles.
                    But no inference can be drawn from hence with regard to God’s dealings with
                    believers in general.</p>
                <p n="11">11. A fourth text (to mention no more) which has been frequently cited in
                    proof of the same doctrine is 1 Peter 4:12: ‘Beloved, think it not strange
                    concerning the fiery trial which is to try you.’ But this is full as foreign to
                    the point as the preceding. The text, literally rendered, runs thus: ‘Beloved,
                    wonder not at the burning which is among you, which is for your trial.’ Now
                    however this may be accommodated to inward trials, in a secondary sense, yet
                    primarily it doubtless refers to martyrdom and the sufferings connected with
                        it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p rend="footnote text">An
                            echo of Henry’s <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>, to this same effect;
                            also an indirect refutation of Moravian interpretations of 1 Pet.
                            4:12.</p></note> Neither therefore is this text anything at all to the
                    purpose for which it is cited. And we may challenge all men to bring one text,
                    either from the Old or New Testament, which is any more to the purpose than
                    this.</p>
                <p n="12">12. ‘But is not darkness much more profitable for the soul than light? Is
                    not the work of God in the heart most swiftly and effectually carried on during
                    a state of inward suffering? Is not a believer more swiftly and throughly
                    purified by sorrow than by joy? By anguish and pain and distress and spiritual
                    martyrdoms than by continual peace?’ So the <hi rend="italic">mystics</hi>
                    teach; so it is written in their books—but not in <hi rend="italic">the oracles
                        of God</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, §2 and n. Cf.
                            Law’s highest mystical flight in <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of
                                Prayer</hi>, Pt. II (1750) (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            VII.129-30): ‘This “coldness” [i.e., darkness] is the divine offspring….
                            It brings a divine effect, or more fruitful progress in the divine
                            life…. Fervour is good and ought to be loved; but tribulation, distress,
                            and coldness in their season are better, because they give means and
                            power of exercising a higher faith, a purer love, and more perfect
                            resignation to God—which are the best state of the soul…. Light and
                            darkness equally assist the pious soul; …in the darkness he lays hold on
                            God, and so [both light and darkness] do him the same good.’</p></note>
                    The Scripture nowhere says that the absence of God best perfects his work in the
                    heart! Rather his presence, and a clear communion with the Father and the Son. A
                    strong consciousness of this will do more in an hour than his absence in an age.
                    Joy in the Holy Ghost will far more effectually purify the soul than the want of
                    that joy; and <pb n="02:220"/>the peace of God is the best means of refining the
                    soul from the dross of earthly affections. Away then with the idle conceit that
                    the kingdom of God is divided against itself; that the peace of God and joy in
                    the Holy Ghost are obstructive of righteousness; and that ‘we are saved’, not
                    ‘by faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Eph. 2:8.</p></note> but by unbelief; not by hope, but by
                    despair!</p>
                <p n="13">13. So long as men dream thus they may well ‘walk in darkness’. Nor can
                    the effect cease till the cause is removed. But yet we must not imagine it will
                    immediately cease, even when the cause is no more. When either ignorance or sin
                    has caused darkness, one or the other may be removed, and yet the light which
                    was obstructed thereby may not immediately return. As it is the free gift of
                    God, he may restore it sooner or later, as it pleases him. In the case of sin we
                    cannot reasonably expect that it should immediately return. The sin began before
                    the punishment, which may therefore justly remain after the sin is at an end.
                    And even in the natural course of things, though a wound cannot be healed while
                    the dart is sticking in the flesh, yet neither is it healed as soon as that is
                    drawn out, but soreness and pain may remain long after.</p>
                <p n="14">14. Lastly, if darkness be occasioned by manifold, heavy, and unexpected
                    temptations, the best way for removing and preventing this is—teach believers
                    always to expect temptation; seeing they dwell in an evil world, among wicked,
                    subtle, malicious spirits, and have an heart capable of all evil.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p rend="footnote text">An unusually
                            explicit avowal of the ‘remains of sin’; see intro. to No. 13, <hi
                                rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, III. 1-9 and n. But notice
                            the distinctions here between ‘involuntary sins’ (as in <hi
                                rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>) and ‘heaviness’ (as in the
                            following sermon).</p></note> Convince them that the whole work of
                    sanctification is not (as they imagined) wrought at once; that when they first
                    believe they are but as new-born babes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124"
                        n="124"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:2.</p></note> who are gradually to
                    grow up, and may expect many storms before they come to the full stature of
                    Christ. Above all let them be instructed, when the storm is upon them, not to
                    reason with the devil, but to pray; to pour out their souls before God, and show
                    him of their trouble. And these are the persons unto whom chiefly we are to
                    apply the great and precious promises—not to the ignorant, till the ignorance is
                    removed; much less to the impenitent sinner. To these we may largely and
                    affectionately declare the loving-kindness of God our Saviour, <pb n="02:221"
                    />and expatiate upon his tender mercies, which have been ever of old. Here we
                    may dwell upon the faithfulness of God, whose ‘word is tried to the
                        uttermost’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:140 (BCP).</p></note> and upon the virtue
                    of that blood which was shed for us, to ‘cleanse us from all sin’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John
                            1:7.</p></note> And God will then bear witness to his word, and bring
                    their souls out of trouble. He will say, ‘Arise, shine; for thy light is come,
                    and the glory of the Lord is risen upon thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127"
                        n="127"><p rend="footnote text">Isa. 60:1.</p></note> Yea, and that light,
                    if thou walk humbly and closely with God, will ‘shine more and more unto the
                    perfect day’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Prov. 4:18.</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
