<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 11: The Witness of the Spirit, Discourse II</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon011</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 11: The Witness of the Spirit, Discourse
                                II</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="269"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="285" to="298"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="267"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 10-11]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The following two essays were written and published more than twenty years apart
                    (1746, 1767), but that they belong together was recognized by Wesley in the
                    collection of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I, where they appear as Sermons
                    10 and 11. While there is no record that either of them was ever preached, the
                    evidence is abundant that their shared and central concern—the ground and
                    character of Christian assurance—was paramount in Wesley’s mind. It was also a
                    bone of contention with his critics. Already, in <hi rend="italic">A Farther
                        Appeal</hi> (1745), Pt. I, III-V, Wesley had entered the lists against men
                    like Edmund Gibson, Bishop of London, Thomas Herring, Archbishop of York, and
                    Richard Smalbroke, Bishop of Lichfield and Coventry—all of whom had understood
                    Wesley’s doctrines of assurance and of religious intuition as ‘enthusiasm’
                    (11:117-76 of this edn.). Presently, he would be denounced by George Lovington,
                    Bishop of Exeter, in <hi rend="italic">The Enthusiasm of Methodists and Papists
                        Compared</hi> (1749). It was, therefore, important in 1746 for him to
                    summarize the issues and to clarify his own position as simply and directly as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>It was clear enough that Wesley’s theory of religious knowledge was frankly
                    intuitionist, but this had been all too easily misconstrued as a one-sided
                    subjectivism. Thus, he had to clarify his distinction between the ways in which
                    assurance might be <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> (‘the witness of our own spirit’)
                    and the objective ground of any such experience (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>,
                    the prior and direct ‘witness of the Holy Spirit’). The question at issue
                    between ‘enthusiasts ’ and ‘rationalists ’ was whether a believer’s
                    consciousness of justification and reconciliation was an inference from his
                    religious and moral feeling or whether those feelings, if valid, were first
                    prompted by a free and direct testimony of the Spirit to one’s divine sonship,
                    prompting to which faith had, responded and in which hope and love could
                    participate. Characteristically, Wesley opts for a both/and solution, stressing
                    the believer’s own consciousness of God’s favour but even more strongly the
                    priority of the Spirit’s prevenient and direct witness as the <pb n="268"/>necessary precondition of any <hi rend="italic">feelings</hi> of assurance.
                    That this is the crucial point for Wesley would appear from the fact that he
                    repeats the same basic argument for it in Discourse II.</p>
                <p>The controversy was as old as second-century Montanism at least, and Wesley’s
                    balanced stress on an objective witness and a subjective one was not new. He had
                    already found a survey of it in an essay on Romans 8 by Alexander Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">A Cordial for Christians Travelling Heaven-Ward</hi> (1696).
                    Hamilton’s conclusion foreshadows Wesley’s: ‘The witness of the Spirit is a
                    twofold testimony for our sonship: by the Spirit himself and from our
                    conscience’ (p. 105). Moreover, according to Hamilton, the Spirit’s testimony is
                    conveyed conjointly, through Scripture by divine illumination, and also by the
                    Spirit’s gracious, sanctifying presence. Wesley seeks to safeguard this notion
                    from subjectivity by insisting that the gifts of the Spirit, including the gift
                    of assurance, are always to be judged by reference to the <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi> of the Spirit (Gal. 5:22-23).</p>
                <p>But why two discourses of this sort, on the same text, with most of the same
                    arguments? An answer to this must be circumstantial; it will illustrate Wesley’s
                    understanding of the sermon genre as a way of repeating himself with fresh and
                    refined nuances. Discourse I is the basic statement; it seeks a middle course
                    between ‘enthusiasm’ and ‘rationalism’ by recourse to the idea of <hi rend="italic">testimonium internum Spiritus Sancti</hi> (the inner witness
                    of the Holy Spirit), in Lutheran and Reformed traditions, linked as they had
                    been to the notion of the inspiration of the Scriptures. But what Wesley had
                    intended as a moderating formulation had drawn a storm of criticism, repeating
                    the charge of ‘enthusiasm’ and ignoring Wesley’s stress on objectivity (cf.
                    Green, <hi rend="italic">Anti-Methodist Publications</hi>, where more than
                    twenty attacks are listed on this point alone, including major essays by John
                    Parkhurst, Theophilus Evans, and William Warburton; see also Umphrey Lee, <hi rend="italic">Early Methodist Enthusiasm</hi>, and R. A. Knox, <hi rend="italic">Enthusiasm</hi>). Moreover, as the Revival was moving on into
                    its second generation, there were cases of real enthusiasm that lent credence to
                    these other criticisms (e.g., William Cudworth and James Relly). By the
                    mid-sixties, then, the time was ripe for a restatement of the doctrine of the
                    ‘twofold testimony’ and also for a rehearsal and refutation of the main
                    objections that had been raised against it over the controversy’s course.
                    Discourse II is, therefore, more than a mere sequel; it is a significant
                    revision of Discourse I. Thus, the two essays are designed to be read together
                    with one eye on the arguments themselves and the other on their theological
                    context in the ongoing Revival.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="269"/>The edited text of Discourse II is based on that of the first
                    edition of 1767. For a stemma illustrating the transmission of that text through
                    its six extant editions issued during Wesley’s lifetime, together with the
                    substantive variant readings from those editions, see the Appendix, Vol. IV. For
                    further details see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 303.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="285"/>
            <head>The Witness of the Spirit, II</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 8:16</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are
                        the children of God.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. None who believes the Scriptures to be the Word of God can doubt the
                        <hi rend="italic">importance</hi> of such a truth as this: a truth revealed
                    therein not once only, not obscurely, not incidentally, but frequently, and that
                    in express terms; but solemnly and of set purpose, as denoting one of the
                    peculiar privileges of the children of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And it is the more necessary to explain and defend this truth, because
                    there is a danger on the right hand and on the left. If we deny it, there is a
                    danger lest our religion degenerate into mere formality; lest, ‘having a form of
                    godliness’, we neglect if not ‘deny, the power of it’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:5.</p>
                    </note> If we
                    allow it, but do not understand what we allow, we are liable to run into all the
                    wildness of enthusiasm.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 37, ‘The Nature of Enthusiasm’.</p>
                    </note>
                    It is therefore needful in the highest degree to guard those who fear God from
                    both these dangers by a scriptural and rational illustration and continuation of
                    this momentous truth.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It may seem something of this kind is the more needful because so little
                    has been wrote on the subject with any clearness, unless some discourses on the
                    wrong side of the question, which explain it quite away. And it cannot be
                    doubted but these were occasioned, at least in great measure, by the crude,
                    unscriptural, irrational explications of others, who ‘knew not what they spake,
                    nor whereof they affirmed’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 1:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. It more clearly concerns the Methodists, so called, clearly to
                    understand, explain, and defend this doctrine, because it is one grand part of
                    the testimony which God has given them to bear to all mankind. It is by his
                    peculiar blessing upon them in searching the Scriptures, confirmed by the
                    experience of his children, that <pb n="286"/>this great evangelical truth has
                    been recovered, which had been for many years wellnigh lost and forgotten.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For the Lutheran
                            scholastics the <hi rend="italic">testimonium internum Spiritus
                                Sancti</hi> was chiefly related to the validation of the truth of
                            Scripture: ‘the supernatural act of the Holy Spirit through the Word of
                            God…illuminating the heart of man and inciting it to obedience unto the
                            faith; so that man, thus illuminated by internal spiritual influences,
                            clearly perceives that the word proposed to him has indeed proceeded
                            from God and thus gives it unyielding assent’ (David Hollar, <hi rend="italic">Examen Theologicum</hi> [1707], p. 116). The notion of
                            assurance was derived from this, but only by implication; cf. <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, pp. 117-18.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">In
                            the Reformed tradition, the inner witness was correlated more
                            specifically with ‘the perseverance and assurance of the saints’. Cf.
                            Heppe, <hi rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, pp. 581-87, and espec.
                            Heidegger, <hi rend="italic">Corpus Theologiae</hi>, XXIV.72: ‘[The
                            elect, assured by the Spirit’s witness] trust that they are in a state
                            of grace, not because of a deliberate intuition of their own dignity but
                            of the divine conferring of it…not just for the present, but certain
                            that they will also persevere in the same, though not without a
                            struggle, …right to life’s end—and so are infallibly salvable to the
                            praise of the glory of God’s grace and their own consolation amid the
                            perpetual misery of life.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the Radical
                            Reformation, the witness of the Spirit had been interiorized and turned
                            toward what Wesley (and other Anglicans) had spoken of as ‘all the
                            wildness of enthusiasm’. Cf. Hugh Barbour and Arthur O. Roberts, eds.,
                                <hi rend="italic">Early Quaker Writings, 1650-1700</hi> (Grand
                            Rapids, Mich., William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1973), pp. 261-62,
                            and G. H. Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Radical Reformation</hi>
                            (Philadelphia, The Westminster Press, 1962), chs. 18-19. In reaction,
                            Anglicans tended to interpret assurance in terms of their <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> of salvation rather than an inner certainty;
                            e.g., cf. Wesley’s reactions to Spangenberg’s questions as to his sense
                            of assurance in JWJ, Feb. 8,1736; and his letter to Thomas Whitehead(?),
                            Feb. 10, 1748; see also Isaac Barrow’s ‘Whitsunday Sermon’, No. 77, in
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.475-78.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. But what is ‘the witness of the Spirit’? The original word,
                    μαρτυρία, may be rendered either (as it is in several places) ‘the witness’, or
                    less ambiguously ‘the testimony’ or ‘the record’: so it is rendered in our
                    translation, ‘This is the record’ (the testimony, the sum of what God testifies
                    in all the inspired writings), ‘that God hath given unto us eternal life, and
                    this life is in his Son.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 5:11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The testimony now
                    under consideration is given by the Spirit of God to and with our spirit. He is
                    the person testifying. What he testifies to us is ‘that we are the children of
                    God’. The immediate result of this testimony is ‘the fruit of the Spirit’;
                    namely, ‘love, joy, peace; longsuffering, gentleness, goodness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:22. Cf.
                            No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, II.12 and n.</p>
                    </note> And
                    without these the testimony itself cannot continue. For it is inevitably
                    destroyed, not only by the commission of any outward sin, or the omission of
                    known duty, but by giving way to any inward sin—in a word, by whatever grieves
                    the Holy Spirit of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. I observed many years ago:</p>
                <quote>
                    <pb n="287"/>It is hard to find words in the language of men to explain the
                    deep things of God. Indeed there are none that will adequately express what the
                    Spirit of God works in his children. But perhaps one might say (desiring any who
                    are taught of God to correct, soften, or strengthen the expression), by ‘the
                    testimony of the Spirit’ I mean an inward impression of the soul, whereby the
                    Spirit of God immediately and directly witnesses to my spirit that I am a child
                    of God, that ‘Jesus Christ hath loved me, and given himself for me;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20. See
                            also No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, IV.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> that all my
                    sins are blotted out, and I, even I, am reconciled to God?<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Sermons,</hi> Vol. 1 [No.10, The Witness of the
                                Spirit, I’, I.7. Note Wesley’s revisions of his earlier text;
                                another example of his habitual indifference to exact
                                quotations].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </quote>
                <p n="3">3. After twenty years’ farther consideration I see no cause to retract any
                    part of this. Neither do I conceive how any of these expressions maybe altered
                    so as to make them more intelligible. I can only add, that if any of the
                    children of God will point out any other expressions which are more clear, and
                    more agreeable to the Word of God, I will readily lay these aside.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Meantime let it be observed, I do not mean hereby that the Spirit of God
                    testifies this by any outward voice; no, nor always by an inward voice, although
                    he may do this sometimes. Neither do I suppose that he always applies to the
                    heart (though he often may) one or more texts of Scripture. But he so works upon
                    the soul by his immediate influence, and by a strong though inexplicable
                    operation, that the stormy wind and troubled waves subside, and there is a sweet
                    calm; the heart resting as in the arms of Jesus, and the sinner being clearly
                    satisfied that God is reconciled, that all his ‘iniquities are forgiven, and his
                    sins covered’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 4:7; cf. Ps. 32:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Now what is the matter of dispute concerning this? Not whether there be
                    a witness or testimony of the Spirit? Not whether the Spirit does testify with
                    our spirit that we are the children of God? None can deny this without flatly
                    contradicting the Scripture, and charging a lie upon the God of truth. Therefore
                    that there is a testimony of the Spirit is acknowledged by all parties.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Neither is it questioned whether there is an <hi rend="italic">indirect</hi> witness or testimony that we are the children of God. This is
                    nearly, if not exactly, the same with ‘the testimony of a good conscience toward
                        God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Pet. 3:21.</p>
                    </note> and is the result of reason or reflection on what
                    we feel in our own souls. Strictly speaking, it is a conclusion drawn partly <pb n="288"/>from the Word of God, and partly from our own experience. The Word
                    of God says everyone who has the fruit of the Spirit<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit, I’, II.12 and n.</p>
                    </note> is a child of God. Experience, or
                    inward consciousness, tells me that I have the fruit of the Spirit And hence I
                    rationally conclude: therefore I am a child of God. This is likewise allowed on
                    all hands, and so is no matter of controversy.</p>
                <p n="7">7. Nor do we assert that there can be any real testimony of the Spirit
                    without the fruit of the Spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> We assert,
                    on the contrary, that the fruit of the Spirit immediately springs from this
                    testimony. Not always, indeed, in the same degree, even when the testimony is
                    first given, and much less afterwards. Neither joy nor peace are always at one
                    stay; no, nor love; as neither is the testimony itself always equally strong and
                    clear.</p>
                <p n="8">8. But the point in question is whether there be any <hi rend="italic">direct testimony</hi> of the Spirit at all; whether there be any other
                    testimony of the Spirit than that which arises from a consciousness of the
                    fruit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. I believe there is, because that is the plain, natural meaning of
                    the text, ‘The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are the
                    children of God.’ It is manifest, here are two witnesses mentioned, who together
                    testify the same thing—the Spirit of God, and our own spirit. The late Bishop of
                    London, in his sermon on this text, seems astonished that anyone can doubt of
                    this, which appears upon the very face of the words. Now ‘the testimony of our
                    own spirit’, says the bishop, is one which is ‘the consciousness of our own
                        sincerity’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This was Thomas Sherlock (cf. <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>) who was
                            Bishop of London, 1748-61. Wesley’s references here are to Sherlock’s
                            earlier sermon on Rom. 8:16, ‘Discourse VIII’, in <hi rend="italic">Several Discourses Preached at the Temple Church</hi> (2nd edn.,
                            1754), pp. 227-49. On p. 235, Sherlock concludes: ‘So then the faithful
                            Christian has two witnesses of his being the son of God: the Holy Spirit
                            of God and his own mind and conscience.’ On pp. 244-45, Sherlock insists
                            that true Christians have ‘the <hi rend="italic">utmost assurance</hi>
                            of being the children of God’. But his conclusion (pp. 246-47) differs
                            significantly: ‘So then you have two ways of judging yourselves which
                            must both concur: you have the inward and outward signs of grace. The
                            inward signs are a pure conscience, a sincere love of God…. The outward
                            signs are acts of obedience conformable to the inward purity and love of
                            your mind.’ See also Sherlock, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1830),
                            I.157, 163. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 155: ‘…there are
                            therefore two witnesses; St. Paul, who witnessed his affection to his
                            countrymen; and <hi rend="italic">his conscience, which witnessed for
                                his sincerity</hi>.’</p>
                    </note> or, to express the same thing a
                    little more clearly, the consciousness of the fruit of the <pb n="289"/>Spirit.
                    When our spirit is conscious of this—of love, joy, peace, long-suffering,
                    gentleness, goodness—it easily infers from these premises that we are the
                    children of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It is true, that great man supposes the other witness to be ‘the
                    consciousness of our own good works’. This, he affirms, is ‘the testimony of
                    God’s Spirit’. But this is included in the testimony of our own spirit; yea, and
                    in sincerity, even according to the common sense of the word. So the Apostle:
                    Our rejoicing is this, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and
                    godly sincerity […] we have had our conversation in the world:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        1:12.</p>
                    </note> where, it is plain, sincerity refers to our words and
                    actions at least as much as to our inward dispositions. So that this is not
                    another witness, but the very same that he mentioned before, the consciousness
                    of our good works being only one branch of the consciousness of our sincerity.
                    Consequently here is only one witness still. If therefore the text speaks of two
                    witnesses, one of these is not the consciousness of good works, neither of our
                    sincerity, all this being manifestly contained in ‘the testimony of our own
                    spirit’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. What then is the other witness? This might easily be learned, if the
                    text itself were not sufficiently clear, from the verse immediately preceding:
                    ‘Ye have received, not the spirit of bondage, but the Spirit of adoption,
                    whereby we cry, Abba, Father.’ It follows, ‘The Spirit itself beareth witness
                    with our spirit, that we are the children of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15-16.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. This is farther explained by the parallel text, ‘Because ye are sons,
                    God hath sent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying Abba,
                        Father.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 4:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Is not this something
                        <hi rend="italic">immediate</hi> and <hi rend="italic">direct</hi>, not the
                    result of reflection or argumentation? Does not this Spirit cry ‘Abba, Father’,
                    in our hearts the moment it is given—antecedently to any reflection upon our
                    sincerity; yea, to any reasoning whatsoever? And is not this the plain, natural
                    sense of the words, which strikes anyone as soon as he hears them? All these
                    texts, then, in their most obvious meaning, describe a direct testimony of the
                    Spirit.</p>
                <p n="5">5. That ‘the testimony of the Spirit of God’ must, in the very nature of
                    things, be antecedent to ‘the testimony of our own <pb n="290"/>spirit’, may
                    appear from this single consideration: we must be holy in heart and life before
                    we can be conscious that we are so. But we must love God before we can be holy
                    at all, this being the root of all holiness. Now we cannot love God till we know
                    he loves us: ‘We love him, because he first loved us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 4:19.</p>
                    </note> And we
                    cannot know his love to us till his Spirit witnesses it to our spirit. Till then
                    we cannot believe it; we cannot say, ‘The life which I now live, I live by faith
                    in the Son of God, who loved me, and gave himself for me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Then, only then we feel</l>
                    <l>Our interest in his blood,</l>
                    <l>And cry, with joy unspeakable,</l>
                    <l>Thou art my Lord, my God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘Spirit of Faith, Come Down’, st. 2, ll. 5-8,
                                in<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Hymns of Petition and Thanksgiving for the Promise of the Father</hi>
                                (1746), 30 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                        IV.197).</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Since therefore the testimony of his Spirit must precede the love of God and all
                    holiness, of consequence it must precede our consciousness thereof.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. this para.
                            with Discourse I, I.8, and note the slight shift in nuance in this later
                            sermon.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. And here properly comes in, to confirm this scriptural doctrine, the
                    experience of the children of God—the experience not of two or three, not of a
                    few, but of a great multitude which no man can number.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 7:9.</p>
                    </note> It
                    has been confirmed, both in this and in all ages, by ‘a cloud of’ living and
                    dying ‘witnesses’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> It is confirmed by <hi rend="italic">your</hi> experience and <hi rend="italic">mine</hi>. The
                    Spirit itself bore witness to my spirit that I was a child of God, gave me an
                        <hi rend="italic">evidence</hi> hereof, and I immediately cried, ‘Abba,
                    Father!’ And this I did (and so did you) before I reflected on, or was conscious
                    of, any fruit of the Spirit. It was from this testimony received that love, joy,
                    peace, and the whole fruit of the Spirit flowed. First I heard,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>‘Thy sins are forgiven! Accepted thou art!’</l>
                    <l>I listened, and heaven sprung up in my heart.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘After
                                Preaching to the Newcastle Colliers’, st. 9, ll. 3-4, beginning ‘Ye
                                neighbours and friends of Jesus, draw near’, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1749), I.311 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, V.116). Orig., ‘They listen, and heaven
                                springs up in their heart.’</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="7">
                    <pb n="291"/>7. But this is confirmed, not only by the experience of the
                    children of God—thousands of whom can declare that they never did know
                    themselves to be in the favour of God till it was directly witnessed to them by
                    his Spirit—but by all those who are convinced of sin, who feel the wrath of God
                    abiding on them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 3:36.</p>
                    </note> These cannot be satisfied with anything less
                    than a direct testimony from his Spirit that he is ‘merciful to their
                    unrighteousness, and remembers their sins and iniquities no more’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            8:12.</p>
                    </note> Tell any of these, ‘You are to know you are a child by
                    reflecting on what he has wrought in you, on your love, joy, and peace;’ and
                    will he not immediately reply, ‘By all this I know I am a child of the devil. I
                    have no more love to God than the devil has; my carnal mind is enmity against
                        God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            8:7.</p>
                    </note> I have no joy in the Holy Ghost;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note> my soul
                    is sorrowful even unto death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt 26:38.</p>
                    </note> I have no peace; my heart is
                    a troubled sea; I am all storm and tempest.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Is there an autobiographical reference here?
                            Cf. JWJ, May 28, 1738, and Jan. 4, 1739. See also John’s letter to his
                            brother Charles, June 27, 1766 (where the double-bracketed words are in
                            shorthand, meant for Charles’s eyes only):</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘[[I]] do not feel the wrath of God abiding on me. Nor can I believe it
                            does. And yet (this is the mystery) [[I do not love God. I never did.]]
                            Therefore [[I never]] <hi rend="italic">believed</hi> in the Christian
                            sense of the word. Therefore [[I am only an]] honest heathen, a
                            proselyte of the Temple, one of the φοβούμενοι τὸν Θεόν [‘God-fearers’].
                            And yet, to be so employed of God! And so hedged in that I can neither
                            get forward or backward! Surely there never was such an instance before,
                            from the beginning of the world!</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘If [[I ever
                            had had]] <hi rend="italic">that faith</hi>, it would not be so strange.
                            But [[I never had any]] other ἔλεγχος of the eternal or the invisible
                            world than [[I have]] now—and that is [[none at all]], unless such as
                            faintly shines from reason’s glimmering ray. [[I have no]] <hi rend="italic">direct</hi> witness (I do not say, that [[I am a child
                            of God]]), but of anything invisible or eternal.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘And yet I dare not preach otherwise than I do,
                            either concerning faith, or love, or justification, or perfection. And
                            yet I find rather an increase than a decrease of zeal, for the whole
                            work of God, and every part of it. I am φερόμενος [‘borne along’], I
                            know not how, [so] that I can’t stand still. I want all the world to
                            come to ὃν οὐκ οἶδα [‘what I do not know’]. Neither am I impelled to
                            this by fear of any kind. [[I have]] no more fear than love. Or if [[I
                            have any fear, it is not that of falling]] into hell, but of falling
                            into nothing!’</p>
                    </note> And which way can these souls possibly be
                    comforted but by a divine testimony (not that they are good, or sincere, or
                    conformable to the Scripture in heart and life, but) that God ‘justifieth the
                        ungodly’—<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> him that, till the moment he is justified, is
                    all ungodly, void of all true holiness? ‘Him that worketh not’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> that worketh nothing that is truly good till
                    he is conscious that he is accepted, ‘not for any works of righteousness which
                    he hath done’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 3:5.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="292"/>but by the mere free mercy of God? Wholly and solely for what the
                    Son of God hath done and suffered for him? And can it be otherwise if ‘a man is
                    justified by faith, without the works of the law’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:28 (cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> If so, what inward or outward
                    goodness can he be conscious of antecedent to his justification? Nay, is not the
                    ‘having nothing to pay’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 7:42.</p>
                    </note> that is, the being
                    conscious that ‘there dwelleth in us no good thing,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 7:18.</p>
                    </note>
                    neither inward nor outward goodness, essentially, indispensably necessary before
                    we can be ‘justified freely through the redemption that is in Jesus
                        Christ’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom 3:24.</p>
                    </note> Was ever any man justified since his coming into
                    the world, or can any man ever be justified till he is brought to that
                    point,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>I give up every plea, beside</l>
                    <l>‘Lord, I am damned—but thou hast died!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘Galatians iii.22’, st. 12, ll. 3-4, in
                                    <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1739), p. 94 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.85). A favourite hymn of
                                Wesley’s, quoted frequently. E.g., Nos. 34, ‘The Original, Nature,
                                Properties, and Use of the Law’, IV.2; and 122, ‘Causes of the
                                Inefficacy of Christianity’, §19. See also the letter to Lady
                                Maxwell, Sept. 22, 1764, and JWJ, Apr. 1, 1778.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="8">8. Everyone therefore who denies the existence of such a testimony does, in
                    effect, deny justification by faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A clue to Wesley’s purposes in this Discourse II:
                                <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the reassertion of ‘faith alone’, but
                            now as a proper precondition of ‘holy living’.</p>
                    </note> It follows
                    that either he never experienced this, either he never was justified, or that he
                    has forgotten (as St. Peter speaks) τοῦ καθαρισμοῦ τῶν πάλαι [αὐτού] ἁμαρτιῶν,
                    ‘the purification from his former sins’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:9. The omission of αὐτοῦ seems an
                            inadvertence; the translation is Wesley’s own (cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>) and is more literal than the AV’s ‘purged from his old
                            sins’.</p>
                    </note> the experience he then had himself, the manner wherein
                    God wrought in his own soul, when his former sins were blotted out.</p>
                <p n="9">9. And the experience even of the children of the world here confirms that
                    of the children of God. Many of these have a desire to please God: some of them
                    take much pains to please him. But do they not, one and all, count it the
                    highest absurdity for any to talk of <hi rend="italic">knowing</hi> his sins are
                    forgiven? Which of <hi rend="italic">them</hi> even pretends to any such thing?
                    And yet many of them are conscious of their own sincerity. Many of them
                    undoubtedly have, in a degree, the testimony of their own spirit, a
                    consciousness of their own uprightness. But this brings them no consciousness
                    that they are forgiven, no knowledge that they are the children of God. Yea, <pb n="293"/>the more sincere they are, the more uneasy they generally are for
                    want of knowing it: plainly showing that this cannot be known in a satisfactory
                    manner by the bare testimony of our own spirit, without God’s directly
                    testifying that we are his children.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>IV. But abundance of objections have been made to this, the chief of which it may
                    be well to consider.</p>
                <p n="1">1. It is objected, first, ‘Experience is not sufficient to prove a doctrine
                    which is not founded on Scripture.’ This is undoubtedly true, and it is an
                    important truth. But it does not affect the present question, for it has been
                    shown that this doctrine is founded on Scripture. Therefore experience is
                    properly alleged to confirm it.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘But madmen, French prophets,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A popular English nickname for the Camisards who
                            had suffered brutal persecution in southeastern France (the Cevennes and
                            Dauphiné) in the first decade of the eighteenth century. The label
                            ‘Camisard’ referred to their habit of wearing white shirts (<hi rend="italic">camisae</hi>) as ritual symbols of their zeal for
                            purity. But they were also visionaries and fanatics, strongly influenced
                            by the apocalyptic emphasis of Pierre Jurieu (1637-1713), and laid claim
                            to direct revelation and Spirit-possession; cf. André Ducasse, <hi rend="italic">La Guerre des Camisards</hi> (Paris, 1946), and
                            Charles Almeras, <hi rend="italic">La Révolte des Camisards</hi> (Paris,
                            1960). Wesley shared the general feeling among Englishmen of his time
                            that these ‘French prophets’ were ‘enthusiasts’ in the literal,
                            pejorative sense of that term. His first meeting with them is recorded
                            in JWJ, Jan. 28, 1739; see also June 6 and 22, 1739. Later (Apr. 3,
                            1786), he will compare them with ‘the Jumpers in Wales’ and some
                            mountain folk near Chapel-en-le-Frith. See also his letter to Conyers
                            Middleton, Jan. 4, 1749, and to <hi rend="italic">The London
                                Magazine</hi>, Dec. 12, 1750.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For
                            accounts of their extravagances in England see Southey, ch. 8; and Knox,
                                <hi rend="italic">Enthusiasm</hi>, pp. 362, 376 ff.</p>
                    </note> and
                    enthusiasts of every kind have imagined they experienced this witness.’ They
                    have so, and perhaps not a few of them did, although they did not retain it
                    long. But if they did not, this is no proof at all that others have not
                    experienced it as a madman’s <hi rend="italic">imagining</hi> himself a king
                    does not prove that there are no <hi rend="italic">real</hi> kings.</p>
                <p><!--Decide if and how to number subsequent paragraphs unnumbered by Wesley.-->‘Nay,
                    many who pleaded strongly for this have utterly decried the Bible.’ Perhaps so,
                    but this was no necessary consequence: thousands plead for it who have the
                    highest esteem for the Bible.</p>
                <p>‘Yea, but many have fatally deceived themselves hereby, and got above all
                        conviction.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s own criticism of the enthusiastic opinions cf. Thomas
                            Maxfield and George Bell in JWJ, Nov. 1, 1762 (and Nov. 24). Many of
                            Wesley’s erstwhile followers (John Cennick, Thomas Bissicks, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>) had ‘got above all conviction’ without
                            disconcerting his own more modest views of assurance and the Holy
                            Spirit’s witness in the human spirit. Cf. No. 37, The Nature of
                            Enthusiasm’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>And yet a scriptural doctrine is no worse, though men abuse it to their own
                    destruction.</p>
                <p n="3">
                    <pb n="294"/>3. ‘But I lay it down as an undoubted truth, the fruit of the
                    Spirit is the witness of the Spirit.’ Not undoubted; thousands doubt of, yea
                    flatly deny it: but to let that pass, ‘If this witness be sufficient there is no
                    need of any other. But it is sufficient, unless in one of these cases: (1). The
                        <hi rend="italic">total absence</hi> of the fruit of the Spirit.’ And this
                    is the case when the direct witness is first given. ‘(2). The <hi rend="italic">not perceiving it</hi>. But to contend for it in this case is to contend
                    for being in the favour of God and not knowing it.’ True, not knowing it at that
                    time any otherwise than by the testimony which is given for that end. And this
                    we do contend for: we contend that the direct witness may shine clear, even
                    while the indirect one is under a cloud.</p>
                <p n="4">4. It is objected, secondly: ‘the design of the witness contended for is to
                    prove that the profession we make is genuine. But it does not prove this.’ I
                    answer, the proving this is not the design of it. It is antecedent to our making
                    any profession at all, but that of being lost, undone, guilty, helpless sinners.
                    It is designed to assure those to whom it is given that they are the children of
                    God; that they are ‘justified freely by his grace, through the redemption that
                    is in Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note> And this does not suppose
                    that their preceding thoughts, words, and actions are conformable to the rule of
                    the Scripture. It supposes quite the reverse, namely, that they are sinners all
                    over, sinners both in heart and life. Were it otherwise God would ‘justify the
                    godly’, and their own works would be ‘counted to them for righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        4:5.</p>
                    </note> And I cannot but fear that a supposition of our being
                    justified by works is at the root of all these objections. For whoever cordially
                    believes that God <hi rend="italic">imputes</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note this appeal to the
                            Puritan insistence on the imputation of Christ’s righteousness as the
                            crucial act in man’s justification and Wesley’s correlation of the
                            witness of the Spirit with this imputation. It amounts to yet another
                            linkage between the Protestant stress on ‘faith alone’ and a ‘catholic’
                            doctrine of prevenience (implied in the notion of
                            <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">direct </hi>witness).</p>
                    </note>
                    to all that are justified ‘righteousness without works’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> will find
                    no difficulty in allowing the witness of his Spirit preceding the fruit of
                    it.</p>
                <p n="5">5. It is objected, thirdly: ‘One evangelist says, “Your heavenly Father
                    will give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 11:13.</p>
                    </note> The
                    other evangelist calls the same thing “good gifts”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 7:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    abundantly <pb n="295"/>demonstrating that the Spirit’s way of bearing witness
                    is by giving good gifts.’ Nay, here is nothing at all about ‘bearing witness’,
                    either in one text or the other. Therefore till this demonstration is more
                    abundantly demonstrated, I let it stand as it is.</p>
                <p n="6">6. It is objected, fourthly: ‘The Scripture says, “The tree is known by its
                        fruit;”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:33.</p>
                    </note> “Prove all things;”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:21.</p>
                    </note> “Try
                    the spirits;”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 4:1.</p>
                    </note> “Examine yourselves.”’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> Most
                    true: therefore let every man who believes he ‘hath the witness in himself’ <hi rend="italic">try</hi> whether it be of God. If the fruit follow, it is;
                    otherwise, it is not. For certainly ‘the tree is known by its fruit.’ Hereby
                        w<hi rend="italic">e prove</hi> if it be of God. ‘But the direct witness is
                    never referred to in the Book of God.’ Not as standing alone, not as a single
                    witness, but as connected with the other; as giving a <hi rend="italic">joint
                        testimony</hi>, testifying <hi rend="italic">with our spirit</hi> that we
                    are children of God. And who is able to prove that it is not
                    <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">thus </hi>referred to in this very
                    Scripture: ‘Examine yourselves whether ye be in the faith; prove your own
                    selves. Know ye not your own selves that Jesus Christ is in you?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> It is by no means clear that they did not
                    know this by a <hi rend="italic">direct</hi> as well as a <hi rend="italic">remote</hi> witness. How is it proved that they did not know it, first, by
                    inward consciousness, and then by love, joy, and peace?</p>
                <p n="7">7. ‘But the testimony arising from the internal and external change is
                    constantly referred to in the Bible.’ It is so. And we constantly refer thereto
                    to confirm the testimony of the Spirit.</p>
                <p><!--Decide if and how to number subsequent paragraphs unnumbered by Wesley.-->‘Nay,
                    all the marks <hi rend="italic">you</hi> have given whereby to distinguish the
                    operations of God’s Spirit from delusion refer to the change wrought in us and
                    upon us.’ This likewise is undoubtedly true.</p>
                <p n="8">8. It is objected, fifthly, that ‘the direct witness of the Spirit does not
                    secure us from the greatest delusions. And is that a witness fit to be trusted
                    whose testimony cannot be depended on, that is forced to fly to something else
                    to prove what it asserts?’ I answer: to secure us from all delusion, God gives
                    us two witnesses that we are his children. And this they testify conjointly.
                    Therefore ‘what God hath joined together, let not man put asunder.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt 19:6; Mark
                            10:9.</p>
                    </note> And while they are joined we cannot be deluded: their
                    testimony can be depended on. They are fit to be trusted in the highest degree,
                    and need nothing else to prove what they assert.</p>
                <p><!--Decide if and how to number subsequent paragraphs unnumbered by Wesley.-->‘Nay,
                    the direct witness only asserts, but does not prove anything.’ By two witnesses
                    shall every word be established.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 18:16.</p>
                    </note> And <pb n="296"/>when
                    the Spirit ‘witnesses with our spirit’, as God designs it to do, then it fully
                    proves that we are children of God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. It is objected, sixthly: ‘You own the change wrought is a sufficient
                    testimony, unless in the case of severe trials, such as that of our Saviour upon
                    the cross. But none of us can be tried in that manner.’ But you or I may be
                    tried in such a manner, and so may any other child of God, that it will be
                    impossible for us to keep our filial confidence in God without the direct
                    witness of his Spirit.</p>
                <p n="10">10. It is objected, lastly, ‘The greatest contenders for it are some of
                    the proudest and most uncharitable of men.’ Perhaps some of the <hi rend="italic">hottest</hi> contenders for it are both proud and
                    uncharitable. But many of the <hi rend="italic">firmest</hi> contenders for it
                    are eminently meek and lowly in heart,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 11:29.</p>
                    </note> and, indeed, in all
                    other respects also,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>True followers of their lamb-like Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Hymn 146, st. 1, l. 4,
                                in<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> Hymns on the Lord’s Supper</hi>
                                (1745), p. 139, beginning, ‘Happy the saints of former days’. For
                                another quotation from this hymn see No. 61, ‘The Mystery of
                                Iniquity’, §29.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>The preceding objections are the most considerable that I have heard, and I
                    believe contain the strength of the cause. Yet I apprehend whoever calmly and
                    impartially considers those objections and the answers together, will easily see
                    that they do not destroy, no, nor weaken the evidence of that great truth, that
                    the Spirit of God does <hi rend="italic">directly</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">indirectly</hi> testify that we are children of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p n="1">V. 1. The sum of all is this: the testimony of the Spirit is an inward
                    impression on the souls of believers, whereby the Spirit of God directly
                    testifies to their spirit that they are children of God. And it is not
                    questioned whether there is a testimony of the Spirit, but whether there is any
                        <hi rend="italic">direct testimony</hi>, whether there is any other than
                    that which arises from a consciousness of the fruit of the Spirit We believe
                    there is: because this is the plain, natural meaning of the text, illustrated
                    both by the preceding words and by the parallel passage in the Epistle to the
                    Galatians; because, in the nature of the thing, the testimony must precede the
                    fruit which springs from it, and because this plain meaning of the <pb n="297"/>Word of God is confirmed by the experience of innumerable children of God;
                    yea, and by the experience of all who are convinced of sin, who can never rest
                    till they have a direct witness; and even of the children of the world who, not
                    having the witness in themselves, one and all declare none can <hi rend="italic">know</hi> his sins forgiven.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And whereas it is objected that experience is not sufficient to prove a
                    doctrine unsupported by Scripture; that madmen and enthusiasts of every kind
                    have imagined such a witness; that the design of that witness is to prove our
                    profession genuine, which design it does not answer; that the Scripture says,
                    ‘The tree is known by its fruit,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt 12:33.</p>
                    </note> ‘Examine yourselves: …prove
                    your own selves,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> and meantime the direct
                    witness is never referred to in all the Book of God; that it does not secure us
                    from the greatest delusions; and, lastly, that the change wrought in us is a
                    sufficient testimony, unless in such trials as Ghrist alone suffered—we answer,
                    (1). Experience is sufficient to <hi rend="italic">confirm</hi> a doctrine which
                    is grounded on Scripture. (2). Though many fancy they experience what they do
                    not, this is no prejudice to real experience. (3). The design of that witness is
                    to assure us we are children of God; and this design it does answer. (4). The
                    true witness of the Spirit is known by its fruit—love, peace, joy—not indeed
                    preceding, but following it (5). It cannot be proved that the direct as well as
                    the indirect witness is not referred to in that very text, ‘Know ye not your own
                    selves…that Jesus Christ is in you?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> (6). The
                    Spirit of God, ‘witnessing with our spirit’, does secure us from all delusion.
                    And, lastly, we are all liable to trials wherein the testimony of our own spirit
                    is not sufficient, wherein nothing less than the direct testimony of God’s
                    Spirit can assure us we are his children.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Two inferences may be drawn from the whole. The first: let none ever
                    presume to rest in any supposed testimony of the Spirit which is separate from
                    the fruit of it. If the Spirit of God does really testify that we are children
                    of God, the immediate consequence will be the fruit of the Spirit, even ‘love,
                    joy, peace, long-suffering, gentleness, goodness, fidelity, meekness,
                        temperance’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22-23 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> And however
                    this fruit may be clouded for a while during the time of strong temptation, so
                    that it does not appear to <pb n="298"/>the tempted person while ‘Satan is
                    sifting him as wheat,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 22:31.</p>
                    </note> yet the substantial part
                    of it remains, even under the thickest cloud. It is true, joy in die Holy
                        Ghost<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            14:17.</p>
                    </note> may be withdrawn during the hour of trial. Yea, the
                    soul may be ‘exceeding sorrowful’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt 26:22, 38.</p>
                    </note> while ‘the hour and
                    power of darkness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 22:53.</p>
                    </note> continues. But even this
                    is generally restored with increase, and he rejoices ‘with joy unspeakable and
                    full of glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. The second inference is: let none rest in any supposed fruit of the
                    Spirit without the witness. There may be foretastes of joy, of peace, of
                    love—and those not delusive, but really from God—long before we have the witness
                    in ourselves, before the Spirit of God witnesses with our spirits that we have
                    ‘redemption in the blood of Jesus, even the forgiveness of sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 1:7;
                            Col. 1:14.</p>
                    </note> Yea, there may be a degree of long-suffering, of
                    gentleness, of fidelity, meekness, temperance (not a shadow thereof, but a real
                    degree, by the preventing grace of God)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture
                                Way of Salvation</hi>, I.2; and 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own
                            Salvation’, II.1, III.3-4.</p>
                    </note> before we are ‘accepted in the
                        Beloved’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> and consequently before we have a testimony of our
                    acceptance. But it is by no means advisable to rest here; it is at the peril of
                    our souls if we do. If we are wise we shall be continually crying to God, until
                    his Spirit cry in our heart, ‘Abba, Father!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> This is the
                    privilege of all the children of God, and without this we can never be assured
                    that we are his children. Without this we cannot retain a steady peace, nor
                    avoid perplexing doubts and fears. But when we have once received this ‘Spirit
                    of adoption’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> that ‘peace which passes all understanding’, and
                    which expels all painful doubt and fear, will ‘keep our hearts and minds in
                    Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> And when this has brought forth its genuine
                    fruit, all inward and outward holiness, it is undoubtedly the will of him that
                    calleth us to give us always what he has once given. So that there is no need
                    that we should ever more be deprived of either the testimony of God’s Spirit or
                    the testimony of our own, the consciousness of our walking in all righteousness
                    and true holiness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:24.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <p>
                <placeName>Newry</placeName>, <date when="1767-04-04">April 4, 1767</date>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>