<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 14: The Repentance of Believers</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon014</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 14: The Repentance of Believers</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="317"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="335" to="352"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="314"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [on Sermons 13-14]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>In the first edition of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I (1746), ‘The Witness of
                    the Spirit’ (Discourse I), was followed by a sermon on ‘The Means of Grace’ to
                    round out the volume. Two years later, Wesley placed his third university
                    sermon, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’ (from 1733), as the first sermon in his
                    second volume, following it with a new sermon on ‘The Great Privilege of those
                    that are Born of God’. The shared theme in this sequence (stressed in three of
                    the sermons and implied in ‘The Means of Grace’) concerned the power bestowed on
                    justified and regenerate believers <hi rend="italic">not to commit sin</hi>—a
                    crucial idea in the holy-living tradition, which then was given its climactic
                    statement, up to that date, in <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>
                    (1750); see No. 40.</p>
                <p>This idea of the Christian’s grace-bestowed power not to commit sin was, however,
                    bound to generate controversy and confusion among both critics and some
                    disciples. With their doctrines of the ineradicable ‘remains of sin’ (<hi rend="italic">fomes peccati</hi>), the Lutherans had taught that the
                    justified believer was <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi> but also
                    that his repented sins were covered by the imputed righteousness of Christ and
                    thus inculpable; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Apology of the Augsburg
                        Confession</hi> (1531), Article II, ‘Original Sin’, especially §§35-45. With
                    similar premises with respect to the <hi rend="italic">fomes peccati</hi> (the
                    Christian is ‘a sinner saved by grace’), the Calvinists stressed rigorous
                    examination of consciences, repentance, the final perseverance of the elect, and
                    the perfect and immutable freedom ‘in the state of glory only’; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Westminster Confession</hi> VI.v, IX.v; see also
                    XIII-XVIII. On the other side, the Moravians and some of Wesley’s own disciples
                    (e.g., Thomas Maxfield, William Cudworth, James Relly) had taken the claim that
                    ‘those born of God do not commit sin’ to its antinomian extreme of sinless—even
                    guiltless—perfection, as if the power not to sin meant the extirpation of all
                    ‘remains of sin’. For an exposition of this view, see the Supplement to <hi rend="italic">The Christian Magazine for the Year 1762</hi>: ‘for all who
                    are united to Christ by the Holy Spirit’s dwelling in them are delivered from
                    the guilt, the power, or, in one word the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of <pb n="315"/>sin’ (p. 579; see also below, pp. 328-32). Moreover, they had
                    appealed to Wesley’s basic soteriology as the logical ground for their
                    interpretation.</p>
                <p>Wesley, caught in the controversy generated by these two polarities, reacted
                    typically and came up with what he regarded as a valid third alternative. Its
                    root notion was a distinction between ‘sin properly so called’ (i.e., ‘the
                    [deliberate] violation of a known law of God’—mortal if unrepented) and all
                    ‘involuntary transgressions’ (culpable only if unrepented and not discarded when
                    discerned or entertained). This distinction already had a history in Catholic
                    moral theory (‘mortal’ versus ‘venial’); cf. Claude Fleury, <hi rend="italic">Les Moeurs des Israélites</hi> (1683; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Manners of
                        the Ancient Israelites…</hi>, ed. Adam Clarke [1852], p. 306). But it had
                    also had a special development among Anglican moralists as well. Richard Lucas
                    had analyzed it in his <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi> (1717),
                    III.299-301 (e.g., ‘Mortal sin is a deliberate transgression of a known law of
                    God tending to the dishonour of God and injury of our neighbour or the
                    deprivation of our own nature’). John Kettlewell, in <hi rend="italic">The
                        Measures of Christian Obedience</hi> (1681), had spoken of ‘voluntary’ and
                    ‘involuntary’ sins (see Bk. IV, chs. 3-4, pp. 330 ff., 335 ff.). Much more to
                    the same effect had been found in Samuel Bradford’s Boyle Lectures for 1699, <hi rend="italic">The Credibility of the Christian Revelation, from its
                        intrinsic evidence; in eight sermons</hi> (1700), Sermon II, p. 445; Hugh
                    Binning, <hi rend="italic">Fellowship With God</hi> (1671), pp. 216-18, and John
                    Weemse [Weemes], <hi rend="italic">The Portraiture of God in Man…</hi> (1627),
                    p. 326 (cf. Weemes’s formulation of the distinction as between ‘sins forgiven ’
                    and ‘sins passed by…’).</p>
                <p>Thus, there was an unstable tension between the claims that a Christian may be
                    delivered from sin’s bondage, and that ‘sin <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> but
                    no longer <hi rend="italic">reigns</hi>’ (see below, I.6 and n.); this continued
                    to plague Wesley in many ways, as one can see from his frequent references to
                    it; see below, II.3, III.1-9 and n.; and cf. Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation
                        by Faith</hi>, II.6; 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’, II.6, 9, III.4-5;
                    14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.2-3; 18, ‘The Marks of
                    the New Birth’, I.5-6; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’,
                    II.8; 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.4-5; 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, III.6; 43, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, III.6-8; 46, ‘The Wilderness State’, II.6,
                    III.14; 58, <hi rend="italic">On Predestination</hi>, §7; 62, ‘The End of
                    Christ’s Coming’, III.3; 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.14; 74,
                    ‘Of the Church’, §21; 76, ‘On Perfection’, II.9; 82, ‘On Temptation’, I.5; 104,
                    ‘On Attending the Church Service’, §18; 128, <pb n="316"/>‘The Deceitfulness of
                    the Human Heart’, II.5. Cf. also Wesley’s letters to John Hosmer, June 7, 1761,
                    to Mary Bishop, May 27, 1771, and to Mrs. Bennis, June 16, 1772.</p>
                <p>What matters most is that Wesley insisted on holding to both traditions—<hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi> and <hi rend="italic">holy living</hi>—without
                    forfeiting the good essence of either. Moreover, he saw no inconsistency in his
                    shifting from one emphasis to the other as circumstances seemed to require. He
                    was more concerned to face the dreadful realities of sin while never yielding to
                    any defeatist notion that God’s grace is intrinsically impotent to save souls
                    ‘to the utmost’, in this life. That enough of his comments on this twin concern
                    could have been misconstrued as a doctrine of ‘sinless perfection’ is apparent
                    both in its exaggerations in Cudworth and others, and also in nineteenth-century
                    developments—especially in American Methodism—in which ‘entire sanctification’
                    was interpreted as ‘a second and separate work of grace’ and normative for the
                    Christian life; cf. Peters, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection and American
                        Methodism</hi>.</p>
                <p>In 1763, in a needed effort to counter the distortions and bring the controversy
                    more nearly back to balance, Wesley wrote and published a sermon entitled <hi rend="italic">A Discourse on Sin in Believers</hi>, ‘in order to remove a
                    mistake which some were labouring to propagate: that there is no sin in any that
                    are justified’ (see JWJ, Mar. 28, and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 257).
                    In 1767 he wrote out its sequel, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                        Believers</hi>, and published it the following year (cf. JWJ, Apr. 17-24,
                    and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 305).</p>
                <p>Here, we find an interesting version of Wesley’s doctrine of ‘entire
                    sanctification’; cf. Pt. II. Shortly after this, when he began to re-arrange the
                    sequence of Vol. I of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> for the edition of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, he quite deliberately inserted these two sermons
                    as Nos. 13 and 14, between ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’ and ‘The Means of
                    Grace’. They are designed, as he says, for the encouragement of ‘the weaker
                    brethren’ whose Christian assurance had been all too easily shaken by their
                    awareness of sin’s residues in their hearts, even in their uncertain pilgrimage
                    of grace toward ‘perfect love’.</p>
                <p>The present text of <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi> is based on the
                    first edition of 1763, and the text of <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                        Believers</hi> is from its first edition of 1767. For stemmata illustrating
                    text transmissions through the editions published in Wesley’s lifetime and the
                    list of substantive variant readings found in these successive editions, see
                    Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, in Vol. IV.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Repentance of Believers</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Mark 1:15</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Repent and believe the gospel.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. It is generally supposed that repentance and faith are only the gate of
                        religion;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Wesley’s letter to Thomas Church, June 17, 1746; also William Tilly,
                            Sermon XII, <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, p. 360: ‘…as one that was
                            yet under the low dispensation, and detained in the <hi rend="italic">porch of repentance</hi>’; and Edward Young (the elder), <hi rend="italic">A Sermon Preached Before His Majesty at
                                White-Hall</hi>, December 29, 1678, p. 24: ‘Repentance was
                            heretofore the porch of the Christian life but modern ages have made it
                            the postern; it is the last thing men set themselves about.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley uses the metaphor of a porch in relating
                            paradise to heaven (‘paradise is the porch of heaven’) in two sermons:
                            73, ‘Of Hell’, I.4; and 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’, I.3. In No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, II.4, he calls paradise
                            the ‘antechamber’ of heaven. Elsewhere, Fleury reports that the
                            Mohammedan divines had called <hi rend="italic">fasting</hi> ‘the gate
                            of religion’; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Manners of the Ancient
                                Israelites</hi>, pp. 176-77.</p>
                    </note> that they are necessary only
                    at the beginning of our Christian course, when we are setting out in the way of
                    the kingdom. And this may seem to be confirmed by the great Apostle, where
                    exhorting the Hebrew Christians to ‘go on to perfection’ he teaches them to
                    ‘leave’ these first ‘principles of the doctrine of Christ: not laying again the
                    foundation of repentance from dead works and faith toward God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                        6:1.</p>
                    </note> which must at least mean that they should comparatively
                    leave these, that at first took up all their thoughts, in order to ‘press
                    forward toward the prize of the high calling of God in Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                        3:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And this is undoubtedly true, that there is a repentance and a faith
                    which are more especially necessary at the beginning: a repentance which is a
                    conviction of our utter sinfulness and guiltiness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This notion of repentance as
                            realistic self-understanding is crucial in Wesley’s evangelical
                            soteriology. Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.1 and n. What is
                            most distinctive about it is Wesley’s insistence that such repentance
                                <hi rend="italic">precedes</hi> justification as, in some sense, a
                            precondition of it. Here again, we have a subtle qualification of the
                            ‘faith alone’ theme; see below, II.6 and n.</p>
                    </note> and helplessness,
                    and which precedes our receiving that kingdom of God which our Lord observes ‘is
                    within us’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Luke 17:21.</p>
                    </note> and <pb n="336"/>a faith whereby we receive that
                    kingdom, even ‘righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        14:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. But notwithstanding this, there is also a repentance and a faith (taking
                    the words in another sense, a sense not quite the same, nor yet entirely
                    different) which are requisite after we have ‘believed the gospel’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark
                        1:15.</p>
                    </note> yea, and in every subsequent stage of our Christian course,
                    or we cannot ‘run the race which is set before us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> And
                    this repentance and faith are full as necessary, in order to our continuance and
                    growth in grace, as the former faith and repentance were in order to our
                    entering into the kingdom of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An extension of the argument in the preceding
                            sermon; cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro.,
                            III.1-9 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>But in what sense are we to repent and believe, after we are justified? This is
                    an important question, and worthy of being considered with the utmost
                    attention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>I. And first, in what sense are we to repent?</p>
                <p n="1">1. Repentance frequently means an inward change, a change of mind from sin
                    to holiness. But we now speak of it in a quite different sense, as it is one
                    kind of self-knowledge—the knowing ourselves sinners, yea, guilty, helpless
                    sinners, even though we know we are children of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Indeed when we first know this, when we first find redemption in the
                    blood of Jesus, when the love of God is first shed abroad in our hearts<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        5:5.</p>
                    </note> and his kingdom set up therein, it is natural to suppose
                    that we are no longer sinners, that all our sins are not only covered<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Pss. 32:1;
                            85:2; Rom. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> but destroyed. As we do not then feel any
                    evil in our hearts, we readily imagine none is there. Nay, some well-meaning men
                    have imagined this, not only at that time, but ever after; having persuaded
                    themselves that when they were justified they were entirely sanctified. Yea,
                    they have laid it down as a general rule, in spite of Scripture, reason, and
                    experience. These sincerely believe and earnestly maintain that all sin is
                    destroyed when we are justified, and that there is no sin in the heart of a
                    believer, but that it is altogether clean from that moment. But though we
                    readily acknowledge, ‘he that believeth is born of God,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:1.</p>
                    </note> and
                    ‘he that is born of God doth not commit sin,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:9.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="337"/>yet we cannot allow that he does not <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> it
                    within: it does not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>, but it does <hi rend="italic">remain</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>, I.6 and n.</p>
                    </note> And a conviction of the sin
                    which <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> in our heart is one great branch of the
                    repentance we are now speaking of.</p>
                <p n="3">3. For it is seldom long before he who imagined all sin was gone feels
                    there is still <hi rend="italic">pride</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For Wesley, as for St. Augustine, pride is
                            the primal sin—as also in Ecclus. 10:13 (‘Pride is the beginning of all
                            sin’). See also Nos. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great Assize</hi>, III.1;
                            21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, I.4-5; 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’,
                            II.1; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, I.8, III.2; 88, ‘On Dress’,
                            §§9-10; 92, ‘On Zeal’, III.2-4; 100, ‘On Pleasing All Men’, I.2, II.2;
                            111, <hi rend="italic">National Sins and Miseries</hi>, §2; 113, <hi rend="italic">The Late Work of God in North America</hi>, II.8; 128,
                            ‘The Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, I.1; 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in
                            Earthen Vessels’, II.5; cf. also Wesley’s letter to Mrs. Pendarves,
                            Sept. 28, 1731, and to Mr. —, Sept. 3, 1756. For Wesley’s references to
                            ‘bosom sin’, cf. No. 48, ‘Self-denial’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> in his
                    heart. He is convinced, both that in many respects he has thought of himself
                    more highly than he ought to think, and that he has taken to himself the praise
                    of something he had received, and gloried in it as though he had not received
                    it. And yet he knows he is in the favour of God. He cannot and ought not to
                    ‘cast away his confidence’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:35.</p>
                    </note> ‘The Spirit still
                    witnesses with his spirit, that he is a child of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Nor is it long before he feels <hi rend="italic">self-will</hi> in his
                    heart, even a will contrary to the will of God. A will every man must inevitably
                    have, as long as he has an understanding. This is an essential part of human
                    nature, indeed of the nature of every intelligent being.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 60, ‘The General
                            Deliverance’, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> Our blessed Lord himself had a will
                    as a man; otherwise he had not been a man.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of the Monothelite controversy and
                            its resolution at the ‘Sixth Ecumenical Council’, in Constantinople,
                            680-81; cf. Henry R. Percival, <hi rend="italic">The Seven Ecumenical
                                Councils, ... Canons and Dogmatic Decrees</hi>, in <hi rend="italic">NPNF</hi>, <hi rend="italic">II</hi>, XIV.325-54. See also Jaroslav
                            Pelikan, <hi rend="italic">The Christian Tradition</hi>, pp.
                        68-75.</p>
                    </note> But his human will was invariably subject to the will of
                    his Father. At all times, and on all occasions, even in the deepest affliction,
                    he could say, ‘Not as I will, but as thou wilt.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:39.</p>
                    </note> But
                    this is not the case at all times, even with a true believer in Christ. He
                    frequently finds his will more or less exalting itself against the will of God.
                    He wills something, because it is pleasing to nature, which is not pleasing to
                    God. And he nills<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Dr. Johnson’s definition of ‘to nill’ (‘to
                            refuse; to reject’) and his citation of its usage in Ben Jonson. That it
                            was already an archaic negative in Wesley’s time may be seen in the 1788
                            edn. of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>; the printer has it ‘wills’, without
                            a care for its sense or meaning.</p>
                    </note> (is averse <pb n="338"/>from) something because it is painful to nature, which is the will of God
                    concerning him. Indeed (suppose he continues in the faith) he fights against it
                    with all his might. But this very thing implies that it really exists, and that
                    he is conscious of it.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Now self-will, as well as pride, is a species of idolatry; and both are
                    directly contrary to the love of God. The same observation may be made
                    concerning <hi rend="italic">the love of the world</hi>. But this likewise even
                    true believers are liable to feel in themselves; and every one of them does feel
                    it, more or less, sooner or later, in one branch or another. It is true, when he
                    first passes from death unto life he desires nothing more but God. He can truly
                    say, ‘All my desire is unto thee,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 38:9.</p>
                    </note> ‘and unto the remembrance
                    of thy name.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 26:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘Whom have I in heaven but thee? And there is
                    none upon earth that I desire besides thee?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 73:25.</p>
                    </note> But it is not so
                    always. In process of time he will feel again (though perhaps only for a few
                    moments) either ‘the desire of the flesh, or the desire of the eye, or the pride
                    of life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            John 2:16 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>), and No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> Nay, if he does not continually watch
                    and pray he may find <hi rend="italic">lust</hi> reviving, yea, and thrusting
                    sore at him that he may fall,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 118:13.</p>
                    </note> till he has scarce any
                    strength left in him. He may feel the assaults of <hi rend="italic">inordinate
                        affection</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:5. Cf. also Kempis, I.vi, II.iv.</p>
                    </note>
                    yea, a strong propensity to ‘love the creature more than the Creator’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            1:25.</p>
                    </note>—whether it be a child, a parent, an husband or wife, or
                    ‘the friend that is as his own soul’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Deut. 13:6.</p>
                    </note> He may feel in a
                    thousand various ways a desire of earthly things or pleasures. In the same
                    proportion he will forget God, not seeking his happiness in him, and
                    consequently being a ‘lover of pleasure more than a lover of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim.
                            3:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. If he does not keep himself every moment he will again feel ‘the desire
                    of the eye’, the desire of gratifying his imagination with something great, or
                    beautiful, or uncommon. In how many ways does this desire assault the soul!
                    Perhaps with regard to the poorest trifles, such as dress, or furniture—things
                    never designed to satisfy the appetite of an immortal spirit. Yet how natural it
                    is for us, even after we ‘have tasted of the powers of the world to come’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                        6:5.</p>
                    </note> to sink again into these foolish, low desires of things that
                    perish in the using! How hard is it, even for those who know in <pb n="339"/>whom they have believed,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> to conquer but one
                    branch of the desire of the eye, curiosity; constantly to trample it under their
                    feet, to desire nothing merely because it is new!</p>
                <p n="7">7. And how hard is it even for the children of God wholly to conquer ‘the
                    pride of life’! St. John seems to mean by this nearly the same with what the
                    world terms ‘the sense of honour’. This is no other than a desire of and delight
                    in ‘the honour that cometh of men’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 5:41, 44.</p>
                    </note>—a desire and love of
                        praise,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley makes frequent references to a ‘desire’, ‘love’, or ‘thirst’ of
                            ‘praise’ or ‘glory’. Cf. Nos. 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, I.4; 26,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’, I.2; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, §2;
                            84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, I.4; 100, ‘On
                            Pleasing All Men’, I.5.</p>
                    </note> and (which is always joined with it)
                    a proportionable <hi rend="italic">fear of dispraise</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This was the main theme of A.
                            H. Francke’s then famous <hi rend="italic">Nicodemus: Or A Treatise
                                Against the Fear of Man</hi> (1706), which Wesley had read in Nov.
                            1733. Cf. Nos. 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.1; and 87,
                            ‘The Danger of Riches’, §3. The idea is closely related to Wesley’s
                            emphasis on singularity as a mark of the Christian who is free from
                            anxiety as to the world’s approval or disapproval. For Wesley’s frequent
                            admonitions to be singular, cf. Nos. 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’,
                            III.4 and n.; and 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, I.6
                            and n. For Wesley, the praise of men is equivalent to flattery, as in
                            Nos. 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.6 (‘that grand
                            fashionable engine—flattery’); 100, ‘On Pleasing All Men’, I.5; and 107,
                            ‘On God’s Vineyard’, V.3. He knew that Cicero had spoken of flattery as
                            ‘the handmaid of vice’ (<hi rend="italic">De Amicitia</hi>, XXIV.89);
                            see also Nos. 35, ‘The Law Established through Faith, I’, II.6; 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III.9; 87, ‘The Danger of
                            Riches’, §16.</p>
                    </note> Nearly allied to this is <hi rend="italic">evil
                        shame</hi>, the being ashamed of that wherein we ought to glory. And this is
                    seldom divided from ‘the fear of man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Prov. 29:25.</p>
                    </note> which brings a thousand
                    snares upon the soul. Now where is he, even among those that seem strong in
                    faith, who does not find in himself a degree of all these evil tempers? So that
                    even these are but in part ‘crucified to the world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:14.</p>
                    </note> for
                    the evil root remains in their heart.</p>
                <p n="8">8. And do we not feel other tempers, which are as contrary to the love of
                    our neighbour as these are to the love of God? The love of our neighbour
                    ‘thinketh no evil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> Do not we find anything of
                    the kind? Do we never find any <hi rend="italic">jealousies</hi>, any evil
                        surmisings,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:4.</p>
                    </note> any groundless or unreasonable suspicions? He
                    that is clear in these respects, let him cast the first stone at his
                        neighbour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 8:7.</p>
                    </note> Who does not sometimes feel other tempers or
                    inward motions which he knows are contrary to brotherly love? If nothing of
                    malice, <pb n="340"/>hatred, or bitterness, is there no touch of envy?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Titus
                            3:3.</p>
                    </note> Particularly toward those who enjoy some (real or
                    supposed) good which we desire but cannot attain? Do we never find any degree of
                        <hi rend="italic">resentment</hi> when we are injured or affronted?
                    Especially by those whom we peculiarly loved, and whom we had most laboured to
                    help or oblige. Does injustice or ingratitude never excite in us any desire of
                        <hi rend="italic">revenge</hi>; any desire of returning evil for evil,
                    instead of ‘overcoming evil with good’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom 12:21.</p>
                    </note> This also shows how
                    much is still in our heart which is contrary to the love of our neighbour.</p>
                <p n="9">9. <hi rend="italic">Covetousness</hi> in every kind and degree is
                    certainly as contrary to this as to the love of God. Whether φιλαργυρία, ‘the
                    love of money’ which is too frequently ‘the root of all evils’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:10.
                            Wesley will become very much more emphatic in his denunciations of the
                            love of money and of the sin of surplus accumulation as the years wear
                            on, and as many Methodists become more and more affluent See below, No.
                            50, ‘The Use of Money’, on Wesley’s increasing alarm and despair over
                            Methodist prosperity unaccompanied by equivalent philanthropy. Cf. also
                            the intro, to No. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’.</p>
                    </note> or
                        πλεονεξία,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., covetousness; cf. Col. 3:5, etc., and Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> thereon.</p>
                    </note> literally, a desire of <hi rend="italic">having more</hi>, or increasing in substance. And how few even
                    of the real children of God are entirely free from both! Indeed one great man,
                    Martin Luther, used to say he ‘never had any covetousness in him (not only in
                    his converted state, but) ever since he was born’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Samuel Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Marrow of Ecclesiastical Historie</hi>, pp. 98-99:
                            ‘Wellerus, also a disciple of Luther’s, recordeth that he oft heard
                            Luther say that he had been frequently assaulted and vexed with all
                            kinds of temptations, except to the sin of covetousness….’ Cf. also John
                            Gillies, <hi rend="italic">Historical Collections Relating to Remarkable
                                Periods of the Success of the Gospel</hi> (1754), Bk. II, ch. 1. A
                            supporting witness here was Thomas Hayne, <hi rend="italic">Life and
                                Death of Martin Luther</hi> (1641), p. 115: ‘Even the Papists agree
                            that Luther was not covetous.’ For other references to Luther, more
                            often disparaging than not, cf. Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by
                                Faith</hi>, III.9; 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>,
                            I.4; 18, ‘The Marks of the New Birth’, IV.3; 38, ‘A Caution against
                            Bigotry’, II.4; 63, ‘The General Spread of the Gospel’, §16; 68, ‘The
                            Wisdom of God’s Counsels’, §10; 94, ‘On Family Religion’, §3; 102, ‘Of
                            Former Times’, §14; 104, ‘On Attending the Church Service’, §25; 107,
                            ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.5; 122, ‘Causes of the Inefficacy of
                            Christianity’, §17. See also Wesley’s letters to Mrs. Hutton, Aug. 22,
                            1744; to Richard Tompson, Feb. 5, 1756; to John Fletcher, Aug. 18, 1775;
                            to Elizabeth Ritchie, Feb. 12, 1779; JWJ, June 15-16, 1741; also his
                            Preface to <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, §12; <hi rend="italic">Farther
                                Appeal</hi>, Pt. III, IV.6 (11:318 of this edn.); and <hi rend="italic">Thoughts Upon a Late Phenomenon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> (1789), §4 (Vol. 9 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note>
                    But if so, I would not scruple to say he was the only man born of a woman
                    (except him that was God as well as man) who had not, who was born without it.
                    Nay, I believe, never was anyone born of God, that lived any considerable time
                    after, who did not feel more or less of <pb n="341"/>it many times, especially
                    in the latter sense. We may therefore set it down as an undoubted truth that <hi rend="italic">covetousness</hi>, together with pride, and self-will, and
                    anger, <hi rend="italic">remain</hi> in the hearts even of them that are
                    justified.</p>
                <p n="10">10. It is their experiencing this which has inclined so many serious
                    persons to understand the latter part of the seventh chapter to the Romans, not
                    of them that ‘are under the law’—that are convinced of sin, which is undoubtedly
                    the meaning of the Apostle—but of them that ‘are under grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:14, 15.</p>
                    </note> that
                    are ‘justified freely, through the redemption that is in Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            3:24.</p>
                    </note> And it is most certain they are thus far right; there
                    does still <hi rend="italic">remain</hi>, even in them that are justified, a
                    ‘mind’ which is in some measure ‘carnal’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:7.</p>
                    </note> (so the Apostle tells even
                    the believers at Corinth, ‘Ye are carnal’);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:3.</p>
                    </note> an heart ‘bent to
                        backsliding’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Hos. 11:7.</p>
                    </note> still ever ready to ‘depart
                    from the living God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> a propensity to pride,
                    self-will, anger, revenge, love of the world, yea, and all evil: a root of
                        bitterness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:15.</p>
                    </note> which, if the restraint were taken off for a
                    moment, would instantly spring up; yea, such a depth of corruption as without
                    clear light from God we cannot possibly conceive. And a conviction of all this
                    sin <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> in their hearts is the repentance which
                    belongs to them that are justified.</p>
                <p n="11">11. But we should likewise be convinced that as sin remains in our hearts,
                    so it <hi rend="italic">cleaves</hi> to our words and actions. Indeed it is to
                    be feared that many of our words are more than mixed with sin, that they are
                    sinful altogether. For such undoubtedly is all <hi rend="italic">uncharitable
                        conversation</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">General
                                Rules</hi>, §4, in which ‘uncharitable or unprofitable conversation’
                            is interdicted.</p>
                    </note> all which does not spring from brotherly
                    love, all which does not agree with that golden rule, ‘What ye would that others
                    should do to you, even so do unto them.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt 7:12; Luke 6:31.</p>
                    </note> Of this
                    kind is all backbiting, all talebearing, all whispering, all evil-speaking; that
                    is, repeating the faults of absent persons—for none would have others repeat his
                    faults when he is absent. Now how few are there, even among believers, who are
                    in no degree guilty of this? Who steadily observe the good old rule, ‘Of the
                    dead and the absent—nothing but good.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This ‘rule’ was, in fact, an immemorial old
                            aphorism. A version of it appears in Diogenes Laertius, ‘Life of Chilon’
                            in <hi rend="italic">Lives of Eminent Philosophers</hi>, I.68-70 (Loeb,
                            184:69-73); another was attributed to Solon by Plutarch; a variant may
                            be found in Propertius, <hi rend="italic">Elegies</hi>, II. xix. 32: <hi rend="italic">absenti nemo non nocuissevelit</hi> (‘let no one be
                            willing to speak evil of the absent’). Wesley recalls it with typical
                            variations in Nos. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.10; and 49, ‘The
                            Cure of Evil-speaking’, §1.</p>
                    </note> And suppose they do, do they <pb n="342"/>likewise abstain from <hi rend="italic">unprofitable
                        conversation</hi>? Yet all this is unquestionably sinful, and ‘grieves the
                    Holy Spirit of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:30.</p>
                    </note> Yea, and for ‘every idle
                    word that men shall speak they shall give an account in the day of
                        judgment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:36.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. But let it be supposed that they continually ‘watch and pray’, and so
                    do ‘not enter into this temptation’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt 26:41; Mark 14:38.</p>
                    </note> that they
                    constantly set a watch before their mouth, and keep the door of their lips:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                            141:3.</p>
                    </note> suppose they exercise themselves herein, that <hi rend="italic">all</hi> their ‘conversation may be in grace seasoned with
                        salt’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Col. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> and meet ‘to minister grace to the hearers’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            4:29.</p>
                    </note> yet do they not daily slide into useless discourse,
                    notwithstanding all their caution? And even when they endeavour to speak for
                    God, are their words pure, free from unholy mixtures? Do they find nothing wrong
                    in their very <hi rend="italic">intention</hi>? Do they speak merely to please
                    God, and not partly to please themselves? Is it wholly to do the will of God,
                    and not their own will also? Or, if they begin with a single eye, do they go on
                    ‘looking unto Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> and talking with him all the
                    time they are with their neighbour? When they are reproving sin do they feel no
                    anger or unkind temper to the sinner? When they are instructing the ignorant do
                    they not find any pride, any self-preference? When they are comforting the
                    afflicted, or provoking one another to love and to good works,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 10:24.</p>
                    </note> do
                    they never perceive any inward self-commendation—‘Now you have spoken well’? Or
                    any vanity, a desire that others should think so, and esteem them on the
                    account? In some or all of these respects how much sin <hi rend="italic">cleaves</hi> to the best conversation even of believers! The conviction of
                    which is another branch of the repentance which belongs to them that are
                    justified.</p>
                <p n="13">13. And how much sin, if their conscience is throughly awake, may they
                    find <hi rend="italic">cleaving to their actions</hi> also? Nay, are there not
                    many of these which, though they are such as the world would not condemn, yet
                    cannot be commended, no, nor excused, if we judge by the Word of God? Are there
                    not many of their actions which they themselves know are not ‘to the glory of
                        God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                            10:31, etc.</p>
                    </note> Many wherein they did not even aim at this, which
                    were not undertaken with an eye to God? And of those that were, are there not
                    many <pb n="343"/>wherein their eye is not singly fixed on God? Wherein they are
                    doing their own will at least as much as his, and seeking to please themselves
                    as much if not more than to please God? And while they are endeavouring to do
                    good to their neighbour, do they not feel wrong tempers of various kinds? Hence
                    their good actions, so called, are far from being strictly such, being polluted
                    with such a mixture of evil! Such are their works of <hi rend="italic">mercy</hi>! And is there not the same mixture in their works of <hi rend="italic">piety</hi>?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The distinction between ‘works of piety’ and of
                            ‘mercy’ was an Anglican commonplace, to be seen, e.g., in ‘Of Good
                            Works’ in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p. 42, and in Joseph Mede’s
                            Discourse XXVI (on Mark 1:15), in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, pp. 81,
                            113, or in Law’s <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, (pp. 18-19).
                            ‘Works of charity’ is a phrase from Kempis, I. xv. ‘Works of piety’ is
                            recorded as a proverb attributed to ‘Pulcheria’ by Edward Gibbon in <hi rend="italic">The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</hi>, ch. 32;
                            Gibbon cites Sozomen, ix. c. 1, 2, 3, and de Tillemont, <hi rend="italic">Mem. Eccles.</hi> xv. 171. For ‘works of mercy’, cf.
                            St. Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologica</hi>, II-i; Q. 32, art.
                            2.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For Wesley’s frequent usage of this
                            pairing of Christian devotion and Christian social action, cf. Nos. 22,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, I.10; 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, II.7,
                            IV.4; 26, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’, I.1, II.1; 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, III.10; 48, ‘Self-denial’,
                            II.6; 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’, II.18; 91, ‘On Charity’, II.4; 92, ‘On
                            Zeal’, II.4, III.7, 12; 98, ‘On Visiting the Sick’, §§1, 2; 106, ‘On
                            Faith, Heb. 11:6’, II.4; 126, ‘On Worldly Folly’, II.3. See also <hi rend="italic">A Plain Account of the People called Methodists</hi>,
                            I.2. It is worth noting that he never set either over against the
                            other.</p>
                    </note> While they are hearing the word which is able to save
                    their souls, do they not frequently find such thoughts as make them afraid lest
                    it should turn to their condemnation rather than their salvation? Is it not
                    often the same case while they are endeavouring to offer up their prayers to
                    God, whether in public, or private? Nay, while they are engaged in the most
                    solemn service. Even while they are at the table of the Lord, what manner of
                    thoughts arise in them? Are not their hearts sometimes wandering to the ends of
                    the earth, sometimes filled with such imaginations as make them fear lest all
                    their sacrifice should be an abomination to the Lord?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Prov. 15:8.</p>
                    </note> So
                    that they are more ashamed of their best duties than they were once of their
                    worst sins.</p>
                <p n="14">14. Again: how many <hi rend="italic">sins of omission</hi> are they
                    chargeable with? We know the words of the Apostle, ‘To him that knoweth to do
                    good, and doth it not, to him it is sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 4:17.</p>
                    </note> But do they not know a
                    thousand instances wherein they might have done good, to enemies, to strangers,
                    to their brethren, either with regard to their bodies or their souls, and they
                    did it not? How many omissions have they been guilty of in their duty toward
                    God? How many opportunities of communicating, of hearing his word, of public or
                    private prayer have they neglected? So great reason had even that holy man
                    Archbishop Ussher, after all his labours for God, to cry <pb n="344"/>out,
                    almost with his dying breath, ‘Lord, forgive me my sins of omission.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Richard Parr,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Life of…James Usher, Late Lord Archbishop of
                                Armagh</hi> (1686), p. 77. Parr was Ussher’s domestic chaplain and
                            present at his deathbed. The saying had already appeared in Nicholas
                            Bernard’s <hi rend="italic">Life and Death of Archbishop Ussher, in a
                                Sermon Preached at his Funeral at Westminster</hi> (1656), which
                            Wesley abridged and published in the <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> (1779),
                            II.588 (Wesley preferred the simplified spelling of his name, ‘Usher’).
                            See also No. 98, ‘On Visiting the Sick’, III.9; <hi rend="italic">A
                                Plain Account of Christian Perfection</hi>, §14 (6); and JWJ, Mar.
                            9, 1746. For Wesley’s other references to ‘sins of omission’, cf. Nos.
                            19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’, III.1; 35, ‘The
                            Law Established through Faith, I’, III.8; and 46, ‘The Wilderness
                            State’, II.3.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="15">15. But besides these outward omissions, may they not find in themselves
                        <hi rend="italic">inward defects</hi> without number? Defects of every kind:
                    they have not the love, the fear, the confidence they ought to have toward God.
                    They have not the love which is due to their neighbour, to every child of
                        man;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No.
                            7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.8 and n.</p>
                    </note> no, nor even that
                    which is due to their brethren, to every child of God, whether those that are at
                    a distance from them, or those with whom they are immediately connected. They
                    have no holy temper in the degree they ought; they are defective in everything:
                    in a deep consciousness of which they are ready to cry out with Mr. de Renty, ‘I
                    am a ground all overrun with thorns;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jean-Baptiste de Saint-Jure, <hi rend="italic">The Holy Life of Monsr. de Renty, A Late Nobleman of France, and
                                Sometimes Councellor to King Lewis the 13th</hi> (Eng. tr. 1658, by
                            E[dward] S[heldon,] Gent.), p. 274: ‘In sum, I am a straggler from God,
                            and a ground overrun with thorns.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley
                            found de Renty’s special combination of mysticism, asceticism, and civic
                            involvement in philanthropy and practical affairs very congenial. Cf.
                            the admiring references in Nos. 55, <hi rend="italic">On the
                                Trinity</hi>, §17; 72, ‘Of Evil Angels’, II.15; 82, ‘On Temptation’,
                            III.5; 114, <hi rend="italic">On the Death of John Fletcher</hi>
                            (penultimate §); 117, ‘On the Discoveries of Faith’, §17. See also the
                            letter to Ann Granville, Oct. 3, 1741; to Lady Maxwell, Mar. 3, 1769; to
                            Philothea Briggs, Aug. 31, 1772; to Ann Bolton, Jan. 14, 1780; to Hannah
                            Ball, Feb. 17, 1780; to Adam Clarke, Jan. 3, 1791.</p>
                    </note> or with
                    Job, ‘I am vile;’ ‘I abhor myself, and repent as in dust and ashes.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 40:4;
                            42:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="16">16. A conviction of their <hi rend="italic">guiltiness</hi> is another
                    branch of that repentance which belongs to the children of God. But this is
                    cautiously to be understood, and in a peculiar sense. For it is certain, ‘there
                    is no condemnation for them that are in Christ Jesus’, that believe in him, and
                    in the power of that faith ‘walk not after the flesh, but after the
                        Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:1.</p>
                    </note> Yet can they no more bear the <hi rend="italic">strict justice</hi> of God now than before they believed. This pronounces
                    them to be still <hi rend="italic">worthy of death</hi> on all the preceding
                    accounts. And it would absolutely condemn them thereto, were it not for the
                    atoning blood. Therefore, they are throughly <pb n="345"/>convinced that they
                    still <hi rend="italic">deserve</hi> punishment, although it is hereby turned
                    aside from them. But here there are extremes on one hand and on the other, and
                    few steer clear of them. Most men strike on one or the other, either thinking
                    themselves condemned when they are not, or thinking they <hi rend="italic">deserve</hi> to be acquitted. Nay, the truth lies between: they still <hi rend="italic">deserve</hi>, strictly speaking, only the damnation of hell.
                    But what they deserve does not come upon them because they ‘have an advocate
                    with the Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:1.</p>
                    </note> His life and death and
                    intercession still interpose between them and condemnation.</p>
                <p n="17">17. A conviction of their <hi rend="italic">utter helplessness</hi> is yet
                    another branch of this repentance. I mean hereby two things: (1). That they are
                    no more able now <hi rend="italic">of themselves</hi> to think one good thought,
                    to form one good desire, to speak one good word, or do one good work, than
                    before they were justified; that they have still no kind or degree of strength
                        <hi rend="italic">of their own</hi>, no power either to do good or resist
                    evil; no ability to conquer or even withstand the world, the devil, or their own
                    evil nature. They ‘can’, it is certain, ‘do all these things’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil 4:13.</p>
                    </note> but
                    it is not by <hi rend="italic">their own strength</hi>. They have power to
                    overcome all these enemies; ‘for sin hath no dominion over’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 6:14.</p>
                    </note>
                    them. But it is not from nature, either in whole or in part; ‘it is the <hi rend="italic">mere</hi> gift of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 6:23. Cf. also No. 85, ‘On Working
                            Out Our Own Salvation’, III.4: ‘For, allowing that all the souls of men
                            are dead in sin by “nature”, this excuses none, seeing there is no man
                            that is in a state of <hi rend="italic">mere</hi> nature; there is no
                            man, unless he has quenched the Spirit, that is wholly void of the grace
                            of God.’</p>
                    </note> Nor is it given all at once, as if they had a stock
                    laid up for many years, but from moment to moment.</p>
                <p n="18">18. By this helplessness I mean, secondly, an absolute inability to
                    deliver ourselves from that guiltiness or desert of punishment whereof we are
                    still conscious; yea, and an inability to remove by all the grace we have (to
                    say nothing of our natural powers) either the pride, self-will, love of the
                    world, anger, and general proneness to <hi rend="italic">depart from God</hi>
                    which we experimentally know to <hi rend="italic">remain</hi> in the heart, even
                    of them that are regenerate; or the evil which, in spite of all our endeavours,
                        <hi rend="italic">cleaves</hi> to all our words and actions. Add to this an
                    utter inability wholly to avoid <hi rend="italic">uncharitable</hi> and, much
                    more, <hi rend="italic">unprofitable conversation</hi>. Add an inability to
                    avoid <hi rend="italic">sins of omission</hi>, or to supply the numberless <hi rend="italic">defects</hi> we are convinced of, especially the want of love
                    and other right tempers both to God and man.</p>
                <p n="19">
                    <pb n="346"/>19. If any man is not satisfied of this, if any believes that
                    whoever is justified is able to remove these sins out of his heart and life, let
                    him make the experiment. Let him try whether, by the grace he has already
                    received, he can expel pride, self-will, or inbred sin in general. Let him try
                    whether he can cleanse his words and actions from all mixture of evil; whether
                    he can avoid all uncharitable and unprofitable conversation, with all sins of
                    omission; and lastly, whether he can supply the numberless defects which he
                    still finds in himself. Let him not be discouraged by one or two experiments,
                    but repeat the trial again and again. And the longer he tries the more deeply
                    will he be convinced of his utter helplessness in all these respects.</p>
                <p n="20">20. Indeed this is so evident a truth that wellnigh all the children of
                    God scattered abroad,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 11:52.</p>
                    </note> however they differ in
                    other points, yet generally agree in this, that although we may ‘by the Spirit
                    mortify the deeds of the body’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:13.</p>
                    </note> resist and conquer both
                    outward and inward sin, although we may <hi rend="italic">weaken</hi> our
                    enemies day by day, yet we cannot <hi rend="italic">drive them out</hi>. By all
                    the grace which is given at justification we cannot extirpate them. Though we
                    watch and pray ever so much, we cannot wholly cleanse either our hearts or
                    hands. Most sure we cannot, till it shall please our Lord to speak to our hearts
                    again, to ‘speak the second time, “Be clean”’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and
                                Sacred Poems</hi> (1749), II.164; cf. <hi rend="italic">Collection
                                of Hymns</hi> (1780, Vol. 7 of this edn., No. 386:5).</p>
                    </note> And
                    then only ‘the leprosy is cleansed.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 8:3.</p>
                    </note> Then only the evil root,
                    the carnal mind, is destroyed, and inbred sin subsists no more.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Here, then is
                            Wesley’s resolution of the dilemma posed by his conflicting views on the
                                <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> of sin, even in the justified, and
                            the Christian hope of their extirpation. ‘<hi rend="italic">We</hi>
                            cannot extirpate them,’ but there is the possibility that God may do so
                            as a special and instantaneous deliverance. Thus, Wesley clings to the
                                <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi> as the general state
                            of believers and yet also to the possibility of the extirpation of the
                            root of sin in some by a special dispensation of grace. This may have
                            been the ground for an implied doctrine of ‘sinless perfection’ which
                            Wesley generally repudiates, and thus could be understood as the warrant
                            for a post-Wesleyan doctrine of ‘entire sanctification as a second and
                            separate work of grace’.</p>
                    </note> But if there be no such second
                    change, if there be no instantaneous deliverance after justification, if there
                    be none but a gradual work of God (that there is a gradual work none denies)
                    then we must be content, as well as we can, to remain full of sin till death.
                    And if so, we must remain <hi rend="italic">guilty</hi> till death, continually
                        <hi rend="italic">deserving</hi> punishment. For it is impossible the guilt
                    or desert of punishment should be <pb n="347"/>removed from us as long as all
                    this sin remains in our heart, and cleaves to our words and actions. Nay, in
                    rigorous justice, all we think, and speak, and act, continually increases
                    it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. In this sense we are to <hi rend="italic">repent</hi> after we are
                    justified. And till we do so we can go no farther. For till we are sensible of
                    our disease it admits of no cure. But supposing we do thus repent, then are we
                    called to ‘believe the gospel’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 1:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And this also is to be understood in a peculiar sense, different from
                    that wherein we believed in order to justification. Believe the ‘glad tidings of
                    great salvation’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 52:7; Rom. 10:15.</p>
                    </note> which God hath prepared for all
                    people. Believe that he who is ‘the brightness of his Father’s glory, the
                    express image of his person’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 1:3.</p>
                    </note> ‘is able to save unto the
                    uttermost all that come unto God through him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 7:25.</p>
                    </note> He is able to save
                    you from all the sin that still remains in your heart. He is able to save you
                    from all the sin that cleaves to all your words and actions. He is able to save
                    you from sins of omission, and to supply whatever is wanting in you. It is true,
                    ‘This is impossible with man; but with [the] God-man all things are
                        possible.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 19:26.</p>
                    </note> For what can be too hard for him who hath
                    ‘all power in heaven and in earth’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 28:18.</p>
                    </note> Indeed his bare power to do
                    this is not a sufficient foundation for our faith that he <hi rend="italic">will</hi> do it, that he will thus exert his power, unless he hath promised
                    it. But this he has done: he has promised it over and over, in the strongest
                    terms. He has given us these ‘exceeding great and precious promises’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet.
                        1:4.</p>
                    </note> both in the Old and the New Testament. So we read in the
                    law, in the most ancient part of the oracles of God, ‘The Lord thy God will
                    circumcise thy heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the Lord thy God with
                    all thy heart and all thy soul.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Deut. 30:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> So in the
                    Psalms: ‘He shall redeem Israel (the Israel of God) from all his sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 130:8
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> So in the Prophet: ‘Then will I sprinkle clean water
                    upon you, and ye shall be clean; from all your filthiness, and from all your
                    idols, will I cleanse you…. And I will put my Spirit within you, […] and ye
                    shall keep my judgments and do them. […] I will also save you from all your
                        uncleannesses.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ezek. 36:25, 27, 29.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> So likewise
                    in the New Testament: ‘Blessed be the Lord God of Israel; for he hath <pb n="348"/>visited and redeemed his people, and hath raised up an horn of
                    salvation for us…. To perform […] the oath which he swore to our father Abraham,
                    that he would grant unto us that we, being delivered out of the hands of our
                    enemies, should serve him without fear, in holiness and righteousness before
                    him, all the days of our life.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke 1:68-69, 72-75 [also BCP, Morning Prayer,
                                Benedictus].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. You have therefore good reason to believe he is not only able but <hi rend="italic">willing</hi> to do this—to ‘cleanse you from all your
                    filthiness of flesh and spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                    </note> to ‘save you from all
                    your uncleannesses’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ezek. 36:29.</p>
                    </note> This is the thing which you
                    now long for: this is the faith which you now particularly need, namely, that
                    the great physician, the lover of my soul, is willing to ‘make me clean’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 8:2,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> But is he willing to do this tomorrow or today? Let him
                    answer for himself: ‘Today, if ye will hear my voice, harden not your
                        hearts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 95:7-8 (AV); Heb. 3:15; 4:7.</p>
                    </note> If you put it off till
                    tomorrow, you ‘harden your hearts’; you refuse to ‘hear his voice’. Believe
                    therefore that he is willing to save you <hi rend="italic">today</hi>. He is
                    willing to save you <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. ‘Behold, now is the accepted
                        time.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 6:2.</p>
                    </note> He now saith, ‘Be thou clean!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 8:3, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                    Only believe; and you also will immediately find, ‘All things are possible to
                    him that believeth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Continue to believe in him ‘that loved thee, and gave himself for
                        thee’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note> that ‘bore all thy sins in his own body on the
                        tree’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Pet. 2:24.</p>
                    </note> and he saveth thee from all condemnation, by his
                    blood continually applied. Thus it is that we continue in a justified state. And
                    when we go ‘from faith to faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 1:17.</p>
                    </note> when we have a faith to be
                    cleansed from indwelling sin, to be saved from all our uncleannesses,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ezek.
                            36:29.</p>
                    </note> we are likewise saved from all that <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi>, that <hi rend="italic">desert</hi> of punishment, which we felt
                    before. So that then we may say, not only,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Every moment, Lord, I <hi rend="italic">want</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>The merit of thy death:</l>
                    <l>but likewise, in the full assurance of faith,</l>
                    <l>Every moment, Lord, I <hi rend="italic">have</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>The merit of thy death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Hymn on Isaiah 32:2, ‘And a Man shall be as an
                                Hiding-Place…’, st. 5, ll. 7-8, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and
                                    Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 146 (<hi rend="italic">Poet.
                                    Wks.</hi>, II.207). The second version is John Wesley’s
                                deliberate revision. See also No. 76, ‘On Perfection’, I.3; and cf.
                                Wesley’s letters to James Hervey, Oct. 15, 1756; to Samuel Furly,
                                May 21, 1762; to Miss March, Apr. 7, 1763; and to Edward Lewly, Jan.
                                12, 1791.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>
                    <pb n="349"/>For by that faith in his life, death, and intercession for us,
                    renewed from moment to moment, we are every whit clean, and there is not only
                    now no condemnation for us, but no such desert of punishment as was before, the
                    Lord cleansing both our hearts and lives.</p>
                <p n="5">5. By the same faith we feel the power of Christ every moment resting upon
                        us,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Cor. 12:9.</p>
                    </note> whereby alone we are what we are, whereby we are
                    enabled to continue in spiritual life, and without which, notwithstanding all
                    our present holiness, we should be devils the next moment. But as long as we
                    retain our faith in him we ‘draw water out of the wells of salvation’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        12:3.</p>
                    </note> Leaning on our Beloved, even Christ in us the hope of
                        glory,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Col. 1:27.</p>
                    </note> who dwelleth in our hearts by faith,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            3:17.</p>
                    </note> who likewise is ever interceding for us at the right
                    hand of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:34.</p>
                    </note> we receive help from him to think and speak
                    and act what is acceptable in his sight.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 19:14.</p>
                    </note> Thus does he
                    ‘prevent them that believe in all their doings, and further them with his
                    continual help’, so that all their designs, conversations, and actions are
                    ‘begun, continued, and ended in him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion, Fourth Collect after Offertory
                            (371).</p>
                    </note> Thus doth he ‘cleanse the thoughts of their hearts, by
                    the inspiration of his Holy Spirit, that they may perfectly love him, and
                    worthily magnify his holy name’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Collect for Purity
                            (337).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Thus it is that in the children of God repentance and faith exactly
                    answer each other.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s most explicit and definitive summary of
                            repentance as prerequisite to justifying faith, and as the groundtone of
                            the continuing Christian life. Cf. above, Nos. 5, ‘Justification by
                            Faith’, IV.6 and n.; and 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.1 and n.; see
                            also 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, III.2;
                            Wesley’s letter to Thomas Church, June 17, 1746, and to Dr. Horne, Mar.
                            10, 1762, as well as his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Luke
                        16:31.</p>
                    </note> By repentance we feel the sin remaining in our hearts, and
                    cleaving to our words and actions. By faith we receive the power of God in
                    Christ, purifying our hearts and cleansing our hands. By repentance we are still
                    sensible that we deserve punishment for all our tempers and words and actions.
                    By faith we are conscious that our advocate with the Father<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    is continually pleading for us, and thereby continually turning aside all
                    condemnation and punishment from us. By repentance we have an abiding conviction
                    that there is no <pb n="350"/>help in us. By faith we receive not only mercy,
                    but ‘grace to help in <hi rend="italic">every</hi> time of need’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            4:16.</p>
                    </note> Repentance disclaims the very possibility of any other
                    help. Faith accepts all the help we stand in need of from him that hath all
                    power in heaven and earth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt 28:18.</p>
                    </note> Repentance says,
                    ‘Without him I can do nothing:’ faith says, ‘I can do all things through Christ
                    strengthening me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:13; cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Through him I cannot only overcome, but expel all
                    the enemies of my soul. Through him I can ‘love the Lord my God with all my
                    heart, mind, soul, and strength’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note> yea, and
                    walk in holiness and righteousness before him all the days of my life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            1:75.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. From what has been said we may easily learn the mischievousness of
                    that opinion that we are <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi> sanctified when we are
                    justified; that our hearts are then cleansed from all sin. It is true we are
                    then delivered (as was observed before) from the dominion of outward sin: and at
                    the same time the power of inward sin is so broken that we need no longer follow
                    or be led by it. But it is by no means true that inward sin is then totally
                    destroyed, that the root of pride, self-will, anger, love of the world, is then
                    taken out of the heart, or that the carnal mind<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:7.</p>
                    </note> and the
                    heart bent to backsliding<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Hosea 11:7.</p>
                    </note> are entirely extirpated. And
                    to suppose the contrary is not, as some may think, an innocent, harmless
                    mistake. No: it does immense harm; it entirely blocks up the way to any farther
                    change. For it is manifest, ‘They that are whole do not need a physician, but
                    they that are sick.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 5:31.</p>
                    </note> If therefore we think we
                    are quite made whole already, there is no room to seek any farther healing. On
                    this supposition it is absurd to expect a farther deliverance from sin, whether
                    gradual or instantaneous.</p>
                <p n="2">2. On the contrary, a deep conviction that we are not yet whole, that our
                    hearts are not fully purified, that there is yet in us ‘a carnal mind’ which is
                    still in its nature ‘enmity against God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:7.</p>
                    </note> that a whole body of
                    sin remains in our heart, weakened indeed, but not destroyed, shows beyond all
                    possibility of doubt the absolute necessity of a farther change. We allow that
                    at the very moment of justification we are ‘born again’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:3, 7; 1 Pet 1:23. Cf.
                            Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, II.7; 19, ‘The Great
                            Privilege of those that are Born of God’, §§1-2; 45, ‘The New Birth’
                            (entire sermon); 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.9-10; 83, ‘On Patience’,
                            §9. Cf. also Wesley’s letter to the Editor of <hi rend="italic">Lloyd’s
                                Evening Post</hi>, Feb. 26, 1771.</p>
                    </note> in that instant we <pb n="351"/>experience that inward change from ‘darkness into marvellous
                        light’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 2:9.</p>
                    </note> from the image of the brute and the devil into the
                    image of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> from the earthly, sensual, devilish mind, to the mind which
                    was in Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> But are we then <hi rend="italic">entirely</hi> changed? Are we <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi>
                    transformed into the image of him that created us? Far from it: we still retain
                    a depth of sin; and it is the consciousness of this which constrains us to groan
                    for a full deliverance to him that is mighty to save.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 63:1.</p>
                    </note> Hence
                    it is that those believers who are not convinced of the deep corruption of their
                    hearts, or but slightly and as it were notionally convinced, have little concern
                    about <hi rend="italic">entire sanctification</hi>. They may possibly hold the
                    opinion that such a thing is to be, either at death, or some time (they know not
                    when) before it. But they have no great uneasiness for the want of it, and no
                    great hunger or thirst after it. They cannot, until they know themselves better,
                    until they repent in the sense above described, until God unveils the inbred
                    monster’s face, and shows them the real state of their souls.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, II.1 and n.</p>
                    </note> Then only, when they feel the burden,
                    will they groan for deliverance from it. Then and not till then will they cry
                    out, in the agony of their soul,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Break off the yoke of inbred sin,</l>
                    <l>And fully set my spirit free!</l>
                    <l>I cannot rest till pure within,</l>
                    <l>Till I am wholly lost in thee!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘Come unto me…Matt. xi. 28’, st. 5, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 91 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, II.145; No. 377 in <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>). Here is an aspiration to sinless
                                perfection that implies its possibility and, as we know from other
                                passages, <hi rend="italic">in this life</hi>. Cf. above, I.20, and
                                No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, V.2 and
                            n.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="3">3. We may learn from hence, secondly, that a deep conviction of our <hi rend="italic">demerit</hi> after we are accepted (which in one sense may be
                    termed <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi>) is absolutely necessary in order to our
                    seeing the true value of the atoning blood; in order to our feeling that we need
                    this as much after we are justified as ever we did before. Without this
                    conviction we cannot but account the blood of the covenant<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 24:8; Heb.
                        10:29.</p>
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">as a common thing</hi>, something of which we have not now any
                    great need, seeing all our past sins are blotted out.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 3:19.</p>
                    </note>
                    Yea, but if both our hearts and lives are thus unclean, there is a kind of guilt
                    which we are contracting every moment, and which of <pb n="352"/>consequence
                    would every moment expose us to fresh condemnation, but that</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>He ever lives above,</l>
                    <l>For us to intercede,</l>
                    <l>His all-atoning love,</l>
                    <l>His precious blood to plead.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘Behold the Man!’ (beginning ‘Arise my soul,
                                arise’), ver. 2, ll. 1-4, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                                    Poems</hi> (1742), p. 264 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                                II.323; No. 194 in <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>). Orig., ‘For
                                me to intercede’, and ‘all-redeeming love’.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>It is this repentance, and the faith intimately connected with it, which are
                    expressed in those strong lines:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>I sin in every breath I draw,</l>
                    <l>Nor do thy will, nor keep thy law</l>
                    <l>On earth as angels do above:</l>
                    <l>But still the Fountain open stands,</l>
                    <l>Washes my feet, my heart, my hands,</l>
                    <l>Till I am perfected in love.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘A Thanksgiving’, st. 16 in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 171 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, II.234, No. 355 in <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>). Orig., ‘Washes my feet, and head, and
                                hands’.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="4">4. We may observe, thirdly, a deep conviction of our utter <hi rend="italic">helplessness</hi>—of our total inability to retain anything we
                    have received, much more to deliver ourselves from the world of iniquity<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        3:6.</p>
                    </note> remaining both in our hearts and lives—teaches us truly to
                    live upon Christ by faith, not only as our Priest, but as our King. Hereby we
                    are brought to ‘magnify him’, indeed, to ‘give him all the glory of his
                        grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> to ‘make him a whole Christ, an entire Saviour’,
                    and truly to ‘set the crown upon his head’. These excellent words, as they have
                    frequently been used,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Presumably, by the antinomians (e.g., Maxfield,
                            Bell, Cudworth) and, quite possibly, by the English Moravians; but
                            Sugden could not locate their literary sources and neither have I, thus
                            far.</p>
                    </note> have little or no meaning. But they are fulfilled in a
                    strong and a deep sense when we thus, as it were, go out of ourselves, in order
                    to be swallowed up in him; when we sink into nothing that he may be all in
                        all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Cor. 15:28.</p>
                    </note> Then, his almighty grace having abolished ‘every
                    high thing which exalted itself against’ him, every temper, and thought, and
                    word, and work is ‘brought to the obedience of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 10:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <p>
                <placeName>Londonderry</placeName>, <date when="1767-04-24">April 24, 1767</date>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>