<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 74: Of the Church</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon074</idno>                        
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 74: Of the Church</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume III: Sermons III,
                                71-114</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1986-11-01">1986-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="3"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="30" to="31"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="31" to="44"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="03:045"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermon 74]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Wesley spent the month of September 1785 in and around Bristol. This was the year
                    after the Deed of Declaration and after Wesley’s ‘ordinations’ of Coke,
                    Whatcoat, and Vasey for their ministries in America. The Deed and the
                    ordinations had been widely taken, not without reason, as portents of separation
                    from the Church of England,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Frank Baker, <hi rend="italic">John Wesley and
                                the Church of England</hi>, chs. 13-16.</p>
                    </note> despite Wesley’s
                    oft-repeated disavowals of all such intentions. Indeed, the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entry for Sunday, September 4, tells us of his reaction to
                    this continuing suspicion: ‘Finding a report had been spread abroad that I was
                    going to leave the Church, to satisfy those that were grieved concerning it, I
                    openly declared in the evening that I had now no more thought of separating from
                    the Church than I had forty years ago.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">JWJ, Sept. 4-30, 1785.</p>
                    </note> He went beyond
                    the ‘open declaration’; he began to write this sermon, ‘Of the Church,’ the
                    first written summary of his ecclesiology. It was finished on September 28, and
                    published in the <hi rend="italic">Arminian Magazine</hi> for the following
                    January and February (1786), IX.8-15, 71-75, without a title but numbered as
                    ‘Sermon XXXI.’ Tyerman omits it from his list of Wesley’s ‘original sermons [for
                    the year 1785] which are well worth reading’ (<hi rend="italic">Life of
                        Wesley</hi>, III.470). Wesley’s reasons for its particular placement in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, VI.171-90, can only be conjectured. It was not
                    reprinted in his lifetime.</p>
                <p>One is bound to be impressed by Wesley’s wholly unselfconscious assumption that,
                    even after all he had done that would inevitably lead to separation, he was, and
                    always had been, a devoted and loyal Anglican. He speaks quite naturally of ‘our
                    [Anglican] liturgy’, as when he cites the eucharistic prayer ‘for the whole
                    state of Christ’s church militant here on earth’ (§5). His personal definition
                    of <hi rend="italic">church</hi> (§14) is, or so he claims, ‘exactly agreeable
                    to the nineteenth article of <hi rend="italic">our church</hi>’ (§16), although
                    he feels free to interpret this article more comprehensively than its authors
                    had ever intended.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">So as, e.g., §§17-19, to include in ‘the church’ all true believers
                            among the Dissenting churches, and even those in the Church of
                        Rome.</p>
                    </note> However, his final conclusions are <pb n="03:046"/>neither
                    Anglican, Lutheran, nor Calvinist. The essence of the church, for Wesley, need
                    not be sought in its visible institutions, not even some invisible <hi rend="italic">numerus electorum</hi>. The church as Body of Christ is the
                    company of all true believers, ‘holy’ because its members are themselves holy
                    (§28). This is, therefore, an unstable blend of Anglican and Anabaptist
                    ecclesiologies; it is also one of Wesley’s more daring syntheses. Its
                    outworkings in the subsequent histories of Methodist and Anglican ecclesiology
                    have yet to be probed as deeply as they deserve, which is also to say that its
                    ecumenical significance has yet to be fully appreciated.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Of the Church</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Ephesians 4:1-6</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">I beseech you that ye walk worthy of the vocation wherewith ye
                        are called, with all lowliness and meekness, with long-suffering, forbearing
                        one another in love; endeavouring to keep the unity of the Spirit in the
                        bond of peace. There is one body, and one Spirit, even as ye are called in
                        one hope of your calling; one Lord, one faith, one baptism; one God and
                        Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. How much do we almost continually hear about the Church! With many it is
                    matter of daily conversation. And yet how few understand what they talk of! How
                    few know what the term means! A more ambiguous word than this, the ‘church’, is
                    scarce to be found in the English language. It is sometimes taken for a building
                    set apart for public worship, sometimes for a congregation or body of people
                    united together in the service of God. It is only in the latter sense that it is
                    taken in the ensuing discourse.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It may be taken indifferently for any number of people, how small or
                    great soever. As ‘where two or three are met together in his name’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            18:20.</p>
                    </note> there is Christ; so (to speak with St. Cyprian) ‘where
                    two or three believers are met together, there is a church.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cyprian, <hi rend="italic">On
                                the Unity of the Church</hi>, xii (<hi rend="italic">Fathers of the
                                Church</hi>, New York, 1947, XXXVI.107; cf. also <hi rend="italic">Ancient Christian Writers</hi>, London, 1957, 25:54-55).</p>
                    </note>
                    Thus <pb n="03:047"/>it is that St. Paul, writing to Philemon, mentions ‘the
                    church which is in his house’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Philem. 2; cf. Col. 4:15.</p>
                    </note> plainly
                    signifying that even a Christian family may be termed a church.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Several of those whom God had ‘called out’ of the world (so the original
                    word properly signifies),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley here assumes the lexical kinship of κλήσεως
                            ἐκλήθητε (Eph. 4:1) and ἐκκλησία with their common verbal root, καλέω.
                            But see K. L. Schmidt, ‘ἐκκλησία’ in Gerhard Kittel, ed., <hi rend="italic">Theological Dictionary of the New Testament</hi>; cf.
                            ‘καλέω’, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> united together in one
                    congregation, formed a larger church: as the church at Jerusalem, that is, all
                    those in Jerusalem whom God had so called. But considering how swiftly these
                    were multiplied after the day of Pentecost, it cannot be supposed that they
                    could continue to assemble in one place; especially as they had not then any
                    large place, neither would they have been permitted to build one. In consequence
                    they must have divided themselves, even at Jerusalem, into several distinct
                    congregations. In like manner, when St. Paul several years after wrote to the
                    church in Rome (directing his letter ‘to all that are in Rome, called to be
                        saints’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            1:7.</p>
                    </note> it cannot be supposed that they had any one building
                    capable of containing them all; but they were divided into several
                    congregations, assembling in several parts of the city.</p>
                <p n="4">4. The first time that the Apostle uses the word ‘church’ is in his preface
                    to the former Epistle to the Corinthians: ‘Paul, called to be an apostle of
                    Jesus Christ, unto the church of God which is at Corinth’; the meaning of which
                    expression is fixed by the following words, ‘to them that are sanctified in
                    Christ Jesus, with all that in every place’ (not Corinth only; so it was a kind
                    of circular letter) ‘call upon the name of Jesus Christ our Lord, both yours and
                        ours’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Cor. 1:1-2.</p>
                    </note> In the inscription of his second letter to the
                    Corinthians he speaks still more explicitly: ‘Unto the church of God which is at
                    Corinth, with all the saints that are in all Achaia’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 1:1.</p>
                    </note> Here he
                    plainly includes all the churches or Christian congregations which were in the
                    whole province.</p>
                <p n="5">5. He frequently uses the word in the plural number. So Gal. 1:2:’Paul, an
                    apostle, …unto the churches of Galatia’—that is, the Christian congregations
                    dispersed throughout that country. In all these places (and abundantly more
                    might be cited) the word church or churches means, not the buildings where the
                        <pb n="03:048"/>Christians assembled (as it frequently does in the English
                    tongue) but the people that used to assemble there—one or more Christian
                    congregations. But sometimes the word ‘church’ is taken in Scripture in a still
                    more extensive meaning, as including all the Christian congregations that are
                    upon the face of the earth. And in this sense we understand it in our
                        liturgy<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note
                            this unselfconscious citation of the BCP as ‘our’.</p>
                    </note> when we
                    say, ‘Let us pray for the whole state of Christ’s church militant here on
                        earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The
                            Prayer for the Church’ in the BCP, Communion.</p>
                    </note> In this sense
                    it is unquestionably taken by St. Paul in his exhortation to the elders of
                    Ephesus, ‘Take heed to the church of God, which he hath purchased with his own
                        blood.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 20:28.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The ‘church’ here undoubtedly means the
                    catholic or universal church, that is, all the Christians under heaven.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Who those are that are properly ‘the church of God’ the Apostle shows at
                    large, and that in the clearest and most decisive manner, in the passage above
                    cited; wherein he likewise instructs all the members of the church how to ‘walk
                    worthy of the vocation wherewith they are called’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="7">[I.]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s basic division of this sermon is by consecutively numbered
                            sections, but he apparently intended to introduce a parallel numbering
                            of three major divisions, prefixing ‘II’ to §20, which would imply an
                            omitted ‘I’ at this point and ‘III’ at §27.</p>
                    </note> 7. Let us
                    consider, first, who are properly ‘the church of God’? What is the true meaning
                    of that term? ‘The church at Ephesus’, as the Apostle himself explains it,
                    means, ‘the saints’, the holy persons, ‘that are in Ephesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:1.</p>
                    </note> and there
                    assemble themselves together to worship God the Father and his Son Jesus
                    Christ—whether they did this in one, or (as we may probably suppose) in several
                    places. But it is the church in general, the catholic or universal church, which
                    the Apostle here considers as ‘one body’; comprehending not only the Christians
                    ‘in the house of Philemon’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Philem 2.</p>
                    </note> or any one family; not
                    only the Christians of one congregation, of one city, of one province or nation;
                    but all the persons upon the face of the earth who answer the character here
                    given. The several particulars contained therein we may now more distinctly
                    consider.</p>
                <p n="8">8. ‘There is one Spirit’ who animates all these, all the living <pb n="03:049"/>members of the church of God. Some understand hereby the Holy
                    Spirit himself, the fountain of all spiritual life. And it is certain, ‘If any
                    man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:9.</p>
                    </note> Others
                    understand it of those spiritual gifts and holy dispositions which are afterward
                    mentioned.</p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘There is’, in all those that have received this Spirit, ‘one hope’, a
                    hope full of immortality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 3:4; cf. No. 72, ‘Of Evil Angels’, II.4 and
                            n. Also note the echoes here of the older debates between the Quakers
                            and the Anglicans.</p>
                    </note> They know, to die is not to be lost: their
                    prospect extends beyond the grave. They can cheerfully say, ‘Blessed be the God
                    and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, who, according to his abundant mercy, hath
                    begotten us again unto a lively hope by the resurrection of Jesus Christ from
                    the dead, to an inheritance incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not
                        away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 1:3-4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. ‘There is one Lord’ who has now dominion over them, who has set up his
                    kingdom in their hearts, and reigns over all those that are partakers of this
                    hope. To obey him, to run the way of his commandments, is their glory and joy.
                    And while they are doing this with a willing mind they, as it were, ‘sit in
                    heavenly places with Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. ‘There is one faith,’ which is the free gift of God, and is the ground
                    of their hope. This is not barely the faith of a heathen;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For Wesley’s categories of
                            faith, see No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, I.2 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> namely, a belief that ‘there is a God’, and that he is
                    gracious and just, and consequently ‘a rewarder of them that diligently seek
                        him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            11:6.</p>
                    </note> Neither is it barely the faith of a devil; though this
                    goes much farther than the former. For the devil believes, and cannot but
                    believe, all that is written both in the Old and New Testament to be true. But
                    it is the faith of St. Thomas, teaching him to say with holy boldness, ‘My Lord
                    and my God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 20:28.</p>
                    </note> It is the faith which enables every true
                    Christian believer to testify with St. Paul, ‘The life which I now live I live
                    by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and gave himself for me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            2:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. ‘There is one baptism,’ which is the outward sign our one Lord has
                    been pleased to appoint of all that inward and spiritual grace which he is
                    continually bestowing upon his church. It is likewise a precious means whereby
                    this faith and hope are given to those that diligently seek him. Some indeed
                    have been inclined <pb n="03:050"/>to interpret this in a figurative sense, as
                    if it referred to that baptism of the Holy Ghost which the apostles received at
                    the day of Pentecost, and which in a lower degree is given to all
                        believers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An allusion to the views of Quakers and pentecostalists who had either
                            rejected sacramental baptism or had claimed that ‘the baptism of the
                            Spirit’ superseded it.</p>
                    </note> But it is a stated rule in
                    interpreting Scripture never to depart from the plain, literal sense, unless it
                    implies an absurdity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For an earlier version of this basic hermeneutical
                            principle, see No. 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, §6 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    And beside, if we thus understood it, it would be a needless repetition, as
                    being included in, ‘There is one spirit.’</p>
                <p n="13">13. ‘There is one God and Father of all’ that have the Spirit of adoption,
                    which ‘crieth in their hearts, Abba, Father’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> which ‘witnesseth’
                    continually ‘with their spirits’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note> that they are the
                    children of God; ‘who is above all’—the Most High, the Creator, the Sustainer,
                    the Governor of the whole universe. ‘And through all’—pervading all space,
                    filling heaven and earth:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Totam</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mens agitans molem, et magno se corpore miscens.</hi>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>,
                                vi.726-27:</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Totamque infusa per artus</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Mens agitat molem et magno se corpore miscet.</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>The all-informing soul,</l>
                    <l>That fills, pervades, and actuates the whole.</l>
                </lg>
                <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also Nos. 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, I.6; 118, ‘On the
                    Omnipresence of God’, II.1; <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §19 (11:51
                    in this edn.); and <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Original Sin</hi>, Pt. I,
                    I.13.</p>
                <p>‘And in you all’—in a peculiar manner living in you that are one body by one
                    spirit:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Making your souls his loved abode,</l>
                    <l>The temples of indwelling God.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Charles Wesley, ‘Groaning for the Spirit of
                        Adoption’, in John and Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                            Poems</hi> (1740), p. 132 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                        I.308).</p>
                </note>
                <p n="14">14. Here then is a clear unexceptionable answer to that question, What is
                    the church? The catholic or universal church is all the persons in the universe
                    whom God hath so called out of the world as to entitle them to the preceding
                    character; as to be ‘one body’, united by ‘one spirit’; having ‘one faith, one
                    hope, one baptism; one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all,
                    and in them all.’</p>
                <p n="15">
                    <pb n="03:051"/>15. That part of this great body, of the universal church,
                    which inhabits any one kingdom or nation, we may properly term a ‘national’
                    church, as the Church of France, the Church of England, the Church of Scotland.
                    A smaller part of the universal church are the Christians that inhabit one city
                    or town, as the church of Ephesus, and the rest of the seven churches mentioned
                    in the Revelation. Two or three Christian believers united together are a church
                    in the narrowest sense of the word. Such was the church in the house of
                    Philemon, and that in the house of Nymphas, mentioned Col. 4:15. A particular
                    church may therefore consist of any number of members, whether two or three, or
                    two or three millions. But still, whether it be larger or smaller, the same idea
                    is to be preserved. They are one body, and have one Spirit, one Lord, one hope,
                    one faith, one baptism, one God and Father of all.</p>
                <p n="16">16. This account is exactly agreeable to the nineteenth Article of our
                    Church, the Church of England—only the Article includes a little more than the
                    Apostle has expressed.</p>
                <quote>Of the Church<lb/> The visible church of Christ is a congregation of faithful
                    men, in which the pure word of God is preached, and the sacraments be duly
                    administered.</quote>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The first half of the first sentence of Art. XIX which,
                        in turn, had been borrowed from Art. VIII of the <hi rend="italic">Augsburg
                            Confession</hi> (1530).</p>
                </note>
                <p>It may be observed that at the same time our Thirty-nine Articles were compiled
                    and published a Latin translation of them was published by the same authority.
                    In this the words were <hi rend="italic">coetus credentium</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An interesting
                            conflation here. The Latin text of the Article (1517) reads <hi rend="italic">coetus fidelium</hi>; but in Art. VIII of the <hi rend="italic">Augsburg Confession</hi> the church is defined as a
                                <hi rend="italic">congregatio sanctorum et vere credentium</hi>. For
                            evidence that Wesley preferred his conflated phrase, see <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §76 (11:77 in this edn.); see
                            also his letter to his brother Charles, Aug. 19, 1785. For the official
                            texts of the Confession and of the Articles, see Philip Schaff, <hi rend="italic">Creeds</hi>, III.3-73, 486-516.</p>
                    </note> ‘a
                    congregation of believers’, plainly showing that by ‘faithful men’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This is English
                            for <hi rend="italic">fidelium</hi>. Thus, it would seem that Wesley had
                            both the Anglican Article and the Lutheran Confession somehow conflated
                            in his mind.</p>
                    </note> the compilers meant men endued with ‘living
                        faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The
                            official texts (as in Arts. XII and XXIX) read ‘lively’ for ‘living’, as
                            does ‘A Catechism’ in the BCP. ‘The Prayer for the Church’ in the Order
                            of Holy Communion refers to God’s ‘true and lively Word’.</p>
                    </note>
                    This brings the Article to a still nearer agreement to the account given by the
                    Apostle.</p>
                <p>But it may be doubted whether the Article speaks of a <pb n="03:052"/>particular
                    church or of the church universal. The title, ‘Of the Church’, seems to have
                    reference to the catholic church. But the second clause of the Article mentions
                    the particular churches of Jerusalem, Antioch, Alexandria, and Rome. Perhaps it
                    was intended to take in both—so to define the universal church as to keep in
                    view the several particular churches of which it is composed.</p>
                <p n="17">17. These things being considered, it is easy to answer that question,
                    What is ‘the Church of England’? It is that part, those members, of the
                    universal church, who are inhabitants of England. The Church of England is that
                    ‘body’ of men in England in whom ‘there is one Spirit, one hope, one Lord, one
                    faith’, which have ‘one baptism’, and ‘one God and Father of all’. This and this
                    alone is the Church of England, according to the doctrine of the Apostle.</p>
                <p n="18">18. But the definition of a church laid down in the Article includes not
                    only this but much more, by that remarkable addition, ‘in which the pure Word of
                    God is preached, and the sacraments be duly administered’. According to this
                    definition those congregations in which the pure Word of God (a strong
                    expression) is not preached are no parts either of the Church of England or the
                    church catholic. As neither are those in which the sacraments are not duly
                    administered.</p>
                <p n="19">19. I will not undertake to defend the accuracy of this definition. I dare
                    not exclude from the church catholic all those congregations in which any
                    unscriptural doctrines which cannot be affirmed to be ‘the pure Word of God’ are
                    sometimes, yea, frequently preached. Neither all those congregations in which
                    the sacraments are not ‘duly administered’. Certainly if these things are so the
                    Church of Rome is not so much as a part of the catholic church; seeing therein
                    neither is ‘the pure Word of God’ preached nor the sacraments ‘duly
                    administered’. Whoever they are that have ‘one Spirit, one hope, one Lord, one
                    faith, one God and Father of all’, I can easily bear with their holding wrong
                    opinions, yea, and superstitious modes of worship. Nor would I on these accounts
                    scruple still to include them within the pale of the catholic church. Neither
                    would I have any objection to receive them, if they desired it, as members of
                    the Church of England.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of the same point about theological
                            opinions already made in No. 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’, <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>. For Wesley’s pluralism and vision of ‘comprehension’
                            cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="20">
                    <pb n="03:053"/>II.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See §7 above n. 11, p. 48.</p>
                    </note> 20. We
                    proceed now to the second point. What is it to ‘walk worthy of the vocation
                    wherewith we are called’?</p>
                <p>It should always be remembered that the word ‘walk’ in the language of the
                    Apostle is of a very extensive signification. It includes all our inward and
                    outward motions, all our thoughts, and words, and actions. It takes in not only
                    everything we do, but everything we either speak or think. It is therefore no
                    small thing to walk, in this sense of the word, ‘worthy of the vocation
                    wherewith we are called’—to think, speak, and act, in every instance in a manner
                    worthy of our Christian calling.</p>
                <p n="21">21. We are called to walk, first, ‘with all lowliness’; to have that mind
                    in us which was also in Christ Jesus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> not to think of ourselves
                    more highly than we ought to think,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:3.</p>
                    </note> to be little, and poor,
                    and mean, and vile in our own eyes; to know ourselves as also we are known<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            13:12.</p>
                    </note> by him to whom all hearts are open;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion, Collect for
                            Purity.</p>
                    </note> to be deeply sensible of our own unworthiness, of the
                    universal depravity of our nature (in which dwelleth no good thing<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        7:18.</p>
                    </note>), prone to all evil, averse to all good, insomuch that we
                    are not only sick but dead in trespasses and sins,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> till God
                    breathes upon the dry bones,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 37:1-10.</p>
                    </note> and creates life by
                    the fruit of his lips.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 57:19.</p>
                    </note> And suppose this is
                    done, suppose he has now quickened us, infusing life into our dead souls; yet
                    how much of the carnal mind remains! How prone is our heart still to depart from
                    the living God! What a tendency to sin remains in our heart, although we know
                    our past sins are forgiven!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of the problem of the residue of sin in
                            believers; cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>,
                            intro., I.6, III. 1-9, and n.</p>
                    </note> And how much sin, in spite of
                    all our endeavours, cleaves both to our words and actions! Who can be duly
                    sensible how much remains in him of his natural enmity to God? Or how far he is
                    still alienated from God by the ignorance that is in him?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="22">22. Yea, suppose God has now thoroughly cleansed our heart, and scattered
                    the last remains of sin; yet how can we be sensible enough of our own
                    helplessness, our utter inability to all good, unless we are every hour, yea,
                    every moment, endued with power from on high? Who is able to think one good
                    thought, or to form one good desire, unless by that Almighty power which worketh
                    in <pb n="03:054"/>us both to will and to do of his good pleasure?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil.
                            2:13.</p>
                    </note> We have need even in this state of grace to be
                    thoroughly and continually penetrated with a sense of this. Otherwise we shall
                    be in a perpetual danger of robbing God of his honour, by glorying in something
                    we have received as though we had not received it.</p>
                <p n="23">23. When our inmost soul is thoroughly tinctured therewith, it remains
                    that we be ‘clothed with humility’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:5.</p>
                    </note> The word used by St. Peter
                    seems to imply that we be covered with it as with a surtout;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A French loanword already
                            defined by Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>, as ‘a large coat
                            worn over all the rest’—which is to say, a mantle, as here.</p>
                    </note>
                    that we be all humility, both within and without, tincturing all we think,
                    speak, and do. Let all our actions spring from this fountain; let all our words
                    breathe this spirit; that all men may know we have been with Jesus, and have
                    learned of him to be lowly in heart.</p>
                <p n="24">24. And being taught of him who was meek as well as lowly in heart,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            11:29.</p>
                    </note> we shall then be enabled to ‘walk with all meekness’,
                    being taught of him who teacheth as never man taught,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 7:46.</p>
                    </note> to
                    be meek as well as lowly in heart. This implies not only a power over anger, but
                    over all violent and turbulent passions. It implies the having all our passions
                    in due proportion; none of them either too strong or too weak, but all duly
                    balanced with each other, all subordinate to reason; and reason directed by the
                    Spirit of God. Let this equanimity govern your whole souls, that your thoughts
                    may all flow in an even stream, and the uniform tenor of your words and actions
                    be suitable thereto. In this patience you will then ‘possess your souls’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            21:19.</p>
                    </note> which are not our own while we are tossed by unruly
                    passions. And by this all men may know that we are indeed followers of the meek
                    and lowly Jesus.</p>
                <p n="25">25. Walk with all long-suffering. This is nearly related to meekness, but
                    implies something more. It carries on the victory already gained over all your
                    turbulent passions, notwithstanding all the powers of darkness, all the assaults
                    of evil men or evil spirits. It is patiently triumphant over all opposition, and
                    unmoved though all the waves and storms thereof go over you. Though provoked
                    ever so often, it is still the same, quiet and unshaken; never being ‘overcome
                    of evil, but overcoming evil with good’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="26">
                    <pb n="03:055"/>26. The ‘forbearing one another in love’ seems to mean not
                    only the not resenting anything, and the not avenging yourselves; not only the
                    not injuring, hurting, or grieving each other, either by word or deed; but also
                    the bearing one another’s burdens;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 6:2.</p>
                    </note> yea, and lessening them by
                    every means in our power. It implies the sympathizing with them in their
                    sorrows, afflictions, and infirmities; the bearing them up when without our help
                    they would be liable to sink under their burdens; the endeavouring to lift their
                    sinking heads, and to strengthen their feeble knees.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Job 4:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="27">[III.]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            §7, above.</p>
                    </note> 27. Lastly: the true members of the church of
                    Christ ‘endeavour’, with all possible diligence, with all care and pains, with
                    unwearied patience (and all will be little enough), ‘to keep the unity of the
                    Spirit in the bond of peace’; to preserve inviolate the same spirit of lowliness
                    and meekness, of long-suffering, mutual forbearance and love; and all these
                    cemented and knit together by that sacred tie, the peace of God filling the
                    heart. Thus only can we be and continue living members of that church which is
                    the body of Christ.</p>
                <p n="28">28. Does it not clearly appear from this whole account why, in the ancient
                    Creed commonly called the Apostles’, we term the universal or catholic church,
                    ‘the holy catholic church’? How many wonderful reasons have been found out for
                    giving it this appellation! One learned man informs us, ‘The church is called
                    holy because Christ the head of it is holy.’ Another eminent author affirms, ‘It
                    is so called because all its ordinances are designed to promote holiness;’ and
                    yet another, ‘Because our Lord <hi rend="italic">intended</hi> that all the
                    members of the church should be holy.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A drastic oversimplification of a complex
                            question about the holiness of the church that runs back at least to
                            Novatian and Cyprian, to the Donatists and Augustine, and which had
                            become focused in the debate about ‘the <hi rend="italic">marks</hi> of
                            the church’: i.e., ‘one, <hi rend="italic">holy</hi>, catholic, and
                            apostolic’. Cf. Heinrich Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Theology of
                                the Evangelical Lutheran Church</hi>, p. 588; and Heinrich Heppe,
                                <hi rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, pp. 662-63. From his own
                            time and tradition, Wesley is echoing the discussion of ‘The Holy
                            Catholick Church’ in John Pearson’s magisterial <hi rend="italic">An
                                Exposition of the Creed</hi> (1659), Art. IX, 343-45. Wesley’s own
                            conclusion is closer to the Donatists and Anabaptists than to most of
                            his fellow Anglicans; cf. Edmund Gibson, <hi rend="italic">Codex Juris
                                Ecclesiastici Anglicani</hi> (1713), Title I, chs. i, vi.</p>
                    </note>
                    Nay, the shortest and the plainest reason that can be given, and the only true
                    one, is: the church is called ‘holy’ because it is holy; because every member
                    thereof is holy, though in different <hi rend="Page">[03:056]</hi>degrees, as he
                    that called them is holy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 1:15.</p>
                    </note> How clear is this! If
                    the church, as to the very essence of it, is a body of believers, no man that is
                    not a Christian believer can be a member of it. If this whole body be animated
                    by one spirit, and endued with one faith and one hope of their calling; then he
                    who has not that spirit, and faith, and hope, is no member of this body. It
                    follows that not only no common swearer, no sabbath-breaker, no drunkard, no
                    whoremonger, no thief, no liar, none that lives in any outward sin; but none
                    that is under the power of anger or pride, no lover of the world—in a word, none
                    that is dead to God—can be a member of his church.</p>
                <p n="29">29. Can anything then be more absurd than for men to cry out, ‘the Church!
                    the Church!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 22:14: ‘Many hear [the
                            Gospel], few believe. Yea, many are members of the visible but few of
                                <hi rend="italic">the invisible church</hi>.’ In CWJ, Oct. 27, 1739,
                            there is a complaint against ‘our modern Pharisees’ who keep only to a
                            minimum of outward observances. ‘And yet these men cry out, “The Church!
                            The Church!” when they themselves will not hear the church….’ This
                            phrase (‘The Church! The Church!’) had been a popular mob outcry, as in
                            the Sacheverell riots of 1709; cf. Thomas Hearne, <hi rend="italic">Reliquiae Hernianae</hi>, I.187-88 (Mar. 4, 1710), and in the Lord
                            Gordon riots of 1780. Addison mentions the cry in <hi rend="italic">The
                                Spectator</hi>, No. 567, July 14, 1714: ‘These people may cry,
                            “Church, Church”, as long as they please, …but the proof of the pudding
                            is in the eating.’</p>
                    </note> and to pretend to be very zealous for it,
                    and violent defenders of it; while they themselves have neither part nor lot
                        therein,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 8:21.</p>
                    </note> nor indeed know what the church is? And yet the
                    hand of God is in this very thing! Even in this his wonderful wisdom appears,
                    directing their mistake to his own glory, and causing ‘the earth to help the
                        woman’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rev. 12:16.</p>
                    </note> Imagining that they are members of it themselves,
                    the men of the world frequently defend the church. Otherwise the wolves that
                    surround the little flock on every side would in a short time tear them in
                    pieces. And for this very reason it is not wise to provoke them more than is
                    unavoidable. Even on this ground let us, if it be possible, as much as lieth in
                    us, live peaceably with all men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:18.</p>
                    </note> Especially as we know
                    not how soon God may call them too out of the kingdom of Satan into the kingdom
                    of his dear Son.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="30">30. In the meantime let all those who are real members of the church see
                    that they walk holy and unblameable in all things. ‘Ye are the light of the
                    world!’ Ye are ‘a city set upon a hill, and cannot <pb n="03:057"/>be hid. O let
                    your light shine before men!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:14, 16.</p>
                    </note> Show them your faith
                    by your works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Jas. 2:18.</p>
                    </note> Let them see by the whole tenor of your
                    conversation that your hope is all laid up above! Let all your words and actions
                    evidence the spirit whereby you are animated! Above all things, let your love
                        abound.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 1:9.</p>
                    </note> Let it extend to every child of man; let it
                    overflow to every child of God. By this let all men know whose disciples ye are,
                    because you love one another.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 13:35.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <p n="">Bristol, <date when="1785-09-28">Sept. 28, 1785</date>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Place and date as in <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>