<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 48: Self-Denial</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 48: Self-Denial</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="236" to="250"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:236"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The concluding trio of sermons in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV, suggest that
                    Wesley had finally rounded out his exposition of the ‘order of salvation’ with
                    his paired essays on the difference between spiritual ‘darkness’ and
                    ‘heaviness’. It was, therefore, time to turn to other, separate problems that
                    continued to arise in any programme of Christian living. This sequence would
                    have seemed natural enough, since Wesley’s concept of theology as a <hi
                        rend="italic">scientia practica</hi> had always meant to him that
                    evangelical doctrine entailed a series of ethical imperatives which issued, in
                    turn, from clear conceptions of sound doctrine.</p>
                <p>It may be somewhat startling to read that, until this sermon, ‘no writer in the
                    English tongue [had] described the nature of self-denial in plain and
                    intelligible terms,’ when one considers the popularity of this topic in Puritan
                    preaching and such familiar classics as Richard Baxter’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Treatise of Self-Denyall</hi> (1660, 1675); William Penn, <hi rend="italic"
                        >No Cross, No Crown…</hi> (1669, 1682); Jeremy Taylor, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Rule and Exercises of Holy Living</hi> (1650), and <hi rend="italic">The
                        Rule and Exercises of Holy Dying</hi> (1651), <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                    I.399-515, 516-604; Thomas Manton, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise of
                        Self-Denial…</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1689), IV.17ff; and
                    William Law, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                        >A Serious Call to a Devout and Holy Life</hi> (1729), in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Works</hi>, Vols. III and IV. And it goes without saying that a reader is
                    free to judge how far Wesley may be compared with such predecessors.</p>
                <p>What he may have had more directly in mind was the fact that the tradition on
                    self-denial had rested on a general consensus, at least in an approval of the
                    ideal. The conventional form of the problem had always come from the
                    discrepancies between profession and practice. In his own lifetime, however,
                    Wesley had seen even the ideal decried, both by the spreading fashions of
                    self-advertised ostentation in eighteenth-century culture and by a rising tide
                    of antinomian rejection of self-denial, <hi rend="italic">on principle</hi>. As
                    far back as 1741 he had been shocked by Count von Zinzendorf’s scornful
                    dismissal of self-abnegation as a Christian virtue (cf. JWJ, September 3, 1741:
                    ‘We believers do as we please and nothing more; we laugh at all talk of
                    “mortification”’). He had gone on to retort <pb n="02:237"/>to this in kind, in
                    his own <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi> of 1743, by instructing the
                    Methodists to ‘trample under foot that enthusiastic doctrine of devils that “we
                    are not to do good unless our heart be free to it.”’ But the tendency of the new
                    piety to turn ‘Christian liberty’ into self-indulgence had persisted; there was
                    evident need for yet another distillation of the ancient Christian wisdom on
                    ‘cross-bearing’ and self-surrender to the will of God; hence, this present
                    sermon.</p>
                <p>The idea, as Wesley defines it here, had been a childhood commonplace in his
                    family; it had been a major premise in Susanna’s theory of Christian
                        nurture.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Nos. 95, On the Education of Children’, and 96, ‘On Obedience to
                            Parents’.</p></note> A sermon on this topic appears as No. 25 in
                    Wesley’s own list of his early sermons.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Heitzenrater, ‘John Wesley’s Early Sermons’, p.
                            117.</p></note> He had preached on Luke 9:23 in Savannah, and very
                    shortly after his return to England (February 21, 1738) he had used the same
                    text for a sermon in one of the oldest churches in the City of London, Great St.
                    Helen’s (in Bishopsgate). In the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for August 16,
                    1744, he had printed a letter about self-denial from his friend, the Revd. Henry
                    Piers (Vicar of Bexley), and a few months later (February 17, 1745), he had
                    inserted another letter into the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> on the same
                    theme, from his ‘book steward’, William Briggs.</p>
                <p>Since then, however, his use of Luke 9:23 had been sparse (only twice, both in
                    1755). One may suppose, therefore, that our text here had been written expressly
                    for inclusion in the fourth volume of his <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>; it should
                    be noticed how much more clearly this sermon reflects the problem as it had to
                    be perceived in the 1750s than it would have appeared in 1738. It was, of
                    course, reprinted in the successive editions of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, but
                    never separately.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:238"/>
            <head>Self-Denial</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Luke 9:23</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And he said to them all, If any man will come after me, let
                        him deny himself, and take up his cross daily, and follow me.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. It has been frequently imagined that the direction here given related
                    chiefly, if not wholly, to the apostles; at least to the Christians of the first
                    ages, or those in a state of persecution. But this is a grievous mistake; for
                    although our blessed Lord is here directing his discourse more immediately to
                    his apostles and those other disciples who attended him in the days of his
                    flesh, yet in them he speaks to us, and to all mankind, without any exception or
                    limitation. The very reason of the thing puts it beyond dispute that the duty
                    which is here enjoined is not peculiar to them, or to the Christians of the
                    early ages. It no more regards any particular order of men, or particular time,
                    than any particular country. No; it is of the most universal nature, respecting
                    all times and all persons. Yea, and all things—not meats and drinks only, and
                    things pertaining to the senses. The meaning is, ‘If any man’, of whatever rank,
                    station, circumstances, in any nation, in any age of the world, ‘will’
                    effectually ‘come after me, let him deny himself in all things; let him take up
                    his cross’ of whatever kind, yea, and that ‘daily, and follow me.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. The ‘denying’ ourselves and the ‘taking up our cross’, in the full
                    extent of the expression, is not a thing of small concern. It is not expedient
                    only, as are some of the circumstantials of religion; but it is absolutely,
                    indispensably necessary, either to our becoming or continuing his disciples. It
                    is absolutely necessary, in the very nature of the thing, to our ‘coming after
                    him’ and ‘following him’, insomuch that as far as we do not practise it we are
                    not his disciples. If we do not continually ‘deny ourselves’, we do not learn of
                    him, but of other masters. If we do not ‘take up our cross daily’, we do not
                    ‘come after him’, but after the world, or the prince <pb n="02:239"/>of the
                    world, or our own ‘fleshly mind’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Col. 2:18.</p></note> If we are not walking in the
                    way of the cross, we are not following him; we are not treading in his steps,
                    but going back from, or at least wide of, him.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It is for this reason that so many ministers of Christ in almost every
                    age and nation, particularly since the Reformation of the Church from the
                    innovations and corruptions gradually crept into it, have wrote and spoke so
                    largely on this important duty, both in their public discourses and private
                    exhortations. This induced them to disperse abroad many tracts upon the subject;
                    and some in our own nation. They knew both from the oracles of God and from the
                    testimony of their own experience how impossible it was not to deny our Master,
                    unless we will deny ourselves; and how vainly we attempt to follow him that was
                    crucified, unless we take up our cross daily.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But may not this very consideration make it reasonable to inquire, ‘If
                    so much has been said and wrote on the subject already, what need is there to
                    say or write any more?’ I answer, there are no inconsiderable numbers, even of
                    people fearing God, who have not had the opportunity either of hearing what has
                    been spoke, or reading what has been wrote upon it. And perhaps if they had read
                    much of what has been written they would not have been much profited. Many who
                    have wrote (some of them large volumes) do by no means appear to have understood
                    the subject. Either they had imperfect views of the very nature of it (and then
                    they could never explain it to others) or they were unacquainted with the due
                    extent of it; they did not see how <hi rend="italic">exceeding broad</hi> this
                    command is; or they were not sensible of the absolute, the indispensable
                    necessity of it. Others speak of it in so dark, so perplexed, so intricate, so
                    mystical a manner, as if they designed rather to conceal it from the vulgar than
                    to explain it to common readers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                            rend="footnote text">It may be William Law that he has in mind here, or
                            even Madame Guyon; but it is true that he found such classics as St.
                            John of the Cross’s <hi rend="italic">Ascent of Mt. Carmel</hi> somewhat
                            ‘dark, perplexed, and intricate’.</p></note> Others speak admirably
                    well, with great clearness and strength, on the necessity of self-denial; but
                    then they deal in generals only, without coming to particular instances, and so
                    are of little use to the bulk of mankind, to men of ordinary capacity and
                    education. And if some of them do descend to particulars, it is to those
                    particulars only which do not affect the generality of men, since they seldom,
                    if ever, occur in common life: such as the enduring imprisonment or tortures;
                    the giving up, <pb n="02:240"/>in a literal sense, their houses or lands, their
                    husbands or wives, children, or life itself—to none of which we are called, nor
                    are likely to be, unless God should permit times of public persecution to
                    return. In the meantime, I know of no writer in the English tongue<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Note the assumption
                            here that Wesley’s readers would not have been interested in
                            cross-checking on so confident a generality.</p></note> who has
                    described the nature of self-denial in plain and intelligible terms such as lie
                    level with common understandings, and applied it to those little particulars
                    which daily occur in common life. A discourse of this kind is wanted still. And
                    it is wanted the more because in every stage of the spiritual life, although
                    there is a variety of particular hindrances of our attaining grace or growing
                    therein, yet are all resolvable into these general ones—either we do not deny
                    ourselves, or we do not take up our cross.</p>
                <p>In order to supply this defect in some degree, I shall endeavour to show, first,
                    what it is for a man to deny himself, and what to take up his cross; and
                    secondly, that if a man be not fully Christ’s disciple, it is always owing to
                    the want of this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. I shall, first, endeavour to show what it is for a man to ‘deny
                    himself and take up his cross daily’. This is a point which is of all others
                    most necessary to be considered and throughly understood, even on this account,
                    that it is of all others most opposed, by numerous and powerful enemies. All our
                    nature must certainly rise up against this, even in its own defence. The world,
                    consequently, the men who take nature, not grace, for their guide, abhor the
                    very sound of it. And the great enemy of our souls, well knowing its importance,
                    cannot but move every stone against it. But this is not all: even those who have
                    in some measure shaken off the yoke of the devil, who have experienced,
                    especially of late years, a real work of grace in their hearts, yet are no
                    friends to this grand doctrine of Christianity, though it is so peculiarly
                    insisted on by their Master. Some of them are as deeply and totally ignorant
                    concerning it as if there was not one word about it in the Bible. Others are
                    farther off still, having unawares imbibed strong prejudices against it. These
                    they have received partly from outside Christians—men of a fair speech and
                    behaviour who want nothing of godliness but the power, nothing of religion but
                    the spirit—and partly from those who did once, if they do not now, ‘taste of the
                    powers of the world to come’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:5.</p></note> But are there any <pb
                        n="02:241"/>of these who do not both practise self-denial themselves and
                    recommend it to others? You are little acquainted with mankind if you doubt of
                    this. There are whole bodies of men who only do not declare war against it. To
                    go no farther than London, look upon the whole body of predestinarians who by
                    the free mercy of God have lately been called out of the darkness of nature into
                    the light of faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Col. 1:12-13.</p></note> Are they patterns of
                    self-denial? How few of them even profess to practise it at all! How few of them
                    recommend it themselves, or are pleased with them that do! Rather do they not
                    continually represent it in the most odious colours, as if it were seeking <hi
                        rend="italic">salvation by works</hi>, or ‘seeking to establish our own
                        righteousness’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:3; a caricature that ignores the
                            commonplace that men like Thomas Manton, Lewis Bayley, George Whitefield
                            (indeed, most Calvinists) taught both predestination <hi rend="italic"
                                >and</hi> self-denial. Wesley may have had a special group in
                            mind—e.g., John Cennick, William Cudworth, James Relty, and their
                            disciples.</p></note> And how readily do antinomians of all kinds, from
                    the smooth Moravian<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A sarcastic reference to the elegant Count von
                            Zinzendorf?</p></note> to the boisterous foul-mouthed Ranter,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">If this is a
                            reference to George Fox (cf. the ‘foul-mouthed…George Fox’ in No. 68,
                            ‘The Wisdom of God’s Counsels’, §9), Wesley has confused his
                            seventeenth-century church history. The Ranters proper (men like
                            Laurence Clarkson, Abiezer Coope, Thomas Tany) were indeed famous for
                            their indifference to customary morality and their cultic swearing, but
                            they were condemned and disowned by the Quakers and even by the
                            Muggletonians (‘The Seekers’). Cf. Robert Barclay, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Anarchy of the Ranters, and Other Libertines…</hi> (1676); abridged
                            in Barbour and Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Early Quaker Writings</hi>,
                            pp. 215 ff. Ironically, the ‘Primitive Methodists’ of the early
                            nineteenth century were also called ‘Ranters’, because of their
                            boisterous preaching services and class meetings.</p></note> join the
                    cry with their silly unmeaning cant of ‘legality’, and ‘preaching the law’!
                    Therefore you are in constant danger of being wheedled, hectored, or ridiculed
                    out of this important gospel doctrine either by false teachers or false brethren
                    (more or less beguiled from the simplicity of the gospel) if you are not deeply
                    grounded therein. Let fervent prayer then go before, accompany, and follow what
                    you are now about to read, that it may be written in your heart by the finger of
                    God, so as never to be erased.</p>
                <p n="2">2. But what is self-denial? Wherein are we to deny ourselves? And whence
                    does the necessity of this arise? I answer, the will of God is the supreme,
                    unalterable rule for every intelligent creature; equally binding every angel in
                    heaven and every man upon earth. Nor can it be otherwise: this is the natural,
                    necessary result of the relation between creatures and their Creator. But if the
                    will of God be our one rule of action in everything, great and <pb n="02:242"
                    />small, it follows by undeniable consequence that we are not to do our own will
                    in anything. Here therefore we see at once the nature, with the ground and
                    reason, of self-denial. We see the nature of self-denial: it is the denying or
                    refusing to follow our own will, from a conviction that the will of God is the
                    only rule of action to us. And we see the reason thereof, because we are
                    creatures; because ‘it is he that hath made us and not we ourselves.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 100:3
                            (AV).</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. This reason for self-denial must hold even with regard to the angels of
                    God in heaven; and with regard to man, innocent and holy, as he came out of the
                    hands of his Creator. But a farther reason for it arises from the condition
                    wherein all men are since the Fall. We are all now ‘shapen in wickedness, and in
                    sin did our mother conceive us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 51:5 (BCP).</p></note> Our nature is
                    altogether corrupt, in every power and faculty. And our will, depraved equally
                    with the rest, is wholly bent to indulge our natural corruption. On the other
                    hand, it is the will of God that we resist and counteract that corruption, not
                    at some times, or in some things only, but at all times, and in all things. Here
                    therefore is a farther ground for constant and universal self-denial.</p>
                <p n="4">4. To illustrate this a little farther. The will of God is a path leading
                    straight to God. The will of man which once ran parallel with it is now another
                    path, not only different from it, but in our present state directly contrary to
                    it. It leads from God; if therefore we walk in the one, we must necessarily quit
                    the other. We cannot walk in both. Indeed a man of ‘faint heart and feeble
                    hands’ may ‘go in two ways’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus. 2:12.</p></note> one after the other;
                    but he cannot walk in two ways at the same time. He cannot at one and the same
                    time follow his own will and follow the will of God; he must choose the one or
                    the other—denying God’s will to follow his own, or denying himself to follow the
                    will of God.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Now it is undoubtedly pleasing for the time to follow our own will, by
                    indulging, in any instance that offers, the corruption of our nature. But by
                    following it in anything we so far strengthen the perverseness of our will; and
                    by indulging it we continually increase the corruption of our nature. So by the
                    food which is agreeable to the palate we often increase a bodily disease. It
                    gratifies the taste; but it inflames the disorder. It brings pleasure; but it
                    also brings death.</p>
                <p n="6"><pb n="02:243"/>6. On the whole, then, to deny ourselves is to deny our own
                    will where it does not fall in with the will of God, and that however pleasing
                    it may be. It is to deny ourselves any pleasure which does not spring from, and
                    lead to, God; that is, in effect, to refuse going out of our way, though into a
                    pleasant, flowery path; to refuse what we know to be deadly poison, though
                    agreeable to the taste.</p>
                <p n="7">7. And everyone that would follow Christ, that would be his real disciple,
                    must not only ‘deny himself’, but ‘take up his cross’ also. A cross is anything
                    contrary to our will, anything displeasing to our nature.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">A notable and rare instance of
                            allegorical interpretation; see also No. 99, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Reward of Righteousness</hi>, §4. Wesley’s standard rule, of course,
                            was that all Scripture is to be interpreted literally unless this leads
                            into an absurdity; cf. No. 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, §6 and
                        n.</p></note> So that taking up our cross goes a little farther than denying
                    ourselves; it rises a little higher, and is a more difficult task to flesh and
                    blood, it being more easy to forego pleasure than to endure pain.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Now in ‘running the race which is set before us’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:1.</p></note>
                    according to the will of God, there is often a cross lying in the way; that is,
                    something which is not only not joyous, but grievous, something which is
                    contrary to our will, which is displeasing to our nature. What then is to be
                    done? The choice is plain: either we must ‘take up our cross’, or we must turn
                    aside from the way of God, ‘from the holy commandment delivered to us’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet.
                            2:21.</p></note>—if we do not stop altogether, or turn back to
                    everlasting perdition.</p>
                <p n="9">9. In order to the healing of that corruption, that evil disease which
                    every man brings with him into the world, it is often needful to pluck out as it
                    were a right eye, to cut off a right hand; so painful is either the thing itself
                    which must be done, or the only means of doing it; the parting suppose with a
                    foolish desire,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Tim. 6:9 (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p></note> with an
                    inordinate affection;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Col. 3:5.</p></note> or a separation from the
                    object of it, without which it can never be extinguished. In the former kind,
                    the tearing away such a desire or affection when it is deeply rooted in the soul
                    is often like the piercing of a sword, yea, like ‘the dividing asunder of the
                    soul and spirit, the joints and marrow’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 4:12. There is a personal note of
                            remembered anguish here, for Wesley had experienced two profoundly
                            disturbing misadventures in love—the successive loss of the only two
                            women he had ever really loved romantically. The first was the Sophy
                            Hopkey affair in Georgia, to which there are some clues in the printed
                                <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, more in Wesley’s diary, but the
                            fullest in his several MS journals of his experiences in Georgia, which
                            will appear in print for the first time in the appendix to Vol. 18 of
                            this edn., containing the Journals and diaries for Georgia. The scars of
                            this disappointment may be seen as late as Dec. 23, 1782 (in a letter to
                            an unnamed friend), and in his letters to Samuel Bradburn, Feb. 14,
                            1786, and to Thomas Roberts, Feb. 12, 1789. Even more deeply disturbing,
                            and more recent, had been his espousal to Grace Murray and his loss of
                            her to John Bennet (through the meddling offices of his brother and
                            George Whitefield); cf. JWJ, July 20-Oct 15, 1749; also Wesley’s MS
                            account of her from her birth to her marriage to Bennet (BL Add. MSS.
                            7119), published in J. A. Leger, <hi rend="italic">John Wesley’s Last
                                Love</hi> (London, J. M. Dent and Sons, Ltd., 1910); see also,
                            Curnock, III.417-22. There are not many more pathetic letters in the
                            Wesley corpus than the one to Thomas Bigg, Oct. 7, 1749, expressing his
                            anguish over ‘the fatal, irrecoverable stroke [that] was struck on
                            Thursday last’, when he and Grace Murray ‘were torn asunder by a
                            whirlwind’ (see 26:388-89 in this edn.).</p></note>
                    <pb n="02:244"/>The Lord then sits upon the soul ‘as a refiner’s fire’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mal. 3:2,
                            3.</p></note> to burn up all the dross thereof. And this is a cross
                    indeed; it is essentially painful; it must be so in the very nature of the
                    thing. The soul cannot be thus torn asunder, it cannot pass through the fire,
                    without pain.</p>
                <p n="10">10. In the latter kind, the means to heal a sin-sick soul,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">‘Sin-sick soul’
                            had been a part of poetic diction for over a century, and was becoming
                            almost a religious cliché, even in prose, found in Brooke’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Fool of Quality</hi>, Cowper’s <hi rend="italic">Olney
                                Hymns</hi>, and in the Wesleys’ <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                                Poems</hi> (1739), p. 92: ‘Pity and heal my sin-sick soul.’ (Cf. <hi
                                rend="italic">OED</hi>.)</p></note> to cure a foolish desire, an
                    inordinate affection, are often painful, not in the nature of the thing, but
                    from the nature of the disease. So when our Lord said to the rich young man, ‘Go
                    sell that thou hast and give it to the poor’ (as well knowing this was the only
                    means of healing his covetousness), the very thought of it gave him so much pain
                    that ‘he went away sorrowful’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 19:21-22.</p></note> choosing rather to part
                    with his hope of heaven than his possessions on earth. This was a burden he
                    could not consent to lift, a cross he would not take up. And in the one kind or
                    the other every follower of Christ will surely have need to ‘take up his cross
                    daily’.</p>
                <p n="11">11. The ‘taking up’ differs a little from ‘bearing his cross’. We are then
                    properly said to ‘bear our cross’ when we endure what is laid upon us without
                    our choice, with meekness and resignation. Whereas we do not properly ‘take up
                    our cross’ but when we voluntarily suffer what it is in our power to avoid; when
                    we willingly embrace the will of God, though contrary to our own; when we choose
                    what is painful because it is the will of our wise and gracious Creator.</p>
                <p n="12">12. And thus it behoves every disciple of Christ to ‘take up’ as well as
                    to ‘bear <hi rend="italic">his</hi> cross’. Indeed in one sense it is not <hi
                        rend="italic">his</hi> alone: it <pb n="02:245"/>is common to him and many
                    others, seeing ‘there is no temptation befalls any man’, εἰ μὴ ἀνθρώπινος, ‘but
                    such as is common to men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 10:13.</p></note> such as is incident
                    and adapted to their common nature and situation in the present world. But in
                    another sense, as it is considered with all its circumstances, it is <hi
                        rend="italic">his</hi>; peculiar to himself. It is prepared of God for him;
                    it is given by God to him, as a token of his love. And if he receives it as
                    such, and (after using such means to remove the pressure as Christian wisdom
                    directs) lies as clay in the potter’s hand,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                        n="24"><p rend="footnote text">See Jer. 18:6.</p></note> it is disposed and
                    ordered by God for his good, both with regard to the quality of it and in
                    respect to its quantity and degree, its duration, and every other
                    circumstance.</p>
                <p n="13">13. In all this we may easily conceive our blessed Lord to act as the
                    physician of our souls, not merely ‘for his own pleasure, but for our profit,
                    that we may be partakers of his holiness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:10.</p></note> If in searching
                    our wounds he puts us to pain, it is only in order to heal them. He cuts away
                    what is putrified or unsound in order to preserve the sound part. And if we
                    freely choose the loss of a limb, rather than the whole body should perish, how
                    much more should we choose, figuratively, to cut off a right hand, rather than
                    the whole soul should be cast into hell!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:30.</p></note></p>
                <p n="14">14. We see plainly, then, both the nature and ground of ‘taking up our
                    cross’. It does not imply the ‘disciplining ourselves’ (as some speak), the
                    literally tearing our own flesh: the wearing haircloth, or iron girdles, or
                    anything else that would impair our bodily health (although we know not what
                    allowance God may make for those who act thus through involuntary ignorance),
                    but the embracing the will of God, though contrary to our own; the choosing
                    wholesome, though bitter, medicines; the freely accepting temporary pain, of
                    whatever kind, and in whatever degree, when it is either essentially or
                    accidentally necessary to eternal pleasure.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. I am, secondly, to show that it is always owing to the want either
                    of self-denial or taking up his cross that any man does not throughly ‘follow
                    him’, is not fully a ‘disciple’ of Christ.</p>
                <p>It is true this may be partly owing, in some cases, to the want of the means of
                    grace; of hearing the true word of God spoken with power; of the sacraments; or
                    of Christian fellowship. But where <pb n="02:246"/>none of these is wanting, the
                    great hindrance of our receiving or growing in the grace of God<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet.
                            3:18.</p></note> is always the want of denying ourselves or taking up
                    our cross.</p>
                <p n="2">2. A few instances will make this plain. A man hears the word which is able
                    to save his soul. He is well pleased with what he hears, acknowledges the truth,
                    and is a little affected by it. Yet he remains ‘dead in trespasses and
                        sins’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            2:1.</p></note> senseless and unawakened. Why is this? Because he will
                    not part with his bosom sin,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See below, No. 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’,
                            §1, for Wesley’s quotation of George Herbert’s use of this phrase in
                            verse. Cf. also Nos. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>,
                            V.1; and 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.3.
                            For Wesley’s frequent usage of such phrases as ‘bosom sin’, ‘darling
                            sin’, ‘darling lust’, etc.; cf. No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, III.2
                            and n.</p></note> though he now knows it is an abomination to the Lord.
                    He came to hear, full of lust and unholy desires; and he will not part with
                    them. Therefore no deep impression is made upon him, but his foolish heart is
                    still hardened; that is, he is still senseless and unawakened, because he will
                    not ‘deny himself’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Suppose he begins to awake out of sleep, and his eyes are a little
                    opened, why are they so quickly closed again? Why does he again sink into the
                    sleep of death? Because he again yields to his bosom sin; he drinks again of the
                    pleasing poison. Therefore it is impossible that any lasting impression should
                    be made upon his heart; that is, he relapses into his fatal insensibility
                    because he will not ‘deny himself’.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But this is not the case with all. We have many instances of those who
                    when once awakened sleep no more. The impressions once received do not wear
                    away; they are not only deep, but lasting. And yet many of these have not found
                    what they seek; they mourn, and yet are not comforted. Now why is this? It is
                    because they do not ‘bring forth fruits meet for repentance’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:8.</p></note> because
                    they do not, according to the grace they have received, ‘cease from evil and do
                        good’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 1:16, 17.</p></note> They do not cease from the easily besetting
                        sin,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Heb. 12:1; and also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p></note> the sin of
                    their constitution, of their education, or of their profession. Or they omit
                    doing the good they may, and know they ought to do, because of some disagreeable
                    circumstance attending it; that is, they do not attain faith, because they will
                    not ‘deny themselves’, or ‘take up their cross’.</p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘But this man did receive “the heavenly gift”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 6:4.</p></note> He did
                    “taste <hi n="02:247"/> of the powers of the world to come”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:5.</p></note> He
                    saw “the light of the glory of God in the face of Jesus Christ”.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        4:6.</p></note> The “peace which passeth all understanding” did “rule his
                    heart and mind”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Phil. 4:7.</p></note> and the love of God was shed abroad<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                        5:5.</p></note> therein by the Holy Ghost which was given unto him. Yet he
                    is now weak as another man. He again relishes the things of earth, and has more
                    taste for the things which are seen than for those which are not seen.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            4:18.</p></note> The eye of his understanding<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:18.</p></note> is
                    closed again, so that he cannot “see him that is invisible”.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:27.</p></note> His
                    love is waxed cold, and the peace of God no longer rules in his heart.’ And no
                    marvel: for he has again given place to the devil, and grieved the Holy Spirit
                    of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            4:30.</p></note> He has turned again unto folly, to some pleasing sin,
                    if not in outward act, yet in heart. He has given place to pride, or anger, or
                    desire; to self-will, or stubbornness. Or he did not stir up the gift of God
                    which was in him;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 1:6.</p></note> he gave way to spiritual
                    sloth, and would not be at the pains of ‘praying always, and watching thereunto
                    with all perseverance’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:18.</p></note> that is, he made shipwreck of
                    the faith<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                            1:19.</p></note> for want of self-denial and ‘taking up his cross
                    daily’.</p>
                <p n="6">6. But perhaps he has not made shipwreck of the faith: he has still a
                    measure of the Spirit of adoption, which continues to witness with his spirit
                    that he is a child of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15-16.</p></note> However, he is not ‘going
                    on to perfection’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:1.</p></note> he is not, as once,
                    hungering and thirsting after righteousness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                        n="47"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:6.</p></note> panting after the
                    whole image and full enjoyment of God, as the hart after the water-brook.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                        42:1.</p></note> Rather he is weary and faint in his mind, and as it were
                    hovering between life and death. And why is he thus, but because he hath
                    forgotten the word of God, ‘By works is faith made perfect’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 2:22.</p></note> He
                    does not use all diligence in working the works of God. He does not ‘continue
                    instant in prayer’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:12.</p></note> private as well as public;
                    in communicating, hearing, meditation, fasting, and religious conference. If he
                    does not wholly neglect some of these means, at least he does not use them all,
                    with his might. Or he is not zealous of works of charity,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">See Titus 2:14.</p></note> as
                    well as works of piety. He is not merciful after his power, with the full
                    ability which God giveth. He does <pb n="02:248"/>not fervently serve the Lord
                    by doing good to men, in every kind and in every degree he can, to their souls
                    as well as their bodies. And why does he not continue in prayer? Because in
                    times of dryness it is pain and grief unto him. He does not continue in hearing
                    at all opportunities, because sleep is sweet; or it is cold, or dark, or rainy.
                    But why does he not continue in works of mercy?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                        n="52"><p rend="footnote text">For this pairing of <hi rend="italic"
                                >piety</hi> (here ‘prayer’) and <hi rend="italic">mercy</hi>, cf.
                            No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.13 and n.
                            65.</p></note> Because he cannot feed the hungry, or clothe the naked,
                    unless he retrench the expense of his own apparel, or use cheaper and less
                    pleasing food. Beside which the visiting the sick or those that are in prison is
                    attended with many disagreeable circumstances. And so are most works of
                    spiritual mercy—reproof, in particular. He <hi rend="italic">would</hi> reprove
                    his neighbour; but sometimes shame, sometimes fear, comes between. For he may
                    expose himself not only to ridicule but to heavier inconveniences too. Upon
                    these and the like considerations he omits one or more, if not all, works of
                    mercy and piety. Therefore his faith is not made perfect, neither can he grow in
                    grace; namely, because he will not ‘deny himself, and take up his daily
                    cross’.</p>
                <p n="7">7. It manifestly follows that it is always owing to the want either of
                    self-denial or taking up his cross that a man does not throughly follow his
                    Lord, that he is not fully a disciple of Christ. It is owing to this that he who
                    is dead in sin does not awake, though the trumpet be blown;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">See Amos 3:16; this is both
                            the text and theme of No. 143, ‘Public Diversions Denounced’.</p></note>
                    that he who begins to awake out of sleep yet has no deep or lasting conviction;
                    that he who is deeply and lastingly convinced of sin does not attain remission
                    of sins; that some who have received this heavenly gift retain it not, but make
                    shipwreck of the faith; and that others, if they do not draw back to perdition,
                    yet are weary and faint in their mind, and do not reach the mark of the prize of
                    the high calling of God in Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:14.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. How easily may we learn hence that they know neither the Scripture
                    nor the power of God who directly or indirectly, in public or in private, oppose
                    the doctrine of self-denial and the daily cross! How totally ignorant are these
                    men of an hundred particular texts, as well as of the general tenor of the whole
                    oracles of God! And how entirely unacquainted must they be with true, <pb
                        n="02:249"/>genuine, Christian experience! Of the manner wherein the Holy
                    Spirit ever did, and does at this day, work in the souls of men! They may talk
                    indeed very loudly and confidently (a natural fruit of ignorance), as though
                    they were the only men who understood either the Word of God, or the experience
                    of his children. But their words are, in every sense, ‘vain words’:<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Exod.
                        5:9.</p></note> they are weighed in the balance and found wanting.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Dan.
                        5:27.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. We may learn from hence, secondly, the real cause why not only many
                    particular persons, but even bodies of men, who were once burning and shining
                        lights,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            John 5:35.</p></note> have now lost both their light and heat. If they
                    did not hate and oppose, they at least lightly esteemed this precious gospel
                    doctrine. If they did not boldly say, <hi rend="italic">Abnegationem omnem
                        proculcamus, internecioni damus</hi> (‘We trample all self-denial under
                    foot, we devote it to destruction’),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text">An echo of the debate, in Latin, between Wesley and
                            Count von Zinzendorf in Gray’s Inn Walks, Sept. 3, 1741, reported in
                            Wesley’s version in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>. There,
                            Zinzendorf is quoted as saying, ‘<hi rend="italic">Abnegationem omnem
                                respuimus, conculcamus</hi>’ (lit. ‘we spew out all abnegations
                            [self-denials], we tread them under foot’). <hi rend="italic"
                                >Proculcamus</hi> is a synonym for <hi rend="italic"
                                >conculcamus</hi>, and this tends to confirm the impression that
                            Wesley reconstructed his reports from memory, then and here. The
                            addition of <hi rend="italic">internecioni damus</hi> is out of order;
                                <hi rend="italic">ad internecionem do</hi> is a fragment from an
                            earlier passage in the debate. For other references to Zinzendorf, see
                            No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, I.5 and
                        n.</p></note> yet they neither valued it according to its high importance,
                    nor took any pains in practising it. <hi rend="italic">Hanc mystici docent</hi>,
                    said that great, bad man—‘The mystic writers teach self-denial.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Apparently yet
                            another snatch from the dispute with Zinzendorf, along with a rare
                            instance of ungracious invective (‘that great, <hi rend="italic"
                                >bad</hi> man’!). It is yet another indication that Wesley’s rift
                            with the Moravians was still rankling, and a measure of how deep it
                            still went.</p></note> No; the inspired writers. And God teaches it to
                    every soul who is willing to hear his voice.</p>
                <p n="3">3. We may learn from hence, thirdly, that it is not enough for a minister
                    of the gospel not to oppose the doctrine of self-denial, to say nothing
                    concerning it. Nay, he cannot satisfy his duty by saying a little in favour of
                    it. If he would indeed be pure from the blood of all men he must speak of it
                    frequently and largely; he must inculcate the necessity of it in the clearest
                    and strongest manner; he must press it with his might on all persons, at all
                    times, and in all places; laying ‘line upon line, line upon line, precept upon
                    precept, precept upon precept’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 28:10, 13.</p></note> So shall he have a
                    conscience void of offence;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Acts 24:16.</p></note> so shall he save his own
                    soul and those that hear him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 1 Tim. 4:16.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4"><pb n="02:250"/>4. Lastly, see that you apply this, every one of you, to
                    your own soul. Meditate upon it when you are in secret; ponder it in your heart.
                    Take care not only to understand it throughly, but to remember it to your life’s
                    end. Cry unto the Strong for strength,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">A favourite phrase derived from Job 9:19; cf.
                            Nos. 72, ‘Of Evil Angels’, III.4; 78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, II.4; 80,
                            ‘On Friendship with the World’, §19; 93, ‘On Redeeming the Time’, III.2;
                            98, ‘On Visiting the Sick’, II.1. See also JWJ, May 26, 1752; and his
                            letters to Mrs. Bennis, Dec. 16, 1772, and to William Minethorp, Nov.
                            29, 1776.</p></note> that you may no sooner understand than enter upon
                    the practice of it. Delay not the time, but practise it immediately, from this
                    very hour. Practise it universally, on every one of the thousand occasions which
                    will occur in all circumstances of life. Practise it daily, without
                    intermission, from the hour you first set your hand to the plough; and
                    perseveringly enduring therein to the end, till your spirit returns to God.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
