<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 30: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse X</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 30: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse X</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="650" to="663"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:650"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Tenth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 7:1-12</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Judge not, that ye be not judged.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be judged; and with
                        what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you again.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And why beholdest thou the mote that is in thy brother’s eye,
                        but considerest not the beam that is in thine own eye?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Or how wilt thou say to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote
                        out of thine eye; and, behold, a beam is in thine own eye?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Thou hypocrite, first cast out the beam out of thine own eye;
                        and then thou shalt see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother’s
                        eye.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Give not that which is holy unto dogs, neither cast your
                        pearls before swine; lest they trample them under their feet, and turn again
                        and rend you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and ye shall find;
                        knock, and it shall be opened unto you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For everyone that asketh, receiveth; and he that seeketh,
                        findeth; and to him that knocketh, it shall be opened.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Or what man is there of you, who, if his son ask bread, will
                        give him a stone? Or if he ask a fish, will give him a serpent?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">If ye, then, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your
                        children, how much more shall your Father which is in heaven give good
                        things to them that ask him!</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Therefore all things whatsoever ye would that men should do to
                        you, do ye even so to them; for this is the law and the prophets.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <p n="1">1. Our blessed Lord, having now finished his main design, having, first,
                delivered the sum of true religion, carefully guarded against those glosses of men
                whereby they would make the Word of God of none effect; and having, next, laid down
                rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                actions, now proceeds to point out the main hindrances of this religion, and
                concludes all with a suitable application.</p>
            <p n="2"><pb n="01:651"/>2. In the fifth chapter our great Teacher has fully described
                inward religion in its various branches. He has there laid before us those
                dispositions of soul which constitute real Christianity; the tempers contained in
                that holiness ‘without which no man shall see the Lord’;<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:14.</p></note> the
                affections which, when flowing from their proper fountain, from a living faith in
                God through Christ Jesus, are intrinsically and essentially good, and acceptable to
                God. In the sixth he has shown how all our actions likewise, even those that are
                indifferent in their own nature, may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to God,
                by a pure and holy intention.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 26, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’, §1 and n., for
                        other comments on holy living understood as purity of intention.</p></note>
                Whatever is done without this he declares is of no value with God; whereas whatever
                outward works are thus consecrated to God are in his sight of great price.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the former part of this chapter he points out the most common and most
                fatal hindrances of this holiness. In the latter he exhorts us by various motives to
                break through all and secure that prize of our high calling.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:14.</p></note></p>
            <p n="4">4. The first hindrance he cautions us against is judging: ‘Judge not, that ye
                be not judged.’ Judge not others, that ye be not judged of the Lord, that ye bring
                not vengeance on your own heads. ‘For with what judgment ye judge, ye shall be
                judged; and with what measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you again’—a plain
                and equitable rule, whereby God permits you to determine for yourselves in what
                manner he shall deal with you in the judgment of the great day.</p>
            <p n="5">5. There is no station of life, nor any period of time, from the hour of our
                first repenting and believing the gospel till we are made perfect in love, wherein
                this caution is not needful for every child of God. For occasions of judging can
                never be wanting. And the temptations to it are innumerable; many whereof are so
                artfully disguised that we fall into the sin before we suspect any danger. And
                unspeakable are the mischiefs produced hereby: always to him that judges another,
                thus wounding his own soul, and exposing himself to the righteous judgment of God;
                and frequently to those who are judged, whose hands hang down, who are weakened and
                hindered in their course, if not wholly turned out of the way,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:13.</p></note> and
                caused to draw back even to perdition. Yea, <pb n="01:652"/>how often when this
                ‘root of bitterness springs up’, are ‘many defiled thereby’;<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:15.</p></note> by reason
                whereof the way of truth itself is evil spoken of,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6"
                    n="6"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 2:2.</p></note> and that worthy name
                blasphemed whereby we are called.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Yet it does not appear that our Lord designed this caution only or chiefly
                for the children of God; but rather for the children of the world, for the men who
                know not God. These cannot but hear of those who are not of the world; who follow
                after the religion above described; who endeavour to be humble, serious, gentle,
                merciful, and pure in heart; who earnestly desire such measures of these holy
                tempers as they have not yet attained, and wait for them in doing all good to all
                men, and patiently suffering evil. Whoever go but thus far cannot be hid, no more
                than ‘a city set upon a hill’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:14.</p></note> And why do not those who
                ‘see’ their ‘good works glorify their Father which is in heaven’?<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:16.</p></note> What
                excuse have they for not treading in their steps? For not imitating their example,
                and being followers of them, as they are also of Christ?<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 11:1.</p></note> Why, in
                order to provide an excuse for themselves, they condemn those whom they ought to
                imitate. They spend their time in finding out their neighbour’s faults,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. this condemnation
                        of fault-finding with No. 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our
                    Neighbour’.</p></note> instead of amending their own. They are so busied about
                others going out of the way, that themselves never come into it at all; at least,
                never get forward, never go beyond a poor dead form of godliness without the
                    power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">See 2
                        Tim. 3:5.</p></note></p>
            <p n="7">7. It is to these more especially that our Lord says, ‘Why beholdest thou the
                mote that is in thy brother’s eye’, the infirmities, the mistakes, the imprudence,
                the weakness of the children of God, ‘but considerest not the beam that is in thine
                own eye?’ Thou considerest not the damnable impenitence, the satanic pride, the
                accursed self-will, the idolatrous love of the world, which are in thyself, and
                which make thy whole life an abomination to the Lord. Above all, with what supine
                carelessness and indifference art thou dancing over the mouth of hell! And ‘how’,
                then, with what grace, with what decency or <pb n="01:653"/>modesty, ‘wilt thou say
                to thy brother, Let me pull out the mote out of thine eye’—the excess of zeal for
                God, the extreme of self-denial, the too great disengagement from worldly cares and
                employments, the desire to be day and night in prayer, or hearing the words of
                eternal life—‘And behold a beam is in thine own eye!’ Not a mote, like one of these.
                ‘Thou hypocrite!’ who pretendest to care for others, and hast no care for thy own
                soul; who makest a show of zeal for the cause of God, when in truth thou neither
                lovest nor fearest him! ‘First cast out the beam out of thine own eye.’ Cast out the
                beam of impenitence. Know thyself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.1 and
                    n.</p></note> See and feel thyself a sinner. Feel that thy inward parts are very
                    wickedness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                        5:9 (BCP).</p></note> that thou are altogether corrupt and abominable,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 53:4
                        (BCP).</p></note> and that the wrath of God abideth on thee.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">See John
                    3:36.</p></note> Cast out the beam of pride. Abhor thyself. Sink down as in dust
                and ashes. Be more and more little, and mean, and base, and vile in thine own eyes.
                Cast out the beam of self-will. Learn what that meaneth, ‘If any man will come after
                me, let him renounce himself.’ Deny thyself and take up thy cross daily.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                    9:23.</p></note> Let thy whole soul cry out, ‘I came down from heaven’ (for so
                thou didst, thou never-dying spirit, whether thou knowest it or no) ‘not to do my
                own will, but the will of him that sent me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">John 6:38. Note this identification of the
                        Christian with Christ; still another accent on ‘participation’.</p></note>
                Cast out the beam of love of the world. Love not the world, neither the things of
                the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                        John 2:15.</p></note> Be thou crucified unto the world, and the world
                crucified unto thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Gal. 6:14.</p></note> Only <hi rend="italic">use</hi> the world, but
                    <hi rend="italic">enjoy</hi> God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Pascal, <hi rend="italic">Pensées</hi>, ed. H. F.
                        Stewart (London, Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1950), pp. 304-5 (French text
                        with Eng. tr.). In the Modern Library and Everyman’s Library edits., cf.
                        Pensée 570. The translation Wesley knew, of course, was that of Basil
                        Kennet, <hi rend="italic">Thoughts on Religion</hi>; cf. 2nd edn., 1727, p.
                        79: ‘For there are two principles which divide the wills of men,
                        covetousness and charity. It is not indeed impossible that covetousness
                        should subsist with faith, or charity with temporal possession. But here’s
                        the difference: the former imploys itself in using God and enjoying the
                        world; the latter in using the world and enjoying God’. Cf. also, St.
                        Augustine, <hi rend="italic">De doctrina Christiana</hi>, I.3.3-35. 39; <hi
                            rend="italic">De diversis quaestionibus</hi>, LXXXIII.30; <hi
                            rend="italic">De civ. Dei</hi>, 15:7; and <hi rend="italic">De
                            Octoginta-tribus Quaestionibus</hi>, XXX. See also St. Francis de Sales,
                            <hi rend="italic">Devout Life</hi>, III. xxxix. See also Nos. 108, ‘On
                        Riches’, II.12; and 142, ‘The Wisdom of Winning Souls’, II.7, and Wesley’s
                        letter to Mrs. Pendarves, Feb. 11, 1731, where he attributes the aphorism to
                        Pascal.</p></note> Seek all thy happiness in him. <pb n="01:654"/>Above all
                cast out the grand beam, that supine carelessness and indifference. Deeply consider
                that ‘one thing is needful’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Luke 10:42.</p></note> the one thing which thou hast
                scarce ever thought of. Know and feel that thou art a poor, vile, guilty worm,
                quivering over the great gulf! What art thou? A sinner born to die; a leaf driven
                before the wind; a vapour ready to vanish away, just appearing, and then scattered
                into air, to be no more seen!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Luke 16:26, and Wesley’s Pref., §5: ‘I am a spirit
                        come from God and returning to God; just hovering over the great gulf, till
                        a few moments hence, I am no more seen.’ See also Wisd. 5:9-14.</p></note>
                See this. ‘And then shalt thou see clearly to cast out the mote out of thy brother’s
                eye.’ Then, if thou hast leisure from the concerns of thy own soul, thou shalt know
                how to correct thy brother also.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But what is properly the meaning of this word, ‘judge not’? What is the <hi
                    rend="italic">judging</hi> which is here forbidden? It is not the same as
                evil-speaking, although it is frequently joined therewith. Evil-speaking is the
                relating anything that is evil concerning an absent person; whereas judging may
                indifferently refer either to the absent or the present. Neither does it necessarily
                imply the speaking at all, but only the <hi rend="italic">thinking evil</hi> of
                another. Not that all kind of thinking evil of others is that judging which our Lord
                condemns. If I see one commit robbery or murder, or hear him blaspheme the name of
                God, I cannot refrain from thinking ill of the robber or murderer. Yet this is not
                evil judging: there is no sin in this, nor anything contrary to tender
                affection.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The thinking of another in a manner that is contrary to love is that judging
                which is here condemned; and this may be of various kinds. For, first, we may think
                another to blame when he is not. We may lay to his charge (at least in our own mind)
                the things of which he is not guilty—the words which he has never spoke, or the
                actions which he has never done. Or we may think his <hi rend="italic">manner</hi>
                of acting was wrong, although in reality it was not. And even where nothing can
                justly be blamed, either in the thing itself or in the manner of doing it, we may
                suppose his <hi rend="italic">intention</hi> was not good, and so condemn him on
                that ground, at the same time that he who searches the heart sees his simplicity and
                godly sincerity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">2
                        Cor. 1:12. Cf. Nos. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.9 and
                        n.; and 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §11 and n.</p></note></p>
            <p n="10">10. But we may not only fall into the sin of judging by condemning the
                innocent, but also, secondly, by condemning the guilty in a higher degree than he
                deserves. This species of judging <pb n="01:655"/>is likewise an offence against
                justice as well as mercy; and yet such an offence as nothing can secure us from but
                the strongest and tenderest affection. Without this we readily suppose one who is
                acknowledged to be in fault to be more in fault than he really is. We undervalue
                whatever good is found in him. Nay, we are not easily induced to believe that
                anything good can remain in him in whom we have found anything that is evil.</p>
            <p n="11">11. All this shows a manifest want of that love which οὐ λογίζεται κακόν,
                ‘thinketh no evil’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >1 Cor. 13:5; see above, No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, III.11 and
                        n.</p></note> which never draws an unjust or unkind conclusion from any
                premises whatsoever. Love will not infer from a person’s falling once into an act of
                open sin that he is accustomed so to do, that he is habitually guilty of it. And if
                he was habitually guilty once, love does not conclude he is so still; much less that
                if he is now guilty of this, therefore he is guilty of other sins also. These evil
                reasonings all pertain to that sinful judging which our Lord here guards us against;
                and which we are in the highest degree concerned to avoid if we love either God or
                our own souls.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        this generous spirit of reserved judgment with Wesley’s harsh judgments
                        heaped upon Oxford in Nos. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>,
                        and 150, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’; see also Charles Wesley’s critique of Oxford
                        in No. 3, ‘<hi rend="italic">Awake, Thou That Steepest</hi>.’</p></note></p>
            <p n="12">12. But supposing we do not condemn the innocent, neither the guilty any
                farther than they deserve; still we may not be altogether clear of the snare; for
                there is a third sort of sinful judging, which is the condemning any person at all
                where there is not sufficient evidence. And be the facts we suppose ever so true;
                yet that does not acquit us. For they ought not to have been supposed, but proved;
                and till they were we ought to have formed no judgment. I say, till they were; for
                neither are we excused; although the facts admit of ever so strong proof, unless
                that proof be produced before we pass sentence, and compared with the evidence on
                the other side. Nor can we be excused if ever we pass a full sentence before the
                accused has spoken for himself. Even a Jew might teach us this, as a mere lesson of
                justice abstracted from mercy and brotherly love. ‘Doth our law’, says Nicodemus,
                ‘judge any man before it hear him, and know what he doth?’<hi
                    rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">John
                        7:51.</p></note></hi> Yea, a heathen could reply, when the chief of the
                Jewish nation desired to have judgment against his prisoner, ‘It is not the manner
                of the <pb n="01:656"/>Romans’ to judge ‘any man before he that is accused have the
                accusers face to face, and have licence to answer for himself concerning the crime
                laid against him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Acts 25:16. Cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>: ‘How excellent a
                        rule, to condemn no one unheard! A rule which, as it is common to all
                        nations (courts of inquisition only excepted), so it ought to direct our
                        proceedings in all affairs, not only in public but private
                life.’</p></note></p>
            <p n="13">13. Indeed we could not easily fall into sinful judging were we only to
                observe that rule which another of those heathen Romans affirms to have been the
                measure of his own practice. ‘I am so far’, says he, ‘from lightly believing every
                man’s or any man’s evidence against another, that I do not easily or immediately
                believe a man’s evidence against himself. I always allow him second thoughts, and
                many times counsel too.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text">Seneca [so identified by Wesley in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Works</hi>, II.344; cf. No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, III.6
                            and n.].</p></note></hi> Go, thou who art called a Christian, and do
                likewise, lest the heathen rise and condemn thee in that day.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 12:41-42.</p></note></p>
            <p n="14">14. But how rarely should we condemn or judge one another, at least how soon
                would that evil be remedied, were we to walk by that clear and express rule which
                our Lord himself has taught us! ‘If thy brother shall trespass against thee’ (or if
                thou hear, or believe that he hath) ‘go and tell him of his fault, between him and
                thee alone.’ This is the first step thou art to take. ‘But if he will not hear, take
                with thee one or two more, that in the mouth of two or three witnesses every word
                may be established.’ This is the second step. ‘If he neglect to hear them, tell it
                unto the church;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Matt. 18:15-17.</p></note> either to the overseers thereof, or to the whole
                congregation. Thou hast then done thy part. Then think of it no more, but commend
                the whole to God.</p>
            <p n="15">15. But supposing thou hast, by the grace of God, ‘cast the beam out of thine
                own eye’, and dost now ‘clearly see the mote or the beam which is in thy brother’s
                eye’; yet beware thou dost not receive hurt thyself by endeavouring to help him.
                Still ‘give not that which is holy unto dogs.’ Do not lightly account any to be of
                this number. But if it evidently appear that they deserve the title, then cast ye
                not ‘your pearls before swine’. Beware of that zeal which is not according to
                    knowledge;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Rom. 10:2.</p></note> for this is another great hindrance in their way who
                would be ‘perfect as their heavenly Father is perfect’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:48.</p></note> They
                who desire this cannot but desire that all <pb n="01:657"/>mankind should partake of
                the common blessing. And when we ourselves first partake of the heavenly gift, the
                divine ‘evidence of things not seen’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:1.</p></note> we wonder that all mankind do not
                see the things which we see so plainly; and make no doubt at all but we shall open
                the eyes of all we have any intercourse with. Hence we are for attacking all we meet
                without delay, and constraining them to see, whether they will or no. And by the ill
                success of this intemperate zeal, we often suffer in our own souls. To prevent this
                spending our strength in vain our Lord adds this needful caution (needful to all,
                but more especially to those who are now warm in their first love), ‘Give not that
                which is holy unto the dogs, neither cast ye your pearls before swine; lest they
                trample them under foot, and turn again and rend you.’</p>
            <p n="16">16. ‘Give not that which is holy unto the dogs.’ Beware of thinking that any
                deserve this appellation till there is full and incontestable proof, such as you can
                no longer resist. But when it is clearly and indisputably proved that they are
                unholy and wicked men, not only strangers to, but enemies to God, to all
                righteousness and true holiness;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:24.</p></note> ‘give not that which is holy’, τὸ
                ἅγιον, the holy thing, emphatically so called, unto these. The holy, the peculiar
                doctrines of the gospel, such as were ‘hid from the ages and generations’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col.
                    1:26.</p></note> of old, and are now made known to us only by the revelation of
                Jesus Christ and the inspiration of his Holy Spirit, are not to be prostituted unto
                these men who know not if there be any Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34"
                    n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 19:2.</p></note> Not indeed that the
                ambassadors of Christ can refrain from declaring them in the great congregation,
                wherein some of these may probably be. We must speak, whether men will hear or
                whether they will forbear.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Ezek. 2:5,7; 3:11. Note the distinction here between
                        doctrinal preaching to large and mixed audiences and doctrinal teaching for
                        individuals and small groups.</p></note> But this is not the case with
                private Christians. They do not bear that awful character; nor are they under any
                manner of obligation to force these great and glorious truths on them who contradict
                and blaspheme, who have a rooted enmity against them. Nay, they ought not so to do,
                but rather to lead them as they are able to bear. Do not begin a discourse with
                these upon remission of sins and the gift of the Holy Ghost; but talk with them in
                their own manner, and upon their own principles. With the rational, honourable,
                unjust Epicure, ‘reason of righteousness, temperance, <pb n="01:658"/>and judgment
                to come’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                        24:25. Cf. Wesley’s own attempt at a similar sardonic discourse in <hi
                            rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, 11:45-94, of this edn.</p></note>
                This is the most probable way to make ‘Felix tremble’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 24:25.</p></note> Reserve
                higher subjects for men of higher attainments.</p>
            <p n="17">17. ‘Neither cast ye your pearls before swine.’ Be very unwilling to pass this
                judgment on any man. But if the fact be plain and undeniable, if it is clear beyond
                all dispute, if the swine do not endeavour to disguise themselves, but rather glory
                in their shame, making no pretence to purity either of heart or life, but working
                all uncleanness with greediness;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:19.</p></note> then ‘cast’ not ‘ye your
                pearls before’ them. Talk not to them of the mysteries of the kingdom; of the things
                which ‘eye hath not seen, nor ear heard’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                        rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:9.</p></note> which of consequence, as they
                have no other inlets of knowledge, no spiritual senses, it cannot enter into their
                hearts to conceive. Tell not them of the ‘exceeding great and precious
                    promises’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">2 Pet.
                        1:4.</p></note> which God hath given us in the Son of his love. What
                conception can they have of being made ‘partakers of the divine nature’ who do not
                even desire to ‘escape the corruption that is in the world through lust’?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic"
                            >Ibid.</hi></p></note> Just as much knowledge as swine have of pearls,
                and as much relish as they have for them, so much relish have they for the deep
                things of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        Cor. 2:10.</p></note> so much knowledge of the mysteries of the gospel, who
                are immersed in the mire of this world, in worldly pleasures, desires, and cares. ‘O
                cast not’ those ‘pearls before’ these, ‘lest they trample them under their feet’,
                lest they utterly despise what they cannot understand, and speak evil of the things
                which they know not. Nay, ’tis probable this would not be the only
                    inconvenience<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >For ‘inconvenience’ as <hi rend="italic">serious</hi> trouble, cf. <hi
                            rend="italic">OED</hi>, 3<hi rend="italic">b</hi>. In Johnson’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> it had come to be a synonym for
                        ‘disadvantageous’. Note Wesley’s usage here in the older
                    tradition.</p></note> which would follow. It would not be strange if they were,
                according to their nature, to ‘turn again, and rend you’; if they were to return you
                evil for good, cursing for blessing, and hatred for your goodwill. Such is the
                enmity of the carnal mind against God<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:7.</p></note> and all the things of God.
                Such the treatment you are to expect from these, if you offer them the unpardonable
                affront of endeavouring to save their souls from death,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">See Jas. 5:20.</p></note> to pluck
                them as brands out of the burning!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Amos 4:11; Zech. 3:2. Cf. No. 4, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.2 and n.</p></note></p>
            <p n="18"><pb n="01:659"/>18. And yet you need not utterly despair even of these, who
                for the present ‘turn again and rend you’. For if all your arguments and persuasives
                fail, there is yet another remedy left; and one that is frequently found effectual
                when no other method avails. This is prayer. Therefore whatever you desire or want,
                either for others or for your own soul, ‘Ask, and it shall be given you; seek, and
                ye shall find; knock, and it shall be opened unto you.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 7:7.</p></note> The neglect
                of this is a third grand hindrance of holiness. Still we ‘have not, because we ask
                    not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas.
                        4:2.</p></note> O how meek and gentle, how lowly in heart, how full of love
                both to God and man, might ye have been at this day, if you had only asked! If you
                had ‘continued instant in prayer’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:12.</p></note> Therefore now, at least,
                ‘Ask, and it shall be given unto you.’ ‘Ask’, that ye may throughly experience and
                perfectly practise the whole of that religion which our Lord has here so beautifully
                described. ‘It shall’ then ‘be given you’ to be holy as he is holy, both in heart
                and in all manner of conversation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 1:15.</p></note> ‘Seek’, in the way he hath
                ordained, in searching the Scriptures, in hearing his Word, in meditating thereon,
                in fasting, in partaking of the Supper of the Lord, and surely ‘ye shall find.’ Ye
                shall find that pearl of great price,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 13:46.</p></note> that faith which overcometh the
                    world,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                        John 5:4.</p></note> that peace which the world cannot give,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">See John
                    14:27.</p></note> that love which is the earnest of your inheritance.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:14.</p></note>
                ‘Knock’: continue in prayer, and in every other way of the Lord. Be not weary or
                faint in your mind. Press on to the mark.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:14.</p></note> Take no denial. Let him not go
                until he bless you.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Gen. 32:26.</p></note> And the door of mercy, of holiness, of heaven
                ‘shall be opened unto you’.</p>
            <p n="19">19. It is in compassion to the hardness of our hearts, so unready to believe
                the goodness of God, that our Lord is pleased to enlarge upon this head, and to
                repeat and confirm what he hath spoken. ‘For everyone’, saith he, ‘that asketh,
                receiveth;’ so that none need come short of the blessing; ‘and he that seeketh’,
                even everyone that seeketh, ‘findeth’ the love and the image of God; ‘and to him
                that knocketh’, to everyone that knocketh, the gate of righteousness shall be
                    opened.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                        118:19.</p></note> So that here is no room for any to be discouraged, as
                though they might ask or seek or knock in vain. Only remember ‘always to pray’, to
                seek, to knock, ‘and not to <pb n="01:660"/>faint’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58"
                    n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 18:1. Orig., ‘and not to be faint’,
                        altered only by Wesley in his personal copy of the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Works</hi>, II.350.</p></note> And then the promise standeth sure. It
                is firm as the pillars of heaven. Yea, more firm; for heaven and earth shall pass
                away; but his word shall not pass away.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Matt. 24:35.</p></note></p>
            <p n="20">20. To cut off every pretence for unbelief, our blessed Lord in the following
                verses illustrates yet farther what he had said, by an appeal to what passes in our
                own breasts. ‘What man’, saith he, ‘is there of you, who, if his son ask bread, will
                give him a stone?’ Will even natural affection permit you to refuse the reasonable
                request of one you love? Or if he ask a fish, will he give him a serpent?’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                    7:10.</p></note> Will he give him hurtful instead of profitable things? So that
                even from what you feel and do yourselves you may receive the fullest assurance, as
                on the one hand that no ill effect can possibly attend your asking, so on the other
                that it will be attended with that good effect, a full supply of all your wants. For
                ‘if ye, being evil, know how to give good gifts unto your children, how much more
                shall your Father which is in heaven’, who is pure, unmixed, essential goodness,
                ‘give good things to them that ask him!’ Or (as he expresses it on another occasion)
                ‘give the Holy Ghost to them that ask him!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">Luke 11:13.</p></note> In him are included all good
                things; all wisdom, peace, joy, love; the whole treasures of holiness and happiness;
                all that God hath prepared for them that love him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62"
                    n="62"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:9.</p></note></p>
            <p n="21">21. But that your prayer may have its full weight with God, see that ye be in
                charity with all men; for otherwise it is more likely to bring a curse than a
                blessing on your own head; nor can you expect to receive any blessing from God while
                you have not charity towards your neighbour. Therefore let this hindrance be removed
                without delay. Confirm your love towards one another and towards all men. And love
                them, not in word only, but in deed and in truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                    n="63"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:18.</p></note> ‘Therefore all things
                whatsoever ye would that men should do to you, do ye even so unto them; for this is
                the law and the prophets.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 7:12.</p></note></p>
            <p n="22">22. This is that royal law, that golden rule of mercy as well as justice,
                which even the heathen emperor<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Echard, <hi rend="italic">Eccles. Hist.</hi>,
                        III.iv. (‘222 A.D.’), p. 389: ‘Though Alexander [Severus—222-35] did not
                        believe in Jesus Christ as a Saviour, yet he reverenced him as a Law-giver,
                        whose institutions excelled all those of the Gentile Philosophers. That
                        command, on which all the Law and the Prophets depend, do not that to
                        another, which you would not have another do to you, he was so fond of, that
                        when he punished any man for acts of injustice, the Crier was commanded
                        publicly to announce it in the Court; and that it might be more regarded, he
                        ordered it to be inscribed upon his palace, his courts of judicature, and
                        his public works and buildings.’ See also, below, §24; and Nos. 2, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.5 and n.; and 150, ‘Hypocrisy
                        in Oxford’, I.10.</p></note> caused to be written <pb n="01:661"/>over the
                gate of his palace: a rule which many believe to be naturally engraved on the mind
                of everyone that comes into the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. John 1:9.</p></note> And thus much is certain, that
                it commends itself, as soon as heard, to every man’s conscience and understanding;
                insomuch that no man can knowingly offend against it without carrying his
                condemnation in his own breast.</p>
            <p n="23">23. ‘This is the law and the prophets.’ Whatsoever is written in that law
                which God of old revealed to mankind, and whatsoever precepts God has given by ‘his
                holy prophets which have been since the world began’,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 1:70.</p></note> they are all
                summed up in these few words, they are all contained in this short direction. And
                this, rightly understood, comprises the whole of that religion which our Lord came
                to establish upon earth.</p>
            <p n="24">24. It may be understood either in a positive or negative sense. If understood
                in a negative sense the meaning is, ‘Whatever ye would not that men should do to
                you, do not ye unto them.’ Here is a plain rule, always ready at hand, always easy
                to be applied. In all cases relating to your neighbour, make his case your own.
                Suppose the circumstances to be changed, and yourself to be just as he is now. And
                then beware that you indulge no temper or thought, that no word pass out of your
                lips, that you take no step which you should have condemned in him, upon such a
                change of circumstances. If understood in a direct and positive sense, the plain
                meaning of it is, ‘Whatsoever you could reasonably desire of him, supposing yourself
                to be in his circumstance, that do, to the uttermost of your power, to every child
                of man.’</p>
            <p n="25">25. To apply this in one or two obvious instances. It is clear to every man’s
                own conscience, we would not that others should <hi rend="italic">judge</hi> us,
                should causelessly or lightly think evil of us; much less would we that any should
                speak evil of us, should publish our real faults or infirmities. Apply this to
                yourself. Do not unto another what you would not he should do unto you; and you will
                never more judge your neighbour, never causelessly or lightly think evil of anyone;
                much less will you speak evil. You will never mention even the real fault of an
                absent person, unless so far as you are convinced it is absolutely needful for the
                good of other souls.</p>
            <p n="26"><pb n="01:662"/>26. Again: we would that all men should love and esteem us,
                and behave towards us according to justice, mercy, and truth. And we may reasonably
                desire that they should do us all the good they can do without injuring themselves;
                yea, that in outward things (according to the known rule) their superfluities should
                give way to our conveniencies, their conveniencies to our necessities, and their
                necessities to our extremities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. South, <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1823),
                        I.282-83: ‘God does not accept the willingness of the mind instead of the
                        liberality of the purse [when it is affluent]. No, assuredly, for the
                        measures that God marks out to thy charity are these: thy superfluities must
                        give place to thy neighbour’s great convenience; thy convenience must vail
                        to thy neighbour’s necessity; and lastly, thy very necessities must yield to
                        thy neighbour’s extremity…. This is the gradual process that must be thy
                        rule…’. Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> quotes this as an
                        example under the word ‘vail’ understood in the sense, ‘to yield’. Cf. also
                        No. 98, ‘On Visiting the Sick’, III.4, where Wesley again quotes ‘this
                        excellent rule’. This pairing of ‘conveniences and necessaries of life’
                        shows up in Nos. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §11; 68, ‘The Wisdom of
                        God’s Counsels’, §16; 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’, I.3, II.3; 108, ‘On
                        Riches’, §4; 111, <hi rend="italic">National Sins and Miseries</hi>, I,1;
                        113, <hi rend="italic">The Late Work of God in North America</hi>, II.7;
                        133, ‘Death and Deliverance’ ¶9 (for the ‘necessaries of life’); 134, ‘Seek
                        First the Kingdom’, ¶¶5, 12, 15. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">Address to the
                            Clergy</hi>, II.3(1), <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 215 (Vol. 14
                        of this edn.); and <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §93 (11:86 of
                        this edn.). It is a commonplace phrase in <hi rend="italic">The
                            Guardian</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>; see also Francis
                        Atterbury, <hi rend="italic">Fourteen Sermons</hi> (1708), p. 303; and John
                        Locke, <hi rend="italic">Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi>, Bk. 2,
                        ch. 23, §12.</p></note> Now then, let us walk by the same rule: let us do
                unto all as we would they should do to us. Let us love and honour all men. Let
                justice, mercy, and truth govern all our minds and actions. Let our superfluities
                give way to our neighbour’s conveniencies (and who then will have any superfluities
                left?); our conveniencies to our neighbour’s necessities; our necessities to his
                    extremities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">For
                        Wesley’s views on surplus accumulation, cf. Nos. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                        VIII’, §9 and n.; and 50, ‘The Use of Money’, intro., espec. I.8-9 and
                        III.1.</p></note></p>
            <p n="27">27. This is pure and genuine morality. This do, and thou shalt live.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                    10:28.</p></note> ‘As many as walk by this rule, peace be to them, and mercy;’
                for they are ‘the Israel of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:16.</p></note> But then be it observed, none
                can walk by this rule (nor ever did from the beginning of the world), none can love
                his neighbour as himself, unless he first love God. And none can love God unless he
                believe in Christ, unless he have redemption through his blood,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:7; Col. 1:14.</p></note>
                and the Spirit of God bearing witness with his spirit that he is a child of
                    God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                        8:16.</p></note> Faith therefore is still the root of all, of present as
                well as future salvation. Still we must say to every sinner, Believe in the Lord <pb
                    n="663"/>Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be saved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74"
                    n="74"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 16:31.</p></note> Thou shalt be saved now,
                that thou mayst be saved for ever; saved on earth, that thou mayst be saved in
                heaven. Believe in him, and thy faith will work by love.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 5:6.</p></note> Thou wilt
                love the Lord thy God because he hath loved thee; thou wilt love thy neighbour as
                thyself. And then it will be thy glory and joy to exert and increase this love, not
                barely by abstaining from what is contrary thereto—from every unkind thought, word,
                and action—but by showing all that kindness to every man which thou wouldst he
                should show unto thee.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
