<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 17: The Circumcision of the Heart</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon017</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 17: The Circumcision of the Heart</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="398" to="414"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="398"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>This is a landmark sermon in more ways than one. First, it is the earliest of
                    Wesley’s sermons in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> and carefully placed at the
                    beginning of his second volume (1748) as an updated version of a sermon written
                    fifteen years earlier for delivery in St. Mary’s, Oxford, on January 1, 1733.
                    Second, it is one of Wesley’s most careful and complete statements of his
                    doctrine of holiness, and he continued to regard it as such thereafter. In a
                    later summary statement of his theological development to John Newton (May 14,
                    1765) he would write: ‘Jan. 1, 1733, I preached the sermon on “The Circumcision
                    of the Heart”, which contains all that I now teach concerning salvation from all
                    sin, and loving God with an undivided heart.’ Still later, (JWJ, September 1,
                    1778), he would recall: ‘I know not that I can write a better [sermon] on “The
                    Circumcision of the Heart” than I did five and forty years ago. Perhaps, indeed,
                    I may have read five or six hundred books more than I had then, and may know a
                    little more history or natural philosophy than I did. But I am not sensible that
                    this has made any essential addition to my knowledge of divinity. Forty years
                    ago [i.e., 1738] I knew and preached every Christian doctrine which I preach
                    now.’ Third, it supports the thesis that the basic elements of Wesley’s
                    soteriology (with the exception of the Moravian emphases on ‘faith <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>’ and on ‘<hi rend="italic">assurance</hi>’) were
                    already in place long before his Aldersgate experience. Original sin is there
                    (though more as a disease than an obliterated <hi rend="italic">imago Dei</hi>)
                    and so also is the <hi rend="italic">non posse non peccare</hi> (I.3: ‘without
                    the Spirit of God we can do nothing but add sin to sin’). Christ’s atonement is
                    affirmed as the sole ground of our redemption, and in I.7, he can add (in 1748)
                    a personal confession in the language of his Aldersgate experience without
                    disturbing the rhetoric or sense in any noticeable way: ‘I have an advocate with
                    the Father…Jesus Christ the righteous is <hi rend="italic">my</hi> Lord and the
                    propitiation for <hi rend="italic">my</hi> sins. I know…he hath reconciled <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, even <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, to God; and I have
                    redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins.’ The theme of the
                    Christian’s participation in God is lovingly spelled out as the essence of
                    Christian existence: ‘the being joined to the Lord in one Spirit. One design…to
                    pursue to the end of time: the enjoyment of God in time and <pb n="399"/>eternity.’ The <hi rend="italic">means</hi> to this single end are also
                    delineated—not faith <hi rend="italic">alone</hi>, but humility (i.e.,
                    repentance), faith, hope, <hi rend="italic">and</hi> love. Fourth, it helped to
                    establish Wesley as a man of mark in the university. How else could one explain
                    those <hi rend="italic">six</hi> university sermons in the next two-and-one-half
                    years (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, out of proportion to the regular rotations;
                    see above, Intro. to Sermon I, pp. 109-11 above).</p>
                <p n="">Wesley’s diary entries show that he began to plan this sermon in late
                    November and began to write it on December 8. The project was then complicated
                    by the appearance of a derogatory letter in <hi rend="italic">Fog’s Weekly
                        Journal</hi>, Saturday, December 9, about ‘this Sect called Methodists’, on
                    the various grounds of their ‘absurd and perpetual melancholy’, their ‘very near
                    affinity to the Essenes among the Jews and the pietists among the Christians in
                    Switzerland [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]’, their ‘proposition that no action
                    whatever is indifferent [which] is the chief hinge on which their whole scheme
                    of religion turns’, and their ‘hypocrisy’, since ‘’tis certain that their
                    Founder took formerly no small liberty in indulging his appetites…’. The obvious
                    effect of any such defamation was the arousal of still more popular curiousity
                    about the Methodists and their founder, and this assured him of a larger or more
                    attentive audience than he might have expected otherwise. But it also made the
                    occasion more crucial for Wesley’s career as a theologian, and this helps to
                    explain the uncommon carefulness of his preparations. He spent close to thirty
                    hours during the following fortnight writing a first draft; he then added as
                    much more time in consultations with others about its further refinement: his
                    brother Charles, his friend Hudson Martin, Euseby Isham (Rector of Lincoln), Dr.
                    Joseph Smith (of Queen’s), Jonathan Colley (chaplain of Christ Church), and
                    Emmanuel Langford (also of Christ Church).</p>
                <p n="">Finally, on Monday, January 1, he mounted St. Mary’s pulpit to expound what
                    would thenceforth become his most distinctive doctrine: Christian perfection
                    understood as perfect love of God and neighbour, rooted in a radical faith in
                    Christ’s revelation of that love and its power. His text was suggested by the
                    occasion, the Feast of the Circumcision of Christ, and its Collect: ‘…Grant us
                    the true circumcision of the spirit that, our hearts and all our members being
                    mortified from all worldly and carnal lusts, we may in all things obey thy
                    blessed will….’ Afterwards, he records his post-sermon mood as ‘chearfull’ and
                    notes that the sermon had ‘found favour with the Rector [Isham] and the
                    Vice-Chancellor’ (William Holmes of St. John’s). He seems not to have realized
                    that Thomas Cockman, a prominent Latinist in the university, famed as the editor
                    and translator of Cicero’s <hi rend="italic">De Officiis (On Moral
                        Obligations)</hi>, 1699, had already preached two sermons before the <pb n="400"/>university, January 2 and 6, 1731, on <hi rend="italic">Salvation
                        by Jesus Christ Alone…</hi>, both thoroughly Christocentric and both
                    remarkably like ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’ on many basic points. The
                    diaries show that Wesley had been out of town on the 2nd and had failed to
                    attend the university service on the 6th. But Cockman’s sermons make clear that
                    there was more evangelical teaching in Oxford than one would surmise from
                    Wesley’s later descriptions of the place. There were those, however, who were
                    unimpressed. A contemporary, Thomas Wilson, Jun. (1703-84), son of the famed
                    Bishop of Sodor and Man, spoke for many in his curt evaluation of this sermon as
                    ‘enthusiastic’; see <hi rend="italic">The Diaries of Thomas Wilson, D.D.;
                        1731-37 and 1750</hi>, ed. C. L. S. Linnell (London, SPCK, 1964), p. 87.</p>
                <p n="">‘The Circumcision of the Heart’ may profitably be paired with ‘Justification
                    by Faith’ as two halves of the same ‘gospel’, and as twin foundation stones in
                    Wesley’s theology as a whole. Moreover, Wesley’s deliberate placement of the
                    two, out of chronological order but with a clear eye to his reader’s interest in
                    the right order of Christian experience and life, is very much worth
                    pondering.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="401"/>
            <head>The Circumcision of the Heart</head>
            <head type="subhead">A Sermon preached at St. Mary’s, Oxford,<lb/>before the
                University,<lb/>on January 1, 1733.</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 2:29</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit and not in the
                        letter.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. ’Tis the melancholy remark of an excellent man that ‘he who now preaches
                    the most essential duties of Christianity runs the hazard of being esteemed by a
                    great part of his hearers “a setter forth of new doctrines”.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 17:18-19. The
                            ‘excellent man’ is probably William Law, whose recent <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi> would have been widely familiar in Oxford: ‘And
                            if in these days we want examples of these several degrees of
                            perfection, if neither clergy nor laity are enough of this spirit; if we
                            are so far departed from it that a man seems, like St. Paul at Athens,
                                <hi rend="italic">a setter forth of strange doctrines</hi> when he
                            recommends self-denial, renunciation of the world, regular devotion,
                            retirement, virginity, and voluntary poverty [the gist of Law’s ethical
                            agenda], it is because we are fallen into an age where the love, not of
                            many but of most, is waxed cold’ (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            IV.80).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For further comments of this sort by
                            Wesley himself, see Nos. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, §1; and 150,
                            ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’, I.1; JWJ, May 28, 1738; and ‘A Short History of
                            the People Called Methodists’, §11.</p>
                    </note> Most men have so <hi rend="italic">lived away</hi> the substance of that religion, the profession
                    whereof they still retain, that no sooner are any of those truths proposed which
                    difference the Spirit of Christ from the spirit of the world than they cry out,
                    ‘Thou bringest strange things to our ears; we would know what these things
                        mean’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                            17:20.</p>
                    </note>—though he is only preaching to them ‘Jesus, and the
                        resurrection’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 17:18.</p>
                    </note> with the necessary consequence of it. If Christ
                    be risen, ye ought then to die unto the world, and to live wholly unto God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. A hard saying this to the ‘natural man’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of
                            Adoption’, §5 and n.</p>
                    </note> who is alive unto the world, and dead
                    unto God, and one that he will not readily be persuaded to receive as the truth
                    of God, unless it be so qualified <pb n="402"/>in the interpretation as to have
                    neither use nor significancy left. He ‘receiveth not the’ words ‘of the Spirit
                    of God’, taken in their plain and obvious meaning. ‘They are foolishness unto
                    him; neither’ indeed ‘can he know them, because they are spiritually
                        discerned:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 2:14.</p>
                    </note> they are perceivable only by that spiritual sense
                    which in him was never yet awakened, for want of which he must reject as idle
                    fancies of men what are both the ‘wisdom’ and the ‘power of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        1:24.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. That ‘circumcision is that of the heart, in the spirit, and not in the
                    letter’, that the distinguishing mark of a true follower of Christ, of one who
                    is in a state of acceptance with God, is not either outward circumcision or
                    baptism, or any other outward form, but a right state of soul—a mind and spirit
                    renewed after the image of him that created it—is one of those important truths
                    that can only be ‘spiritually discerned’. And this the Apostle himself intimates
                    in the next words: ‘Whose praise is not of men, but of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 2:29; this is a
                            subjective genitive: ‘praise from God’. See also John 12:43 and 1 Cor.
                            4:5; the stress is on God’s approval of Christian virtue in the
                            ‘renewed’ creature. Cf. No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, I.6 and n.</p>
                    </note> As if he had said, ‘Expect
                    not, whoever thou art who thus followest thy great Master, that the world, the
                    men who follow him not, will say, “Well done, good and faithful servant!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        25:23.</p>
                    </note> Know that the “circumcision of the heart”, the seal of thy
                    calling, is “foolishness with the world”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 1:20-21.</p>
                    </note> Be content to
                    wait for thy applause till the day of thy Lord’s appearing. In that day shalt
                    thou “have praise of God”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 4:5; cf. Rom. 2:29.</p>
                    </note> in the great
                    assembly of men and angels.’</p>
                <p>I design, first, particularly to inquire wherein this circumcision of the
                        heart<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">All
                            printed edits, up to <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, II (1787), read
                            ‘circumcision of heart’ here and in I.1, below; Wesley’s final reading
                            quietly restores the definite article.</p>
                    </note> consists; and secondly
                    to mention some reflections that naturally arise from such an inquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. I am first to inquire wherein that circumcision of the heart consists
                    which will receive the praise of God. In general we may observe it is that
                    habitual disposition of soul which in the Sacred Writings is termed ‘holiness’,
                    and which directly implies the being cleansed from sin, ‘from all filthiness
                    both of flesh and <pb n="403"/>spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                    </note> and by consequence
                    the being endued with those virtues which were also in Christ Jesus, the being
                    so ‘renewed in the image of our mind’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:23.</p>
                    </note> as to be ‘perfect, as our
                    Father in heaven is perfect’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:48.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. To be more particular, circumcision of heart implies humility, faith,
                    hope, and charity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:13 (where ‘humility’ does not
                            appear). Note that here Wesley uses the AV translation of ἀγάπη
                            (‘charity’), whereas in II.9, below, he shifts to his much preferred
                            usage, ‘love’. Cf. No. 91, ‘On Charity’ for his arguments for ‘love’;
                            but see above, No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, III.6, where he uses
                            ‘charity’, and below, No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, III.3, where he
                            speaks of ‘“charity” or love’; see also the MS sermon, No. 149, ‘On
                            Love’, II.1-2, where he discusses ‘the true meaning of the word
                            “charity”’. Later, in JWJ, July 4, 1776, he will record: ‘In the evening
                            I showed, to a still more crowded audience, the nature and necessity of
                            Christian love, ἀγάπη, vilely rendered “charity” to confound poor
                            English readers.’ For all that, ‘charity’ was standard usage among the
                            generality of those same ‘poor English readers’; four of their principal
                            translations read ‘charity’. Wesley, therefore, seems to have bowed to
                            common usage where it seemed needful, but continued to advocate ‘love’
                            as a happier choice than ‘charity’ for ἀγάπη. Cf. his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, and Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.9; 65, ‘The
                            Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.2; 76, ‘On Perfection’, 1.4; 80,
                            ‘On Friendship with the World’, §24; 83, ‘On Patience’, §10. Cf. also
                            his letter to Ann Bolton, Dec. 5, 1772.</p>
                    </note> Humility, a right
                    judgment of ourselves,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo here, and in this whole para., of William
                            Law, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.103-4. See also Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’,
                            II.1 and n.; and 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, I.7 and n. This stress on
                            humility, and the equation of humility, self-knowledge, and repentance,
                            is one of Law’s main themes, but so also it had been in Jeremy Taylor
                            and other Anglican divines.</p>
                    </note> cleanses our minds from those
                    high conceits of our own perfections, from the undue opinions of our own
                    abilities and attainments which are the genuine fruit of a corrupted nature.
                    This entirely cuts off that vain thought, ‘I am rich, and wise, and have need of
                    nothing;’ and convinces us that we are by nature ‘wretched, and poor, and
                    miserable, and blind, and naked’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 3:17.</p>
                    </note> It convinces us that in
                    our best estate we are of ourselves all sin and vanity; that confusion, and
                    ignorance, and error, reign over our understanding; that unreasonable, earthly,
                    sensual, devilish passions usurp authority over our will: in a word, that there
                    is no whole part in our soul, that all the foundations of our nature are out of
                        course.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jonathan Swift, <hi rend="italic">Gulliver’s Travels</hi>, II.
                        viii.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. At the same time we are convinced that we are not sufficient of
                    ourselves to help ourselves; that without the Spirit of God we can do nothing
                    but add sin to sin; that it is he alone ‘who worketh <pb n="404"/>in us’ by his
                    almighty power, either ‘to will or do’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:13. Cf. No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our
                            Own Salvation’, I.1-4.</p>
                    </note> that which is good—it being as
                    impossible for us even to think a good thought without the supernatural
                    assistance of his Spirit as to create ourselves, or to renew our whole souls in
                    righteousness and true holiness.</p>
                <p n="4">4. A sure effect of our having formed this right judgment of the sinfulness
                    and helplessness of our nature is a disregard of that ‘honour which cometh of
                        man’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 5:41, 44.</p>
                    </note> which is usually paid to some supposed
                    excellency in us. He who knows himself neither desires nor values the applause
                    which he knows he deserves not. It is therefore ‘a very small thing with him to
                    be judged by man’s judgment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 4:3.</p>
                    </note> He has all reason to
                    think, by comparing what it has said either for or against him with what he
                    feels in his own breast, that the world, as well as the god of this world, was
                    ‘a liar from the beginning’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 8:44.</p>
                    </note> And even as to those who
                    are not of the world, though he would choose (if it were the will of God) that
                    they should account of him as of one desirous to be found a faithful steward of
                    his Lord’s goods,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 12:42.</p>
                    </note> if haply this might be a
                    means of enabling him to be of more use to his fellow-servants, yet as this is
                    the one end of his wishing for their approbation, so he does not at all rest
                    upon it. For he is assured that whatever God wills he can never want instruments
                    to perform; since he is able, even of these stones, to raise up servants<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            3:9.</p>
                    </note> to do his pleasure.</p>
                <p n="5">5. This is that lowliness of mind which they have learned of Christ who
                    follow his example and tread in his steps. And this knowledge of their disease,
                    whereby they are more and more cleansed from one part of it, pride and vanity,
                    disposes them to embrace with a willing mind the second thing implied in
                    ‘circumcision of heart’—that faith which alone is able to make them whole, which
                    is the one medicine given under heaven to heal their sickness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the correlations here of
                            faith, wholeness, and the theme of θεραπεία ψυχής. Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, III.8 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. The best guide of the blind, the surest light of them that are in
                    darkness, the most perfect instructor of the foolish,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 2:19-20.</p>
                    </note>
                    is faith. But it must be such a faith as is ‘mighty through God, to the pulling
                    down of strongholds’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 10:4.</p>
                    </note> to the overturning all the
                        <pb n="405"/>prejudices of corrupt reason, all the false maxims revered
                    among men, all evil customs and habits, all that ‘wisdom of the world’ which ‘is
                    foolishness with God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:19.</p>
                    </note> as ‘casteth down
                    imaginations’ (reasonings) ‘and every high thing that exalteth itself against
                    the knowledge of God, and bringeth into captivity every thought to the obedience
                    of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 10:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. ‘All things are possible to him that’ thus ‘believeth:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark
                        9:23.</p>
                    </note> ‘the eyes of his understanding being enlightened,’ he <hi rend="italic">sees</hi> what is his calling,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:18.</p>
                    </note> even to
                    ‘glorify God, who hath bought him with’ so high ‘a price, in his body and in his
                    spirit, which now are God’s’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 6:20.</p>
                    </note> by redemption, as well
                    as by creation. He feels what is ‘the exceeding greatness of his power’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        1:19.</p>
                    </note> who, as he raised up Christ from the dead, so is able to
                    quicken us—‘dead in sin’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:1, 5.</p>
                    </note>—‘by his Spirit which
                    dwelleth in us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:11.</p>
                    </note> ‘This is the victory which overcometh the world,
                    even our faith:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:4.</p>
                    </note> that faith which is not only an unshaken assent
                    to all that God hath revealed in Scripture, and in particular to those important
                    truths, ‘Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 1:15.</p>
                    </note> he
                    ‘bare our sins in his own body on the tree’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:24.</p>
                    </note> ‘he is the
                    propitiation for our sins; and not for ours only, but also for the sins of the
                    whole world;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">N.B. The following part of this paragraph is now
                                added to the sermon formerly preached. [The preceding quotation is
                                from 1 John 2:2.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> but likewise the revelation of
                    Christ in our hearts: a divine evidence or conviction of his love, his free,
                    unmerited love to me a sinner;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 11:1. This definition of faith is one that
                            Wesley came to regard as normative; cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, I.11 and n.</p>
                    </note> a sure confidence
                    in his pardoning mercy, wrought in us by the Holy Ghost—a confidence whereby
                    every true believer is enabled to bear witness, ‘I know that my Redeemer
                        liveth;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job
                            19:15.</p>
                    </note> that <hi rend="italic">I</hi> ‘have an advocate with
                    the Father’, that ‘Jesus Christ the righteous is’ <hi rend="italic">my</hi>
                    Lord, and ‘the propitiation for <hi rend="italic">my</hi> sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        2:1-2.</p>
                    </note> I know he ‘hath loved <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, and given
                    himself for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 5:2.</p>
                    </note> He ‘hath reconciled
                        <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, even <hi rend="italic">me</hi> to God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            5:10.</p>
                    </note> and <hi rend="italic">I</hi> ‘have redemption through
                    his blood, even the forgiveness of sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:14. In 1732 Wesley was still
                            preoccupied with holy living. Here, in 1748, he has added his discovery
                            of <hi rend="italic">justifying</hi> faith as unmerited mercy and as the
                            assurance of forgiveness through the merits of Christ’s propitiatory
                            death.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">
                    <pb n="406"/>8. Such a faith as this cannot fail to show evidently the
                    power of him that inspires it, by delivering his children from the yoke of sin,
                    and ‘purging their consciences from dead works’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 9:14.</p>
                    </note> by
                    strengthening them so that they are no longer constrained to ‘obey sin in the
                    desires thereof’; but instead of ‘yielding their members unto’ it, ‘as
                    instruments of unrighteousness’, they now ‘yield’ them-selves entirely ‘unto
                    God, as those that are alive from the dead’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 6:12-13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. Those who are thus by faith ‘born of God’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                    have also ‘strong consolation through hope’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:18.</p>
                    </note> This is the next
                    thing which the ‘circumcision of the heart’ implies—even the testimony of their
                    own spirit with the Spirit which witnesses in their hearts, that they are the
                    children of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:16; see above, Nos. 10 and 11, ‘The Witness of the Spirit’,
                            Discourses I and II; and No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own
                        Spirit.’</p>
                    </note> Indeed it is the same Spirit who works in them that
                    clear and cheerful confidence that their heart is upright toward God; that good
                    assurance that they now do, through his grace, the things which are acceptable
                    in his sight; that they are now in the path which leadeth to life, and shall, by
                    the mercy of God, endure therein to the end. It is he who giveth them a lively
                    expectation of receiving all good things at God’s hand—a joyous prospect of that
                    ‘crown of glory’ which is ‘reserved in heaven’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:4; 5:4.</p>
                    </note> for them. By this
                    anchor a Christian is kept steady in the midst of the waves of this troublesome
                    world, and preserved from striking upon either of those fatal rocks, presumption
                    or despair. He is neither discouraged by the misconceived severity of his Lord,
                    nor does he ‘despise the richness of his goodness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:4.</p>
                    </note> He
                    neither apprehends the difficulties of the race set before him<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> to
                    be greater than he has strength to conquer, nor expects them to be so little as
                    to yield him the conquest till he has put forth all his strength. The experience
                    he already has in the Christian warfare, as it assures him his ‘labour is not in
                        vain’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                            15:58.</p>
                    </note> if ‘whatever his hand findeth to do, he doth it with
                    his might,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eccles. 9:10.</p>
                    </note> so it forbids his entertaining so vain a
                    thought as that he can otherwise gain any advantage, as that any virtue can be
                    shown, any praise attained, by ‘faint hearts and feeble hands’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ecclus. 2:12; cf. Ezek.
                            7:12.</p>
                    </note>—or indeed by any but those who pursue the same <pb n="407"/>course with the great Apostle of the Gentiles: ‘I (says he) so run,
                    not as uncertainly; so fight I, not as one that beateth the air. But I keep
                    under my body, and bring it into subjection; lest by any means when I have
                    preached to others, I myself should be a castaway.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 9:26-27.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. By the same discipline is every good soldier of Christ to ‘inure
                    himself to endure hardships’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> Confirmed and
                    strengthened by this, he will be able not only to renounce ‘the works of
                        darkness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:12.</p>
                    </note> but every appetite, too, and every affection
                    which is not subject to the law of God. For ‘everyone’, saith St. John, ‘who
                    hath this hope purifieth himself, even as he is pure.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:3.</p>
                    </note> It
                    is his daily care, by the grace of God in Christ, and through the blood of the
                    covenant, to purge the inmost recesses of his soul from the lusts that before
                    possessed and defiled it: from uncleanness, and envy, and malice, and wrath,
                    from every passion and temper that is ‘after the flesh’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 8:15, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                    that either springs from or cherishes his native corruption; as well knowing
                    that he whose very ‘body is the temple of God’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 6:19.</p>
                    </note> ought to admit
                    into it nothing common or unclean; and that ‘holiness becometh’ that ‘house for
                        ever<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            93:6 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> where the Spirit of holiness vouchsafes to
                        dwell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            echo of the Puritan stress on self-examination and of Jeremy Taylor’s
                            doctrine of repentance; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Unum Necessarium</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, II.419-646).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. Yet lackest thou one thing, whosoever thou art, that to a deep
                    humility and a steadfast faith hast joined a lively hope, and thereby in a good
                    measure cleansed thy heart from its inbred pollution. If thou wilt be perfect,
                    add to all these charity: add love, and thou hast the ‘circumcision of the
                    heart’. ‘Love is the fulfilling of the law,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘the end of the
                        commandment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 1:5.</p>
                    </note> Very excellent things are
                    spoken of love; it is the essence, the spirit, the life of all virtue. It is not
                    only the first and great command,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 22:38.</p>
                    </note> but it is all the
                    commandments in one. Whatsoever things are just, whatsoever things are pure,
                    whatsoever things are amiable or honourable; if there be any virtue, if there be
                    any praise,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:8.</p>
                    </note> they are all comprised in this one word—love. In
                    this is perfection and glory and happiness. The royal law of heaven and earth is
                    this, ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy
                    soul, and with all thy mind, and with dl thy strength.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 12:30.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">
                    <pb n="408"/>12. Not that this forbids us to love anything besides God: it
                    implies that we ‘love our brother also’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:21.</p>
                    </note> Not yet does it
                    forbid us (as some have strangely imagined) to take pleasure in anything but
                        God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            obvious rejoinder to the accusation in the letter to <hi rend="italic">Fog’s Weekly Journal</hi> that the Oxford Methodists ‘avoid, as
                            much as is possible, every object that may affect them with any pleasant
                            and grateful sensation…, fancying…that religion was designed to
                            contradict nature.’</p>
                    </note> To suppose this is to suppose the
                    fountain of holiness is directly the author of sin, since he has inseparably
                    annexed pleasure to the use of those creatures which are necessary to sustain
                    the life he has given us. This therefore can never be the meaning of his
                    command. What the real sense of it is both our blessed Lord and his apostles
                    tell us too frequently and too plainly to be misunderstood. They all with one
                    mouth bear witness that the true meaning of those several declarations—‘The Lord
                    thy God is one Lord; thou shalt have no other gods but me,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Deut. 6:4, 14; Mark 12:29,
                            32.</p>
                    </note> ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy
                        strength,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 12:30, etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘Thou shalt cleave unto him;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 13:4; Acts
                            11:23.</p>
                    </note> ‘The desire of thy soul shall be to his name’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        26:8.</p>
                    </note>—is no other than this. The one perfect good shall be your
                    ultimate end. One thing shall ye desire for its own sake—the fruition of him
                    that is all in all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:20-28.</p>
                    </note> One happiness shall
                    ye propose to your souls, even an union with him that made them, the having
                    ‘fellowship with the Father and the Son’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 1:3.</p>
                    </note> the being ‘joined
                    to the Lord in one Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 6:17.</p>
                    </note> One design ye are to
                    pursue to the end of time—the enjoyment of God in time and in eternity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note here the
                            combination of the theme of participation <hi rend="italic">and</hi> of
                            ‘the enjoyment of God’; cf. the Westminster Catechism, Q. and A.
                        1.</p>
                    </note> Desire other things so far as they tend to this. Love the
                    creature—as it leads to the Creator. But in every step you take be this the
                    glorious point that terminates your view. Let every affection, and thought, and
                    word, and work, be subordinate to this. Whatever ye desire or fear, whatever ye
                    seek or shun, whatever ye think, speak, or do, be it in order to your happiness
                    in God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No.
                            6, ‘The Righteousness of Faith’, II.9 and n.</p>
                    </note> the sole end as
                    well as source of your being.</p>
                <p n="13">13. Have no end, no ultimate end, but God. Thus our Lord: ‘One thing is
                        needful.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 10:42.</p>
                    </note> And if thine eye be singly fixed on this <pb n="409"/>one thing, ‘thy whole body shall be full of light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        6:22.</p>
                    </note> Thus St. Paul: ‘This one thing I do; […] I press toward the
                    mark, for the prize of the high calling in Christ Jesus.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:13-14.</p>
                    </note> Thus
                    St. James: ‘Cleanse your hands, ye sinners, and purify your hearts, ye
                        double-minded.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 4:8.</p>
                    </note> Thus St. John: ‘Love not the
                    world, neither the things that are in the world. […] For all that is in the
                    world, the lust of the flesh, the lust of the eye, and the pride of life, is not
                    of the Father, but is of the world.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:15-16. See below, II.9; also No. 7, ‘The
                            Way to the Kingdom’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> The seeking happiness in
                    what gratifies either the desire of the flesh, by agreeably striking upon the
                    outward senses; the desire of the eye, of the imagination, by its novelty,
                    greatness, or beauty; or the pride of life,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:16—Wesley’s favourite text for
                            an inclusive triad of sinful passions. Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> whether by pomp, grandeur, power, or
                    the usual consequence of them, applause and admiration: ‘is not of the
                    Father’—cometh not from, neither is approved by, the Father of spirits—‘but of
                    the world’—it is the distinguishing mark of those who will not have him reign
                    over them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Thus have I particularly inquired what that ‘circumcision of the
                    heart’ is which will obtain the praise of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, §3 and n.</p>
                    </note> I am in the
                    second place to mention some reflections that naturally arise from such an
                    inquiry, as a plain rule whereby every man may judge himself whether he be of
                    the world or of God.</p>
                <p>And, first, it is clear from what has been said that no man has a title to the
                    praise of God unless his heart is circumcised by humility, unless he is little,
                    and base, and vile in his own eyes; unless he is deeply convinced of that inbred
                    ‘corruption of his nature, whereby he is very far gone from original
                        righteousness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Art. IX, ‘Of Original or Birth Sin’ in the
                            Thirty-nine Articles.</p>
                    </note> being prone to all evil, averse to all
                    good, corrupt and abominable; having a ‘carnal mind’, which ‘is enmity against
                    God, and is not subject to the Law of God, nor indeed can be’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:7.</p>
                    </note>
                    unless he continually feels in his inmost soul that without the Spirit of God
                    resting upon him he can neither think, nor desire, nor speak, nor act, anything
                    good or well-pleasing in his sight.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="410"/>No man, I say, has a title to the praise of God till he feels his
                    want of God: nor indeed till he seeketh that ‘honour, which cometh of God
                        only’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            5:44. Cf. above, §3 and n.</p>
                    </note> and neither desires nor pursues
                    that which cometh of man, unless so far only as it tends to this.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Another truth which naturally follows from what has been said is that
                    none shall obtain the honour that cometh of God unless his heart be circumcised
                    by faith, even a ‘faith of the operation of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> unless,
                    refusing to be any longer led by his senses, appetites, or passions, or even by
                    that blind leader of the blind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 15:14.</p>
                    </note> so idolized by the world,
                    natural reason, he lives and ‘walks by faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:7.</p>
                    </note> directs every step as
                    ‘seeing him that is invisible’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:27.</p>
                    </note> ‘looks not at the things
                    that are seen, which are temporal, but at the things that are not seen, which
                    are eternal’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 4:18.</p>
                    </note> and governs all his desires, designs, and
                    thoughts, all his actions and conversations, as one who is entered in within the
                        veil,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            6:19.</p>
                    </note> where Jesus sits at the right hand of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Col. 3:1;
                            Mark 16:19; Acts 7:55.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. It were to be wished that they were better acquainted with this faith
                    who employ much of their time and pains in laying another foundation, in
                    grounding religion on ‘the eternal <hi rend="italic">fitness</hi> of things’, on
                    ‘the intrinsic <hi rend="italic">excellence</hi> of virtue’, and the <hi rend="italic">beauty</hi> of actions flowing from it—on the <hi rend="italic">reasons</hi>, as they term them, of good and evil, and the <hi rend="italic">relations</hi> of beings to each other.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The men complained of here
                            range from the third Earl of Shaftesbury (cf. his <hi rend="italic">Inquiry Concerning Virtue or Merit</hi>, and his <hi rend="italic">Characteristics of Men, Manners, Opinions, Times</hi> [1st edn.,
                            1711; 4th edn., 1727]), to Samuel Clarke (<hi rend="italic">Discourse
                                Concerning the Unchangeable Obligations of Natural Religion and the
                                Truth and Certainty of the Christian Revelation</hi> [1706], espec.
                            pp. 46 ff.; see also his <hi rend="italic">Demonstration of the Being
                                and Attributes of God</hi> [1705], Prop. XII, and espec. pp.
                            247-48), to Richard Fiddes (<hi rend="italic">A General Treatise of
                                Morality</hi> [1724]), to Francis Hutcheson’s <hi rend="italic">Inquiry</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi>. They include both
                            deists and rationalists; cf. John Leland, <hi rend="italic">A View of
                                the Principal Deistical Writers…</hi>, 1754-56, 3 vols. (3rd edn.,
                            1757). See also <hi rend="italic">Notes and Queries</hi> (6th series),
                            VIII.79, 138. For more complaints of the same sort, cf. No. 34, ‘The
                            Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law’, II.5.</p>
                    </note>
                    Either these accounts of the grounds of Christian duty coincide with the
                    scriptural or not. If they do, why are well-meaning men perplexed, and drawn
                    from the weightier matters of the law by a cloud of terms whereby the easiest
                    truths are explained into obscurity? If they are not, then it behoves them to
                    consider who is the author of this new doctrine, whether he is likely to be ‘an
                    angel <pb n="411"/>from heaven’ who ‘preacheth another gospel’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:8.</p>
                    </note> than
                    that of Christ Jesus—though if he were, God, not we, hath pronounced his
                    sentence: ‘Let him be accursed!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Our gospel, as it knows no other foundation of good works than faith, or
                    of faith than Christ, so it clearly informs us we are not his disciples while we
                    either deny him to be the author or his Spirit to be the inspirer and perfecter
                    both of our faith and works. ‘If any man have not the Spirit of Christ, he is
                    none of his.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:9.</p>
                    </note> He alone can quicken those who are dead unto God,
                    can breathe into them the breath of Christian life, and so prevent, accompany,
                    and follow them with his grace as to bring their good desires to good effect.
                    And ‘as many as are thus led by the Spirit of God, they are the sons of
                        God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            8:14.</p>
                    </note> This is God’s short and plain account of true religion
                    and virtue; and ‘other foundation can no man lay.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. From what has been said we may, thirdly, learn that none is truly ‘led
                    by the Spirit’ unless that ‘Spirit bear witness with his spirit, that he is a
                    child of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:16. Cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, IV.2 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    unless he see the prize and the crown before him, and ‘rejoice in hope of the
                    glory of God’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:2.</p>
                    </note> so greatly have they erred who have taught that in
                    serving God we ought not to have a view to our own happiness. Nay, but we are
                    often and expressly taught of God to have ‘respect unto the recompense of
                        reward’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:26.</p>
                    </note> to balance the toil with the ‘joy set before
                        us’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> these ‘light afflictions’ with that ‘exceeding
                    weight of glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:17.</p>
                    </note> Yea, we are ‘aliens to the
                    covenant of promise’, we are ‘without God in the world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> until
                    God of ‘his abundant mercy hath begotten us again unto a living hope’ of the
                    ‘inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                            1:3-4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. But if these things are so, ’tis high time for those persons to deal
                    faithfully with their own souls—who are so far from finding in themselves this
                    joyful assurance, that they fulfil the terms and shall obtain the promises of
                    that covenant, as to quarrel with the covenant itself, and blaspheme the terms
                    of it, to complain they are too severe, and that no man ever did or shall live
                    up to them! <pb n="412"/>What is this but to reproach God, as if he were an hard
                    master requiring of his servants more than he enables them to perform; as if he
                    had mocked the helpless works of his hands by binding them to impossibilities,
                    by commanding them to overcome where neither their own strength nor his grace
                    was sufficient for them?</p>
                <p n="7">7. These blasphemers might almost persuade those to imagine themselves
                    guiltless who, in the contrary extreme, hope to fulfil the commands of God
                    without taking any pains at all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note this early version of what will become
                            Wesley’s definition of enthusiasm; cf. No. 37, ‘The Nature of
                            Enthusiasm’, §27.</p>
                    </note> Vain hope! that a child of Adam should ever
                    expect to see the kingdom of Christ and of God without striving, without ‘<hi rend="italic">agonizing</hi>’ first ‘to enter in at the strait gate’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 13:24.
                            Note Wesley’s preference here for ‘agonizing’ over ‘striving’ as a
                            translation of ἀγωνίζεστε; cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, and Nos.
                            25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, III.6; 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’,
                            III.1, 5, 6; 89, ‘The More Excellent Way’, §5.</p>
                    </note> That one who
                    was ‘conceived and born in sin’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 51:5.</p>
                    </note> and whose ‘inward parts
                    are very wickedness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> should once entertain a thought
                    of being ‘purified as his Lord is pure’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:3.</p>
                    </note> unless he ‘tread
                    in his steps’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 2:21.</p>
                    </note> and ‘take up his cross daily’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        9:23.</p>
                    </note> unless he ‘cut off the right hand’, and ‘pluck out the
                    right eye and cast it from him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 18:8-9.</p>
                    </note> that he should ever
                    dream of shaking off his old opinions, passions, tempers, of being ‘sanctified
                    throughout in spirit, soul, and body’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 5:23.</p>
                    </note> without a
                    constant and continued course of general self-denial!</p>
                <p n="8">8. What less than this can we possibly infer from the above cited words of
                    St. Paul, who, ‘living in “infirmities, in reproaches, in necessities, in
                    persecutions, in distresses” for Christ’s sake, who being full of “signs, and
                    wonders, and mighty deeds”, who having been “caught up into the third heaven”,
                    yet reckoned’ (as a late author strongly expresses it) that ‘all his virtues’
                    would be ‘insecure, and’ even ‘his salvation in danger, without this constant
                    self-denial. […] “So run I”, says he, “not as uncertainly; so fight I, not as
                    one that beateth the air.” By which he plainly teaches us that he who does not
                    thus run, who does not thus’ deny himself daily, does ‘run uncertainly, and
                    fighteth to as little purpose as he that “beateth the air”.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Law, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.117),
                            who quotes in turn 2 Cor. 12:10, 12; ver. 2, and 1 Cor. 9:26. Note how
                            close Law comes to turning St. Paul’s triad (‘faith, hope, and love’)
                            into a quartet by his addition of ‘self-denial’ as an equal theological
                            virtue; Wesley follows him here in his stress on its equivalent,
                            ‘humility’. Cf. John Worthington, whose <hi rend="italic">Great Duty of
                                Self-Resignation to the Divine Will</hi> (1675, 1689) was extracted
                            by Wesley for his <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>,
                        XXIII-XXIV.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">
                    <pb n="413"/>9. To as little purpose does he talk of ‘fighting the fight of
                        faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Tim. 6:12.</p>
                    </note> as vainly hope to attain the crown of incorruption
                    (as we may, lastly, infer from the preceding observations), whose heart is not
                    circumcised by love. Cutting off both the lust of the flesh, the lust of the
                    eye, and the pride of life,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:16; see above, I.13 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    engaging the whole man, body, soul, and spirit, in the ardent pursuit of that
                    one object, is so essential to a child of God that ‘without it whosoever liveth
                    is counted dead before him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Collects, Quinquagesima, which speaks of
                            charity as ‘that most excellent gift, …the very bond of peace and of all
                            virtues.’</p>
                    </note> ‘Though I speak with the tongues of men and angels,
                    and have not love, I am as sounding brass, or a tinkling cymbal. Though I have
                    the gift of prophecy, and understand all mysteries, and all knowledge, and
                    though I have all faith so as to remove mountains, and have not love, I am
                    nothing. Nay, though I give all my goods to feed the poor, and my body to be
                    burned, and have not love, it profiteth me nothing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                        13:1-3.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. Here then is the sum of the perfect law: this is the true
                    ‘circumcision of the heart’. Let the spirit return to God that gave it, with the
                    whole train of its affections. ‘Unto the place from whence all the rivers came,
                        thither’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 1:7.</p>
                    </note> let them flow again. Other sacrifices from
                    us he would not; but the living sacrifice of the heart he hath chosen. Let it be
                    continually offered up to God through Christ, in flames of holy love. And let no
                    creature be suffered to share with him: for he is a jealous God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:5,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> His throne will he not divide with another: he will
                    reign without a rival. Be no design, no desire admitted there but what has him
                    for its ultimate object. This is the way wherein those children of God once
                    walked, who being dead still speak to us:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 11:4.</p>
                    </note> ‘Desire not to
                    live but to praise his name; let all your thoughts, words, and works tend to his
                    glory. Set your heart firm on him, and on other things only as they are in and
                    from him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Is
                            this, and are the following three quotations, an imagined summary of
                            what the saints have to tell us? More probably they are quotations from
                            older devotional texts known to Wesley and to at least some of his
                            audience, but not yet located in this context.</p>
                    </note> ‘Let your soul
                    be filled with so entire a love of him that you may love nothing but for his
                    sake.’ ‘Have a <pb n="414"/>pure intention of heart, a steadfast regard to his
                    glory in all your actions.’ ‘Fix your eye upon the blessed hope of your calling,
                    and make all the things of the world minister unto it.’ For then, and not till
                    then, is that ‘mind in us which was also in Christ Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note>
                    when in every motion of our heart, in every word of our tongue, in every work of
                    our hands, we ‘pursue nothing but in relation to him, and in subordination to
                    his pleasure’; when we, too, neither think, nor speak, nor act, to fulfil our
                    ‘own will, but the will of him that sent us’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 5:30; 6:38.</p>
                    </note> when whether
                    we ‘eat, or drink, or whatever we do, we do all to the glory of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            10:31.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>