<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 29: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse IX</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 29: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse IX</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="632" to="649"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:632"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Ninth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 6:24-34</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">No man can serve two masters; for either he will hate the one
                        and love the other, or else he will hold to the one and despise the other.
                        Ye cannot serve God and mammon.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Therefore I say unto you, Take no thought for your life, what
                        ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for your body, what ye shall
                        put on. Is not the life more than meat, and the body than raiment?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Behold the fowls of the air: for they sow not, neither do they
                        reap, nor gather into barns; yet your heavenly Father feedeth them. Are ye
                        not much better than they?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Which of you by taking thought can add one cubit unto his
                        stature?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And why take ye thought for raiment? Consider the lilies of
                        the field, how they grow; they toil not, neither do they spin:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And yet I say unto you, that even Solomon in all his glory was
                        not arrayed like one of these.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Wherefore, if God so clothe the grass of the field, which
                        today is, and tomorrow is cast into the oven, shall he not much more clothe
                        you, O ye of little faith?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Therefore take no thought, saying, What shall we eat? or, What
                        shall we drink? or, Wherewithal shall we be clothed?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">(For after all these things do the Gentiles seek); for your
                        heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">But first seek ye the kingdom of God and his righteousness;
                        and all these things shall be added unto you.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Take therefore no thought for the morrow; for the morrow shall
                        take thought for the things of itself: sufficient unto the day is the evil
                        thereof.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <pb n="01:633"/>
            <p n="1">1. It is recorded of the nations whom the King of Assyria, after he had carried
                Israel away into captivity, placed in the cities of Samaria: ‘They feared the Lord,
                and served their own gods.’ ‘These nations’, saith the inspired writer, ‘feared the
                Lord,’ performed an outward service to him (a plain proof that they had a fear of
                God, though not according to knowledge)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Rom. 10:2.</p></note> ‘and served their graven
                images, both their children, and their children’s children; as did their fathers, so
                did they unto this day.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                            rend="endnote text">2 Kgs. 17:33, 41.</p></note></hi></p>
            <p>How nearly does the practice of most modern Christians resemble this of the ancient
                heathens! ‘They fear the Lord’: they also perform an outward service to him, and
                hereby show they have some fear of God; but they likewise ‘serve their own gods’.
                There are those who ‘teach them’ (as there were who taught the Assyrians) ‘the
                manner of the God of the land’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                        rend="footnote text">2 Kgs. 17:27.</p></note> the God whose name the country
                bears to this day, and who was once worshipped there with an holy worship.
                ‘Howbeit’, they do not serve him alone; they do not fear him enough for this; but
                ‘every nation maketh gods of their own, every nation in the cities wherein they
                    dwell.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Kgs.
                        17:29.</p></note> ‘These nations fear the Lord’, they have not laid aside
                the outward form of worshipping him. But ‘they serve their graven images,’ silver
                and gold, the work of men’s hands. Money, pleasure, and praise, the gods of this
                world, more than divide their service with the God of Israel. This is the manner
                both of ‘their children and their children’s children; as did their fathers, so do
                they unto this day.’</p>
            <p n="2">2. But although, speaking in a loose way, after the common manner of men, those
                poor heathens were said to ‘fear the Lord’, yet we may observe the Holy Ghost
                immediately adds, speaking according to the truth and real nature of things: ‘They
                fear not the Lord, neither do after the law and commandment which the Lord commanded
                the children of Jacob. With whom the Lord made a covenant, and charged them, saying,
                Ye shall not fear other gods nor serve them…. But the Lord your God ye shall fear,
                and he shall deliver you out of the hand of all your enemies.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">2 Kgs. 17:34, 35, 39.</p></note></p>
            <p>The same judgment is passed by the unerring Spirit of God, and indeed by all, the
                eyes of whose understanding he hath opened<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:18.</p></note> to discern the things of God,
                upon these poor Christians, <pb n="01:634"/>commonly so called. If we speak
                according to the truth and real nature of things, ‘they fear not the Lord, neither
                do they serve him.’ For they do not ‘after the covenant the Lord hath made with
                them, neither after the law and commandment which he hath commanded them’, saying,
                Thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou serve.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 4:8.</p></note>
                ‘They serve other gods’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Deut. 7:4.</p></note> unto this day. And ‘no man can
                serve two masters.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Matt. 6:24.</p></note></p>
            <p n="3">3. How vain is it for any man to aim at this—to attempt the serving of two
                masters! Is it not easy to foresee what must be the unavoidable consequence of such
                an attempt? ‘Either he will hate the one, and love the other; or else he will hold
                to the one, and despise the other.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                        rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> The two parts
                of this sentence, although separately proposed, are to be understood in connection
                with each other; for the latter part is a consequence of the former. He will
                naturally ‘hold to’ him whom he loves. He will so cleave to him as to perform to him
                a willing, faithful, and diligent service. And in the meantime he will so far at
                least ‘despise’ the master he hates as to have little regard to his commands, and to
                obey them, if at all, in a slight and careless manner. Therefore, whatsoever the
                wise men of the world may suppose, ‘Ye cannot serve God and mammon.’</p>
            <p n="4">4. Mammon was the name of one of the heathen gods, who was supposed to preside
                over riches.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">It was
                        Milton who fixed the tradition that Mammon (Mamon) was the name of a Syrian
                        god; cf. <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, i. 678-751, ii. 228-83; and
                        see also <hi rend="italic">The Jewish Encyclopedia</hi>. Blackall, <hi
                            rend="italic">Works</hi>,II. 660-61, repeats this bit of lore: ‘And ’tis
                        agreed, I think, by all that the word Mammon is a Syriac word signifying
                        riches or treasure,’ but in this place, ‘signifies not a thing but a person;
                        Mammon is here plainly spoken of as a God, i.e., as an idol or false god’
                        and ‘was accounted by the ancient heathens the god of <hi rend="italic"
                            >money</hi>.’</p><p rend="footnote text">The Greek μαμωνᾶ is more
                        probably a transcription of the Aramaic māmônā, meaning ‘gain’ or ‘riches’;
                        cf. Sirach 31:8 and Enoch 63:10; see also <hi rend="italic">Pirke Aboth</hi>
                        2:12. St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">On the Sermon on the Mount</hi>
                        (II.xiv.47), comments that its Punic equivalent is ‘lucre’. Cf. Nos. 28,
                        ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §26; 50, ‘The Use of Money’, §1; and 122,
                        ‘Causes of the Inefficacy of Christianity’, §8.</p></note> It is here
                understood of riches themselves, gold and silver, or in general, money; and by a
                common figure of speech, of all that may be purchased thereby, such as ease, honour,
                and sensual pleasure.</p>
            <p>But what are we here to understand by ‘serving God’; and what by ‘serving
                mammon’?</p>
            <p>We cannot ‘serve God’ unless we believe in him. This is the only true foundation of
                serving him. Therefore believing in God <pb n="01:635"/>as ‘reconciling the world to
                    himself<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        5:19.</p></note> through Christ Jesus, the believing in him as a loving,
                pardoning God, is the first great branch of his service.</p>
            <p>And thus to believe in God implies to <hi rend="italic">trust</hi> in him as our
                strength, without whom we can do nothing,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See John 15:5.</p></note> who every moment endues us
                with power from on high, without which it is impossible to please him; as our help,
                our only help in time of trouble, who compasseth us about with songs of
                    deliverance;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Ps. 32:7 (AV).</p></note> as our shield, our defender, and the lifter up of
                our head above all our enemies that are round about us.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 27:6.</p></note></p>
            <p>It implies to trust in God as our happiness; as the centre of spirits, the only rest
                of our souls; the only good who is adequate to all our capacities, and sufficient to
                satisfy all the desires he hath given us.</p>
            <p>It implies (what is nearly allied to the other) to trust in God as our end; to have
                an eye to him in all things; to use all things only as means of enjoying him;
                wheresoever we are, or whatsoever we do, to see him that is invisible looking on us
                well-pleased, and to refer all things to him in Christ Jesus.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thus to believe is the first thing we are to understand by ‘serving God’.
                The second is, to love him.</p>
            <p>Now, to love God in the manner the Scripture describes, in the manner God himself
                requires of us, and by requiring engages to work in us, is to love him as the one
                God; that is, ‘with all our heart, and with all our soul, and with all our mind, and
                with all our strength’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30.</p></note> It is to desire God alone
                for his own sake, and nothing else but with reference to him; to rejoice in God; to
                delight in the Lord; not only to seek, but find happiness in him; to enjoy God as
                the chiefest among ten thousand;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                        rend="footnote text">S. of S. 5:10.</p></note> to rest in him as our God and
                our all—in a word, to have such a possession of God as makes us always happy.</p>
            <p n="6">6. A third thing we are to understand by ‘serving God’ is to resemble or
                imitate him.</p>
            <p>So the ancient Father: <hi rend="italic">Optimus Dei cultus, imitari quem
                    colis</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Is
                        this Wesley’s memory of St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">De civ. Dei</hi>,
                        viii.17, ‘<hi rend="italic">religionis summa sit imitari quem colis</hi>’?
                        If not, ‘the ancient father’ remains unidentified. In his abridged edn. of
                        Arndt’s <hi rend="italic">True Christianity</hi>, Wesley includes the
                        aphorism: ‘The whole of religion…is to imitate whom thou dost worship…. This
                        was well understood by Plato, in whose school was the maxim, “The perfection
                        of man consisteth in the imitation of God.”’ (<hi rend="italic">Christian
                            Lib.</hi>, I.228-29). Wesley may also have remembered Tillotson’s
                        comment that ‘<hi rend="italic">Deus optimus maximus</hi> was the constant
                        title of God, both among the Greeks and Romans’, and his added quotation
                        from Seneca, <hi rend="italic">primus deorum cultus est deos credere</hi>,
                        etc. (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.678). The idea is found in St. Cyprian
                        (Migne, <hi rend="italic">PL</hi>, IV.215) but not Wesley’s actual phrase.
                        See also Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Earnest Appeal</hi>, §28 (11:55 of this
                        edn.).</p></note>—‘It is the best worship or service of God, to imitate him
                you worship.’<pb n="01:636"/></p>
            <p>We here speak of imitating or resembling him in the spirit of our minds.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                    4:23.</p></note> For here the true Christian imitation of God begins. God is a
                Spirit; and they that imitate or resemble him must do it in spirit and in
                    truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">See John
                        4:24.</p></note></p>
            <p>Now God is love;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        John 4:8, 16.</p></note> therefore they who resemble him in the spirit of
                their minds are transformed into the same image. They are merciful even as he is
                    merciful.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Luke 6:36.</p></note> Their soul is all love. They are kind, benevolent,
                compassionate, tender-hearted; and that not only to the good and gentle, but also to
                the froward. Yea, they are, like him, loving unto every man,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 145:9 (BCP).</p></note> and
                their mercy extends to all his works.</p>
            <p n="7">7. One thing more we are to understand by ‘serving God’, and that is, the
                obeying him; the glorifying him with our bodies as well as with our spirits;<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                    6:20.</p></note> the keeping his outward commandments; the zealously doing
                whatever he hath enjoined; the carefully avoiding whatever he hath forbidden; the
                performing all the ordinary actions of life with a single eye and a pure
                heart—offering them all in holy, fervent love, as sacrifices to God through Jesus
                Christ.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Let us consider now what we are to understand, on the other hand, by
                ‘serving mammon’. And first, it implies the <hi rend="italic">trusting</hi> in
                riches, in money, or the things purchasable thereby, as our strength, the means
                whereby we shall perform whatever cause we have in hand; the trusting in them as our
                help, by which we look to be comforted in or delivered out of trouble.</p>
            <p>It implies the trusting in the world for happiness; the supposing that ‘a man’s life
                consisteth’ (the comfort of his life) ‘in the abundance of the things which he
                    possesseth;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Luke 12:15.</p></note> the looking for rest in the things that are seen; for
                content, in outward plenty; the expecting that satisfaction in the things of the
                world which can never be found out of God.</p>
            <p>And if we do this we cannot but make the world our end; the ultimate end, if not of
                all, at least of many of our undertakings, <pb n="01:637"/>many of our actions and
                designs—in which we shall aim only at an increase of wealth; at the obtaining
                pleasure or praise; at the gaining a larger measure of temporal things, without any
                reference to things eternal.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The ‘serving mammon’ implies, secondly, loving the world; desiring it for
                its own sake; the placing our joy in the things thereof, and setting our hearts upon
                them; the seeking (what indeed it is impossible we should find) our happiness
                therein; the resting with the whole weight of our souls upon the staff of this
                broken reed, although daily experience shows it cannot support, but will only ‘enter
                into our hand and pierce it’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Isa. 36:6.</p></note></p>
            <p n="10">10. To resemble, to be conformed to the world, is the third thing we are to
                understand by ‘serving mammon’; to have not only designs, but desires, tempers,
                affections suitable to those of the world; to be of an earthly, sensual mind,
                chained down to the things of earth; to be self-willed, inordinate lovers of
                ourselves; to think highly of our own attainments; to desire and delight in the
                praise of men; to fear, shun, and abhor reproach; to be impatient of reproof, easy
                to be provoked, and swift to return evil for evil.</p>
            <p n="11">11. To ‘serve mammon’ is, lastly, to obey the world, by outwardly conforming
                to its maxims and customs; to walk as other men walk, in the common road, in the
                broad, smooth, beaten path; to be in the fashion; to follow a multitude; to do like
                the rest of our neighbours; that is, to do the will of the flesh and the mind, to
                gratify our appetites and inclinations—to sacrifice to ourselves, to aim at our own
                ease and pleasure in the general course both of our words and actions.</p>
            <p>Now what can be more undeniably clear than that we ‘cannot’ thus ‘serve God and
                mammon’?</p>
            <p n="12">12. Does not every man see that he cannot <hi rend="italic">comfortably</hi>
                serve both? That to trim between God and the world<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                    n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Johnson’s definition of ‘trim’ is ‘to balance; to
                        fluctuate between two parties’, and he gives a sample usage from South’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Sermons</hi>: ‘For men to pretend that their will obeys
                        the law, while all besides their will serves the faction; what is this but a
                        gross, fulsome juggling with their duty, and a kind of <hi rend="italic"
                            >trimming</hi> it between God and the devil.’</p></note> is the sure way
                to be disappointed in both, and to have no rest either in one or the other? How
                uncomfortable a condition must he be in, who, having the fear but not the love of
                God, who, serving him, but not with all his heart, has only the toils and not the
                joys of religion! He has religion enough to make him miserable, but not enough to
                    <pb n="01:638"/>make him happy: his religion will not let him enjoy the world,
                and the world will not let him enjoy God. So that by halting between both he loses
                both, and has no peace either in God or the world.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Does not every man see that he cannot serve both <hi rend="italic"
                    >consistently</hi> with himself? What more glaring inconsistency can be
                conceived than must continually appear in his whole behaviour who is endeavouring to
                obey both these masters, striving to ‘serve God and mammon’! He is indeed a ‘sinner
                that goeth two ways’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Ecclus. 2:12.</p></note>—one step forward and another backward. He is
                continually building up with one hand and pulling down with the other. He loves sin,
                and he hates it: he is always seeking, and yet always fleeing from God. He would,
                and he would not. He is not the same man for one day, no, not for an hour together.
                He is a motley mixture of all sorts of contrarieties; a heap of contradictions
                jumbled in one. Oh, be consistent with thyself, one way or the other. Turn to the
                right hand or to the left.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Gen. 24:49, etc.</p></note> If ‘mammon’ be God, serve
                thou him; if the Lord, then serve him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See 1 Kgs. 18:21.</p></note> But never think of serving
                either at all unless it be with thy whole heart.</p>
            <p n="14">14. Does not every reasonable, every thinking man see that he cannot <hi
                    rend="italic">possibly</hi> ‘serve God and mammon’? Because there is the most
                absolute contrariety, the most irreconcilable enmity, between them. The contrariety
                between the most opposite things on earth, between fire and water, darkness and
                light, vanishes into nothing when compared to the contrariety between God and
                mammon. So that in whatsoever respect you serve the one, you necessarily renounce
                the other. Do you believe in God through Christ? Do you <hi rend="italic">trust</hi>
                in him as your strength, your help, your shield, and your exceeding great
                    reward?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">See Gen.
                        15:1.</p></note> As your happiness? Your end in all, above all things? Then
                you cannot <hi rend="italic">trust</hi> in riches. It is absolutely impossible you
                should, so long as you have this faith in God. Do you thus ‘trust in riches’?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Mark
                    10:24.</p></note> Then you have denied the faith.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 5:8.</p></note> You do not
                trust in the living God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                        rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 4:10; 6:17.</p></note> Do you <hi rend="italic"
                    >love</hi> God? Do you seek and find happiness in him? Then you cannot love the
                world, neither the things of the world. You are crucified to the world and the world
                crucified to you.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Gal. 6:14.</p></note> Do you ‘love the <pb n="01:639"/>world’?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                    2:15.</p></note> Are your affections set on things beneath?<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">See Col. 3:2.</p></note> Do you
                seek happiness in earthly things? Then it is impossible you should love God. Then
                the love of the Father is not in you. Do you <hi rend="italic">resemble</hi> God?
                Are you merciful, as your Father is merciful?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                    n="38"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 6:36.</p></note> Are you transformed by
                the renewal of your mind<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:2.</p></note> into the image of him that
                created you? Then you cannot be conformed to the present world.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic"
                    >Ibid.</hi></p></note> You have renounced all its affections and lusts. Are you
                conformed to the world? Does your soul still bear the image of the earthly?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                    15:49.</p></note> Then you are not renewed in the spirit of your mind.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:23.</p></note>
                You do not bear the image of the heavenly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:49.</p></note> Do you <hi
                    rend="italic">obey God</hi>? Are you zealous to do his will on earth as the
                angels do in heaven? Then it is impossible you should <hi rend="italic">obey
                    mammon</hi>. Then you set the world at open defiance. You trample its customs
                and maxims under foot, and will neither follow nor be led by them. Do you follow the
                world? Do you live like other men? Do you please men? Do you please yourself? Then
                you cannot be a servant of God. You are of your master and father, the devil.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See John
                    8:44.</p></note></p>
            <p n="15">15. Therefore thou shalt worship the Lord thy God, and him only shalt thou
                    serve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        4:8.</p></note> Thou shalt lay aside all thoughts of obeying two masters, of
                serving God and mammon. Thou shalt propose to thyself no end, no help, no happiness,
                but God. Thou shalt seek nothing in earth or heaven but him; thou shalt aim at
                nothing but to know, to love, and enjoy him. And because this is all your business
                below, the only view you can reasonably have, the one design you are to pursue in
                all things, ‘Therefore I say unto you’ (as our Lord continues his discourse) ‘Take
                no thought for your life, what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink; nor yet for
                your body, what ye shall put on.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:25.</p></note> A deep and weighty direction,
                which it imports us well to consider and throughly to understand.</p>
            <p n="16">16. Our Lord does not here require that we should be utterly without thought,
                even touching the concerns of this life. A giddy, careless temper is at the farthest
                remove from the whole religion of Jesus Christ. Neither does he require us to be
                ‘slothful in business’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:11.</p></note> to be slack and dilatory
                therein. This likewise is contrary to the whole spirit and genius of his religion. A
                Christian abhors sloth as much as drunkenness, and flees from idleness as he does
                from adultery. He well knows that there is one kind of <pb n="01:640"/>thought and
                care with which God is well-pleased; which is absolutely needful for the due
                performance of those outward works unto which the providence of God has called
                him.</p>
            <p>It is the will of God that every man should labour to ‘eat his own bread’;<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">2 Thess.
                    3:12.</p></note> yea, and that every man should provide for his own, for them of
                his own household. It is likewise his will that we should ‘owe no man
                    anything’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        13:8.</p></note> but ‘provide things honest in the sight of all men’.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                    12:17.</p></note> But this cannot be done without taking some thought, without
                having some care upon our minds; yea, often not without long and serious thought,
                not without much and earnest care. Consequently this care to provide for ourselves
                and our household, this thought how to render to all their dues, our blessed Lord
                does not condemn. Yea, it is good and acceptable in the sight of God our
                    Saviour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                        2:3.</p></note></p>
            <p>It is good and acceptable to God that we should so take thought concerning whatever
                we have in hand as to have a clear comprehension of what we are about to do, and to
                plan our business before we enter upon it. And it is right that we should carefully
                consider from time to time what steps we are to take therein; as well as that we
                should prepare all things beforehand for the carrying it on in the most effectual
                manner. This care, termed by some, ‘the care of the head’, <hi rend="superscript"
                    >π;</hi> it was by no means our Lord’s design to condemn.</p>
            <p n="17">17. What he here condemns is ‘the care of the heart’: the anxious, uneasy
                care; the care that hath torment; all such care as does hurt, either to the soul or
                body. What he forbids is that care which sad experience shows wastes the blood and
                drinks up the spirits;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>, on
                        ‘Humours’; see also the poetic tradition on ‘care’, as in Spenser’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Mother Hubbard’s Tale</hi>, ll. 903-4, and Shakespeare’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Julius Caesar</hi>, II.i.231-32 (‘fantasies which busy
                        care draws in the brains of men’).</p></note> which anticipates all the
                misery it fears, and comes to torment us before the time. He forbids only that care
                which poisons the blessings of today by fear of what may be tomorrow; which cannot
                enjoy the present plenty through apprehensions of future want. This care is not only
                a sore disease, a grievous sickness of soul, but also an heinous offence against
                God, a sin of the deepest dye. It is an high affront to the gracious Governor and
                wise Disposer of all things; necessarily implying that the great <pb n="01:641"
                />Judge does not do right,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Gen. 18:25.</p></note> that he does not order all
                things well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Mark 7:37.</p></note> It plainly implies that he is wanting either in
                wisdom, if he does not know what things we stand in need of, or in goodness, if he
                does not provide those things for all who put their trust in him. Beware, therefore,
                that you take not thought in this sense: be ye anxiously careful for nothing.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil
                    4:6.</p></note> Take no uneasy thought. This is a plain, sure rule—<hi
                    rend="italic">uneasy</hi> care is <hi rend="italic">unlawful</hi> care. With a
                single eye to God, do all that in you lies to provide things honest in the sight of
                all men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:17.
                        For Wesley’s use of the <hi rend="italic">in se est</hi> theme, see above,
                        pp. 72-73.</p></note> And then give up all into better hands: leave the
                whole event to God.</p>
            <p n="18">18. ‘Take no thought’ of this kind, no uneasy thought, even ‘for your life,
                what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink, nor yet for your body, what ye shall put
                on. Is not the life more than meat, and the body than raiment?’ If then God gave you
                life, the greater gift, will he not give you food to sustain it? If he hath given
                you the body, how can ye doubt but he will give you raiment to cover it? More
                especially if you give yourselves up to him, and serve him with your whole heart.
                ‘Behold’, see before your eyes, ‘the fowls of the air: for they sow not, neither do
                they reap, nor gather into barns;’ and yet they lack nothing, ‘yet your heavenly
                Father feedeth them. Are ye not much better than they?’ Ye that are creatures
                capable of God? Are ye not of more account in the eyes of God? Of a higher rank in
                the scale of beings?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Cf. No. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’, I.14 and n.</p></note> ‘And
                which of you by taking thought can add one cubit to his stature?’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:27. In both Johnson’s <hi
                            rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> and <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> ‘cubit’ is
                        defined as a measure of <hi rend="italic">space</hi>, the sense in which
                        Wesley uses it here. Cf., however, his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, where
                        he uses it as a measure of <hi rend="italic">time</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic"
                            >And which of you</hi>, if you are ever so careful, can even add a
                        moment to your own life thereby? This seems by far the most easy and natural
                        sense of the words.’</p></note> What profit have you then from this anxious
                thought? It is every way fruitless and unavailing.</p>
            <p>‘And why take ye thought for raiment?’ Have ye not a daily reproof wherever you turn
                your eyes? ‘Consider the lilies of the field, how they grow; they toil not, neither
                do they spin. And yet I say unto you, that even Solomon in all his glory was not
                arrayed like one of these. Wherefore if God so clothe the grass of the field, which
                today is, and tomorrow is cast into the oven’, is cut down, burnt up, and seen no
                more, ‘shall he not much more clothe you, O ye of little faith?’ You, whom he made
                to endure for <pb n="01:642"/>ever and ever, to be pictures of his own
                    eternity!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Wisd.
                        2:23.</p></note> Ye are indeed of little faith. Otherwise ye could not doubt
                of his love and care; no, not for a moment.</p>
            <p n="19">19. ‘Therefore take no thought, saying, What shall we eat,’ if we lay up no
                treasure upon earth? ‘What shall we drink,’ if we serve God with all our strength,
                if our eye be singly fixed on him? ‘Wherewithal shall we be clothed,’ if we are not
                conformed to the world, if we disoblige those by whom we might be profited? ‘For
                after all these things do the Gentiles seek,’ the heathens who know not God. But ye
                are sensible, ‘your heavenly Father knoweth that ye have need of all these things.’
                And he hath pointed out to you an infallible way of being constantly supplied
                therewith. ‘Seek ye first the kingdom of God, and his righteousness, and all these
                things shall be added unto you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:31-33.</p></note></p>
            <p n="20">20. ‘Seek ye first the kingdom of God.’ Before ye give place to any other
                thought or care let it be your concern that the God and Father of our Lord Jesus
                Christ, who ‘gave his only-begotten Son, to the end that believing in him ye might
                not perish, but have everlasting life’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:16.</p></note> may reign in your heart, may
                manifest himself in your soul, and dwell and rule there: ‘that he may cast down
                every high thing which exalteth itself against the knowledge of God, and bring into
                captivity every thought to the obedience of Christ.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 10:5.</p></note> Let
                God have the sole dominion over you. Let him reign without a rival. Let him possess
                all your heart, and rule alone. Let him be your one desire, your joy, your love; so
                that all that is within you may continually cry out, ‘The Lord God omnipotent
                    reigneth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        19:6.</p></note></p>
            <p>‘Seek the kingdom of God and his righteousness.’ Righteous-ness is the fruit of God’s
                reigning in the heart. And what is righteousness but love?<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                        Kingdom’, I.7 and n.</p></note> The love of God and of all mankind, flowing
                from faith in Jesus Christ, and producing humbleness of mind, meekness, gentleness,
                long-suffering, patience, deadness to the world;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65"
                    n="65"><p rend="footnote text">See Col. 3:12; see also Gal. 5:22-23.</p></note>
                and every right disposition of heart toward God and toward man. And by these it
                produces all holy actions, whatsoever are lovely or of good report;<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil.
                    4:8.</p></note> whatsoever works of <pb n="01:643"/>faith and labour of
                    love<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                        Thess. 1:3.</p></note> are acceptable to God and profitable to man.</p>
            <p>‘His righteousness.’ This is all <hi rend="italic">his</hi> righteousness still: it
                is his own free <hi rend="italic">gift</hi> to us, for the sake of Jesus Christ the
                    righteous,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        John 2:1.</p></note> through whom alone it is purchased for us. And it is
                his <hi rend="italic">work</hi>: it is he alone that worketh it in us by the
                inspiration of his Holy Spirit.</p>
            <p n="21">21. Perhaps the well observing this may give light to some other Scriptures
                which we have not always so clearly understood. St. Paul, speaking in his Epistle to
                the Romans concerning the unbelieving Jews, saith, ‘They, being ignorant of God’s
                righteousness, and going about to establish their own righteousness, have not
                submitted themselves unto the righteousness of God.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 10:3.</p></note> I believe
                this may be one sense of the words:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                        rend="footnote text">This sentence is inserted only in the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Works</hi>, 1771.</p></note> they were ‘ignorant of God’s
                righteousness’, not only of the righteousness of Christ, imputed to every
                    believer,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Note
                        Wesley’s nearly casual use of this phrase, destined to become a bone of
                        contention between him and the Calvinists; cf. Nos. 20, <hi rend="italic"
                            >The Lord Our Righteousness</hi> (intro., pp. 444-46); and 21, ‘Sermon
                        on the Mount, I’, I.11. See also Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Remarks on Mr.
                            Hill’s Review</hi>, espec. 12:III, where Wesley weighs and balances the
                        pros and cons of what he calls ‘that ambiguous, unscriptural phrase, so
                        liable to be misinterpreted’ (‘the imputed righteousness of Christ’). His
                        conclusion (§44): ‘With regard to [the doctrine] that we are justified
                        merely for the sake of what Christ has <hi rend="italic">done</hi> and <hi
                            rend="italic">suffered</hi>, I have constantly and earnestly maintained
                        [that] above four and thirty years. And I have frequently used the <hi
                            rend="italic">phrase</hi> [<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ‘the imputed
                        righteousness of Christ’], hoping thereby to please others…. But it has had
                        a contrary effect…. Therefore I will use it no more, unless it occur in an
                        hymn, or steal upon me unawares….’</p></note> whereby all his sins are
                blotted out, and he is reconciled to the favour of God; but (which seems here to be
                more immediately understood) they were ignorant of that inward righteousness, of
                that holiness of heart, which is with the utmost propriety termed ‘God’s
                righteousness’, as being both his own free gift through Christ, and his own work, by
                his almighty Spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >In this implied rejection of self-righteousness Wesley manages an indirect
                        assertion of the <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi> and yet yoked, as always,
                        with holiness of heart; cf. No. 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’,
                    I.11.</p></note> And because they were ignorant of this they ‘went about to
                establish their own righteousness’. They laboured to establish that outside
                righteousness which might very properly be termed ‘their own’; for neither was it
                wrought by the Spirit of God nor was it owned or accepted of him. They might work
                this themselves, by their own natural strength; and when they had done, it was a
                stink in his nostrils. And yet, trusting in <pb n="01:644"/>this, they would ‘not
                submit themselves unto the righteousness of God’. Yea, they hardened themselves
                against that faith whereby alone it was possible to attain it. ‘For Christ is the
                end of the law for righteousness to everyone that believeth.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 10:4.</p></note> Christ, when
                he said, ‘It is finished,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                        rend="footnote text">John 19:30.</p></note> put an end to that law—to the
                law of external rites and ceremonies—that he might ‘bring in a better
                    righteousness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Cf. Heb. 7:19.</p></note> through his blood, by that one oblation of
                himself once offered,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                        rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion, Prayer of Consecration.</p></note> even
                the image of God, into the inmost soul of ‘everyone that believeth’.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Nearly related to these are those words of the Apostle in his Epistle to
                the Philippians: ‘I count all things but dung that I may win Christ,’ an entrance
                into his everlasting kingdom, ‘and be found in him’, believing in him, ‘not having
                mine own righteousness, which is of the law, but that which is through the faith of
                Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77"
                    n="77"><p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:8-9.</p></note>—‘not having my own
                righteousness, which is of the law’, a barely external righteousness, the outside
                religion I formerly had when I hoped to be accepted of God because I was, ‘touching
                the righteousness which is in the law, blameless’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78"
                    n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:6.</p></note>—‘but that which is through
                the faith of Christ, the righteousness which is of God by faith:’ that holiness of
                heart, that renewal of the soul in all its desires, tempers, and affections, ‘which
                is of God’. It is the work of God and not of man, ‘by faith’; through the faith of
                Christ, through the revelation of Jesus Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79"
                    n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 1:12.</p></note> in us, and by faith in his
                    blood;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:25.</p></note> whereby alone we obtain the remission of our sins, and an
                inheritance among those that are sanctified.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">See Acts 20:32.</p></note></p>
            <p n="23">23. ‘Seek ye first’ this ‘kingdom of God’ in your hearts, this
                ‘righteousness’, which is the gift and work of God, the image of God renewed in your
                souls—‘and all these things’ shall be added unto you: all things needful for the
                body; such a measure of all as God sees most for the advancement of his kingdom.
                These ‘shall be added’, they shall be thrown in, over and above. In seeking the
                peace and the love of God you shall not only find what you more immediately seek,
                even the kingdom that cannot be moved; but also what you seek not, not at all for
                its own sake, but only in reference to the other. You shall find in your way to the
                kingdom all outward things, so far as they are expedient for you. This care <pb
                    n="645"/>God hath taken upon himself: cast you all your care upon him.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet.
                    5:7.</p></note> He knoweth your wants; and whatsoever is lacking he will not
                fail to supply.</p>
            <p n="24">24. ‘Therefore take no thought for the morrow.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 6:34.</p></note> Not
                only, take ye no thought how to lay up treasures on earth, how to increase in
                worldly substance; take no thought how to procure more food than you can eat, or
                more raiment than you can put on; or more money than is required from day to day for
                the plain, reasonable purposes of life: but take no <hi rend="italic">uneasy</hi>
                thought even concerning those things which are absolutely needful for the body. Do
                not trouble yourself now with thinking what you shall do at a season which is yet
                afar off. Perhaps that season will never come; or it will be no concern of
                yours—before then you will have passed through all the waves, and be landed in
                eternity. All those distant views do not belong to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>, who
                are but a creature of a day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Pindar, <hi rend="italic">Pythian Odes</hi>, viii. 95.
                        Cf. Wesley’s Pref., §5 and n.</p></note> Nay, what have you to do with ‘the
                morrow’, more strictly speaking? Why should you perplex yourself without need? God
                provides for you today what is needful to sustain the life which he hath given you.
                It is enough. Give yourself up into his hands. If you live another day he will
                provide for that also.</p>
            <p n="25">25. Above all, do not make the care of future things a pretence for neglecting
                present duty. This is the most fatal way of ‘taking thought for the morrow’. And how
                common is it among men! Many, if we exhort them to keep a conscience void of
                    offence,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        24:16.</p></note> to abstain from what they are convinced is evil, do not
                scruple to reply: ‘How then must we live? Must we not take care of ourselves and of
                our families?’ And this they imagine to be a sufficient reason for continuing in
                known, wilful sin. They say, and perhaps think, they would serve God now were it not
                that they should by and by lose their bread. They would prepare for eternity; but
                they are afraid of wanting the necessaries of life. So they serve the devil for a
                morsel of bread; they rush into hell for fear of want; they throw away their poor
                souls lest they should some time or other fall short of what is needful for their
                bodies.</p>
            <p>It is not strange that they who thus take the matter out of God’s hand should be so
                often disappointed of the very things they seek; that while they throw away heaven
                to secure the things of earth <pb n="01:646"/>they lose the one, but do not gain the
                other. The jealous God, in the wise course of his providence, frequently suffers
                this. So that they who will not cast their care on God, who, taking thought for
                temporal things, have little concern for things eternal, lose the very portion which
                they have chosen. There is a visible blast on all their undertakings: whatsoever
                they do it doth not prosper. Insomuch that after they have forsaken God for the
                world they lose what they sought, as well as what they sought not. They fall short
                of the kingdom of God and his righteousness; nor yet are other things added unto
                them.</p>
            <p n="26">26. There is another way of ‘taking thought for the morrow’, which is equally
                forbidden in these words. It is possible to take thought in a wrong manner, even
                with regard to spiritual things; to be so careful about what may be by and by as to
                neglect what is now required at our hands. How insensibly do we slide into this if
                we are not continually watching unto prayer!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 4:7.</p></note> How easily are we
                carried away in a kind of waking dream,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Diogenes Laertius, <hi rend="italic">Lives</hi>,
                        V.18 (Loeb, 184:460-61), where Aristotle is said to have spoken of hope as
                        ‘a kind of waking dream’.</p></note> projecting distant schemes, and drawing
                fine scenes in our own imagination! We think what good we will do when we are in
                such a place, or when such a time is come! How useful we will be, how plenteous in
                good works, when we are easier in our circumstances! How earnestly we will serve God
                when once such an hindrance is out of the way!</p>
            <p>Or, perhaps, you are now in heaviness of soul:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88"
                    n="88"><p rend="footnote text">Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> and
                        the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> both define ‘heaviness’ as a ‘dejection or
                        dejectedness of mind’. Johnson adds ‘depression of spirit’. Cf. Nos. 46 and
                        47: ‘The Wilderness State’ and ‘Heaviness through Manifold
                    Temptations’.</p></note> God as it were hides his face from you. You see little
                of the light of his countenance; you cannot taste his redeeming love. In such a
                temper of mind how natural is it to say, ‘O how I will praise God when the light of
                his countenance shall be again lifted up upon my soul!<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="footnote text">See Num. 6:26.</p></note> How will
                I exhort others to praise him when his love is again shed abroad in my heart!<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                    5:5.</p></note> Then I will do thus and thus: I will speak for God in all
                places; I will not be ashamed of the gospel of Christ.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 1:16.</p></note> Then I
                will redeem the time,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Eph. 5:16.</p></note> I will use to the uttermost
                every talent I have received.’ Do not believe thyself. Thou wilt not do it then
                unless thou dost it now. ‘He that is <pb n="01:647"/>faithful in that which is
                little’, of whatsoever kind it be, whether it be worldly substance or the fear or
                love of God, ‘will be faithful in that which is much.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:10.</p></note> But if
                thou now hidest one talent in the earth, thou wilt then hide five.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 25:18.</p></note> That
                is, if ever they are given; but there is small reason to expect they ever will.
                Indeed ‘unto him that hath’, that is, uses what he hath, ‘shall be given, and he
                shall have more abundantly. But from him that hath not’, that is, uses not the grace
                which he hath already received, whether in a larger or smaller degree, ‘shall be
                taken away even that which he hath.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 13:12. Both Poole (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Annotations</hi>) and Henry (<hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>) explain
                        this paradox in terms of election; cf. Poole’s distinction between those who
                        have ‘the seed of God’ or ‘the root of grace’ in them and those who do not.
                        Henry reminds us ‘that God is debtor to no man. His grace is his own; he
                        gives or withholds it at pleasure. The difference must be resolved into
                        God’s sovereignty.’ For Wesley’s very different interpretation, cf. No. 85,
                        ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, III.4-6: ‘No man sins because he has not
                        grace, but because he does not use the grace which he hath…. Stir up the
                        spark of grace which is now in you and he will give you more
                    grace.’</p></note></p>
            <p n="27">27. And ‘take no thought’ for the temptations of tomorrow. This also is a
                dangerous snare. Think not, ‘When such a temptation comes, what shall I do, how
                shall I stand? I feel I have not power to resist: I am not able to conquer that
                enemy.’ Most true: you have not <hi rend="italic">now</hi> the power which you do
                not <hi rend="italic">now</hi> stand in need of. You are not able at <hi
                    rend="italic">this time</hi> to conquer that enemy; and at <hi rend="italic"
                    >this time</hi> he does not assault you. With the grace you have now you could
                not withstand the temptations which you have not. But when the temptation comes the
                grace will come. In greater trials you will have greater strength. When sufferings
                abound, the consolations of God will in the same proportion abound also. So that in
                every situation the grace of God will be sufficient for you.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 12:9.</p></note> He
                doth not suffer you ‘to be tempted’ today ‘above that ye are able to bear. And in
                every temptation he will make a way to escape.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97"
                    n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 10:13.</p></note> ‘As thy day, so thy
                strength shall be.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Cf. Deut. 33:25.</p></note></p>
            <p n="28">28. ‘Let the morrow’ therefore ‘take thought for the things of itself.’ That
                is, when the morrow comes, then think of it. Live thou today. Be it thy earnest care
                to improve the present hour. This is your own, and it is your all. The past is as
                nothing, as though it had never been. The future is nothing to you. It is not yours;
                perhaps it never will be. There is no depending on what is yet to come; for you
                ‘know not what a day may bring forth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 27:1.</p></note>
                <pb n="01:648"/>Therefore live today: lose not an hour; use this moment; for it is
                your portion. ‘Who knoweth the things which have been before him,’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus. 23:20; Sus.
                    42.</p></note> ‘or which shall be after him under the sun?’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 6:12.</p></note> The
                generations that were from the beginning of the world, where are they now? Fled
                away, forgotten. They <hi rend="italic">were</hi>: they lived their day; they were
                shook off of the earth, as leaves off of their trees.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Homer, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Iliad</hi>, vi. 146. See No. 70, ‘The Case of Reason Impartially
                        Considered’, II.2 and n.</p></note> They mouldered away into common dust.
                Another and another race succeeded; then they ‘followed the generation of their
                fathers, and shall never’ more ‘see the light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103"
                    n="103"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 49:19 (BCP).</p></note> Now is thy turn
                upon the earth. ‘Rejoice, O young man, in the days of thy youth.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="footnote text">Eccles. 11:9.</p></note> Enjoy
                the very, very now;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. St. Augustine’s analysis of time (past, future, and
                        present) in <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, XI.xi-xxxi, where times past
                        and future signify determinate actions registered in either <hi
                            rend="italic">memoria</hi> or <hi rend="italic">expectatio</hi>, but
                        where <hi rend="italic">time present</hi> is grasped by ‘contuition’ in that
                        ‘moment’ which eludes clock-time and is the ‘truly, truly <hi rend="italic"
                            >now</hi>’, the time of human freedom. Cf. John Byrom, ‘Time Past,
                        Future, and Present’, in <hi rend="italic">The Poems of John Byrom</hi>, ed.
                        A. W. Ward (Manchester, printed for the Chetham Society, 1894), Vol. I, Pt.
                        II, p. 567:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Time present only is within thy pow’r:</l>
                        <l>Now, now improve, then whilst thou can’st, the hour!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, IV.2 and n.; and
                        33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.7.</p></note> by enjoying him ‘whose
                years fail not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Cf. Heb. 1:12.</p></note> Now let thine eye be singly fixed on him, in
                ‘whom is no variableness, neither shadow of turning’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:17.</p></note> Now give
                him thy heart; now stay thyself on him; now be thou holy as he is holy.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 1:15,
                        16.</p></note> Now lay hold of the blessed opportunity of doing his
                acceptable and perfect will.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:2.</p></note> Now ‘rejoice to suffer the
                loss of all things, so thou mayst win Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110"
                    n="110"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:8.</p></note></p>
            <p n="29">29. Gladly suffer today, for his name’s sake, whatsoever he permits this day
                to come upon thee. But look not at the sufferings of tomorrow. ‘Sufficient unto the
                day is the evil thereof.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:34.</p></note> Evil it is, speaking after the
                manner of men; whether it be reproach or want, pain or sickness. But in the language
                of God, all is blessing: ‘It is a precious balm,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112"
                    n="112"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 141:6 (BCP).</p></note> prepared by the
                wisdom of God, and <pb n="01:649"/>variously dispensed among his children according
                to the various sicknesses of their souls. And he gives in one day sufficient for
                that day, proportioned to the want and strength of the patient. If therefore thou
                snatchest today what belongs to the morrow, if thou addest this to what is given
                thee already, it will be more than thou canst bear: this is the way, not to heal,
                but to destroy thy own soul. Take therefore just as much as he gives thee today:
                today do and suffer his will. Today give up thyself, thy body, soul, and spirit, to
                God, through Christ Jesus; desiring nothing but that God may be glorified in all
                thou art, all thou dost, all thou sufferest; seeking nothing but to know God, and
                his Son Jesus Christ, through the Eternal Spirit; pursuing nothing but to love him,
                to serve him, and to enjoy him, at this hour, and to all eternity!</p>
            <p>Now unto God the Father, who hath made me and all the world; unto God the Son, who
                hath redeemed me and all mankind; unto God the Holy Ghost, who sanctifieth me and
                all the elect people of God: be honour, and praise, majesty, and dominion, for ever
                and ever! Amen.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p rend="footnote text">A
                        rare instance of a formal ascription (cf. No. 1, Sal<hi rend="italic">vation
                            by Faith</hi>, III.9 and n.); it is a conflation of fragments from ‘A
                        Catechism’ in the BCP.</p></note></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
