<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 22: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse II</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon022</idno>                   
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 22: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse II</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="488" to="509"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic">Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic">there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="468"/>the former part of [ch. 7]
                    he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic">and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="488"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Second</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 5:5-7</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are the meek; for they shall inherit the
                    earth.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after
                        righteousness; for they shall be filled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are the merciful; for they shall obtain mercy.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. When ‘the winter is past’, when ‘the time of singing is come, and the
                    voice of the turtle is heard in the land’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">S. of S. 2:11-12.</p>
                    </note> when he that
                    comforts the mourners is now returned, ‘that he may abide with them for
                        ever’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 14:16.</p>
                    </note> when at the brightness of his presence the clouds
                    disperse, the dark clouds of doubt and uncertainty, the storms of fear flee
                    away, the waves of sorrow subside, and their spirit again ‘rejoiceth in God
                    their Saviour’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:47.</p>
                    </note> then is it that this word is eminently
                    fulfilled; then those whom he hath comforted can bear witness, ‘Blessed (or
                    happy) are the meek; for they shall inherit the earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. But who are the meek? Not those who grieve at nothing because they know
                    nothing, who are not discomposed at the evils that occur because they discern
                    not evil from good. Not those who are sheltered from the shocks of life by a
                    stupid insensibility; who have either by nature or art the virtue of stocks and
                    stones, and resent nothing because they feel nothing. Brute philosophers<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nicholas Rowe’s
                            lines from the prologue to <hi rend="italic">The Ambitious
                                Step-Mother</hi> (inaccurately cited in the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>), quoted by Wesley in No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Important Question</hi>, III.3:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Let not the Stoic boast his mind unmoved,</l>
                            <l>The brute philosopher, who ne’er has proved</l>
                            <l>The joy of loving, or of being loved.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">See below, No. 136, ‘On Mourning for the Dead’,
                            and Wesley’s assertions that Christians ought not feel deep grief. Is
                            the disposition recommended there Christian meekness or
                        stoicism?</p>
                    </note> are <pb n="489"/>wholly unconcerned in this matter.
                        Apathy<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">ἀπάθεια: a crowning virtue in Stoic ethics signifying the ideal state
                            of freedom from passion (παθεία) or any other disturbing emotions. Cf.
                            primary sources (Dionysius, Arrian, Plutarch) in Liddell and Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>; see also Lampe, <hi rend="italic">Patristic Greek Lexicon</hi>, espec. the citations
                            from Clement of Alexandria.</p>
                    </note> is as far from meekness as from
                    humanity. So that one would not easily conceive how any Christians of the purer
                    ages, especially any of the Fathers of the Church, could confound these, and
                    mistake one of the foulest errors of heathenism for a branch of true
                    Christianity.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Nor does Christian meekness imply the being without zeal for God, any
                    more than it does ignorance or insensibility. No; it keeps clear of every
                    extreme, whether in excess or defect. It does not destroy but balance the
                    affections, which the God of nature never designed should be rooted out by
                    grace, but only brought and kept under due regulations.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The familiar Thomist principle
                            that grace does not destroy nature but perfects it (<hi rend="italic">gratia non tollit naturam sed perfecit</hi>).</p>
                    </note> It poises
                    the mind aright. It holds an even scale with regard to anger and sorrow and
                    fear; preserving the mean in every circumstance of life, and not declining
                    either to the right hand or the left.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Chr. 34:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Meekness therefore seems properly to relate to ourselves. But it may be
                    referred either to God or our neighbour. When this due composure of mind has
                    reference to God it is usually termed resignation—a calm acquiescence in
                    whatsoever is his will concerning us, even though it may not be pleasing to
                    nature, saying continually, ‘It is the Lord; let him do what seemeth him
                        good.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Sam.
                            3:18. Note this composite definition of a familiar theme of the mystics.
                            Its nearest source was Law’s <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.242): ‘Resignation to the divine will
                            signifies a cheerful approbation and acceptance of everything that comes
                            from God….’ But in the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi> (cf. the
                            Index in the 2nd edn., 1837, Vol XXX) Wesley cites the same idea in
                            almost the same words from Molinos, De Renty, Antoinette Bourignon, and
                                <hi rend="italic">The Country Parson’s Advice</hi> (cf.
                            XLV.169-291). E.g., in Miguel Molinos, The <hi rend="italic">Spiritual
                                Guide Which Disentangles the Soul</hi>, 1688 (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, XXXVIII.249-93), resignation is defined as ‘a total and
                            absolute consignment of thyself into the hands of God, with a perfect
                            submission to his holy will….’ See also Nos. 69, ‘The Imperfection of
                            Human Knowledge’, IV, ¶3; 82, ‘On Temptation’, III.10; and 83, ‘On
                            Patience’, §10; see also the Diary for Sept 2, 1736, for his report of
                            reading ‘Worthington on Resignation’; this would have been John
                            Worthington, Cambridge Platonist and advocate of theological pluralism,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Great Duty of Self-Resignation to the Divine
                                Will</hi> (1675).</p>
                    </note> When we consider it more strictly with
                    regard to ourselves we style it patience or contentedness. When it is exerted
                    toward <pb n="490"/>other men then it is mildness to the good and gentleness to
                    the evil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley
                            is here digesting and adjudicating a very large literature on the theme
                            of ‘Christian meekness’. His sources here include Joseph Trapp, <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Moral and Practical Subjects</hi> (1725),
                            I.145; Joseph Mede, ‘Discourse XXXII’, in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            pp. 160-61; William Bates, ‘Sermon on the Mount’, in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, II.193-94; and, of course, Offspring Blackall and Henry
                            Hammond. For Blackall meekness is chiefly ‘the mastery of passion’; the
                            Christian who ‘can show anger when there is just cause for it’ still
                            keeps it under control (Discourse V, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.42
                            ff.; there follows an interesting analysis of anger amongst the
                            ‘Christian tempers’). Hammond defines meekness as ‘a softness and
                            mildness and quietness of spirit’ in relation to God and our submission
                            to his will and in relation to our fellows, ‘whether superiors, equals
                            or inferiors’ (<hi rend="italic">Practical Catechism</hi>, pp. 87-95).
                            John Norris cites Aristotle’s <hi rend="italic">Ethics</hi> (IV) which
                            defines meekness as <hi rend="italic">moderation</hi> but then proceeds
                            to identify it ‘as an instance of charity, …since charity obliges us to
                            promote both our own and our neighbour’s happiness. It must,
                            consequently, oblige us to moderate and govern [our] passion’ (<hi rend="italic">Practical Discourses</hi>, III.59). Anger is
                            especially difficult to control in a degree that is Plato’s τὸ μέτριοv
                            (‘the just right’): hence meekness is a <hi rend="italic">necessary</hi>
                            Christian virtue. See also Heylyn, <hi rend="italic">Theological
                                Lectures</hi>, pp. 60-61: ‘The immediate office of meekness is to
                            govern the passions.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For other comments on
                            meekness in the Wesley corpus, cf. Nos. 23, ‘Sermon on the Mount, III’,
                            III.12; 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.4; 83, ‘On
                            Patience’, §4; 92, ‘On Zeal’, II.2; 110, <hi rend="italic">Free
                                Grace</hi>, §12; 120, ‘The Unity of the Divine Being’, §22; also his
                            letter to the Bishop of Gloucester, Nov. 26, 1762.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. They who are truly meek can clearly discern what is evil; and they can
                    also suffer it. They are <hi rend="italic">sensible</hi> of everything of this
                    kind; but still meekness holds the reins. They are exceeding ‘zealous for the
                    Lord of hosts’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Kgs. 19:31; Isa. 9:7; 37:32.</p>
                    </note> but their zeal is always
                    guided by knowledge, and tempered in every thought and word and work with the
                    love of man as well as the love of God. They do not desire to extinguish any of
                    the passions which God has for wise ends implanted in their nature. But they
                    have the mastery of all; they hold them all in subjection, and employ them only
                    in subservience to those ends. And thus even the harsher and more unpleasing
                    passions are applicable to the noblest purposes. Even hate and anger and fear,
                    when engaged against sin, and regulated by faith and love, are as walls and
                    bulwarks to the soul, so that the wicked one cannot approach to hurt it.</p>
                <p n="6">6. ’Tis evident this divine temper is not only to abide but to increase in
                    us day by day. Occasions of exercising, and thereby increasing it, will never be
                    wanting while we remain upon earth. We ‘have need of patience, that after we
                    have done’ and suffered ‘the will of God, we may receive the promise’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            10:36.</p>
                    </note> We have need of resignation, that we may in all
                    circumstances say, ‘Not as I will, <pb n="491"/>but as thou wilt.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        26:39.</p>
                    </note> And we have need of ‘gentleness toward all men’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim.
                            2:24.</p>
                    </note> but especially toward the evil and the unthankful;
                    otherwise we shall be overcome of evil, instead of overcoming evil with
                        good.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rom. 12:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Nor does meekness restrain only the outward act, as the scribes and
                    Pharisees taught of old, and the miserable teachers who are not taught of God
                    will not fail to do in all ages. Our Lord guards us against this, and shows the
                    true extent of it, in the following words: ‘Ye have heard that it was said by
                    them of old time, Thou shalt not kill; and whosoever shall kill shall be in
                    danger of the judgment. But I say unto you, that whosoever shall be angry with
                    his brother without a cause shall be in danger of the judgment; and whosoever
                    shall say to his brother, Raca, shall be in danger of the council; but whosoever
                    shall say, Thou fool, shall be in danger of hell-fire.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt.
                                5:21-22. [Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.4 and
                            n.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Our Lord here ranks under the head of murder even that anger which goes
                    no farther than the heart; which does not show itself by an outward unkindness,
                    no, not so much as a passionate word.</p>
                <p>‘Whosoever is angry with his brother’—with any man living, seeing we are all
                    brethren; whosoever feels any unkindness in his heart, any temper contrary to
                    love; whosoever is angry ‘without a cause’—without a sufficient cause, or
                    farther than that cause requires—‘shall be in danger of the judgment’, ἔνοχος
                    ἔσται, ‘shall’ in that moment ‘be obnoxious to’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.4
                            and n.; and 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’, II.2 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> the righteous judgment of God.</p>
                <p>But would not one be inclined to prefer the reading of those copies which omit
                    the word εἰκῆ, ‘without a cause’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">εἰκῆ appears in many good manuscripts, including
                            the <hi rend="italic">Codex Bezae</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>; Bengel and others rejected it as a gloss and Wesley followed
                            them in the <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>. Modern critical texts and
                            translations omit it.</p>
                    </note> Is it not entirely superfluous? For if
                        <hi rend="italic">anger at persons</hi> be a temper contrary to love, how
                    can there be a cause, a sufficient cause for it? Any that will justify it in the
                    sight of God?</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Anger at sin</hi> we allow. In this sense we may ‘be angry and’
                    yet we ‘sin not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:26.</p>
                    </note> In this sense our Lord
                    himself is once recorded to have <pb n="492"/>been angry: ‘He looked round about
                    upon them with anger, being grieved for the hardness of their hearts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark
                        3:5.</p>
                    </note> He was grieved at the sinners, and angry at the sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> for Matt. 5:22: ‘We ought not for any cause
                            to be angry at the <hi rend="italic">person</hi> of the sinner, but at
                            his <hi rend="italic">sin</hi> only.’ Law makes the same point in <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            IV.224). In his section on loving all men (the good and the bad)
                            equally, he says we must learn to distinguish between <hi rend="italic">actions</hi> and <hi rend="italic">persons</hi>, that we must
                            always love persons, <hi rend="italic">all</hi> persons—good and bad—for
                            reasons that never change, in the same way that justice and truth never
                            change, because they are grounded in God’s love. Cf. also Seneca, <hi rend="italic">Moral Essays: ‘De Ira’ (‘On Anger’)</hi>, ii. 28: ‘<hi rend="italic">Magna pars hominum est, quae non peccatis irascitur
                                sed peccatibus</hi>’ (‘The greater part of mankind are angry not
                            with the sin but with the sinner’). Cf. Wesley’s early sermon (133),
                            ‘Death and Deliverance’, ¶11; and No. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’,
                            III.8. See also Hymn 262, ll. 27-32, in <hi rend="italic">A Collection
                                of Hymns</hi> (1780):</p>
                        <l>Thou hatest all iniquity,</l>
                        <l>But nothing thou hast made.</l>
                        <l>O may I learn the art,</l>
                        <l>With meekness to reprove,</l>
                        <l>
                            <hi rend="italic">To hate the sin with all my heart,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <hi rend="italic">But still the sinner love.</hi>
                        </l>
                    </note> And this is
                    undoubtedly right before God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘And whosoever shall say to his brother, Raca.’ Whosoever shall give way
                    to anger, so as to utter any contemptuous word. It is observed by commentators
                    that <hi rend="italic">Raca</hi> is a Syriac word which properly signifies
                    empty, vain, foolish: so that it is as inoffensive an expression as can well be
                    used toward one at whom we are displeased.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Raca’ (ῥάχα) is clearly more than this. If,
                            as Poole had suggested (<hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>), it is Syriac, then its verbal root
                            signifies ‘spitting’ as a sign of contempt. Cf. Bengel, <hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>, and the
                            papyri references in Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English
                                Lexicon</hi>. Also, cf. Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.4 and
                            n.; and 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’, II.2 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> And yet whosoever shall use this, as our Lord assures us,
                    ‘shall be in danger of the council’—rather, ‘shall be obnoxious thereto’. He
                    shall be liable to a severer sentence from the Judge of all the earth.</p>
                <p>‘But whosoever shall say, Thou fool’—whosoever shall so give place to the devil
                    as to break out into reviling, into designedly reproachful and contumelious
                    language, ‘shall be obnoxious to hell-fire’—shall in that instant be liable to
                    the highest condemnation. It should be observed that our Lord describes all
                    these as obnoxious to capital punishment: the first to strangling, usually
                    inflicted on those who were condemned in one of the inferior courts; the second
                    to stoning, which was frequently inflicted on those who were condemned by the
                    Great Council at <hi rend="Page">[01:493]</hi>Jerusalem; the third to burning
                    alive, inflicted only on the highest offenders, in the ‘valley of the sons of
                    Hinnom’, Γῆ ‘Εννών, from which that word is evidently taken which we translate
                        hell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Josh. 15:8, גיא הנם; Wesley’s Greek here is neither the Septuagint’s nor
                            St. Matthew’s; cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Matt.
                    5:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. And whereas men naturally imagine that God will excuse their defect in
                    some duties for their exactness in others, our Lord next takes care to cut off
                    that vain though common imagination. He shows that it is impossible for any
                    sinner to <hi rend="italic">commute</hi> with God, who will not accept one duty
                    for another, nor take a part of obedience for the whole.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 16, ‘The Means of
                            Grace’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> He warns us that the performing our duty
                    to God will not excuse us from our duty to our neighbour; that works of piety,
                    as they are called, will be so far from commending us to God if we are wanting
                    in charity, that on the contrary that want of charity will make all those works
                    an abomination to the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.13 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘Therefore, if thou bring thy gift to the altar, and there rememberest that thy
                    brother hath ought against thee’—on account of thy unkind behaviour toward him,
                    of thy calling him ‘Raca’, or ‘Thou fool’—think not that thy gift will atone for
                    thy anger, or that it will find any acceptance with God so long as thy
                    conscience is defiled with the guilt of unrepented sin. ‘Leave there thy gift
                    before the altar, and go thy way; first be reconciled to thy brother’ (at least
                    do all that in thee lies toward being reconciled) ‘and then come and offer thy
                        gift.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 5:[22,] 23-24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. And let there be no delay in what so nearly concerneth thy soul.
                    ‘Agree with thine adversary quickly’—now; upon the spot—‘while thou art in the
                    way with him’—if it be possible, before he go out of thy sight—‘lest at any time
                    the adversary deliver thee to the judge’—lest he appeal to God, the Judge of
                    all—‘and the judge deliver thee to the officer’—to Satan, the executioner of the
                    wrath of God—‘and thou be cast into prison’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:25.</p>
                    </note>—into hell, there to be
                    reserved to the judgment of the great day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Jude 6.</p>
                    </note> ‘Verily I say unto
                    thee, thou shalt by no means come out thence till thou hast paid the uttermost
                        farthing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:26.</p>
                    </note> But this it is <pb n="494"/>impossible for thee
                    ever to do; seeing thou hast nothing [with which] to pay.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 7:42.</p>
                    </note>
                    Therefore if thou art once in that prison the smoke of thy torment must ‘ascend
                    up for ever and ever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 14:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. Meantime, ‘the meek shall inherit the earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 37:11; cf. Matt
                        5:5.</p>
                    </note> Such is the foolishness of worldly wisdom! The wise of the
                    world had warned them again and again that if they did not resent such
                    treatment, if they would tamely suffer themselves to be thus abused, there would
                    be no living for them upon earth; that they would never be able to procure the
                    common necessaries of life, nor to keep even what they had; that they could
                    expect no peace, no quiet possession, no enjoyment of anything. Most
                    true—suppose there were no God in the world; or suppose he did not concern
                    himself with the children of men. But ‘when God ariseth to judgment, and to help
                    all the meek upon earth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 76:9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> how doth he laugh
                    all this heathen wisdom to scorn, and turn the ‘fierceness of man to his
                        praise’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 76:10 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He takes a peculiar care to provide them
                    with all things needful for life and godliness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 1:3.</p>
                    </note> He secures to them
                    the provision he hath made, in spite of the force, fraud, or malice of men. And
                    what he secures he ‘gives them richly to enjoy’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:17.</p>
                    </note> It
                    is sweet to them, be it little or much. As ‘in patience they possess their
                        souls’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Luke 21:19. Cf. No. 83, ‘On Patience’, and espec. §5 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    so they truly possess whatever God hath given them. They are always content,
                    always pleased with what they have. It pleases them because it pleases God; so
                    that while their heart, their desire, their joy is in heaven, they may truly be
                    said to ‘inherit the earth’.</p>
                <p n="13">13. But there seems to be a yet farther meaning in these words, even that
                    they shall have a more eminent part in the ‘new earth, wherein dwelleth
                        righteousness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 3:13.</p>
                    </note> in that inheritance, a
                    general description of which (and the particulars we shall know hereafter) St.
                    John has given in the twentieth chapter of the Revelation. ‘And I saw an angel
                    come down from heaven…. And he laid hold on the dragon, that old serpent, …and
                    bound him a thousand years…. And I saw the souls of them that were <pb n="495"/>beheaded for the witness of Jesus, and for the Word of God, and of them which
                    had not worshipped the beast, neither his image, neither had received his mark
                    upon their foreheads or in their hands; and they lived and reigned with Christ a
                    thousand years. But the rest of the dead lived not again until the thousand
                    years were expired. This is the first resurrection. Blessed and holy is he that
                    hath part in the first resurrection: on such the second death hath no power; but
                    they shall be priests of God and of Christ, and shall reign with him a thousand
                        years.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                            20:1-2, 4-6. For Wesley’s ‘last words’ on ‘the millennium’, cf. his
                            letter to Christopher Hopper, June 3, 1788, and to Walter Churchey, June
                            26, 1788.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Our Lord has hitherto been more immediately employed in removing the
                    hindrances of true religion: such is pride,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance
                                of Believers</hi>, I.3 and n.</p>
                    </note> the first, grand hindrance
                    of all religion, which is taken away by ‘poverty of spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:3.</p>
                    </note>
                    levity and thoughtlessness, which prevent any religion from taking root in the
                    soul till they are removed by holy <hi rend="italic">mourning</hi>; such are
                    anger, impatience, discontent, which are all healed by Christian <hi rend="italic">meekness</hi>. And when once these hindrances are
                    removed—these evil diseases of the soul which were continually raising false
                    cravings therein, and filling it with sickly appetites—the native appetite of a
                    heaven-born spirit returns; it hungers and thirsts after righteousness. And
                    ‘blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after righteousness; for they shall
                    be filled.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Righteousness (as was observed before) is the image of God, the mind
                    which was in Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> It is every holy and
                    heavenly temper in one; springing from as well as terminating in the love of God
                    as our Father and Redeemer, and the love of all men for his sake.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Blackall’s
                            definition of righteousness as ‘twofold’: both ‘actual, personal, and
                            inherent righteousness’ (always imperfect) and ‘imputed righteousness…,
                            i.e., our justification and acquittal by God…for the sake of Christ’
                                (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.61). Here he follows Hammond, who
                            had drawn the same distinction in his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                                Catechism</hi>, p. 96. Wesley pushes beyond their point and
                            interprets righteousness as holiness: the perfect love of God and ‘of
                            all men for <hi rend="italic">his sake</hi>’. Cf. Nos. 83, ‘On
                            Patience’, § 10; and 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, §§2,
                        3.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘Blessed are they which do hunger and thirst after’ this; in order fully
                    to understand which expression we should observe, <pb n="496"/>first, that
                    hunger and thirst are the strongest of all our bodily appetites. In like manner
                    this hunger in the soul, this thirst after the image of God, is the strongest of
                    all our spiritual appetites when it is once awakened in the heart; yea, it
                    swallows up all the rest in that one great desire to be renewed after the
                    likeness of him that created us. We should, secondly, observe that from the time
                    we begin to hunger and thirst those appetites do not cease, but are more and
                    more craving and importunate till we either eat and drink, or die. And even so,
                    from the time that we begin to hunger and thirst after the whole mind which was
                    in Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> these spiritual appetites do not cease, but cry
                    after their food with more and more importunity. Nor can they possibly cease
                    before they are satisfied, while there is any spiritual life remaining. We may,
                    thirdly, observe that hunger and thirst are satisfied with nothing but meat and
                    drink. If you would give to him that is hungry all the world beside, all the
                    elegance of apparel, all the trappings of state, all the treasure upon earth,
                    yea thousands of gold and silver; if you would pay him ever so much honour, he
                    regards it not; all these things are then of no account with him. He would still
                    say, ‘These are not the things I want; give me food, or else I die.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen.
                            25:29-34; 30:1.</p>
                    </note> The very same is the case with every soul
                    that truly hungers and thirsts after righteousness. He can find no comfort in
                    anything but this: he can be satisfied with nothing else. Whatever you offer
                    beside, it is lightly esteemed; whether it be riches, or honour, or pleasure, he
                    still says, ‘This is not the thing which I want. Give me love or else I
                    die!’</p>
                <p n="4">4. And it is as impossible to satisfy such a soul, a soul that is athirst
                    for God, the living God, with what the world accounts religion, as with what
                    they account happiness. The religion of the world implies three things: first,
                    the doing no harm, the abstaining from outward sin—at least from such as is
                    scandalous, as robbery, theft, common swearing, drunkenness; secondly, the doing
                    good—the relieving the poor, the being charitable, as it is called; thirdly, the
                    using the means of grace—at least the going to church and to the Lord’s
                        Supper.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            interesting summary of ‘the [invalid] religion of the world’ (an earlier
                            account of which had been given in No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>; cf. espec. I.6). Note, however, that it is also a
                            précis of Wesley’s own <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi>, the seed of
                            which can be found in his early sermon (Sept. 3, 1732), ‘Public
                            Diversions Denounced’, II.2 (No. 143). Thus, the <hi rend="italic">Rules</hi> by themselves, outside the context of faith, are no
                            better than any other set of moralistic dicta. Cf. also Nos. 23, ‘Sermon
                            on the Mount, III’, II.4; 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.7, 11; 33,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, I.2, II.2-4; 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own
                            Salvation’, II.4 (where Wesley has an approving reference); 89, ‘The
                            More Excellent Way’, §5; 98, ‘On Visiting the Sick’, §1; 115, ‘Dives and
                            Lazarus’, II.7; 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §§15 ff.;
                            cf. also <hi rend="italic">A Blow at the Root</hi>, §4 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 250, Vol. 13 of this edn.); and JWJ,
                            Nov. 25, 1739. For Wesley’s comments on ‘the saints of the world’ cf.
                            No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.5 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> He in whom these three <pb n="497"/>marks are found is termed
                    by the world a religious man. But will this satisfy him who hungers after God?
                    No. It is not food for his soul. He wants a religion of a nobler kind, a
                    religion higher and deeper than this. He can no more feed on this poor, shallow,
                    formal thing, than he can ‘fill his belly with the east wind’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 15:2.</p>
                    </note> True, he
                    is careful to abstain from the very appearance of evil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess. 5:22.</p>
                    </note>
                    He is zealous of good works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p>
                    </note> He attends all the
                    ordinances of God. But all this is not what he longs for. This is only the
                    outside of that religion which he insatiably hungers after. The knowledge of God
                    in Christ Jesus; ‘the life that is hid with Christ in God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:3.</p>
                    </note> the
                    being ‘joined unto the Lord in one Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 6:17.</p>
                    </note> the having
                    ‘fellowship with the Father and the Son’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 1:3.</p>
                    </note> the ‘walking in
                    the light as God is in the light’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 1:7.</p>
                    </note> the being ‘purified even
                    as he is pure’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:3.</p>
                    </note>—this is the religion, the righteousness he
                    thirsts after. Nor can he rest till he thus rests in God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Yet another usage of Wesley’s
                            favourite line from St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>,
                            I.1; cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Steepest’</hi>, II.5
                            and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘Blessed are they who’ thus ‘hunger and thirst after righteousness; for
                    they shall be filled.’ They shall be filled with the thing which they long for,
                    even with righteousness and true holiness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:24.</p>
                    </note> God shall satisfy them
                    with the blessings of his goodness, with the felicity of his chosen. He shall
                    feed them with the bread of heaven, with the manna of his love.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John
                            6:58.</p>
                    </note> He shall give them to drink of his pleasures, as out of
                    the river<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 36:8 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> which he that drinketh of shall never
                        thirst<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            John 4:14.</p>
                    </note>—only for more and more of the water of life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 21:6; 22:1,
                            17.</p>
                    </note> This thirst shall endure for ever.</p>
                <pb n="498"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>The painful thirst, the fond desire,</l>
                    <l>Thy joyous presence shall remove;</l>
                    <l>But my full soul shall still require</l>
                    <l>A whole eternity of love.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘Pleading the Promise of
                                Sanctification’, st. 22. This was first published as an appendix to
                                No. 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi> (1741), and was
                                reprinted in the brothers’ <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                                    Poems</hi> (1742), p. 263 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                                II.322). Orig.,</p>
                            <lg>
                                <l>While my full soul doth still require</l>
                                <l>The whole eternity of love.</l>
                            </lg>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="6">6. Whosoever then thou art to whom God hath given to ‘hunger and thirst
                    after righteousness’, cry unto him that thou mayst never lose that inestimable
                    gift, that this divine appetite may never cease. If many rebuke thee, and bid
                    thee hold thy peace, regard them not; yea, cry so much the more, ‘“Jesus,
                    Master, have mercy on me!”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 17:13.</p>
                    </note> Let me not live but to be
                    holy as thou art holy!’ No more ‘spend thy money for that which is not bread’,
                    nor thy ‘labour for that which satisfieth not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 55:2.</p>
                    </note> Canst thou hope to
                    dig happiness out of the earth? To find it in the things of the world? O trample
                    under foot all its pleasures, despise its honours, count its riches as dung and
                    dross—yea, and all the things which are beneath the sun—‘for the excellency of
                    the knowledge of Christ Jesus’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil 3:8.</p>
                    </note> for the entire renewal of thy
                    soul in that image of God wherein it was originally created.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note> Beware of quenching
                    that blessed hunger and thirst by what the world calls religion—a religion of
                    form, of outward show, which leaves the heart as earthly and sensual as
                        ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 23, ‘Sermon on the Mount, III’, IV.1. Wesley’s usage of the term
                            ‘religion’ varies. More often than not, he equates it with
                            ‘Christianity’, as ‘the true religion’. But he will also, as here, use
                            ‘religion’ with a naturalistic connotation and, thus, as antithetical to
                            Christianity.</p>
                    </note> Let nothing satisfy thee but the power of
                    godliness, but a religion that is spirit and life; the dwelling in God and God
                    in thee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            John 4:12-13.</p>
                    </note> the being an inhabitant of eternity;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa.
                            57:15.</p>
                    </note> the entering in by the blood of sprinkling<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        12:24.</p>
                    </note> ‘within the veil’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 6:19.</p>
                    </note> and ‘sitting in heavenly
                    places with Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">
                    <pb n="499"/>III. 1. And the more they are filled with the life of God, the
                    more tenderly will they be concerned for those who are still without God in the
                        world,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            2:12.</p>
                    </note> still dead in trespasses and sins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> Nor shall
                    this concern for others lose its reward. ‘Blessed are the merciful; for they
                    shall obtain mercy.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The word used by our Lord more immediately implies the compassionate, the
                    tender-hearted; those who, far from despising, earnestly grieve for those that
                    do not hunger after God. This eminent part of brotherly love is here (by a
                    common figure) put for the whole; so that ‘the merciful’, in the full sense of
                    the term, are they who ‘love their neighbours as themselves’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 19:19, etc. Cf.
                            below, III.3 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Because of the vast importance of this love—without which, ‘though we
                    spake with the tongues of men and angels, though we had the gift of prophecy and
                    understood all mysteries and all knowledge, though we had all faith so as to
                    remove mountains; yea, though we gave all our goods to feed the poor, and our
                    very bodies to be burned, it would profit us nothing’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                    13:1-3.</p>
                    </note>—the wisdom of God has given us by the Apostle Paul a full and
                    particular account of it, by considering which we shall most clearly discern who
                    are ‘the merciful that shall obtain mercy’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. <hi rend="italic">Charity</hi>, or love (as it were to be wished it had
                    been rendered throughout, being a far plainer and less ambiguous word),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 17, ‘The
                            Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2 and n. Notice how οἱ ἐλεήμονες here
                            reminds Wesley of ἀγάπη in 1 Cor. 13, and provides him with the occasion
                            for this extended comment on the latter.</p>
                    </note> the love of our
                    neighbour as Christ hath loved us, ‘suffereth long’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:4.</p>
                    </note> is
                    patient toward all men. It suffers all the weakness, ignorance, errors,
                    infirmities, all the frowardness and littleness of faith in the children of God;
                    all the malice and wickedness of the children of the world. And it suffers all
                    this, not only for a time, for a short season, but to the end: still feeding our
                    enemy when he hungers; if he thirst, still giving him drink; thus continually
                    ‘heaping coals of fire’, of melting love, ‘upon his head’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And in every step toward this desirable end, the ‘overcoming evil with
                        good’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 12:21.</p>
                    </note> ‘love is kind’ (χρηστεύεται, a word not easily
                        <hi rend="Page">[01:500]</hi>translated)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:4. χρηστεύσμαι (‘to be kind or
                            merciful’) and its cognates occur in <hi rend="italic">Christian</hi>
                            texts (e.g., 1 Clement 14:3; Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                                History</hi>, V., I.46, etc.) and in the Psalms of Solomon 9:11; cf.
                            Lampe, <hi rend="italic">Patristic Greek Lexicon</hi>. Its original
                            sense was ‘pleasant’, ‘comfortable’ (as of well-fitting clothes); hence
                            its remarkable usage in Rom. 2:4.</p>
                    </note>—it is soft, mild, benign.
                    It stands at the utmost distance from moroseness, from all harshness or sourness
                    of spirit; and inspires the sufferer at once with the most amiable sweetness and
                    the most fervent and tender affection.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Consequently, ‘Love envieth not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:4.</p>
                    </note> It is impossible
                    it should; it is directly opposite to that baneful temper. It cannot be that he
                    who has this tender affection to all, who earnestly wishes all temporal and
                    spiritual blessings, all good things in this world and the world to come, to
                    every soul that God hath made, should be pained at his bestowing any good gift
                    on any child of man. If he has himself received the same he does not grieve but
                    rejoice that another partakes of the common benefit. If he has not he blesses
                    God that his brother at least has, and is herein happier than himself. And the
                    greater his love, the more does he rejoice in the blessings of all mankind, the
                    farther is he removed from every kind and degree of envy toward any
                    creature.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Love οὐ περπερεύεται: not ‘vaunteth not itself’, which coincides with
                    the very next words, but rather (as the word likewise properly imports) ‘is not
                    rash’ or ‘hasty’ in judging.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> In classical Greek
                            πέρπερος means ‘braggart, windbag’. Its cognate forms (even here) have
                            more of a connotation of boasting than hasty judgment. Bengel, <hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>, had
                            taken it thus. Even so, Wesley (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>) translates
                            it ‘rashly’, and adds: ‘does not hastily condemn anyone.’ Cf. III.10,
                            below; also No. 149, ‘On Love’, II.7.</p>
                    </note> It will not hastily
                    condemn anyone. It does not pass a severe sentence on a slight or sudden view of
                    things. It first weighs all the evidence, particularly that which is brought in
                    favour of the accused. A true lover of his neighbour is not like the generality
                    of men, who, even in cases of the nicest nature, ‘see a little, presume a great
                    deal, and so jump to the conclusion’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley had found this aphorism in an essay by Henry
                            Grove (1648-1738) in <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, No. 626 (Nov.
                            29, 1714), where it is attributed to John Locke. It can be found in ‘Of
                            the Conduct of the Understanding’ (§16, on ‘Haste’), written in 1697 but
                            not included in any of Locke’s published writings until 1762 (fourteen
                            years after this sermon!). It may be found in modern edns. of Locke’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>—e.g., the 1963 Scientia Verlag Aalen
                            reprint of the London, 1823 edn. (III.238). Grove was a disciple of
                            Locke and obviously had access to the unpublished MS of ‘Conduct…’. He
                            and <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi> thus were Wesley’s source for
                            this bit of Lockean wisdom which Wesley quotes here <hi rend="italic">exactly</hi>.</p>
                    </note> No; he proceeds with wariness and
                    circumspection, taking heed to every step; willingly subscribing to that rule of
                    the ancient heathen (O where <pb n="501"/>will the modern Christian appear!): ‘I
                    am so far from lightly believing what one man says against another that I will
                    not easily believe what a man says against himself. I will always allow him
                    second thoughts, and many times counsel too.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In No. 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount, X’, §13,
                            Wesley cites Seneca as the source for a slightly different version of
                            this quotation. This is confirmed by Susanna Wesley’s quotation of it as
                            a ‘rule of Seneca’s’ but with no more specific citation; cf. Adam
                            Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Memoirs</hi>, p. 317. But <hi rend="italic">where</hi> in Seneca?</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. It follows, love ‘is not puffed up’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:4.</p>
                    </note> It does not incline
                    or suffer any man ‘to think more highly of himself than he ought to think’, but
                    rather ‘to think soberly’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:3.</p>
                    </note> Yea, it humbles the soul unto
                    the dust. It destroys all high conceits engendering pride, and makes us rejoice
                    to be as nothing, to be little and vile, the lowest of all, the servant of
                        all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Mark 9:35.</p>
                    </note> They who are ‘kindly affectioned one to another
                    with brotherly love’ cannot but ‘in honour prefer one another’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            12:10.</p>
                    </note> Those who, ‘having the same love, are of one accord’,
                    do ‘in lowliness of mind each esteem other better than themselves’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            2:2-3.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. It ‘doth not behave itself unseemly’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> It is not rude or
                    willingly offensive to any. It ‘renders to all their due: fear to whom fear,
                    honour to whom honour’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 13:7.</p>
                    </note> courtesy, civility,
                    humanity to all the world, in their several degrees ‘honouring all men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            2:17.</p>
                    </note> A late writer defines good breeding, nay, the highest
                    degree of it, politeness: ‘A continual desire to please, appearing in all the
                        behaviour.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In No. 100, ‘On Pleasing All Men’, II.4, Wesley quotes ‘Mr. Addison’s
                            well-known definition of politeness: “A constant desire of pleasing all
                            men, appearing through the whole conversation”’—obviously a repetition
                            of this definition here. The characterization of it as ‘well-known’
                            poses a problem, though, for I have yet to locate it in any of Addison’s
                            published works or in any of the indexes of <hi rend="italic">The
                                Spectator</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">The Tatter</hi>. Nor is it cited in <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>, or
                            Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>. Something very like it
                            may be seen in <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, No. 386 (May 23,
                            1712), but the author was Richard Steele; see also Steele in <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, No. 33 (Apr. 11, 1711), for a
                            similar phrasing; cf. Addison in <hi rend="italic">The Freeholder</hi>,
                            No. 38 (Apr. 30, 1712), for the same sentiment in different
                        words.</p>
                    </note> But if so, there is none so well-bred as a Christian, a
                    lover of all mankind; for he cannot but desire to ‘please all men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        10:33.</p>
                    </note> ‘for their good to edification’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 15:2.</p>
                    </note> And this
                    desire cannot be hid: it will necessarily appear in all his intercourse with
                    men. For his ‘love is without dissimulation’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:9.</p>
                    </note> it will appear in
                    all his actions and <pb n="502"/>conversation. Yea, and will constrain him,
                    though without guile, to ‘become all things to all men, if by any means he may
                    save some’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 9:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. And in becoming all things to all men ‘love seeketh not her own.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        13:5.</p>
                    </note> In striving to please all men the lover of mankind has no
                    eye at all to his own temporal advantage. He covets no man’s silver, or gold, or
                    apparel: he desires nothing but the salvation of their souls. Yea, in some sense
                    he may be said ‘not to seek his own’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 10:24.</p>
                    </note> spiritual, any more
                    than temporal advantage. For while he is on the full stretch to save their souls
                    from death he as it were forgets himself. He does not think of himself so long
                    as that zeal for the glory of God swallows him up. Nay, at some times he may
                    almost seem, through an excess of love, to give up himself, both his soul and
                    his body; while he cries out with Moses, ‘Oh! this people have sinned a great
                    sin […]! Yet now, if thou wilt, forgive their sin. And if not, blot me out of
                    the book which thou hast written.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Exod. 32:31-32. [Both 1771 and 1787 edns.
                                have an exclamation mark here.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Or with St. Paul, ‘I
                    could wish that myself were accursed from Christ for my brethren, my kinsmen
                    according to the flesh!’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 9:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. No marvel that ‘such love is not provoked,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:5. Cf. also Nos.
                            91, ‘On Charity’, I.5 and n. (see also, above, III.6); and 149, ‘On
                            Love’, II.7.</p>
                    </note> οὐ παροξύνεται. Let it be observed, the word
                    ‘easily’, strangely inserted in the translation, is not in the original. St.
                    Paul’s words are absolute: ‘Love is not provoked’—it is not provoked to
                    unkindness toward anyone.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In classical Greek παροξόνεται means ‘irritable’ or
                            ‘quick-tempered’ or, literally, ‘in a paroxysm’ (as in a fever). Most
                            modern translations tilt away from Wesley’s absolute, as in Arndt and
                            Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, the RSV (‘not
                            irritable’), NEB (‘not quick to take offence’) or Phillips’s colloquial
                            (‘not touchy’).</p>
                    </note> Occasions indeed will frequently occur,
                    outward provocations of various kinds. But love does not yield to provocation.
                    It triumphs over all. In all trials it looketh unto Jesus, and is more than
                    conqueror in his love.</p>
                <p>’Tis not improbable that our translators inserted that word as it were to <hi rend="italic">excuse</hi> the Apostle, who, as they supposed, might
                    otherwise appear to be wanting in the very love which he so beautifully
                    describes. They seem to have supposed this from a <pb n="503"/>phrase in the
                    Acts of the Apostles, which is likewise very inaccurately translated. When Paul
                    and Barnabas disagreed concerning John, the translation runs thus: ‘And the
                    contention was so sharp between them that they departed asunder.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                15:39.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> This naturally induces the reader to suppose
                    that they were equally sharp therein; that St. Paul, who was undoubtedly right
                    with regard to the point in question (it being quite improper to take John with
                    them again, who had deserted them before) was as much provoked as Barnabas, who
                    gave such a proof of his anger as to leave ‘the work’ for which he had been ‘set
                    apart by the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 13:2.</p>
                    </note> But the original imports
                    no such thing; nor does it affirm that St. Paul was provoked at all. It simply
                    says, καὶ ἐγένετο παροξυσμός,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 15:39; the original reads ἐγένετο δὲ
                            παροξυσμός. It may be that St. Paul was not ‘provoked at all’, but the
                            point that the disagreement was very sharp is quite clear. Wesley’s
                            interest here is to safeguard his doctrine of ‘perfect love’, even
                            though he is not firmly supported on <hi rend="italic">lexical</hi>
                            grounds. But the point about St. Paul’s equanimity is made repeatedly,
                            e.g., Nos. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’,
                            II.5; 61, ‘The Mystery of Iniquity’, §17; 91, ‘On Charity’, I.6. Cf.
                            also the <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, as well as <hi rend="italic">Remarks on A Defence of… Aspasio Vindicated</hi>, §4; see, finally,
                            the extract from Bolton’s <hi rend="italic">Discourse…of True
                                Happiness</hi> (1631), in the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>,
                            VII.273-74.</p>
                    </note> ‘And there was a sharpness, a paroxysm’ of anger;
                    in consequence of which Barnabas left St. Paul, took John, and went his own way.
                    ‘Paul’ then ‘chose Silas and departed, being recommended by the brethren to the
                    grace of God’ (which is not said concerning Barnabas), ‘and he went through
                    Syria and Cilicia’, as he had proposed, ‘confirming the churches’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            15:40-41.</p>
                    </note> But to return.</p>
                <p n="11">11. Love prevents a thousand provocations which would otherwise arise,
                    because it ‘thinketh no evil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> Indeed the merciful man
                    cannot avoid knowing many things that are evil, he cannot but see them with his
                    own eyes and hear them with his own ears. For love does not put out his eyes, so
                    that it is impossible for him not to see that such things are done. Neither does
                    it take away his understanding, any more than his senses, so that he cannot but
                    know that they are evil. For instance: when he sees a man strike his neighbour,
                    or hears him blaspheme God, he cannot either question the thing done or the
                    words spoken, or doubt of their being evil. Yet οὐ λογίζεται τὸ κακόν. The word
                        <hi rend="Page">[01:504]</hi>λογίζεται (‘thinketh’) does not refer either to
                    our seeing and hearing, or to the first and involuntary acts of our
                    understanding; but to our willingly thinking what we need not; our <hi rend="italic">inferring</hi> evil where it does not appear: to our <hi rend="italic">reasoning</hi> concerning things which we do not see, our <hi rend="italic">supposing</hi> what we have neither seen nor heard.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An eccentric
                            interpretation of λογίζομαι; normally, it means ‘to reckon, calculate,
                            consider, or ponder’; cf. Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>; and Liddell and Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>.</p>
                    </note> This is what
                    true love absolutely destroys. It tears up, root and branch, all <hi rend="italic">imagining</hi> what we have not known. It casts out all
                    jealousies, all evil surmisings, all readiness to believe evil. It is frank,
                    open, unsuspicious; and as it cannot design, so neither does it fear, evil.</p>
                <p n="12">12. It ‘rejoiceth not in iniquity’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:6.</p>
                    </note> common as this is,
                    even among those who bear the name of Christ; who scruple not to rejoice over
                    their enemy when he falleth either into affliction, or error, or sin. Indeed,
                    how hardly can they avoid this who are zealously attached to any party! How
                    difficult is it for them not to be pleased with any fault which they discover in
                    those of the opposite party! With any real or supposed blemish, either in their
                    principles or practice! What warm defender of any cause is clear of these? Yea,
                    who is so calm as to be altogether free? Who does not rejoice when his adversary
                    makes a false step which he thinks will advantage his own cause? Only a man of
                    love. He alone weeps over either the sin or folly of his enemy, takes no
                    pleasure in hearing or in repeating it, but rather desires that it may be
                    forgotten for ever.</p>
                <p n="13">13. But he ‘rejoiceth in the truth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                    wheresoever it is found, in the ‘truth which is after godliness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus
                        1:1.</p>
                    </note> bringing forth its proper fruit, holiness of heart and
                    holiness of conversation. He rejoices to find that even those who oppose him,
                    whether with regard to opinions or some points of practice, are nevertheless
                    lovers of God, and in other respects unreprovable. He is glad to hear good of
                    them, and to speak all he can, consistently with truth and justice. Indeed, good
                    in general is his glory and joy, wherever diffused throughout the race of
                    mankind. As a citizen of the world<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Francis Bacon, ‘Goodness and Goodness of
                            Nature’, No. 13, in <hi rend="italic">Essays</hi>: ‘If a man be gracious
                            and courteous to strangers, it shows he is a citizen of the world.’ The
                            phrase goes back to Plutarch’s anecdote about Socrates’s claim to being
                            a ‘cosmian’ (κόσμιος) rather than a citizen of Athens only; cf.
                            Plutarch, ‘On Exile’, ll. 600-601, in <hi rend="italic">Moralia</hi>
                            (Loeb, 405:28-29). A similar story is told of Diogenes; cf. Diogenes
                            Laertius, ‘Diogenes’ in <hi rend="italic">Lives</hi>, VI.63 (Loeb,
                            185:64-65). In Cicero, <hi rend="italic">De Legibus (Laws)</hi>, I.
                            xxiii. 61, he speaks of a liberated mind realizing itself ‘not bound by
                            walls, like people in a single town, but <hi rend="italic">civem urbis
                                mundi quasi unius urbis</hi>’ (‘a citizen of the whole world as if
                            it were one great city’).</p>
                    </note> he claims a share in the happiness
                    of all the inhabitants of <hi rend="Page">[01:505]</hi>it. Because he is a man
                    he is not unconcerned in the welfare of any man; but enjoys whatsoever brings
                    glory to God and promotes peace and goodwill among men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                    2:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="14">14. This love ‘covereth all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:7.</p>
                    </note> (So without all
                    doubt πάντα στέγει should be translated; for otherwise it would be the very same
                    with πάντα ὑπομένει, ‘endureth all things’.)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Did Wesley suppose that none of his readers
                            would know that στέγω had so wide a range of meanings (including ‘to
                            cover’, but more usually ‘to endure’) that no single usage is ‘without
                            all doubt’, even here? Cf. Liddell and Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, and Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc.
                                cit.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> Because the merciful man ‘rejoiceth not in
                    iniquity’, neither does he willingly make mention of it. Whatever evil he sees,
                    hears, or knows, he nevertheless conceals so far as he can without making
                    himself ‘partaker of other men’s sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 5:22.</p>
                    </note> Wheresoever or with
                    whomsoever he is, if he sees anything which he approves not it goes not out of
                    his lips unless to the person concerned, if haply he may gain his brother. So
                    far is he from making the faults or failures of others the matter of his
                    conversation, that of the absent he never does speak at all unless he can speak
                    well. A talebearer, a backbiter, a whisperer, an evil-speaker, is to him all one
                    as a murderer. He would just as soon cut his neighbour’s throat as thus murder
                    his reputation. Just as soon would he think of diverting himself by setting fire
                    to his neighbour’s house as of thus ‘scattering abroad arrows, firebrands, and
                    death, and saying, Am I not in sport?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 26:18-19.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>He makes one only exception. Sometimes he is convinced that it is for the glory
                    of God or (which comes to the same) the good of his neighbour that an evil
                    should not be covered. In this case, for the benefit of the innocent he is
                    constrained to declare the guilty. But even here: (1). He will not speak at all
                    till love, superior love, constrains him; (2). He cannot do it from a general
                    confused view of doing good or of promoting the glory of God, but from a clear
                    sight of some particular end, some determinate good which he pursues; (3). Still
                    he cannot speak unless he be fully convinced <pb n="506"/>that this very means
                    is necessary to that end—that the end cannot be answered, at least not so
                    effectually, by any other way; (4). He then doth it with the utmost sorrow and
                    reluctance, using it as the last and worst medicine, a desperate remedy in a
                    desperate case, a kind of poison never to be used but to expel poison;
                    consequently, (5). He uses it as sparingly as possible. And this he does with
                    fear and trembling, lest he should transgress the law of love by speaking too
                    much, more than he would have done by not speaking at all.</p>
                <p n="15">15. Love ‘believeth all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:7.</p>
                    </note> It is always willing to
                    think the best, to put the most favourable construction on everything. It is
                    ever ready to believe whatever may tend to the advantage of anyone’s character.
                    It is easily convinced of (what it earnestly desires) the innocence or integrity
                    of any man; or, at least, of the sincerity of his repentance, if he had once
                    erred from the way. It is glad to excuse whatever is amiss, to condemn the
                    offender as little as possible, and to make all the allowance for human weakness
                    which can be done without betraying the truth of God.</p>
                <p n="16">16. And when it can no longer believe, then love ‘hopeth all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> Is any evil related of any man?
                    Love hopes that the relation is not true, that the thing related was never done.
                    Is it certain it was?—‘But perhaps it was not done with such circumstances as
                    are related; so that, allowing the fact, there is room to hope it was not so ill
                    as it is represented.’ Was the action apparently, undeniably evil? Love hopes
                    the intention was not so. Is it clear the design was evil too?—‘Yet might it not
                    spring, [not]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">All published edns. (including Sugden’s) read, ‘…might it not spring
                            from the settled temper of the heart, but…’—which clearly is not what
                            Wesley meant.</p>
                    </note> from the settled temper of the heart, but from
                    a start of passion, or from some vehement temptation, which hurried the man
                    beyond himself?’ And even when it cannot be doubted but all the actions,
                    designs, and tempers are equally evil; still love hopes that God will at last
                    make bare his arm, and get himself the victory; and that there shall be ‘joy in
                    heaven over this one sinner that repenteth, more than over ninety and nine just
                    persons that need no repentance.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 15:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="17">17. Lastly, it ‘endureth all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:7. ὑπομένει here is not merely a
                            synonym for στέγει. Its nuance is ‘to stand one’s ground’ rather than to
                            flee; thus ‘to remain steadfast’ in difficulties.</p>
                    </note> This
                    completes the <pb n="507"/>character of him that is truly merciful. He endureth
                    not some, not many things only, not most, but absolutely ‘all things’. Whatever
                    the injustice, the malice, the cruelty of men can inflict, he is able to suffer.
                    He calls nothing intolerable; he never says of anything, ‘This is not to be
                    borne.’ No; he can not only do but suffer all things through Christ which
                    strengtheneth him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 4:13.</p>
                    </note> And all he suffers does
                    not destroy his love, nor impair it in the least. It is proof against all. It is
                    a flame that burns even in the midst of the great deep. ‘Many waters cannot
                    quench his love, neither can the floods drown it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">S. of S. 8:7.</p>
                    </note> It
                    triumphs over all. It ‘never faileth’, either in time or in eternity.</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>In obedience to what heaven decrees,</l>
                    <l>Knowledge shall fail and prophecy shall cease.</l>
                    <l>But lasting charity’s more ample sway,</l>
                    <l>Nor bound by time, nor subject to decay,</l>
                    <l>In happy triumph shall for ever live,</l>
                    <l>And endless good diffuse, and endless praise receive.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Matthew Prior,
                                ‘Charity,’ 31-36. Cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection of Moral
                                    and Sacred Poms</hi>, I.87-89. See also No. 36, ‘The Law
                                Established through Faith, II’, II.1, where Wesley again quotes the
                                last two lines as well as two later ones.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>So shall ‘the merciful obtain mercy’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:7.</p>
                    </note> not only by the
                    blessing of God upon all their ways, by his now repaying the love they bear to
                    their brethren a thousandfold into their own bosom, but likewise by an
                    ‘exceeding and eternal weight of glory’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:17.</p>
                    </note> in the ‘kingdom
                    prepared for them from the beginning of the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                    25:34.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="18">18. For a little while you may say, ‘Woe is me, that I am constrained to
                    dwell with Mesech, and to have my habitation among the tents of Kedar!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 120:4
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> You may pour out your soul, and bemoan the loss of
                    true genuine love in the earth. Lost indeed! You may well say (but not in the
                    ancient sense), ‘See how <hi rend="italic">these</hi> Christians love one
                        another!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The ancient sense’ here refers to the famous claim in Tertullian’s <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>, ch. 39, §7: ‘see how the Christians love
                            one another!’; this was echoed by Julian, <hi rend="italic">Epistle</hi>
                            49, as reported in Sozomen, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical
                                History</hi>, V. xvi: ‘Ought we not to consider that the progress of
                            Atheism [i.e., Christianity] has been principally owing to the humanity
                            evinced by Christians <hi rend="italic">towards strangers</hi>…? It is,
                            therefore, requisite that each of us be diligent in the discharge of <hi rend="italic">our</hi> duty.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley was
                            fond of this claim about Christian benevolence and repeats it, as in
                            Nos. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, I.4; 49, ‘The Cure
                            of Evil-speaking’, II.5; 53, <hi rend="italic">On the Death of George
                                Whitefield</hi>, ΙII.9; 110, <hi rend="italic">Free Grace</hi> (‘To
                            the Reader’). Cf. also Wesley’s letter to his mother, July 6,
                        1738.</p>
                    </note> These Christian kingdoms that <pb n="508"/>are tearing out
                    each other’s bowels, desolating one another with fire and sword! These Christian
                    armies that are sending each other by thousands, by ten thousands, quick into
                        hell!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            55:15 (AV).</p>
                    </note> These Christian nations that are all on fire with
                    intestine broils, party against party, faction against faction! These Christian
                    cities where deceit and fraud, oppression and wrong, yea, robbery and murder, go
                    not out of their streets! These Christian families, torn asunder with envy,
                    jealousy, anger, domestic jars—without number, without end! Yea, what is most
                    dreadful, most to be lamented of all, these Christian churches!—churches (‘Tell
                    it not in Gath;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Sam. 1:20.</p>
                    </note> but alas, how can we hide
                    it, either from Jews, Turks, or pagans?) that bear the name of Christ, ‘the
                    Prince of Peace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 9:6.</p>
                    </note> and wage continual war with
                    each other! That convert sinners by burning them alive: that are ‘drunk with the
                    blood of the saints’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 17:6.</p>
                    </note> Does this praise belong
                    only to ‘Babylon the great, the mother of harlots and abominations of the
                        earth’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 17:5.</p>
                    </note> Nay, verily; but Reformed churches (so called)
                    have fairly learned to tread in her steps. Protestant churches, too, know to
                    persecute, when they have power in their hands, even unto blood. And meanwhile,
                    how do they also anathematize each other! Devote each other to the nethermost
                    hell! What wrath, what contention, what malice, what bitterness is everywhere
                    found among them! Even when they agree in essentials, and only differ in
                    opinions, or in the circumstantials of religion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley is painfully
                            sensitive to Christianity’s bloody record, and the horrors of war are
                            frequently recounted in the sermons. E.g., cf. Nos. 102, ‘Of Former
                            Times’, §13, where he speaks of ‘that savage barbarity’; 111, <hi rend="italic">National Sins and Miseries</hi>, I.4, ‘that foul
                            monster, war’; 128, ‘The Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, II.4, the
                            ‘foul monster, war’. Cf. also Nos. 92, ‘On Zeal’, §1, where he cites ‘an
                            eminent German writer’ who has written about the persecutions; and 102,
                            ‘Of Former Times’, §14, where he is identified only as ‘an eminent
                            writer’. Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> says the
                            persecutions were usually reckoned as ten in number. See also Bishop
                            Joseph Hall, <hi rend="italic">Soliloquies</hi>, X, in <hi rend="italic">Select Works</hi>, III.346. And cf. No. 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’, as a
                            counterweight to this spirit of persecution.</p>
                    </note> Who ‘follows
                    after’ only ‘the things that make for peace, and things wherewith one may edify
                        another’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 14:19.</p>
                    </note> O God! How long? Shall thy promise fail?
                    Fear it not, ye little flock.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 12:32.</p>
                    </note> Against hope believe in
                        hope.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rom. 4:18.</p>
                    </note> It is your Father’s <pb n="509"/>&gt;good
                        pleasure<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 12:32.</p>
                    </note> yet to renew the face of the earth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 104:30
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Surely all these things shall come to an end,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                            7:9.</p>
                    </note> and the inhabitants of the earth shall learn
                        righteousness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 26:9.</p>
                    </note> ‘Nation shall not lift up
                    sword against nation, neither shall they know war any more.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 2:4.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘The mountain of the Lord’s house shall be established in the top of the
                        mountains;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 2:2.</p>
                    </note> and all the kingdoms of the
                    world shall become the kingdoms of our God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 11:15.</p>
                    </note> ‘They shall not’ then
                    ‘hurt or destroy in all his holy mountain;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 11:9.</p>
                    </note> but ‘they shall
                    call their walls salvation and their gates praise.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 60:18.</p>
                    </note>
                    They shall all be without spot or blemish,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet 1:19.</p>
                    </note> loving one
                    another, even as Christ hath loved us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 15:12.</p>
                    </note> Be thou part of the
                    first-fruits, if the harvest is not yet. Do thou love thy neighbour as
                        thyself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Lev. 19:18; Matt. 19:19, etc.</p>
                    </note> The Lord God fill thy heart
                    with such a love to every soul that thou mayst be ready to lay down thy life for
                    his sake! May thy soul continually overflow with love, swallowing up every
                    unkind and unholy temper, till he calleth thee up into the region of love, there
                    to reign with him for ever and ever!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>