<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 49: The Cure of Evil-Speaking</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 49: The Cure of Evil-Speaking</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="251" to="262"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p n="">Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a
                combination of OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these
                docx into XML using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched
                them up manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:251"/>
            <introduction>
                <p><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></p>
                <p>If, as we saw in ‘Self-denial’, pietists are all too easily tempted to a sort of
                    religious narcissism, so also they find it hard to resist their strong
                    temptations to high-minded censoriousness. Wesley saw the dangers here and
                    roundly asserts (more hopefully, perhaps, than realistically) that ‘a
                    distinguishing mark of a Methodist [is that] he censures no man behind his
                    back.’ The magnitude of this problem within the closeknit fellowship of
                    Methodist class meetings, etc., is reflected in a formal compact that was drawn
                    up by the brothers Wesley, in John’s own handwriting, and eleven of their
                    colleagues, including Edward and Charles Perronet, on January 29, 1752:</p>
                <quote>It is agreed by us whose names are underwritten:</quote>
                <quote>1. That we will not listen, or willingly inquire after any ill concerning
                    each other.</quote>
                <quote>2. That if we do hear any ill of each other, we will not be forward to
                    believe it.</quote>
                <quote>3. That as soon as possible we will communicate what we hear, by speaking or
                    writing to the person concerned.</quote>
                <quote>4. That till we have done this we will not write or speak a syllable of it to
                    any other person whatsoever.</quote>
                <quote>5. That neither will we mention it after we have done this to any other
                    person.</quote>
                <quote>6. That we will not make any exception to any of these rules, unless we think
                    ourselves absolutely obliged in conscience so to do.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">See <hi rend="italic"
                                >Letters</hi>, 26:490 in this edn.</p></note></quote>
                <p>This concern is confirmed by the fact that Wesley preached against
                    ‘evil-speaking’ at least nine times in that year, then twice in 1753, and once
                    again in 1758. The effectiveness of these various efforts, and of this written
                    sermon summing up the issue, may be gauged from the fact that we hear no more of
                    it until an oral sermon in 1786, and another written sermon—on how to reprove a
                    neighbour to his face—in 1787 (No. 65, <hi rend="italic">The Duty of Reproving
                        our Neighbour</hi>).</p>
                <p>In light of Wesley’s definition of evil-speaking (‘neither more nor less than
                    speaking evil of an <hi rend="italic">absent</hi> person’) it is worth noting
                    that he does not use the terms ‘gossip’, on the one hand, or ‘candour’, on the
                    other. This reminds us that, in the eighteenth century, neither term meant to
                        <hi n="02:252"/> Wesley what they later came to mean, by cynical extension
                    in the case of ‘gossip’ and by inference in the case of ‘candour’ (cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">OED</hi> and Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>).</p>
                <p>This ‘tract for the times’ has no other publishing history than its place as a
                    sort of addendum in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Cure of Evil-Speaking</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 18:15-17</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">If thy brother shall sin against thee, go and tell him his
                        fault between thee and him alone: if he will hear thee, thou hast gained thy
                        brother.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">But if he will not hear, take with thee one or two more, that
                        by the mouth of two or three witnesses every word may be
                    established.</hi></p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">And if he will not hear them, tell it to the church: but if he
                        will not hear the church, let him be to thee as an heathen man and a
                        publican.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. ‘Speak evil of no man,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Titus 3:2.</p></note> says the great Apostle—as
                    plain a command as ‘Thou shalt do no murder.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                        n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 19:18.</p></note> But who even among
                    Christians regards this command? Yea, how few are there that so much as
                    understand it? What is ‘evil-speaking’? It is not (as some suppose) the same
                    with lying or slandering. All a man says may be as true as the Bible; and yet
                    the saying of it is evil-speaking. For evil-speaking is neither more nor less
                    than speaking evil of an absent person; relating something evil which was really
                    done or said by one that is not present when it is related.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">The original μηδένα βλασφημεῖν
                            is a prohibition against seditious language (cf. βλασφημέω in Liddell
                            and Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, as well as
                            Bauer’s commentary in Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Greek-English Lexicon</hi>), but without reference to the presence
                            or absence of the person blasphemed. This point is ignored in the
                            standard commentaries; it is not even made in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Notes</hi> on this text. But see No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.11 and n.</p></note> Suppose, having
                    seen a man drunk, or heard him curse or swear, I tell this when he is absent, it
                    is evil-speaking. In our language this is also by an extremely proper name
                    termed ‘backbiting’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. both Johnson’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi> and <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>; they agree with
                            Wesley’s stress on malice toward <hi rend="italic">absent</hi>
                            persons.</p></note> Nor is there any <hi n="02:253"/> material
                    difference between this and what we usually style ‘talebearing’. If the tale be
                    delivered in a soft and quiet manner (perhaps with expressions of goodwill to
                    the person, and of hope that things may not be quite so bad) then we call it
                        ‘whispering’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">King John</hi>, IV.ii.188-89: ‘When
                            they talk of him, they shake their heads / And whisper one another in
                            the ear.’</p></note> But in whatever manner it be done the thing is the
                    same—the same in substance if not in circumstance. Still it is evil-speaking;
                    still this command, ‘Speak evil of no man,’ is trampled under foot if we relate
                    to another the fault of a third person when he is not present to answer for
                    himself.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And how extremely common is this sin among all orders and degrees of
                    men! How do high and low, rich and poor, wise and foolish, learned and
                    unlearned, run into it continually! Persons who differ from each other in all
                    things else, nevertheless agree in this. How few are there that can testify
                    before God, ‘I am clear in this matter I have always set a watch before my
                    mouth, and kept the door of my lips!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 141:3.</p></note> What conversation do you
                    hear of any considerable length whereof evil-speaking is not one ingredient? And
                    that even among persons who in the general have the fear of God before their
                        eyes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            3:18.</p></note> and do really desire to have a conscience void of
                    offence toward God and toward man.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Acts 24:16.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. And the very commonness of this sin makes it difficult to be avoided. As
                    we are encompassed with it on every side, so if we are not deeply sensible of
                    the danger, and continually guarding against it, we are liable to be carried
                    away by the torrent. In this instance almost the whole of mankind is, as it
                    were, in a conspiracy against us. And their example steals upon us we know not
                    how, so that we insensibly slide into the imitation of it. Besides, it is
                    recommended from within as well as from without. There is scarce any wrong
                    temper in the mind of man which may not be occasionally gratified by it, and
                    consequently incline us to it. It gratifies our <hi rend="italic">pride</hi> to
                    relate those faults of others whereof we think ourselves not to be guilty. <hi
                        rend="italic">Anger</hi>, resentment, and all unkind tempers are indulged by
                    speaking against those with whom we are displeased. And in many cases, by
                    reciting the sins of their neighbours, men indulge their own ‘foolish and
                    hurtful desires’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:9 (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Notes</hi>).</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. Evil-speaking is the more difficult to be avoided because it frequently
                    attacks us in disguise. We speak thus out of a noble, <pb n="02:254"/>generous
                    (’tis well if we do not say, ‘holy’) ‘indignation’ against these vile creatures!
                    We commit sin from mere hatred of sin! We serve the devil out of pure zeal for
                    God! It is merely in order to punish the wicked that we run into this
                    wickedness. So do ‘the passions’ (as one speaks) ‘all justify themselves’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Francis
                            Hutcheson, ‘Concerning Moral Good and Evil’, in <hi rend="italic">An
                                Inquiry Into the Original of Our Ideas of Beauty and Virtue</hi>
                            (1726), Treatise II, Sec. II, viii. 152. Cf. also No. 92, ‘On Zeal’, §2.
                            For other references to Hutcheson, cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own
                            Spirit’, §5 and n. See also Thomas Browne, <hi rend="italic">Religio
                                Medici</hi> (1642), I.19: ‘…as reason is a rebel unto faith, so
                            passion unto reason;’ and Pope’s <hi rend="italic">Essay on Man</hi>,
                            ii.42: ‘What reason weaves by passion is undone.’</p></note> and palm
                    sin upon us under the veil of holiness!</p>
                <p n="5">5. But is there no way to avoid the snare? Unquestionably there is. Our
                    blessed Lord has marked out a plain way for his followers in the words above
                    recited. None who warily and steadily walks in this path will ever fall into
                    evil-speaking. This rule is either an infallible preventive or a certain cure of
                    it. In the preceding verses our Lord had said, ‘Woe to the world because of
                        offences!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 18:7.</p></note> Unspeakable misery will arise in the world from
                    this baleful fountain. (‘Offences’ are all things whereby anyone is turned out
                    of, or hindered in, the ways of God.) ‘For it must be that offences come.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic"
                                >Ibid.</hi></p></note> Such is the nature of things; such the
                    weakness, folly, and wickedness of mankind. ‘But woe to that man’, miserable is
                    that man, ‘by whom the offence cometh. Wherefore if thy hand, thy foot, thine
                    eye cause thee to offend’—if the most dear enjoyment, the most beloved and
                    useful person, turn thee out of or hinder thee in the way—‘pluck it out, cut
                    them off, and cast them from thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 18:7-9.</p></note> But how can we avoid
                    giving offence to some, and being offended at others? Especially suppose they
                    are quite in the wrong, and we see it with our own eyes? Our Lord here teaches
                    us how: he lays down a sure method of avoiding offences and evil-speaking
                    together. ‘If thy brother shall sin against thee, go and tell him of his fault,
                    between thee and him alone: if he will hear thee, thou hast gained thy brother.
                    But if he will not hear thee, take with thee one or two more, that by the mouth
                    of two or three witnesses every word may be established. And if he will not hear
                    them, tell it to the church: but if he will not hear the church, let him be to
                    thee as an heathen man and a publican.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. First, ‘if thy brother shall sin against thee, go and tell him of his
                    fault, between thee and him alone.’ The most literal way of <pb n="02:255"
                    />following this first rule, where it is practicable, is the best. Therefore, if
                    thou seest with thine own eyes a brother, a fellow-Christian, commit undeniable
                    sin, or hearest it with thine own ears, so that it is impossible for thee to
                    doubt the fact, then thy part is plain: take the very first opportunity of going
                    to him; and if thou canst have access, ‘tell him of his fault between thee and
                    him alone.’ Indeed great care is to be taken that this is done in a right <hi
                        rend="italic">spirit</hi>, and in a right <hi rend="italic">manner</hi>. The
                    success of a reproof greatly depends on the spirit wherein it is given.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 65, ‘The
                            Duly of Reproving our Neighbour’.</p></note> Be not therefore wanting in
                    earnest prayer to God that it may be given in a lowly spirit; with a deep,
                    piercing conviction that it is God alone who maketh thee to differ, and that if
                    any good be done by what is now spoken, God doth it himself. Pray that he would
                    guard thy heart, enlighten thy mind, and direct thy tongue to such words as he
                    may please to bless. See that thou speak in a meek as well as a lowly spirit;
                    ‘for the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of God.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:20.</p></note> If he
                    ‘be overtaken in a fault’, he can no otherwise be ‘restored’ than ‘in the spirit
                    of meekness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Gal. 6:1.</p></note> If he ‘opposes’ the truth, yet he cannot be
                    ‘brought to the knowledge’ thereof but by ‘gentleness’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:25.</p></note>
                    Still speak in a spirit of tender love, ‘which many waters cannot quench’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">S. of S.
                        8:7.</p></note> If love is not conquered, it conquers all things. Who can
                    tell the force of love?</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Love can bow down the stubborn neck,</l>
                    <l>The stone to flesh convert;</l>
                    <l>Soften and melt and pierce and break</l>
                    <l>An adamantine heart.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley,
                            ‘Against Hope, Believing in Hope’, in John and Charles Wesley, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1740), p. 157 (<hi
                                rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi> I.329).</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p>Confirm then your love toward him, and you will thereby ‘heap coals of fire upon
                    his head’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Prov. 25:22; Rom. 12:20.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. But see that the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> also wherein you speak be
                    according to the gospel of Christ. Avoid everything in look, gesture, word, and
                    tone of voice that savours of <hi rend="italic">pride</hi> or self-sufficiency.
                    Studiously avoid everything magisterial or dogmatical; everything that looks
                    like arrogance or assuming. Beware of the most distant approach to disdain,
                    overbearing, or <hi rend="italic">contempt</hi>. With equal care <pb n="02:256"
                    />avoid all appearance of <hi rend="italic">anger</hi>, and though you use great
                    plainness of speech, yet let there be no reproach, no railing accusation, no
                    token of any warmth but that of love. Above all, let there be no shadow of <hi
                        rend="italic">hate</hi> or ill will, no bitterness or sourness of
                    expression; but use the air and language of sweetness, as well as gentleness,
                    that all may appear to flow from love in the heart. And yet this sweetness need
                    not hinder your speaking in the most serious and solemn manner, as far as may be
                    in the very words of the oracles of God (for there are none like them), and as
                    under the eye of him who is coming to judge the quick and [the] dead.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 4:1; 1
                            Pet. 4:5. See also ‘The Apostles’ Creed’ and ‘The Creed Commonly Called
                            Nicene’ (BCP).</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. If you have not an opportunity of speaking to him in person, or cannot
                    have access, you may do it by a messenger, by a common friend in whose prudence
                    as well as uprightness you can throughly confide. Such a person, speaking in
                    your name, and in the spirit and manner above described, may answer the same
                    end, and in a good degree supply your lack of service. Only beware you do not
                    feign want of opportunity in order to shun the cross; neither take it for
                    granted that you cannot have access without ever making the trial. Whenever you
                    can speak in your own person it is far better. But you should rather do it by
                    another than not at all: this way is better than none.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But what if you can neither speak yourself, nor find such a messenger as
                    you can confide in? If this is really the case, it then only remains to write.
                    And there may be some circumstances which make this the most advisable way of
                    speaking. One of these circumstances is when the person with whom we have to do
                    is of so warm and impetuous a temper as does not easily bear reproof, especially
                    from an equal or inferior. But it may be so introduced and softened in writing
                    as to make it far more tolerable. Besides, many will read the very same words
                    which they could not bear to hear. It does not give so violent a shock to their
                    pride, nor so sensibly touch their honour. And suppose it makes little
                    impression at first, they will perhaps give it a second reading, and upon
                    farther consideration lay to heart what before they disregarded. If you add your
                    name, this is nearly the same thing as going to him and speaking in person. And
                    this should always be done, unless it be rendered improper by some very
                    particular reason.</p>
                <p n="5"><pb n="02:257"/>5. It should be well observed, not only that this is a step
                    which our Lord absolutely commands us to take, but that he commands us to take
                    this step first, before we attempt any other. No alternative is allowed, no
                    choice of anything else; this is the way; walk thou in it.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 30:21.</p></note> It
                    is true he enjoins us, if need require, to take two other steps. But they are to
                    be taken successively <hi rend="italic">after</hi> this step, and neither of
                    them <hi rend="italic">before</hi> it. Much less are we to take any other step
                    either before or beside this. To do anything else, or not to do this, is
                    therefore equally inexcusable.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Do not think to excuse yourself for taking an entirely different step by
                    saying, ‘Why, I did not speak to anyone till I was so <hi rend="italic"
                        >burdened</hi> that I could not refrain.’ You was burdened! It was no wonder
                    you should, unless your conscience was seared;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                        n="24"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Tim. 4:2. Cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of
                            Our Own Spirit’, §19 and n.</p></note> for you was under the guilt of
                    sin, of disobeying a plain commandment of God. You ought immediately to have
                    gone and ‘told your brother of his fault between you and him alone’. If you did
                    not, how should you be other than burdened (unless your heart was utterly
                    hardened) while you was trampling the command of God under foot, and ‘hating
                    your brother in your heart’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Zech. 7:10.</p></note> And what a way have you
                    found to <hi rend="italic">unburden</hi> yourself? God reproves you for a sin of
                    omission, for not telling your brother of his fault; and you comfort yourself
                    under his reproof by a sin of commission, by telling your brother’s fault to
                    another person! Ease bought by sin is a dear purchase: I trust in God you will
                    have no ease, but will be burdened so much the more till you ‘go to your brother
                    and tell him’, and no one else.</p>
                <p n="7">7. I know but of one exception to this rule. There may be a peculiar case
                    wherein it is necessary to accuse the guilty, though absent, in order to
                    preserve the innocent. For instance: you are acquainted with the design which a
                    man has against the property or life of his neighbour. Now the case may be so
                    circumstanced that there is no other way of hindering that design from taking
                    effect but the making it known without delay to him against whom it is laid. In
                    this case therefore this rule is set aside, as is that of the Apostle, ‘Speak
                    evil of no man,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Titus 3:2.</p></note> and it is lawful, yea, it is our bounden duty to
                    speak evil of an absent person, in order to prevent his doing evil to others and
                    himself at the same time. But <pb n="02:258"/>remember meanwhile that all
                    evil-speaking is in its own nature deadly poison. Therefore if you are sometimes
                    constrained to use it as a medicine, yet use it with fear and trembling, seeing
                    it is so dangerous a medicine that nothing but absolute necessity can excuse
                    your using it at all. Accordingly use it as seldom as possible; never but when
                    there is such a necessity. And even then use as little of it as is possible;
                    only so much as is necessary for the end proposed. At all other times, ‘go and
                    tell him of his fault, between thee and him alone.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. But what ‘if he will not hear’? If he repay evil for good? If he be
                    enraged rather than convinced? What if he hear to no purpose, and go on still in
                    the evil of his way? We must expect this will frequently be the case; the
                    mildest and tenderest reproof will have no effect, but the blessing we wished
                    for another will return into our own bosom.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27"
                        n="27"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 35:13.</p></note> And what are we to
                    do then? Our Lord has given us a clear and full direction. Then ‘take with thee
                    one or two more:’ this is the second step. Take one or two whom you know to be
                    of a loving spirit, lovers of God and of their neighbour. See likewise that they
                    be of a lowly spirit, and ‘clothed with humility’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:5.</p></note> Let
                    them also be such as are meek and gentle, patient and longsuffering; not apt to
                    ‘return evil for evil, or railing for railing, but contrariwise blessing’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            3:9.</p></note> Let them be men of understanding, such as are endued
                    with wisdom from above; and men unbiased, free from partiality, free from
                    prejudice of any kind. Care should likewise be taken that both the persons and
                    their characters be well known to him. And let those that are acceptable to him
                    be chosen preferable to any others.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Love will dictate the manner wherein they should proceed, according to
                    the nature of the case. Nor can any one particular manner be prescribed for all
                    cases. But perhaps in general one might advise, before they enter upon the thing
                    itself, let them mildly and affectionately declare that they have no anger or
                    prejudice toward him, and that it is merely from a principle of goodwill that
                    they now come, or at all concern themselves with his affairs. To make this the
                    more apparent, they might then calmly attend to your repetition of your former
                    conversation with him, and to what he said in his own defence, before they
                    attempted to <pb n="02:259"/>determine anything. After this they would be better
                    able to judge in what manner to proceed, ‘that by the mouth of two or three
                    witnesses, every word might be established’; that whatever you have said may
                    have its full force by the additional weight of their authority.</p>
                <p n="3">3. In order to this, may they not, (1). Briefly repeat what you spoke, and
                    what he answered? (2). Enlarge upon, open, and confirm the reasons which you had
                    given? (3). Give weight to your reproof, showing how just, how kind, and how
                    seasonable it was? And, lastly, enforce the advices and persuasions which you
                    had annexed to it? And these may likewise hereafter, if need should require,
                    bear witness of what was spoken.</p>
                <p n="4">4. With regard to this, as well as the preceding rule, we may observe that
                    our Lord gives us no choice, leaves us no alternative, but expressly commands us
                    to do this, and nothing else in the place of it He likewise directs us when to
                    do this. Neither sooner, nor later: namely, <hi rend="italic">after</hi> we have
                    taken the first, and <hi rend="italic">before</hi> we have taken the third step.
                    It is then only that we are authorized to relate the evil another has done to
                    those whom we desire to bear a part with us in this great instance of brotherly
                    love. But let us have a care how we relate it to any other person till both
                    these steps have been taken. If we neglect to take these, or if we take any
                    others, what wonder if we are burdened still! For we are sinners against God and
                    against our neighbour. And how fairly soever we may colour it, yet if we have
                    any conscience our sin will find us out, and bring a burden upon our soul.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. That we may be throughly instructed in this weighty affair our Lord
                    has given us a still farther direction. ‘If he will not hear them’—then and not
                    till then—‘tell it to the church.’ This is the third step. All the question is
                    how this word, ‘the church’, is here to be understood. But the very nature of
                    the thing will determine this beyond all reasonable doubt. You cannot tell it to
                    the national church, the whole body of men termed ‘the Church of England’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Note this
                            unselfconscious assumption that ‘church’, in its broader denotation, is
                            the Church of England. For Wesley’s understanding of himself as
                            Anglican, see Vol. 1, Intro., p. 88.</p></note> Neither would it answer
                    any Christian end if you could: this therefore is not the meaning of the word.
                    Neither can you tell it to that whole body of people in England with whom you
                    have a more immediate connexion. Nor indeed would this answer <pb n="02:260"
                    />any good end: the word therefore is not to be understood thus. It would not
                    answer any valuable end to tell the faults of every particular member to ‘the
                    church’ (if you would so term it), the congregation or <hi rend="italic"
                        >society</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                            rend="footnote text">I.e., the United Society of Methodists, here
                            understood as an <hi rend="italic">ecclesiola</hi>, most of whose
                            members were registered on one or another parish roll in the Church of
                            England.</p></note> united together in London. It remains that you tell
                    it to the elder or elders of the church, to those who are overseers of that
                    flock of Christ to which you both belong, who watch over yours and his soul ‘as
                    they that must give account’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:17.</p></note> And this should be done, if
                    it conveniently can, in the presence of the person concerned, and, though
                    plainly, yet with all the tenderness and love which the nature of the thing will
                    admit. It properly belongs to their office to determine concerning the behaviour
                    of those under their care, and to ‘rebuke’, according to the demerit of the
                    offence, ‘with all authority’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Titus 2:15.</p></note> When therefore you have done
                    this, you have done all which the Word of God or the law of love requireth of
                    you. You are not now partaker of his sin, but if he perish his blood is on his
                    own head.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ezek. 33:4-6.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. Here also let it be observed that this, and no other, is the third step
                    which we are to take; and that we are to take it in its order, after the other
                    two; not before the second, much less the first, unless in some very particular
                    circumstance. Indeed in one case the second step may coincide with this: they
                    may be, in a manner, one and the same. The elder or elders of the church may be
                    so connected with the offending brother that they may set aside the necessity,
                    and supply the place of the ‘one or two’ witnesses. So that it may suffice to
                    tell it to them after you have told it to your brother, ‘between you and him
                    alone’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. When you have done this you have delivered your own soul.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 14:14,
                            20; 33:9. Cf. above, No. 36, ‘The Law Established through Faith, ΙI’,
                            I.5 and n.</p></note> ‘If he will not hear the church’, if he persist in
                    his sin, ‘let him be to thee as an heathen man and a publican.’ You are under no
                    obligation to think of him any more—only when you commend him to God in prayer.
                    You need not speak of him any more, but leave him to his own Master. Indeed you
                    still owe to him, as to all other heathens, earnest, tender goodwill. You owe
                    him courtesy, and as occasion offers all the offices of humanity. But have no
                    friendship, no familiarity with him; no other intercourse than with an open
                    heathen.</p>
                <p n="4"><pb n="02:261"/>4. But if this be the rule by which Christians walk, which
                    is the land where the Christians live?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, IV.1 and n.</p></note> A few you may possibly
                    find scattered up and down who make a conscience of observing it. But how very
                    few! How thinly scattered upon the face of the earth! And where is there any
                    body of men that universally walk thereby? Can we find them in Europe? Or, to go
                    no farther, in Great Britain or Ireland? I fear not: I fear we may search these
                    kingdoms throughout, and yet search in vain. Alas for the Christian world! Alas
                    for Protestants, for Reformed Christians! ‘O who will rise up with me against
                    the wicked? Who will take God’s part against the evil-speakers?’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 94:16
                            (BCP). ‘</p></note>Art thou the man?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                        n="38"><p rend="footnote text">1 Kgs. 13:14.</p></note> By the grace of God
                    wilt thou be one who art not carried away by the torrent? Art thou fully
                    determined, God being thy helper, from this very hour to set a watch, a
                    continual ‘watch before thy mouth, and keep the door of thy lips’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            141:3.</p></note> From this hour wilt thou walk by this rule, ‘speaking
                    evil of no man’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Titus 3:2.</p></note> If thou seest thy brother do evil, wilt thou
                    ‘tell him of his fault between thee and him alone’? Afterwards ‘take one or two
                    witnesses’, and then only ‘tell it to the church’? If this be the full purpose
                    of thy heart, then learn one lesson well: <hi rend="italic">Hear evil of no
                        man</hi>. If there were no hearers, there would be no speakers of evil. And
                    is not (according to the vulgar proverb) the receiver as bad as the thief? If
                    then any begin to speak evil in thy hearing, check him immediately. Refuse to
                    hear the voice of the charmer, charm he never so sweetly:<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 58:5 (BCP).</p></note>
                    let him use ever so soft a manner, so mild an accent, ever so many professions
                    of goodwill for him whom he is stabbing in the dark, whom he smiteth under the
                    fifth rib.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Sam. 2:23; 3:27.</p></note> Resolutely refuse to hear, though the
                    whisperer complain of being ‘burdened’ till he speak. Burdened! thou fool, dost
                    thou ‘travail with’ thy cursed <hi rend="italic">secret</hi>, ‘as a woman
                    travaileth with child’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 13:8; Rev. 12:2, etc.</p></note> Go then
                    and be delivered of thy burden, in the way the Lord hath ordained. First, ‘go
                    and tell thy brother of his fault, between thee and him alone.’ Next, ‘take with
                    thee one or two’ common friends, and tell him in their presence. If neither of
                    these steps take effect, then ‘tell it to the church.’ But at the peril of thy
                    soul tell it to no one else, either before or after, unless in that one exempt
                    case, when it is absolutely needful to preserve <pb n="02:262"/>the innocent.
                    Why shouldst thou burden another as well as thyself by making him partaker of
                    thy sin?</p>
                <p n="5">5. O that all you who bear the reproach of Christ,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:26.</p></note> who are
                    in derision called ‘Methodists’, would set an example to the Christian world, so
                    called, at least in this one instance! Put ye away evil-speaking, talebearing,
                    whispering: let none of them proceed out of your mouth. See that you ‘speak evil
                    of no man;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Titus 3:2.</p></note> of the absent nothing but good. If ye must be
                    distinguished, whether ye will or no, let this be the distinguishing mark of a
                    Methodist: ‘He censures no man behind his back: by this fruit ye may know
                        him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 7:16, 20.</p></note> What a blessed effect of this self-denial
                    should we quickly feel in our hearts! How would our ‘peace flow as a
                        river’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 48:18.</p></note> when we thus ‘followed peace with all men’!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            12:14.</p></note> How would the love of God abound in our own souls
                    while we thus confirmed our love to our brethren! And what an effect would it
                    have on all that were united together in the name of the Lord Jesus! How would
                    brotherly love continually increase when this grand hindrance of it was removed!
                    All the members of Christ’s mystical body would then <hi rend="italic">naturally
                        care for</hi> each other: ‘If one member suffered, all would suffer with it;
                    if one was honoured, all would rejoice with it;’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 12:26.</p></note>
                    and everyone would love his brother ‘with a pure heart fervently’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        1:22.</p></note> Nor is this all: but what an effect might this have even on
                    the wild unthinking world! How soon would they descry in us what they could not
                    find among all the thousands of their brethren, and cry (as Julian the Apostate
                    to his heathen courtiers), ‘See how these Christians love one another!’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">See No. 22,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, III.18 and n.</p></note> By this chiefly
                    would God convince the world, and prepare them also for his kingdom, as we may
                    easily learn from those remarkable words in our Lord’s last, solemn prayer: ‘I
                    pray for them who will believe in me, that they all may be one, as thou, Father,
                    art in me, and I in thee; that the world may believe that thou hast sent
                        me!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 17:20-21.</p></note> The Lord hasten the time! The Lord enable us
                    thus to love one another, not only ‘in word and in tongue, but in deed and in
                        truth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 John 3:18.</p></note> even as Christ hath loved us.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
