<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 6: The Righteousness of Faith</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon006</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 6: The Righteousness of Faith</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="200" to="215"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="200"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>John Wesley was not as ebullient an orator as George Whitefield or even his
                    brother Charles. And yet his preaching in the years just after 1738 seems to
                    have been attended with more hysterical responses from his hearers. In the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, June 12, 1742, he records preaching on ‘the
                    righteousness of faith ‘from his father’s tombstone at Epworth.’ While I was
                    speaking several dropped down as dead; and among the rest such a cry was heard
                    of sinners groaning for the righteousness of faith as almost drowned my voice.’
                    An even more tumultuous scene in Wapping is recounted in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, June 15, 1739. Hysterical phenomena, as side effects of his
                    preaching, receive an occasional mention in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>
                    from 1739 through 1744. They seem to have tapered off thereafter.</p>
                <p>A credible hypothesis concerning these phenomena—and the contrast between the
                    effects of John Wesley’s preaching in this period and that of other
                    evangelicals—has been offered by Bernard Holland, ‘“A Species of Madness”: The
                    Effect of John Wesley’s Early Preaching’, WHS, XXXIX.77-85, and this is
                    confirmed in large part in this sermon on ‘the righteousness of faith’.
                    Holland’s point is that whereas Whitefield and Charles Wesley sought consciously
                    (and fervently) to drive their hearers to a ‘conviction of sin’, they spared
                    them the extremes of <hi rend="italic">despair</hi> by suggesting that once
                    penitents began to ‘groan’ <hi rend="italic">for</hi> faith, this was in itself
                    a proleptic sign of their acceptance even before their conscious sense of
                    assurance of forgiveness. Robert Philip, in his <hi rend="italic">Life and Times
                        of…Whitefield</hi> (1837), pp. 580-83, stresses this distinction, and
                    Melville Horne, John Fletcher’s curate at Madeley, who had heard Whitefield and
                    both the Wesleys, reached much the same conclusion: ‘[Charles Wesley, rather
                    than] denouncing wrath on sincere penitents…comforted them by insinuating that
                    they were in a salvable state…. To the best of my knowledge, Mr. John Wesley did
                    not admit this distinction into his pulpit;’ cf. <hi rend="italic">An
                        Investigation…of Justifying Faith</hi>, pp. 28 ff.</p>
                <p>Holland, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, p. 81, suggests that it was on
                    principle that John drove his penitent and half-penitent hearers out of any
                    refuge of hope to real despair: ‘In spite of their longing to be reconciled to
                    God, they were <pb n="201"/>nevertheless still damned until faith was given
                    them. It was <hi rend="italic">this</hi> that so intensified the feeling of
                    helplessness and anxiety…that some fell down, or cried out or became delirious.’
                    Cf. William Sargant, <hi rend="italic">Battle for the Mind</hi> (New York,
                    Doubleday, 1957), p.78, for a psychiatric comment on John Wesley’s impact on
                    guilt-ridden audiences in this period; but see also Ian Ramage, <hi rend="italic">Battle for the Free Mind</hi> (London, Allen and Unwin, 1967),
                    pp. 238-59, for a useful critique of Sargant. It is in this sense that we can
                    understand Wesley’s candid admission in <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>
                    that ‘it is my endeavour to drive all I can into what <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
                    may term another species of “madness”, …which I term “repentance” or
                    “conviction”’ as preparatory to the gift of faith (see Pt. I, VII.12; also
                    VII.11, 13-15, in Vol. 11, pp. 196-99 of this edn.). Later, the starkness of
                    this demand for despair was softened, and with it came a proportional decrease
                    in hysterical concomitants. In 1746 it is asked in Conference, ‘But can it be
                    conceived that God has any regard to the sincerity of an unbeliever?’ The
                    answer, now, is different from earlier ones: ‘Yes; so much that if he persevere
                    therein, God will infallibly give him faith;’ cf. MS Minutes, 1746, §20.</p>
                <p>The following year the efficacy of <hi rend="italic">sincerity</hi> in repentance
                    is actually emphasized; <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, June 16, 1747. In 1767, in
                    light of his experiences in the Revival and in reaction to the polemics of the
                    Calvinists, Wesley came round to what amounts to an abandonment of his
                    insistences of 1739-44: ‘It is high time for us…to return to the plain word, “He
                    that feareth God and worketh righteousness is <hi rend="italic">accepted</hi>
                    with him”’ (JWJ, Dec. 30, 1767). And in a very late sermon (1791) he actually
                    deplores deliberate efforts to drive persons to despair as a means of bringing
                    them to faith (see No.106, ‘On Faith, Heb.11:6’, I.11-12; see also No. 117, ‘On
                    the Discoveries of Faith’, §§11-15).</p>
                <p>This present sermon, however, is focused on a radical contrast between ‘the
                    righteousness of the <hi rend="italic">law</hi>’ and ‘the righteousness of <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>’, between the two covenants of <hi rend="italic">works</hi> and of <hi rend="italic">grace</hi>. The righteousness of the
                    law, with its corresponding covenant of works, demands absolute and perfected
                    perfection; nothing short of this is worth anything at all. The unmistakable
                    inference is that since Adam’s sin <hi rend="italic">this</hi> righteousness is
                    utterly unattainable; hence, despair. The righteousness of faith, on the other
                    hand, is God’s mercy freely given. It is God’s pardon warranted by Christ’s
                    atonement, and therefore both just and justifying. It is worth noticing how
                    relentlessly Wesley builds up the demands of the law, reducing the moralist to
                    despair, and how thoroughly he refutes all objections to a repentant sinner’s
                    eager acceptance of God’s sheer, unmerited mercy (cf. Charlotte Elliott’s later
                    hymn [1834]: ‘Just as I <pb n="202"/>am, without one plea’). Here, then, <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi> is once again unnuanced. Yet also, the residues
                    of Wesley’s holy living tradition reassert themselves and remind us of his
                    constant search for an alternative to any of the traditional polarities.</p>
                <p>Wesley preached on the passage in Rom. 10:5-8 at least seven times between 1740
                    and 1789, twice before this present sermon which was, apparently, written
                    expressly for <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>. For a list of variant readings in the
                    editions published in Wesley’s lifetime, see Appendix, Vol. 4, ‘Wesley’s
                    Text’.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Justification by Faith</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 10:5-8</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Moses describeth the righteousness which is of the law, that
                        the man which doeth those things shall live by them.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise:
                        Say not in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? (that is, to bring
                        Christ down from above;)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Or, Who shall descend into the deep? (that is, to bring Christ
                        again from the dead.)</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">But what saith it? The word is nigh thee, even in thy mouth
                        and in thy heart; that is, the word of faith which we preach.</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matthew Henry had recognized the echoes here of Isa.
                            59:21, ‘…in thy mouth’, and Jer. 31:33, ‘…in thy heart’; Poole and
                            Wesley (in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>) ignore these texts. All
                            ignore the remarkable parallel in the Septuagint translation of Deut.
                            30:11-14, which St. Paul would have known as a matter of course and
                            would have taken as a reference to Torah: ‘For this Torah which I give
                            thee this day is not too great nor too far from thee. It is not in
                            heaven saying, “Who shall go up for us to heaven and take it for us?” …
                            Nor is it beyond the sea saying, “Who will cross beyond the sea for us
                            and receive it for us?” … But the word [i.e., God’s Torah] is near to
                            thee, in thy mouth and in thy heart and in thy hands, to do it [i.e.,
                            obey it].’ In Baruch 3:29 and 4 Esd. 4:7-9, it is denied that wisdom is
                            so accessible to human grasp; see R. H. Charles, <hi rend="italic">Pseudepigrapha</hi> (Oxford, Clarendon Press, 1913), II.564-65. The
                            parallel, cited by Sugden, I.132, to Jubilees 24:32, is merely verbal.
                            The point here for Wesley is that St. Paul had then set the
                            ‘righteousness of the law’ and the ‘righteousness of faith’ in
                            antithesis as the contrast between the Adamic ‘covenant of works’ and
                            the ‘covenant of grace which God through Christ hath established with
                            men in all ages’. It is this contrast Wesley intends to stress here.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. The Apostle does not here oppose the covenant given by Moses to the
                    covenant given by Christ. If we ever imagined this it was for want of observing
                    that the latter as well as the former part of these words were spoken by Moses
                    himself to the people of Israel, and that concerning the covenant which then
                        was.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Deut. 30:11, 12, 14.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> But it is <pb n="203"/>the
                    covenant of <hi rend="italic">grace</hi> which God through Christ hath
                    established with men in all ages (as well before, and under the Jewish
                    dispensation, as since God was manifest in the flesh), which St. Paul here
                    opposes to the covenant of <hi rend="italic">works</hi>, made with Adam while in
                    paradise, but commonly supposed to be the only covenant which God had made with
                    man, particularly by those Jews of whom the Apostle writes.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This dialectic between the two
                            covenants of works and grace had not been central in Latin or Lutheran
                            theologies, but had been for Reformed dogmatics in general (see Heinrich
                            Heppe, <hi rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, ch. xvi, pp. 371-409);
                            Wesley would have come by it through the Puritans (Ames and Perkins, and
                            espec. the <hi rend="italic">Westminster Confession</hi>, VII.2 ff.). A
                            classical statement of ‘covenant soteriology’ was in Cocceius, <hi rend="italic">Summa doctrinae</hi> (1648); see above, p. 81. For
                            Wesley’s interest in this idea see in his selections in the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, especially John Preston, ‘The New
                            Covenant or the Saints’ Portion’ (1629), x.81-84; Isaac Ambrose,
                            ‘Looking Unto Jesus’ (1658), Bk. II, ch. ii, Sect. II, in
                            XIV.85-99;Jeremy Taylor, <hi rend="italic">Holy Dying</hi> (ch. v, Sect.
                            iv, XVI.200-3; William Beveridge, ‘Thoughts on Religion’, Arts. IX, X,
                            XLVII.61-78. Wesley’s own variations on this theme may be seen in Nos.
                            12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §20; 35, ‘The Law Established
                            through Faith, I’, II.3-4; 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’, §19. Cf. also
                                <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, May 13, 1746, and <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Heb. 8:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Of these it was that he so affectionately speaks in the beginning of
                    this chapter. ‘My heart’s desire and prayer to God for Israel is, that they may
                    be saved. For I bear them record that they have a zeal for God, but not
                    according to knowledge. For they, being ignorant of God’s righteousness’ (of the
                    justification that flows from his mere grace and mercy, freely forgiving our
                    sins through the Son of his love, through the redemption which is in
                        Jesus),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note> ‘and seeking to establish their own righteousness’
                    (their own holiness, antecedent to faith in ‘him that justifieth the
                        ungodly’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            4:5.</p>
                    </note> as the ground of their pardon and acceptance), ‘have not
                    submitted themselves unto the righteousness of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:1-3.</p>
                    </note> and
                    consequently seek death in the error of their life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Wisd. 1:12. For Wesley’s
                            other uses of this text from an Apocryphal book, cf. Nos. 21, ‘Sermon on
                            the Mount, I’, §3; 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, I.4;
                            65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, II.3; 115, ‘Dives and
                            Lazarus’, III.2; and 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’, §11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. They were ignorant that ‘Christ is the end of the law for righteousness
                    to everyone that believeth;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 10:4.</p>
                    </note> that by the oblation of <pb n="204"/>himself once offered<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Communion, Prayer of Consecration.</p>
                    </note>
                    he had put an end to the first law or covenant (which indeed was not given by
                    God to Moses, but to Adam in his state of innocence), the strict tenor whereof,
                    without any abatement, was, ‘Do this and live;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 42:18 ; Luke 10:28. In the Colman
                            Collection Vol. XX, there is a MS in Wesley’s hand entitled, ‘The Duty
                            of Receiving the Lord’s Supper’, extracted (in part) from Robert Nelson,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Great Duty of Frequenting the Christian
                                Sacrifice</hi> (1711), but with additions from Wesley himself and
                            other authors. The ‘covenant’ idea does not appear in Nelson but does in
                            Wesley’s MS, fol. 18-23; see espec. fol. 18-19, where he has ‘Try to do
                            this, and live.’ See <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 412, and Vol. 8
                            of this edn.</p>
                    </note> and at the same time purchased for us that
                    better covenant, ‘Believe and live:’ ‘Believe and thou shalt be saved;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                            16:31.</p>
                    </note> now saved both from the guilt and power of sin, and of
                    consequence from the wages of it.</p>
                <p n="4">4. And how many are equally ignorant now, even among those who are called
                    by the name of Christ? How many who have now a ‘zeal for God’, yet have it not
                    ‘according to knowledge’, but are still ‘seeking to establish their own
                    righteousness’ as the ground of their pardon and acceptance, and therefore
                    vehemently refuse to ‘submit themselves unto the righteousness of God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            10:2-3.</p>
                    </note> Surely my heart’s desire and prayer to God for you,
                    brethren, is that ye may be saved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 10:1.</p>
                    </note> And in order to remove
                    this grand stumbling-block out of your way I will endeavour to show, first, what
                    ‘the righteousness’ is ‘which is of the law’, and what ‘the righteousness which
                    is of faith’; secondly, the folly of trusting in ‘the righteousness…of the law’,
                    and the wisdom of ‘submitting to that which is of faith’.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, ‘The righteousness which is of the law saith, The man
                    which doth these things shall live by them.’ Constantly and perfectly observe
                    all these things, to do them, and then thou shalt live for ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. this text
                            expounded literally in Wesley’s sermon on Gen. 1:27, No. 141, ‘The Image
                            of God’, II.1.</p>
                    </note> This law or covenant (usually called the
                    covenant of <hi rend="italic">works</hi>) given by God to man in paradise,
                    required an obedience perfect in all its parts, entire and wanting nothing, as
                    the condition of his eternal continuance in the holiness and happiness wherein
                    he was created.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It required that man should fulfil all righteousness, inward and
                    outward, negative and positive: that he should not only abstain from every idle
                    word, and avoid every evil work, but <pb n="205"/>should keep every affection,
                    every desire, every thought, in obedience to the will of God; that he should
                    continue holy, as he which had created him was holy, both in heart and in all
                    manner of conversation; that he should continue holy, as he which had created
                    him was holy, both in heart and in all manner of conversation; that he should be
                    pure in heart, even as God is pure, perfect as his Father in heaven was
                        perfect;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 5:48.</p>
                    </note> that he should love the Lord his God with all his
                    heart, with all his soul, with all his mind, and with all his strength;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 22:37,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> that he should love every soul which God had made even
                    as God had loved him; that by this universal benevolence he should ‘dwell in God
                    (who is love) and God in him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:16.</p>
                    </note> that he should serve
                    the Lord his God with all his strength, and in all things singly aim at his
                    glory.</p>
                <p n="3">3. These were the things which the righteousness of the law required, that
                    he who did them might live thereby. But it farther required that this entire
                    obedience to God, this inward and outward holiness, this conformity both of
                    heart and life to his will, should be perfect in <hi rend="italic">degree</hi>.
                    No abatement, no allowance could possibly be made for falling short in any
                    degree as to any jot or tittle either of the outward or the inward law. If every
                    commandment relating to outward things was obeyed, yet that was not sufficient
                    unless every one was obeyed with all the strength, in the highest measure and
                    most perfect manner. Nor did it answer the demand of this covenant to love God
                    with every power and faculty, unless he were loved with the full capacity of
                    each, with the whole possibility of the soul.</p>
                <p n="4">4. One thing more was indispensably required by the righteousness of the
                    law, namely that this universal obedience, this perfect holiness both of heart
                    and life, should be perfectly uninterrupted also, should continue without any
                    intermission from the moment wherein God created man, and breathed into his
                    nostrils the breath of life, until the days of his trial should be ended, and he
                    should be confirmed in life everlasting.</p>
                <p n="5">5. The righteousness, then, which is of the law speaketh on this wise.
                    ‘Thou, O man of God, stand fast in love, in the image of God wherein thou art
                    made. If thou wilt remain in life, keep the commandments which are now written
                    in thy heart. Love the Lord thy God with all thy heart. Love as thyself every
                    soul that he hath made. Desire nothing but God. Aim at God in every thought, in
                    every word and work. Swerve not in one motion of <pb n="206"/>body or soul from
                    him, thy mark, and the prize of thy high calling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:14.</p>
                    </note> And
                    let all that is in thee praise his holy name,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 103:1.</p>
                    </note> every power and
                    faculty of thy soul, in every kind, in every degree, and at every moment of
                    thine existence. “This do, and thou shalt live;”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 10:28. Cf. Ezek. 18:19,
                            22; 33:13.</p>
                    </note> thy light shall shine, thy love shall flame more
                    and more, till thou art received up into the house of God in the heavens, to
                    reign with him for ever and ever.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley belabours this demand for absolute
                            perfection to underscore the glaring contrast between human aspirations
                            and the human actuality. But he also believed that since the ideal had
                            been actual in Adam (see Nos. 141, ‘The Image of God’; and 76, ‘On
                            Perfection’, I.1 ff.), we may look forward to its restoration as the
                                ‘<hi rend="italic">fullness</hi> of salvation’. This notion of
                            salvation as the recovery of the <hi rend="italic">imago Dei</hi> is a
                            basic Wesleyan theme; cf. No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by
                                Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. ‘But the righteousness which is of faith speaketh on this wise: Say not
                    in thine heart, Who shall ascend into heaven? that is, to bring down Christ from
                    above’ (as though it were some impossible task which God required thee
                    previously to perform in order to thine acceptance); ‘or, Who shall descend into
                    the deep? that is, to bring up Christ from the dead’ (as though that were still
                    remaining to be done for the sake of which thou wert to be accepted). ‘But what
                    saith it? The word’ (according to the tenor of which thou mayest now be accepted
                    as an heir of life eternal) ‘is nigh thee, even in thy mouth and in thy heart;
                    that is, the word of faith which we preach,’ the new covenant which God hath now
                    established with sinful man through Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 8:8, 13; 12:24. See
                            also Jer. 31:31; 32:40.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. By ‘the righteousness which is of faith’ is meant that condition of
                    justification (and in consequence of present and final salvation, if we endure
                    therein unto the end)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., double justification. See above, No. 5,
                            ‘Justification by Faith’, II.5 and n.; see also Wesley’s letters to
                            Thomas Church, Feb. 2, 1745, and June 17, 1746, and his <hi rend="italic">Letter to a Gentleman at Bristol</hi>, Jan. 6, 1758.
                            Cf. his <hi rend="italic">Remarks on Mr. Hill’s Review</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Remarks on Mr. Hill’s Farrago Double-Distilled</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 341, 345, both in Vol. 13 of
                            this edn.)</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For some of Wesley’s sources here,
                            cf. Richard Baxter, <hi rend="italic">Confession</hi> (1655), pp. 297,
                            344 ff., 362-63; John Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">Imputatio Fidei</hi>,
                            ch. 3 (1); <hi rend="italic">Common Places of Martin Bucer</hi>, tr. and
                            ed. by D. F. Wright, in <hi rend="italic">The Courtenay Library of
                                Reformation Classics</hi> (Appleford, Abingdon, Berks., England, The
                            Sutton Courtenay Press, 1972), IV.162.</p>
                    </note> which was given by God
                    to <hi rend="italic">fallen man</hi> through the merits and mediation of his
                    only begotten Son. This was in part revealed to Adam soon after his fall, being
                    contained in the original promise made to him and his seed concerning the seed
                    of the woman, who should ‘bruise the serpent’s head’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gen.
                                3:15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> It was a little more clearly revealed to
                    Abraham <pb n="207"/>by the angel of God from heaven, saying, ‘By myself have I
                    sworn, saith the Lord’, that ‘in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be
                        blessed.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 22:16, 18.</p>
                    </note> It was yet more fully made known to Moses,
                    to David, and to the prophets that followed; and through them to many of the
                    people of God in their respective generations. But still the bulk even of these
                    were ignorant of it; and very few understood it clearly. Still ‘life and
                    immortality’ were not so ‘brought to light’ to the Jews of old as they are now
                    unto us ‘by the gospel’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 1:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Now this covenant saith not to sinful man, ‘Perform unsinning obedience
                    and live.’ If this were the term, he would have no more benefit by all which
                    Christ hath done and suffered for him than if he was required, in order to
                        life,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Life’
                            rather than an expected ‘live’ appears in all edns. Wesley is evidently
                            here balancing the noun ‘life’, as a state of being against its antonym,
                            ‘the dead’.</p>
                    </note> to ‘ascend into heaven and bring down Christ from
                    above’; or to ‘descend into the deep’, into the invisible world, and ‘bring up
                    Christ from the dead’. It doth not require any impossibility to be done
                    (although to mere man what it requires would be impossible, but not to man
                    assisted by the Spirit of God); this were only to mock human weakness. Indeed,
                    strictly speaking, the covenant of <hi rend="italic">grace</hi> doth not require
                    us to <hi rend="italic">do</hi> anything at all, as absolutely and indispensably
                    necessary in order to our justification, but only to <hi rend="italic">believe</hi> in him who for the sake of his Son and the propitiation which
                    he hath made, ‘justifieth the ungodly that worketh not’, and ‘imputes his faith
                    to him for righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> Even so Abraham ‘believed
                    in the Lord; and he counted it to him for righteousness’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gen.
                                15:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘And he received the sign of circumcision, a
                    seal of the righteousness of faith…; that he might be the father of all them
                    that believe…; that righteousness might be imputed unto them also.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom.
                                4:11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Now it was not written for his sake alone
                    that it (i.e. faith) was imputed to him; but for us also, to whom it shall be
                    imputed’ (to whom faith shall be imputed for righteousness, shall stand in the
                    stead of <pb n="208"/>perfect obedience, in order to our acceptance with God)
                    ‘if we believe on him who raised up Jesus our Lord from the dead; who was
                    delivered’ to death ‘for our offences, and was raised again for our
                        justification’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 4:23-25.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘for the assurance
                    of the remission of our sins, and of a second life to come to them that
                        believe.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">π;
                            The same point, in nearly these words, is made by John Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">Imputatio Fidei</hi>, pp. 15-18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. What saith then the covenant of forgiveness, of unmerited love, of
                    pardoning mercy? ‘Believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou shalt be
                        saved.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            16:31.</p>
                    </note> In the day thou believest, thou shalt surely live.
                    Thou shalt be restored to the favour of God; and in his pleasure is life. Thou
                    shalt be saved from the curse and from the wrath of God. Thou shalt be quickened
                    from the death of sin into the life of righteousness. And if thou endure to the
                    end, believing in Jesus, thou shalt never taste the second death, but having
                    suffered with the Lord shalt also live and reign with him for ever and ever.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Now ‘this word is nigh thee’. This condition of life is plain, easy,
                    always at hand. ‘It is in thy mouth and in thy heart’ through the operation of
                    the Spirit of God. The moment ‘thou believest in thine heart in him whom God
                    hath raised from the dead, and confessest with thy mouth the Lord Jesus as thy
                    Lord and thy God, thou shalt be saved’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:8-9.</p>
                    </note> from condemnation,
                    from the guilt and punishment of thy <hi rend="italic">former</hi> sins, and
                    shalt have power to serve God in true holiness all the <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> days of thy life.</p>
                <p n="11">11. What is the difference then between the ‘righteousness which is of the
                    law’ and the ‘righteousness which is of faith’? Between the first covenant, or
                    the covenant of works, and the second, the covenant of grace? The essential,
                    unchangeable difference is this: the one supposes him to whom it is given to be
                    already holy and happy,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, I.4 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> created in the image and enjoying the favour of God; and
                    prescribes the condition whereon he may continue therein, in love and joy, life
                    and immortality. The other supposes him to whom it is given to be now unholy and
                    unhappy; fallen short of the glorious image of God, having the wrath of God
                    abiding on him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 3:36.</p>
                    </note> and hastening through sin, whereby his soul
                    is <pb n="209"/>dead, to bodily death and death everlasting. And to man in this
                    state it prescribes the condition whereon he may regain the pearl he has lost;
                    may recover the favour, and the image of God, may retrieve the life of God in
                    his soul, and be restored to the knowledge and the love of God, which is the
                    beginning of life eternal.</p>
                <p n="12">12. Again, the covenant of works, in order to man’s <hi rend="italic">continuance</hi> in the favour of God, in his knowledge and love, in
                    holiness and happiness, required of perfect man a <hi rend="italic">perfect</hi>
                    and uninterrupted <hi rend="italic">obedience</hi> to every point of the law of
                    God; whereas the covenant of grace, in order to man’s <hi rend="italic">recovery</hi> of the favour and life of God, requires only <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>—living faith in him who through God justifies him
                    that <hi rend="italic">obeyed not</hi>.</p>
                <p n="13">13. Yet again: the covenant of works required of Adam and all his children
                    to <hi rend="italic">pay the price themselves</hi>, in consideration of which
                    they were to receive all the future blessings of God. But in the covenant of
                    grace, seeing we have nothing to pay, God ‘frankly forgives us all’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            7:42.</p>
                    </note> provided only that we believe in him who hath <hi rend="italic">paid the price for us</hi>; who hath given himself a
                    ‘propitiation for our sins, for the sins of the whole world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="14">14. Thus the first covenant required what is now <hi rend="italic">afar
                        off</hi> from all the children of men, namely, unsinning obedience, which is
                    far from those who are ‘conceived and born in sin’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 51:5. See also BCP,
                            Baptism, Exhortation. This phrase, borrowed by Cranmer from Archbishop
                            Herman von Wied, remains in the Church of England text. The idea in
                            altered forms is retained in the Scottish and South African rites; the
                            phrase was dropped from the American Episcopal Prayer Book in
                        1928.</p>
                    </note> whereas the second requires what is nigh at hand, as though
                    it should say, Thou art sin: God is love. Thou by sin art fallen short of the
                    glory of God; yet there is mercy with him. Bring then all thy sins to the
                    pardoning God, and they shall vanish away as a cloud. If thou wert not ungodly
                    there would be no room for him to justify thee as ungodly. But now draw near, in
                    full assurance of faith. He speaketh, and it is done. Fear not, only believe;
                    for even the just God ‘justifieth all that believe in Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. These things considered, it will be easy to show, as I proposed to
                    do in the second place, the folly of trusting in the ‘righteousness which is of
                    the law’, and the wisdom of ‘submitting to the righteousness which is of
                        faith’.<pb n="210"/>
                </p>
                <p>The folly of those who still trust in the ‘righteousness which is of the law’,
                    the terms of which are, ‘Do this and live,’ may abundantly appear from
                        hence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Orig.
                            (1746 and 1754), ‘thence’, altered in Wesley’s hand in Vol. 1 of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, and in the printed errata to that volume;
                            in this instance the revision had also been made in 1769 (followed by
                            1787), while the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> followed the text of
                            1754.</p>
                    </note> They set out wrong. Their very first step is a
                    fundamental mistake. For before they can ever think of claiming any blessing on
                    the terms of this covenant, they must suppose themselves to be in his state with
                    whom this covenant was made. But how vain a supposition is this, since it was
                    made with Adam in a state of innocence. How weak therefore must that whole
                    building be which stands on such a foundation! And how foolish are they who thus
                    build on the sand!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:26-27.</p>
                    </note> Who seem never to
                    have considered that the covenant of works was not given to man when he was dead
                    in trespasses and sins,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> but when he was alive to God,
                    when he knew no sin, but was holy as God is holy;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:21; cf. 1 Pet.
                            1:16.</p>
                    </note> who forget that it was never designed for the <hi rend="italic">recovery</hi> of the favour and life of God once lost, but
                    only for the <hi rend="italic">continuance</hi> and increase thereof, till it
                    should be complete in life everlasting.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note how the covenant of works is reinstated
                            here, by implication, for those who have been justified (who have thus
                            recovered ‘the favour and life of God once lost’) and have thus been
                            started on their way to sanctification. Cf. Nos. 27, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, VII’, §2; 35, ‘The Law Established through Faith, I’, II.6; and
                            45, ‘The New Birth’, III.1. Cf. also JWJ, Jan. 11, 1744, and <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> for Jas. 2:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Neither do they consider, who are thus ‘seeking to establish their own
                    righteousness which is of the law’, what manner of obedience or righteousness
                    that is which the law indispensably requires. It must be perfect and entire in
                    every point, or it answers not the demand of the law. But which of you is able
                    to perform such obedience? Or, consequently, to live thereby? Who among you
                    fulfils every jot and tittle even of the outward commandments of God? Doing
                    nothing, great or small, which God forbids? Leaving nothing undone which he
                    enjoins? Speaking no ‘idle word’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:36.</p>
                    </note> Having your conversation
                    always ‘meet to minister grace to the hearers’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:29.</p>
                    </note> And ‘whether you
                    eat or drink, or whatever you do, doing all to the glory of God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            10:31.</p>
                    </note> And how much less are you able to fulfil all the
                    inward commandments of God? Those which require that every temper and motion of
                    your soul should be holiness unto the Lord? Are you able to ‘love God with all
                    your <pb n="211"/>heart’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Deut. 6:5; Matt. 22:37, etc.</p>
                    </note> To love
                    all mankind as your own soul? To ‘pray without ceasing’? ‘In everything to give
                        thanks’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Thess. 5:17-18.</p>
                    </note> To have God always before you? And to keep
                    every affection, desire, and thought in obedience to his law?</p>
                <p n="3">3. You should farther consider that the righteousness of the law requires,
                    not only the obeying every command of God, negative and positive, internal and
                    external, but likewise in the perfect degree. In every instance whatever the
                    voice of the law is, ‘Thou shalt serve the Lord thy God with all thy
                        strength.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note> It allows no abatement of any
                    kind. It excuses no defect. It condemns every coming short of the full measure
                    of obedience, and immediately pronounces a curse on the offender. It regards
                    only the invariable rules of justice, and saith, ‘I know not to show
                        mercy.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This, of course, was the point at issue in Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">The Merchant of Venice</hi>, which Wesley not only
                            knew but annotated; cf. IV. i. 179-82:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>…In the course of justice none of us</l>
                            <l>Should see salvation: we do pray for mercy,</l>
                            <l>And that same prayer doth teach us all to render</l>
                            <l>The deeds of mercy.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">See also Jas. 2:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <!--The note about Jas. 2:13 is also part of footnote 47.-->
                <p n="4">4. Who then can appear before such a Judge, who is ‘extreme to mark what is
                    done amiss’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            130:3 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> How weak are they who desire to be tried at the
                    bar where ‘no flesh living can be justified’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 143:2; Rom. 3:20; Gal.
                        2:16.</p>
                    </note>—none of the offspring of Adam. For suppose we did now keep
                    every commandment with all our strength; yet one single breach which ever was
                    utterly destroys our whole claim to life. If we have ever offended, in any one
                    point, this righteousness is at an end. For the law condemns all who do not
                    perform uninterrupted as well as perfect obedience. So that according to the
                    sentence of this, for him who hath once sinned, in any degree, ‘there remaineth
                    only a fearful looking for of fiery indignation which shall devour the
                        adversaries’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:26-27.</p>
                    </note> of God.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Is it not then the very foolishness of folly<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 14:24; 15:2,
                        14.</p>
                    </note> for fallen man to seek life by this righteousness? For man,
                    who was ‘shapen in wickedness’, and ‘in sin did his mother conceive him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 51:5
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> man, who <pb n="212"/>is by nature all ‘earthly,
                    sensual, devilish’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> altogether ‘corrupt and
                        abominable’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 53:1 (AV).</p>
                    </note> in whom, till he find grace, ‘dwelleth no
                    good thing’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:18.</p>
                    </note> nay, who cannot of himself think one good
                    thought? Who is indeed all sin, a mere lump of ungodliness, and who commits sin
                    in every breath he draws; whose actual transgressions, in word and deed, are
                    more in number than the hairs of his head! What stupidity, what senselessness
                    must it be for such an unclean, guilty, helpless worm as this to dream of
                    seeking acceptance by ‘his own righteousness’, of living by ‘the righteousness
                    which is of the law’!</p>
                <p n="6">6. Now whatsoever considerations prove the folly of trusting in the
                    ‘righteousness which is of the law’ prove equally the wisdom of submitting to
                    ‘the righteousness which is of God by faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:9.</p>
                    </note> This were easy to be
                    shown with regard to each of the preceding considerations. But to waive this,
                    the wisdom of the first step hereto, the disclaiming our own righteousness,
                    plainly appears from hence, that it is acting according to truth, to the real
                    nature of things. For what is it more than to acknowledge with our heart as well
                    as lips the true state wherein we are?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., repentance; cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, II.1 and n.</p>
                    </note> To acknowledge that we bring with us
                    into the world a corrupt, sinful nature; more corrupt indeed than we can easily
                    conceive, or find words to express? That hereby we are prone to all that is
                    evil, and averse from all that is good; that we are full of pride, self-will,
                    unruly passions, foolish desires; vile and inordinate affections; lovers of the
                    world, lovers of pleasure more than lovers of God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 3:4.</p>
                    </note>
                    That our lives have been no better than our hearts, but many ways ungodly and
                    unholy, insomuch that our actual sins, both in word and deed, have been as the
                    stars of heaven for multitude?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 1:10; 10:22; 28:62.</p>
                    </note> That on all
                    these accounts we are displeasing to him who is of purer eyes than to behold
                        iniquity,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Hab. 1:13.</p>
                    </note> and deserve nothing from him but indignation
                    and wrath and death, the due wages of sin?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 6:23.</p>
                    </note> That we cannot by
                    any of our righteousness (for indeed we have none at all) nor by any of our
                    works (for they are as the tree from which they grow) appease the wrath of God,
                    or avert the punishment we have justly deserved? Yea, that if left to ourselves
                    we shall only wax worse and <pb n="213"/>worse, sink deeper and deeper into sin,
                    offend God more and more both with our evil works and with the evil tempers of
                    our carnal mind, till we fill up the measure of our iniquities, and bring upon
                    ourselves swift destruction?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> And is not this the very
                    state wherein by nature we are? To acknowledge this, then, both with our heart
                    and lips, that is, to disclaim our own righteousness, ‘the righteousness which
                    is of the law’, is to act according to the real nature of things, and
                    consequently is an instance of true wisdom.</p>
                <p n="7">7. The wisdom of submitting to ‘the righteousness of faith’ appears farther
                    from this consideration, that it is ‘the righteousness of God’. I mean here, it
                    is that method of reconciliation with God which hath been chosen and established
                    by God himself, not only as he is the God of wisdom, but as he is the sovereign
                    Lord of heaven and earth, and of every creature which he hath made. Now as it is
                    not meet for man to say unto God, ‘What dost thou?’—as none who is not utterly
                    void of understanding will contend with one that is mightier than he, with him
                    whose kingdom ruleth over all—so it is true wisdom, it is a mark of a sound
                    understanding, to acquiesce in whatever he hath chosen, to say in this as in all
                    things, ‘It is the Lord; let him do what seemeth him good.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Sam. 3:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. It may be farther considered that it was of mere grace, of free love, of
                    undeserved mercy, that God hath vouchsafed to sinful man any way of
                    reconciliation with himself; that we were not cut away from his hand, and
                    utterly blotted out of his remembrance. Therefore whatever method he is pleased
                    to appoint, of his tender mercy, of his unmerited goodness, whereby his enemies,
                    who have so deeply revolted from him, so long and obstinately rebelled against
                    him, may still find favour in his sight, it is doubtless our wisdom to accept it
                    with all thankfulness.</p>
                <p n="9">9. To mention but one consideration more. It is wisdom to aim at the best
                    end by the best means.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. St. Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Summa
                                Theologica</hi>, II. ii, Q. 45.</p>
                    </note> Now the best end which
                    any creature can pursue is happiness in God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Here Wesley’s eudaemonism is explicitly
                            stated and linked to its premise ‘in God’ (μετουσία θεοῦ). This, too, is
                            one of Wesley’s favourite themes. Cf. Nos. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the
                            Heart’, I.12; 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, III.6, 7; 87, ‘The Danger of
                            Riches’, I.12 (for a negative statement); and 149, ‘On Love’, III.4. See
                            also Wesley’s letters to Frances Godfrey, Aug. 2, 1789, and to Thomas
                            Broadbent, Jan. 29, 1791.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Susanna Wesley held
                            the same view. In a letter to her brother, Samuel Annesley, Jan. 20,
                            1722, she had written: ‘Unspeakable are the blessings of privacy and
                            leisure when the mind emerges from the corrupt animality to which she is
                            united, and by a flight peculiar to her nature, soars beyond the bounds
                            of time and place, in contemplation of the Invisible Supreme, whom she
                            perceives to be her only happiness, her proper centre!’ (Moore, I.328).
                            Cf. also John Norris, ‘Contemplation and Love’, in <hi rend="italic">A
                                Collection of Miscellanies</hi> (1723), pp. 238-39, and Bishop
                            Francis Gastrell, <hi rend="italic">The Certainty of Necessity of
                                Religion in General</hi> (1697), 315, 317, 336. See also No. 5,
                            ‘Justification by Faith’, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> And the best end a <pb n="214"/>fallen creature can pursue is the recovery of the favour and image
                    of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            distinctive emphasis here on justification as the recovery of the favour
                            of God (the standard Protestant emphasis) but also the restoration of
                            the lost image of God (the standard catholic emphasis); cf. above, No.
                            1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note> But
                    the best, indeed the only means under heaven given to man whereby he may regain
                    the favour of God, which is better than life itself, or the image of God, which
                    is the true life of the soul, is the submitting to the ‘righteousness which is
                    of faith’, the believing in the only-begotten Son of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 3:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. Whosoever therefore thou art who desirest to be forgiven and
                    reconciled to the favour of God, do not say in thy heart, ‘I must <hi rend="italic">first do this</hi>: I must <hi rend="italic">first</hi>
                    conquer every sin, break off every evil word and work, and do all good to all
                    men; or I must <hi rend="italic">first</hi> go to Church, receive the Lord’s
                    Supper, hear more sermons, and say more prayers.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s controversy with
                            Philip Molther in JWJ, Dec. 31, 1739, over ‘the way to faith’, where
                            Wesley takes a different line: ‘I believe [by contrast with Molther and
                            the Moravians] it right for him who knows he has not faith…to go to
                            church, to communicate, to fast’, etc. Here, then, is an illustration of
                            Wesley’s way of shifting ground according to his opposition. Moravian
                            antinomianism provoked him to defend ‘the means of grace’; Anglican
                            over-confidence in the means of grace calls for a rebuke against any
                            false reliance on them as <hi rend="italic">necessary conditions</hi> of
                            justification.</p>
                    </note> Alas, my brother, thou art clean gone out of
                    the way. Thou art still ‘ignorant of the righteousness of God’, and art ‘seeking
                    to establish thy own righteousness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:3.</p>
                    </note> as the ground of thy
                    reconciliation. Knowest thou not that thou canst do nothing but sin till thou
                    art reconciled to God? Wherefore then dost thou say, I must do this and this <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, and then I shall believe? Nay, but <hi rend="italic">first believe</hi>. Believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, the
                    propitiation for thy sins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 2:2; 4:10.</p>
                    </note> Let this good
                    foundation <hi rend="italic">first</hi> be laid, and then thou shalt do all
                    things well.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Mark 7:37.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Neither say in thy heart, ‘I can’t be accepted yet because I am not <hi rend="italic">good enough</hi>.’ Who is good enough, who ever was, to merit
                    acceptance at God’s hands? Was ever any child of Adam good enough for this? Or
                    will any, till the consummation of all things? And as for thee, thou art not
                    good at all; there dwelleth in thee no <pb n="215"/>good thing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            7:18.</p>
                    </note> And thou never wilt be till thou believe in Jesus.
                    Rather thou wilt find thyself worse and worse. But is there any need of being
                    worse in order to be accepted?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 6:1, and Nos. 35, 36, ‘The Law Established
                            through Faith’, Discourses I and II.</p>
                    </note> Art thou not <hi rend="italic">bad enough</hi> already? Indeed thou art, and that God
                    knoweth. And thou thyself canst not deny it. Then delay not. All things are now
                    ready. ‘Arise, and wash away thy sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 22:16.</p>
                    </note> The fountain is open.
                    Now is the time to wash thee white in the blood of the Lamb. Now he shall ‘purge
                    thee as with hyssop, and thou shalt be clean; he shall wash thee, and thou shalt
                    be whiter than snow’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 51:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Do not say, ‘But I am not <hi rend="italic">contrite enough</hi>: I am
                    not sensible enough of my sins.’ I know it. I would to God thou wert more
                    sensible of them, more contrite a thousandfold than thou art. But do not stay
                    for this. It may be God will make thee so, not before thou believest, but by
                    believing. It may be thou wilt not weep much till thou lovest much,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                            7:47-48.</p>
                    </note> because thou hast had much forgiven. In the
                    meantime, look unto Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> Behold how he loveth
                        thee!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            John 11:36.</p>
                    </note> What could he have done more for thee which he
                    hath not done?</p>
                <p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>O Lamb of God, was ever pain,</l>
                        <l>Was ever love like thine!</l>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Samuel Wesley, Sen. (1662-1735) closes ‘On the
                                Crucifixion’ with these two lines. The poem was a favourite of the
                                Wesleys, first published in John Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Collection of Psalms and Hymns</hi> (Charleston, 1737)—where
                                his father’s authorship is not credited—and frequently reprinted
                                thereafter. Adam Clarke first identified the author and entitled the
                                poem, ‘A Hymn on the Passion’. Sugden says that the MS of it was
                                found in the Epworth Rectory garden after the fire of 1709. Cf.
                                Wesley’s letter to Lady Maxwell, July 10, 1764.</p>
                        </note>
                    </lg>
                </p>
                <p>Look steadily upon him till he looks on thee, and breaks thy hard heart. Then
                    shall thy ‘head be waters, and thy eyes fountains of tears’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer. 9:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Nor yet do thou say, ‘I must <hi rend="italic">do</hi> something more
                    before I come to Christ.’ I grant, supposing thy Lord should delay his coming,
                    it were meet and right to wait<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Another characteristic usage. ‘To wait’, for
                            Wesley, was not at all a passive stance; he speaks of ‘waiting’ as
                            active obedience to God’s commands and rejects ‘quietism’ on principle.
                            Even so, good works done while ‘waiting’ are not ‘meritorious’; thus he
                            rejects moralism with equal consistency. Cf. MS Minutes for Aug. 2, 1745
                            (§50): ‘Q. 11. How shall we wait for the fulfilling of this promise [of
                            sanctification]? A. In universal obedience; in keeping all the
                            commandments; in denying ourselves, and taking up our cross daily;
                            [with] prayer, searching the Scripture, communicating, and fasting.’ Cf.
                            also No. 16, ‘The ‘Means of Grace’, III.1.</p>
                    </note> for his appearing
                    in doing, <pb n="216"/>so far as thou hast power, whatsoever he hath commanded
                    thee. But there is no necessity for making such a supposition. How knowest thou
                    that he will delay? Perhaps he will appear as the day-spring from on high,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        1:78.</p>
                    </note> before the morning light. O do not set him a time. Expect
                    him every hour. Now, he is nigh! Even at the door!</p>
                <p>5. And to what end wouldst thou wait for <hi rend="italic">more
                        sincerity</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Sincerity’ was a much discussed virtue, valued
                            more highly by the pietists than the moralists. Cf. above, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.9 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    before thy sins are blotted out? To make thee more worthy of the grace of God?
                    Alas, thou art still ‘establishing thy own righteousness’. He will have mercy,
                    not because thou art worthy of it, but because his compassions fail not;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Lam.
                        3:22.</p>
                    </note> not because thou art righteous, but because Jesus Christ
                    hath atoned for thy sins.</p>
                <p>Again, if there be anything good in <hi rend="italic">sincerity</hi>, why dost
                    thou expect it <hi rend="italic">before</hi> thou hast faith?—seeing faith
                    itself is the only root of whatever is really good and holy.</p>
                <p>Above all, how long wilt thou forget that whatsoever thou dost, or whatsoever
                    thou hast, before thy sins are forgiven thee, it avails nothing with God toward
                    the procuring of thy forgiveness? Yea, and that it must all be cast behind thy
                    back, trampled under foot, made no account of, or thou wilt never find favour in
                    God’s sight? Because until then thou canst not ask it as a mere sinner, guilty,
                    lost, undone, having nothing to plead, nothing to offer to God but only the
                    merits of his well-beloved Son, ‘who loved <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, and gave
                    himself for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. To conclude. Whosoever thou art, O man, who hast the sentence of death
                    in thyself, who feelest thyself a condemned sinner, and hast the wrath of God
                    abiding on thee:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 3:36.</p>
                    </note> unto thee said the Lord, not ‘Do this;
                    perfectly obey all my commands and live:’ but, ‘Believe in the Lord Jesus
                    Christ, and thou shalt be saved.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 16:31; cf. Rom. 10:9.</p>
                    </note> ‘The word of
                    faith is nigh unto thee.’ Now, at this instant, in the present moment, and in
                    thy present state, sinner as thou art, just as thou art, believe the
                        gospel,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark
                            1:15.</p>
                    </note> and ‘I will be merciful unto thy unrighteousness, and
                    thy iniquities will I remember no more.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 8:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>