<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 3: ‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</title>
                <title type="subtitle">A Sermon preached on Sunday, <date when="1742-04-04">April 4,
                        1742</date>, before the University of Oxford. By Charles Wesley, M.A.,
                    Student of Christ Church.</title>
                <author>Wesley, Charles</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-23</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon003</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 3: ‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</title>
                            <date when="1742-04-04"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="142" to="158"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="109"/>
            <introduction>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 1-4]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As we have seen, these first four sermons in this first volume of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> were ‘prefixed’ to the other eight on the advice of
                    friends, and also as proof of the consistency of Wesley’s new preaching, whether
                    before the University of Oxford or to the masses in Moorfields. But they also
                    serve another function, unavowed but crucial: they mark out the successive
                    stages of Wesley’s alienation from any further career as a reformer within the
                    university, as he made the radical shift in his commitment to the Revival as his
                    new vocation.</p>
                <p>Along with other ordained Oxford M.A.s, the brothers Wesley were subject to
                    occasional appointment as preachers in the <hi rend="italic">rota</hi> of
                    university services on Sundays and saints’ days (most of them in the Church of
                    St. Mary the Virgin, but others in St. Peter’s in the East and certain college
                        chapels).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Oxford University Statutes, tr. by G. R. M. Ward (1845), Vol. I, ‘The
                            Laudian Statutes’ (1636), Title XVI, chs. 1-7.</p>
                    </note> Attendance
                    upon these services was a stated obligation of ‘all doctors, masters, graduates,
                    and scholars’, who were enjoined to ‘be present at them from their beginning to
                    their end…’; no one was ‘permitted to wander abroad to another church, or
                    churches, under pain of chastisement…’, etc. (ch. 10). Even though these
                    injunctions were often honoured in the breach, such occasions were still
                    splendid sounding boards for eloquent preachers with earnest messages.</p>
                <p>John Wesley’s first ‘university sermon’ had been delivered in St. Mary’s on
                    November 15, 1730, ‘On Gen. 1:27’ (see No. 141, Vol. IV); a second on July 23,
                    1732 (‘A Consecration Sermon’, not extant); a third on January 1, 1733 (‘The
                    Circumcision of the Heart’; see No. 17 below). This last may be reckoned as a
                    landmark in the development of Wesley’s theology, and must also have made a
                    favourable general impression, for in the next two and a half years he was
                    invited to deliver <pb n="110"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">six</hi> more university
                    sermons: March 26, 1733 (Easter); April 1, 1733 (Low Sunday); May 13, 1733
                    (Whitsunday); February 10, 1734; June 11, 1734 (St. Barnabas’s); September 21,
                    1735 (St. Matthew’s). This is out of all proportion to any typical rotation, and
                    even if Wesley was serving as substitute for other appointed preachers, that
                    would have required the approval of the Vice-Chancellor (cf. <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>, XVI, ch. 6). The least that this can mean is that John
                    Wesley was more widely appreciated at Oxford as a preacher than the popular
                    stereotypes have suggested.</p>
                <p>This fact sheds some light on the arrangement by the university officials for
                    Wesley to preach again in Oxford soon after his return from Georgia (probably in
                    expectation of his resumption of his duties there); the new appointment was set
                    for the Festival of St. Barnabas, June 11, 1738. By that time, of course, Wesley
                    had undergone the radical change of heart and mind described in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for May 24, about which his Oxford colleagues
                    would have known nothing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Intro., above, p.4; see also Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Wesley</hi>, I.141-95, for a careful analysis of the
                            theological developments involved in this ‘conversion’; JWJ, Feb. 7-May
                            28, sheds light on Wesley’s mood as he revised his sermon for this
                            crucial new occasion.</p>
                    </note> Meanwhile, he had already tested his
                    ‘new gospel’ (‘salvation by faith alone’) in several churches in and near
                    London, and his presentation of it had almost invariably stirred up more offence
                    than conversions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, Feb. 5 (Milbank, Westminster); Feb. 12 (St. Andrew’s,
                            Holborn); Feb. 26 (thrice in London, the first, in St. Lawrence Jewry,
                            being the most blessed ‘because it gave the most offence’); Mar. 6
                            (after being counselled by Böhler to ‘preach faith <hi rend="italic">till</hi> you have it; and then, <hi rend="italic">because</hi> you
                            have it, you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> preach faith’); Mar. 17, 26,
                            and 27; Apr. 2, 25, 26; May 7, 9, 14, and 21 (this last being also the
                            day of Charles Wesley’s experience of assurance).</p>
                    </note> In most of
                    these instances, as he records with a trace of self-righteousness, he had been
                    thenceforth barred from this pulpit and that. The Aldersgate experience had not
                    produced a new doctrine, but a new resolution to make the most of his
                    opportunities to expound the one to which he had already come.</p>
                <p>He was by now very well aware of the controversial character of his message, and
                    he could not have expected a sympathetic hearing at Oxford. ‘Salvation by Faith’
                    was, however, the first public occasion after his ‘Aldersgate’ experience for a
                    positive evangelical manifesto. It is worth noting that its Moravian substance
                    is qualified by echoes from the Edwardian <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, as in
                    the claim that salvation involved a power not to commit sin (<hi rend="italic">posse non peccare</hi>). There is also an obvious Anglican nuance in the
                    definition of saving faith presented here.</p>
                <p>When his turn as university preacher came round again (<date when="1741-07-25">July 25, 1741</date>), the Revival was in full swing and Wesley had found
                    in its <pb n="111"/>leadership an alternative career. He had not only begun to
                    shift his loyalties from Oxford to his own Societies; he had also become one of
                    Oxford’s harsher critics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This may be seen in the Latin and English versions
                            of a sermon on Isa. 1:21 which he had first prepared in 1739, probably
                            in connection with his exercises for the B.D. degree which, as Fellow of
                            Lincoln College, he was expected to take in due course (see below, Nos.
                            150, 151).</p>
                    </note> John Gambold had already advised him that he would
                    face a hostile audience, but Wesley was in no mood to mollify them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, June 18,
                            1741: ‘All here [Gambold had said of the Oxford community] are so
                            prejudiced that they will mind nothing you say.’ Wesley’s reaction: ‘I
                            know that. However, I am to deliver my own soul, whether they will hear
                            or whether they will forbear’ (one of Wesley’s standard formulae of
                            alienation). A fortnight later even Wesley and Gambold had come to a
                            parting of their ways (cf. JWJ, July 2). Earlier, he had finally got
                            round to reading ‘that celebrated book, Martin Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Comment on the Epistle to the Galatians</hi>’; his
                            negative reaction to it was intemperate (see JWJ, June 15).</p>
                    </note>
                    Indeed, the whole <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> record for June and July
                    reflects a mounting tension, as if Wesley was aware of the crisis. On June 28 he
                    preached ‘at Charles Square [London], to the largest congregation that, I
                    believe, was ever seen there, on “Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian”
                    [cf. Acts 26:28]’. This was the sermon that, revised and with its new
                    ‘application’ explicitly aimed at Oxford, he delivered on the festival day of
                    St. James the Apostle, July 25.</p>
                <p>Its theme—the radical difference between nominal and real Christianity—was
                    already a familiar one in Puritan preaching;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, proem and n.</p>
                    </note> it was, however, already
                    conventional to ignore the text’s plain reference to Agrippa’s being almost
                    persuaded to become a Christian rather than to his already being a nominal one.
                    Wesley draws out the distinctions between the two stages of Christian experience
                    (‘almost’ and ‘altogether’). Part I paints a vivid picture of the high-minded
                    hypocrite (the ‘almost Christian’) and concludes with Wesley’s confession ‘that
                    this had been his own state in all his days at Oxford’ (I.13). Part II
                    delineates the ‘altogether Christian’ according to his new conceptions, and
                    openly expresses doubt that there are many such in Oxford even now (II.7-9).
                    There are no records of this sermon’s reception on this occasion, but it would
                    not have been lost on his Methodist readers that their leader had bearded the
                    Anglican establishment in one of its citadels and had survived.</p>
                <p>In the following year Charles Wesley came up for an appointment as preacher in
                    St. Mary’s on <date when="1742-04-04">April 4, 1742</date>. His evangelical
                    conversion had preceded his brother’s, either on <date when="1738-05-03">May 3,
                        1738</date> (when ‘it pleased God to open his <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> so
                    that he saw clearly what was the nature of [saving] <pb n="112"/>faith…’) or on
                        <date when="1738-05-19">May 19</date> (when he ‘had found rest to his
                        soul’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            both CWJ and JWJ for these dates and experiences.</p>
                    </note> In any
                    case, Charles was more exuberant in temperament and rhetoric than his elder
                        brother.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            above, p. 2, n. 6: ‘…in connection I beat you; but in strong, pointed
                            sentences you beat me.’</p>
                    </note> He had already preached a sermon on
                    justification ‘before the university [July 1739] with great boldness…’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">CWJ, Sunday, July
                            1, 1739; this is followed (on Monday) by a note that the Vice-Chancellor
                            and ‘all were against [that] sermon as liable to be misunderstood’. Had
                            this been Charles’s reinforcing sequel to John’s <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>?</p>
                    </note> His bidding prayer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the
                            unpublished MS of a sermon on Rom. 3:27-28.</p>
                    </note> indicates that
                    this preaching service had been held in Christ Church Cathedral rather than St.
                    Mary’s. On June 30, 1740, he reports having spent a week in Oxford ‘preaching
                    repentance’ but also in discovering that ‘learned Gallio cared for none of these
                        things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 18:17 for this analogy between a Roman proconsul’s and Oxford’s
                            indifference.</p>
                    </note> Now, he was scheduled to preach in St. Mary’s
                    itself—for the first and last time.</p>
                <p>Charles’s message, with a barrage of invidious questions for its climax, fell
                    largely on deaf ears; this is reported by a visitor who was in the audience:
                    Thomas Salmon, a popular historian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The times of the day the University go to this
                            church are ten in the morning and two in the afternoon, on Sundays and
                            holidays, the sermon usually lasting about half an hour. But when I
                            happened to be at Oxford, in 1742, Mr. Wesley, the Methodist, of Christ
                            Church, entertained his audience two hours, having insulted and abused
                            all degrees from the highest to the lowest, was in a manner hissed out
                            of the pulpit by the lads;’ Thomas Salmon, <hi rend="italic">A
                                Foreigner’s Companion through the Universities of Cambridge and
                                Oxford</hi> (1748), p. 25, and quoted in CWJ, Apr. 15,
                        1750.</p>
                    </note> Charles Wesley’s denial of Salmon’s report appears in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for April 15, 1750, and is emphatic;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘And it would
                            have been high time for them to do so, if the historian [Salmon] said
                            true. But, unfortunately for him, I measured the time by my watch and it
                            was within the hour; I abused neither high nor low, as my sermon in
                            print will prove; neither was I hissed out of the pulpit or treated with
                            the least incivility, either by young or old….’</p>
                    </note> he may have
                    been right about the time, since the sermon as printed can be read aloud in
                    thirty minutes. On the other hand, Charles’s accusations must surely have
                    aroused resentment in his auditory, and Salmon would have been a competent judge
                    of that. In any case this sermon would have persuaded any Methodist reader of
                    Charles’s wholehearted identification with his brother’s cause and theirs. <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> is then a lively evangelical
                    statement, a personal identification with the Revival and a valedictory to
                    Oxford.</p>
                <p>By August 1744 the Revival was gaining momentum, the network (‘connexion’) of the
                    Methodist Societies had extended over into Wales <pb n="113"/>and had come under
                    serious persecution by English mobs, the first ‘conference’ had just been held
                    (June 25-29), and John Wesley had found his true mission in life. Even so, his
                    turn as university preacher came up yet again for August 24 (another festival,
                    this one for St. Bartholomew). This, of course, was an anniversary of the
                    notorious Massacre of Paris (in 1572) and, again, of the Great Ejectment of the
                    Nonconformists in England in 1662, in which both of Wesley’s grandfathers had
                    suffered. Benjamin Kennicott’s explanation of Wesley’s appointment was that ‘as
                    no clergyman [could] avoid his turn, so the university can refuse none;
                    otherwise Mr. Wesley would not have preached.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">At this time, Kennicott was an undergraduate
                            at Wadham College, but he was destined to set Old Testament studies in
                            England upon a new level with his great <hi rend="italic">Vetus
                                Testamentum cum Variis Lectionibus</hi> (Vol. 1, 1776; Vol. 2,
                            1780). His account of Wesley’s sermon appeared in <hi rend="italic">WMM</hi>, 1866, 47-48.</p>
                    </note> Actually, though, that rule was
                    flexible; there was ample precedent for substitutions. One must wonder,
                    therefore, how the appointment came about. Was it a gesture of academic freedom?
                    Did Wesley have a stronger base in Oxford than would appear from the record?
                    There is no indication that he had claimed his turn as by right, but it would
                    never have crossed his mind to avoid it. Thus, the stage was set for a
                    confrontation—and another valedictory.</p>
                <p>Parts I-III of <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> constitute a
                    positive account of Wesley’s conception of the ‘order of salvation’ (Part I), an
                    interesting missiological perspective (Part II), and an early statement of
                    Wesley’s eschatological ideas (Part III)—the sum of these parts is evangelical
                    and Anglican. The mood changes in Part IV where he comes to his ‘plain and
                    practical application’. Here the judgment is passed, with scant charity, that
                    Oxford’s hypocrisies are an intolerable offence to God and a general hindrance
                    to the Christian mission. Kennicott’s uncharitable suspicion was that this final
                    salvo ‘was what [Wesley] had been preparing for all along…’:</p>
                <quote>[In the conclusion] he fired his address with so much zeal and unbounded
                    satire as quite spoiled what otherwise might have been turned to great
                    advantage…. I liked some of his freedom: such as calling the generality of young
                    townsmen ‘a generation of triflers’…. But considering how many shining lights
                    are here that are the glory of the Christian cause, his sacred censure was much
                    too flaming and strong and his charity much too weak…. Having summed up the
                    measure of our iniquities, he concluded with a lifted up eye in this most solemn
                    form, ‘It is time for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, Lord, to lay to <hi rend="italic">thine</hi> hand’—words full of such presumption and seeming
                    imprecation that they gave an universal shock…. Had these things been omitted
                    and his censures moderated, I think his discourse, as to style and delivery,
                    would have been uncommonly pleasing to others as well as to myself. He is
                    allowed to be a man of great parts, and that by the excellent Dean <pb n="114"/>of Christ Church;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John Conybeare, who succeeded Joseph Butler as
                            Bishop of Bristol, and author of <hi rend="italic">Defence of Revealed
                                Religion…</hi> (1732), one of the eighteenth century’s more famous
                            replies to Tindal and other deists.</p>
                    </note> for the day he preached
                    the dean generously said of him, ‘John Wesley will always be thought a man of
                    sound sense, though an enthusiast!’ However, the Vice-Chancellor<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Walter Hodges,
                            Provost of Oriel.</p>
                    </note> sent for the sermon, and I hear that the
                    heads of college intend to shew their resentment.</quote>
                <p>Another eyewitness report of the same event was recorded by William Blackstone,
                    already a Fellow of All Souls and on his way to the fame he would earn as author
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Laws of England</hi> (1765-69). In
                    a letter to a family friend (Aug. 28) the young Blackstone reports on Wesley’s
                    sermon, which seems to have become the talk of the town:</p>
                <quote>We were last Friday [Aug. 24] entertained at St. Mary’s by a curious sermon
                    from Wesley the Methodist. Among other equally modest particulars, he informed
                    us, 1st, that there was not one Christian among all the Heads of Houses; 2ndly,
                    that pride, gluttony, avarice, luxury, sensuality and drunkenness were general
                    characteristics of all Fellows of Colleges, who were useless to a proverbial
                    uselessness. Lastly, that the younger part of the University were a generation
                    of triflers, all of them perjured and none of them of any religion at all. His
                    notes were demanded by the Vice-Chancellor, but on mature deliberation it has
                    been thought proper to punish him by a mortifying neglect….<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the facsimile of the
                            letter in John Fletcher Hurst, <hi rend="italic">The History of
                                Methodism</hi>, II.604-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That ‘mortifying neglect’ began at once. Charles Wesley records that ‘we [John
                    Wesley, Charles Wesley, Messrs. Piers and Meriton] walked back in form, the
                    little band of us four; for of the rest durst none join himself to us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. CWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Methodists, then and later, could see no proper warrant for anyone to have taken
                    offence at such a sermon; after all, Wesley had simply preached the gospel and
                    applied it ‘close and home’. Thomas Jackson’s later comment on it is
                    typical:</p>
                <quote>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> contains a beautiful and
                    forcible description of spiritual religion, with the manner by which it is
                    acquired by individuals and then spreads from one to another until it shall
                    cover the earth. The concluding application to the heads of colleges and halls,
                    to the fellows and tutors and to the body of undergraduates, assumes their
                    general and wide departure from the true Christian character, and [their]
                    abandonment to formality, worldliness, levity, and sloth. It contains nothing
                    sarcastic and irritating, nothing that was designed to give unnecessary pain or
                    offence; but is marked throughout by seriousness, fidelity, and tender
                        affection.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Rev. Charles Wesley</hi> (1841),
                            I.403.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <pb n="115"/>John Wesley himself was much more of a realist and also more aware
                    of his own intention:</p>
                <quote>I preached, I suppose the last time, at <placeName>St. Mary’s</placeName>. Be
                    it so. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully delivered my own
                    soul.</quote>
                <quote>The Beadle came to me afterwards and told me the Vice-Chancellor had sent him
                    for my notes. I sent them without delay, not without admiring the wise
                    providence of God. Perhaps few men of note would have given a sermon of mine the
                    reading if I had put it into their hands; but by this means it came to be read,
                    probably more than once, by every man of eminence in the University.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">JWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That he never regretted the affair or its consequences would appear from a
                    complacent recollection of it in 1781 in ‘A Short History of the People called
                    Methodists’:</p>
                <quote>Friday, August 24, St. Bartholomew’s Day, I preached for the last time before
                    the University of Oxford. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully
                    delivered my own soul. And I am well pleased that it should be the very day on
                    which, in the last century,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, the Great Ejectment in
                            1662.</p>
                    </note> near two thousand burning and shining lights were put
                    out at one stroke. Yet what a wide difference is there between their case and
                    mine! They were turned out of house and home, and all that they had; whereas I
                    am only hindered from preaching, without any other loss; and that in a kind of
                    honourable manner; it being determined that when my next turn to preach came
                    they would pay another person to preach for me. And so they did twice or thrice,
                    even to the time that I resigned my fellowship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">§30. See Vol. 9 of this edn. and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 420.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>What would have been most obvious to his Methodist readers was the heroic stature
                    of their leader who had preached ‘plain truth’ to academic people to their face
                    and at the cost of rejection by them. What clearer proof could there be of his
                    fidelity to the gospel under all circumstances and of his total commitment in
                    his ministry among them? It was no small matter for a tenured don to have
                    forsaken his privileged status in a class-conscious English society in exchange
                    for ‘The Foundery’, ‘The New Room’, and a career among the masses. They knew,
                    all too well, how rudely the Methodists had been treated, to the point of savage
                    persecution, condoned by magistrates and clergy alike in the years between 1739
                    and 1746; they could still foresee dangerous days ahead. <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> as published was an evangelical proclamation;
                    it was also an act of defiance.</p>
                <p>These ‘prefixed’ sermons, therefore, serve a particular junction in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> as a bloc: they proclaim the Wesleyan message in
                    prophetic terms, and they signify Wesley’s transference of his allegiance from
                    the <pb n="116"/>Academy to his new vocation as a preacher of ‘plain truth for
                    plain people’. Together they dispel any impression of inconsistency. His message
                    in St. Mary’s had been the same as it was now in Moorfields. Thus, these sermons
                    could serve as a multifaceted introductory quartet to the larger endeavour of
                        <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi>.</p>
                <p>The edited text of <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi> is based upon the
                    first edition of 1738. For a stemma illustrating its publishing history through
                    its thirty-one editions in Wesley’s lifetime, together with substantive variant
                    readings, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                    10.</p>
                <p>The text for <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi> is based upon its first
                    edition, 1741. For a stemma and table of variant readings through the
                    twenty-eight extant editions during Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix.
                    See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 50.</p>
                <p>The first edition of <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> followed
                    here, was published shortly after the sermon itself was preached in 1742. For a
                    stemma and variant readings from the fifty-two extant editions in Charles
                    Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 59.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> was also published shortly after
                    its delivery in 1744 and ran through at least fifteen editions in Wesley’s
                    lifetime. For a stemma of these editions and a list of variant readings, see
                    Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 92.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="142"/>            
            <head>‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</head>
            <head type="subhead"> Sermon preached on <date when="1742-04-04">Sunday, April 4,
                    1742</date>,<lb/>before the University of Oxford.<lb/>By Charles Wesley,
                M.A.,<lb/>Student of Christ Church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Half-title reproduced from <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>,
                        I (1746). The drop-title prefixed to the individual editions of the sermon
                        was simply ‘Ephes. v. 14’; some variant of this continued in all subsequent
                        editions until 1795, when its present full title, ‘Awake, Thou That
                        Sleepest’, appeared for the first time. See ‘Intro. Com.’, pp. 111-12
                        above.</p>
                </note>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Ephesians 5:14</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Awake, thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead, and Christ
                        shall give thee light.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p>In discoursing on these words I shall, with the help of God,</p>
                <p>First, describe the sleepers to whom they are spoken;</p>
                <p>Secondly, enforce the exhortation, ‘Awake thou that sleepest, and arise from the
                    dead;’ and,</p>
                <p>Thirdly, explain the promise made to such as do awake and arise—‘Christ shall
                    give thee light.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And first, as to the sleepers here spoken to. By sleep is signified
                    the natural state of man:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An allegorical interpretation following a line
                            established by St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Expositions on the
                                Psalms</hi> (<hi rend="italic">NPNF</hi>, I, VIII.7, 159, 175, 259),
                            and echoed in Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi> The source of the quotation is unknown;
                            it may have come from a then familiar Christian liturgical passage. In
                                <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> Wesley shies away from allegory and
                            comes nearer to Matthew Henry’s comment in <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>: ‘God calls upon
                            sinners…that they would break off their sins by repentance and enter on
                            a course of holy obedience, and he encourages them to essay and do their
                            utmost that way.’</p>
                    </note> that deep sleep of the soul into which the
                    sin of Adam hath cast all who spring from his loins; that supineness, indolence,
                    and stupidity, that insensibility of his real condition, wherein every man comes
                    into the world, and continues till the voice of God awakes him.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Now ‘they that sleep, sleep in the night.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:7.</p>
                    </note> The
                    state of nature is a state of utter darkness, a state wherein ‘darkness covers
                    the <pb n="143"/>earth, and gross darkness the people.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 60:2.</p>
                    </note> The
                    poor unawakened sinner, how much knowledge soever he may have as to other
                    things, has no knowledge of himself. In this respect ‘he knoweth nothing yet as
                    he ought to know.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 8:2.</p>
                    </note> He knows not that he is a fallen spirit, whose
                    only business in the present world is to recover from his fall, to regain that
                    image of God<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    wherein he was created. He sees <emph>no necessity</emph> for ‘the one thing
                        needful’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Luke 10:42. This is the famous <hi rend="italic">unum necessarium</hi>,
                            the interpretation of which had exercised Anglicans and Puritans alike.
                            See Jeremy Taylor’s treatise with this title, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, II.419-646; also the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                                Lib.</hi>, XXIII.57-58. It was a favourite text for Charles and John
                            Wesley; John Wesley records that he preached from it at least fifty
                            times during his ministry. Cf. his early sermon (May 1734) on this text,
                            No. 146.</p>
                    </note> even that inward universal change, that ‘birth from
                        above’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 3:3; ἄνωθεν here would seem to imply ‘anew’, i.e., a new birth
                            (‘from above’, of course). There is an old puzzle as to the ambiguous
                            meaning of ἄνωθεν continuing still as between Bultmann, Schnackenburg,
                            Brown, and others. In Greek it has a double usage: ‘from above’ (as of
                            place) and ‘anew’ (as in time). This ambiguity is absent from all its
                            Aramaic and Hebrew equivalents. In John 19:23 it clearly means ‘from the
                            top’. Cf. Nos. 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of
                            Salvation</hi>, I.4; and 45, ‘The New Birth’, II.3.</p>
                    </note> (figured
                    out by baptism) which is the beginning of that total renovation, that
                    sanctification of spirit, soul, and body, ‘without which no man shall see the
                        Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            12:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Full of all diseases as he is, he fancies himself in perfect health.
                    Fast bound in misery and iron, he dreams that he is happy and at liberty. He
                    says, ‘Peace, peace,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 6:14; 8:11.</p>
                    </note> while the devil as ‘a
                    strong man armed’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 11:21.</p>
                    </note> is in full possession of his
                    soul. He sleeps on still, and takes his rest, though hell is moved from beneath
                    to meet him;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Isa. 14:9.</p>
                    </note> though the pit, from whence there is no
                        return,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Job 10:21; 16:22.</p>
                    </note> hath opened its mouth to swallow him
                        up.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Num.
                            16:30.</p>
                    </note> A fire is kindled around him, yet he knoweth it not;
                    yea, it burns him, yet he lays it not to heart.</p>
                <p n="4">4. By one who sleeps we are therefore to understand (and would to God we
                    might all understand it!) a sinner satisfied in his sins, contented to remain in
                    his fallen state, to live and die without the image of God; one who is ignorant
                    both of his disease and of the only remedy for it; one who never was warned, or
                    never regarded the warning voice of God ‘to flee from the wrath to come’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        3:7.</p>
                    </note> one that never yet saw he was in danger of hell-fire, or <pb n="144"/>cried out in the earnestness of his soul, ‘What must I do to be
                        saved?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            16:30.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. If this sleeper be not outwardly vicious, his sleep is usually the
                    deepest of all: whether he be of the Laodicean spirit, ‘neither cold nor
                        hot’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                            3:15.</p>
                    </note> but a quiet, rational, inoffensive, good-natured
                    professor of the religion of his fathers; or whether he be zealous and orthodox,
                    and ‘after the most straitest sect of our religion lives a Pharisee’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                            26:5.</p>
                    </note> that is, according to the scriptural account, one that
                        <emph>justifies himself</emph>, one that labours ‘to establish his own
                        righteousness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:3.</p>
                    </note> as the ground of his
                    acceptance with God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. This is he who ‘having a form of godliness, denies the power
                        thereof’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 3:5; see above, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> yea, and probably reviles it,
                    wheresoever it is found, as mere extravagance and delusion. Meanwhile the
                    wretched self-deceiver thanks God that he ‘is not as other men are, adulterers,
                    unjust, extortioners’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 18:11.</p>
                    </note> No, he doth no wrong to
                    any man. He ‘fasts twice in the week’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 18:12.</p>
                    </note> uses all the means
                    of grace, is constant at church and sacrament; yea, and ‘gives tithes of all
                    that he has’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> does all the good that he
                    can. ‘Touching the righteousness of the law’, he is ‘blameless’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            3:6.</p>
                    </note> he wants nothing of godliness but the power; nothing of
                    religion but the spirit; nothing of Christianity but the truth and the life.</p>
                <p n="7">7. But know ye not that however highly esteemed among men such a Christian
                    as this may be, he is an abomination in the sight of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:15, and note
                            Charles Wesley’s agreement with his brother in the early years of the
                            Revival that even the best of the ‘almost Christians’ are ‘abominations
                            in the sight of God’. For later assuagements of this harsh judgment see
                            III.6 and n. 179.</p>
                    </note> and an heir of every woe which the Son of
                    God yesterday, today, and for ever denounces against ‘scribes and Pharisees,
                        hypocrites’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 23:13.</p>
                    </note> He hath ‘made clean the outside of the cup and
                    the platter’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 23:25.</p>
                    </note> but within is full of all filthiness. ‘An
                    evil disease cleaveth’ still ‘unto him,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 41:8.</p>
                    </note> so that ‘his inward
                    parts are very wickedness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> Our Lord fitly compares him
                    to a ‘painted sepulchre’, which ‘appears beautiful without’, but nevertheless is
                    ‘full of dead men’s bones and of all uncleanness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 23:27; Wesley is
                            here following Wycliffe, Tyndale, and the ‘Great Bible’ in translating
                            κεκονιαμένοις (lit., ‘whitewashed’) as ‘painted’. See III.11.</p>
                    </note>
                    The bones <pb n="145"/>indeed are no longer dry; ‘the sinews and flesh are come
                    up upon them, and the skin covers them above: but there is no breath in
                        them,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ezek. 37:8.</p>
                    </note> no Spirit of the living God. And ‘if any man have
                    not the Spirit of Christ, he is none of his.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:9.</p>
                    </note> ‘Ye are Christ’s’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        3:23.</p>
                    </note> ‘if so be that the Spirit of God dwell in you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:9.</p>
                    </note> But if not, God knoweth that ye abide in death, even until
                    now.</p>
                <p n="8">8. This is another character of the sleeper here spoken to. He abides in
                    death, though he knows it not. He is dead unto God, ‘dead in trespasses and
                        sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            2:1.</p>
                    </note> ‘For to be carnally minded is death.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:6.</p>
                    </note> Even as
                    it is written, ‘By one man sin entered into the w world, and death by sin; and
                    so death passed upon all men’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:12.</p>
                    </note>—not only temporal death, but
                    likewise spiritual and eternal. ‘In the day thou eatest (said God to Adam) thou
                    shalt surely die.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 2:17.</p>
                    </note> Not bodily (unless as he
                    then became mortal) but spiritually: thou shalt lose the life of thy soul; thou
                    shalt die to God, shalt be separated from him, thy essential life and
                    happiness.</p>
                <p n="9">9. Thus first was dissolved the vital union of our soul with God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Both Wesleys were
                            body-soul dualists, and the notion of the Fall as a radical disruption
                            of the aboriginal body-soul equilibrium goes back at least to Wesley’s
                            early MS sermon on Gen. 1:27; see Nos. 141, ‘The Image of God’; and 41,
                                <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, III.5 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    insomuch that ‘in the midst of’ natural ‘life we are’ now ‘in’ spiritual
                        ‘death’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            echo from the committal service in the BCP, Burial.</p>
                    </note> And
                    herein we remain till the Second Adam becomes a quickening spirit to us, till he
                    raises the dead, the dead in sin, in pleasure, riches, or honours. But before
                    any dead soul can live, he ‘hears (hearkens to) the voice of the Son of
                        God’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 5:25.</p>
                    </note> he is made sensible of his lost estate, and
                    receives the sentence of death in himself. He knows himself to be ‘dead while he
                        liveth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Tim. 5:6.</p>
                    </note> dead to God and all the things of God; having no
                    more power to perform the actions of a living Christian than a dead body to
                    perform the functions of a living man.</p>
                <p n="10">10. And most certain it is that one dead in sin has not ‘senses exercised
                    to discern’ spiritual ‘good and evil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 5:14.</p>
                    </note> ‘Having eyes, he sees
                    not; he hath ears, and hears not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 8:18.</p>
                    </note> He doth not ‘taste and
                    see that the Lord is gracious’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 34:8 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He ‘hath not seen God at
                    any time’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            1:18; 1 John 4:12.</p>
                    </note> nor ‘heard his voice’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 5:37.</p>
                    </note> nor
                    ‘handled the Word of life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:1.</p>
                    </note> In vain is <pb n="146"/>the
                    name of Jesus ‘like ointment poured forth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">S. of S. 1:3.</p>
                    </note> and ‘all his
                    garments smell of myrrh, aloes, and cassia’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 45:8.</p>
                    </note> The soul that
                    sleepeth in death hath no perception of any objects of this kind. His heart is
                    ‘past feeling’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:19.</p>
                    </note> and understandeth none of these things.</p>
                <p n="11">11. And hence, having no spiritual senses, no inlets of spiritual
                        knowledge,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An especial emphasis in the Wesleys’ theory of religious knowledge
                            derived from Descartes and Malebranche through John Norris. The human
                            spirit is a ‘spiritual sensorium’, analogous to our physical senses, and
                            thus the capacity for intuitions of spiritual reality is comparable to
                            sight and sound. Cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.
                            Sin (‘sleep’, ‘death’) deadens all spiritual stimuli (‘inlets of
                            spiritual knowledge’). Thus, conversion or awakening is, by analogy, the
                            discovery of a new world.</p>
                    </note> the natural man receiveth not the
                    things of the Spirit of God; nay, he is so far from receiving them that
                    whatsoever is spiritually discerned is mere foolishness unto him. He is not
                    content with being utterly ignorant of spiritual things, but he denies the very
                    existence of them. And spiritual sensation itself is to him the foolishness of
                        folly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Prov. 14:24.</p>
                    </note> ‘How’, saith he, ‘can these things be?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                        3:9.</p>
                    </note> How can any man <emph>know</emph> that he is alive to God?
                    Even as you know that your body is now alive. Faith is the life of the soul: and
                    if ye have this life abiding in you, ye want no marks to evidence it <emph>to
                        yourself</emph>, but that ἔλεγχος Πνεύματος,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:1. Where had
                            Charles come across this reading? The <hi rend="italic">Textus
                                Receptus</hi> here reads πραγμάτων ἔλεγχος, and this agrees with all
                            the critical editions. For the translation ‘evidence and conviction’,
                            cf. John’s note in <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>; for John’s repeated use
                            of ‘divine consciousness’, see Nos. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, I.2; 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, IV.2; 12, ‘The
                            Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §8; 17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’,
                            I.7; 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, II.1;
                            46, ‘The Wilderness State’, I.1; 70, ‘The Case of Reason Impartially
                            Considered’, II.1; 106, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, §1; 108, ‘On Riches’,
                            I.1; 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §10; 132, ‘On Faith,
                            Heb. 11:1’, §1. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>,
                            §§6-7, and <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. I, I.4 (11:46,
                            106-7 of this edn.). J. Clifford Hindley has studied the Wesleys’
                            religious epistemology in his ‘Philosophy of Enthusiasm…’ in <hi rend="italic">The London Quarterly and Holborn Review</hi>, Vol.
                            182, Nos. 2 and 3 (April and July 1957), pp. 99-109, 199-210; see also
                            Umphrey Lee, <hi rend="italic">The Historical Backgrounds of Early
                                Methodist Enthusiasm</hi> (New York, Columbia University Press,
                            1931).</p>
                    </note> that divine consciousness, that ‘witness of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        5:9.</p>
                    </note> which is more and greater than ten thousand human
                    witnesses.</p>
                <p n="12">12. If he doth not now bear witness with thy spirit that thou art a child
                    of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            8:16.</p>
                    </note> O that he might convince thee, thou poor unawakened
                    sinner, by his demonstration and power, that thou art a child of the devil! O
                    that as I prophesy there might now be ‘a <pb n="147"/>noise and a shaking’, and
                    may ‘the bones come together, bone to his bone’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ezek. 37:7.</p>
                    </note>
                    Then ‘come from the four winds, O breath, and breathe on these slain that they
                    may live!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ezek.
                            37:9.</p>
                    </note> And do not ye harden your hearts and resist the Holy
                    Ghost, who even now is come to ‘convince you of sin’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 8:46.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘because you believe not on the name of the only-begotten Son of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                            3:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Wherefore, ‘Awake, thou that sleepest, and arise from the dead.’ God
                    calleth thee now by my mouth; and bids thee know thyself,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For this Wesleyan correlation
                            of self-knowledge and repentance, see No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’,
                            II.1 and n.</p>
                    </note> thou fallen spirit, thy true state and only
                    concern below: ‘What meanest thou, O sleeper? Arise! Call upon thy God, if so be
                    thy God will think upon thee, that thou perish not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jonah 1:6.</p>
                    </note> A
                    mighty tempest is stirred up round about thee, and thou art sinking into the
                    depths of perdition, the gulf of God’s judgments. If thou wouldst escape them,
                    cast thyself into them. ‘Judge thyself’, and thou shalt ‘not be judged of the
                        Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Cor. 11:31.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Awake, awake! Stand up this moment, lest thou ‘drink at the Lord’s hand
                    the cup of his fury’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 51:17.</p>
                    </note> Stir up thyself ‘to lay
                    hold on the Lord’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Chr. 7:22.</p>
                    </note> ‘the Lord thy
                    righteousness, mighty to save!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer. 23:6; Isa. 63:1.</p>
                    </note> ‘Shake thyself
                    from the dust.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 52:2.</p>
                    </note> At least, let the earthquake of God’s
                    threatenings shake thee. Awake and cry out with the trembling gaoler, ‘What must
                    I do to be saved?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 16:30.</p>
                    </note> And never rest till thou
                    believest on the Lord Jesus, with a faith which is his gift, by the operation of
                    his Spirit.</p>
                <p n="3">3. If I speak to any one of you more than to another it is to thee who
                    thinkest thyself unconcerned in this exhortation. ‘I have a message from God
                    unto thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Judg. 3:20.</p>
                    </note> In his name I ‘warn <emph>thee</emph> to flee
                    from the wrath to come’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 3:7.</p>
                    </note> Thou unholy soul, see thy
                    picture in condemned Peter, lying in the dark dungeon between the soldiers,
                    bound with two chains, the keepers before the door keeping the prison.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts
                            12:6.</p>
                    </note> The night is far spent, the morning is at hand<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            13:12.</p>
                    </note> when thou art to be brought forth to execution. And in
                    these dreadful circumstances thou art fast asleep; thou art fast asleep in the
                    devil’s arms, on the brink of the pit, in the jaws of everlasting
                        destruction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Thess. 1:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">
                    <pb n="148"/>4. O may ‘the angel of the Lord come upon thee, and the light
                    shine into thy prison’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 12:7.</p>
                    </note> And mayst thou feel the
                    stroke of an almighty hand raising thee with, ‘Arise up quickly, gird thyself,
                    and bind on thy sandals, cast thy garment about thee, and follow me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                            12:7-8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Awake, thou everlasting spirit, out of thy dream of worldly happiness.
                    Did not God create thee for himself? Then thou canst not rest till thou restest
                    in him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, I.1: ‘<hi rend="italic">Fecisti nos ad te et inquietum est cor nostrum, donec requiescat in
                                te</hi>’ (‘Thou hast made us for thyself, and restless is our heart
                            till it comes to rest in thee’). Cf. also Nos. 22, ‘ Sermon on the
                            Mount, II’, II.4; 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, II.2; 73, ‘Of Hell’,
                            I.4; 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, III.1; 78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, II.2; 84,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III.3. For a
                            quotation of the Latin, and the translation, cf. No. 120, ‘The Unity of
                            the Divine Being’, §9. Cf. also Charles Wesley’s hymn in <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Hymns</hi>, No. 335, ll. 5-6:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>My heart is pained, nor can it be</l>
                            <l>At rest, till it finds rest in thee.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </note> Return, thou
                    wanderer. Fly back to thy ark.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gen. 8:9.</p>
                    </note> ‘This is not thy
                        home.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley uses a similar phrase at least three different times.
                            Cf. ‘After the Death of a Friend’, ver. 7, l. 2: ‘This earth, I know, is
                            not my place.’ The same line also occurs in ‘Desiring to be Dissolved’,
                            ver. 5. Both poems were printed in John Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A
                                Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi> (1744, <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 78), III.266, 270. Cf. also Charles Wesley’s Hymn
                            No. 41, ‘The Traveller’, st. 2, l. 2, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns for
                                Those That Seek and Those That Have Redemption</hi> (1747), p. 51:
                            ‘This earth, we know, is not our place.’ John Wesley closes his
                            correspondence with ‘John Smith’, Mar. 22, 1748, by quoting the entire
                            stanza:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Strangers and pilgrims here below,</l>
                            <l>This earth, we know, is not
                                our place:</l>
                            <l>And hasten through the vale of woe,</l>
                            <l>And
                                restless to behold thy face,</l>
                            <l>Swift to our heavenly country
                                move,</l>
                            <l>Our everlasting home above.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also Nos. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great
                                Assize</hi>, IV.4; and 108, ‘On Riches’, II.12.</p>
                    </note> Think not
                    of building tabernacles here. Thou art but ‘a stranger, a sojourner upon
                        earth’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Chr. 29:15.</p>
                    </note> a creature of a day,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the echoes here of a
                            familiar theme in Augustan literature, oft-repeated by both Wesleys; cf.
                            Pindar, <hi rend="italic">Pythian Odes</hi>, viii.95-96 (‘Creatures of a
                            day…man is but a dream’); see also No. 124, ‘Human Life a Dream’, §2 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> but just launching out into an unchangeable state. Make
                    haste; eternity is at hand. Eternity depends on this moment: an eternity of
                    happiness, or an eternity of misery!</p>
                <p n="6">6. In what state is thy soul? Was God, while I am yet speaking, to require
                    it of thee, art thou ready to meet death and judgment? Canst thou stand in his
                    sight, ‘who is of purer eyes than to behold <pb n="149"/>iniquity’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Hab.
                            1:13.</p>
                    </note> Art thou ‘meet to be partaker of the inheritance of the
                    saints in light’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> Hast thou ‘fought a good
                    fight and kept the faith’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> Hast thou secured ‘the
                    one thing needful’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 10:42.</p>
                    </note> Hast thou recovered the
                    image of God, even ‘righteousness and true holiness’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:24.</p>
                    </note> Hast
                    thou ‘put off the old man and put on the new’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:22, 24; Col. 3:9, 10.</p>
                    </note>
                    Art thou ‘clothed upon with Christ’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Hast thou oil in thy lamp?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 25:4.</p>
                    </note> Grace in thy heart? Dost
                    thou ‘love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy mind, and with
                    all thy soul, and with all thy strength’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30.</p>
                    </note> Is ‘that mind in
                    thee which was also in Christ Jesus’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> Art thou a Christian
                    indeed? That is, a new creature? Are ‘old things passed away, and all things
                    become new’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Cor. 5:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Art thou ‘partaker of the divine nature’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:4.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘Knowest thou not that Christ is in thee, except thou be reprobate?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            13:5.</p>
                    </note> Knowest thou that ‘God dwelleth in thee, and thou in
                    God, by his Spirit which he hath given thee’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:24; 4:12, 13.</p>
                    </note> Knowest
                    thou not that ‘thy body is a temple of the Holy Ghost, which thou hast of
                        God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Cor. 6:19.</p>
                    </note> Hast thou ‘the witness in thyself’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        5:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘the earnest of thine inheritance’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 1:14.</p>
                    </note> Art
                    thou ‘sealed by that Spirit of promise unto the day of redemption’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 1:13;
                            4:30.</p>
                    </note> ‘Hast thou received the Holy Ghost?’ Or dost thou start
                    at the question, not knowing whether there be any Holy Ghost?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 19:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. If it offends thee, be thou assured that thou neither art a Christian
                    nor desirest to be one. Nay, thy ‘very prayer is turned into sin’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 109:6
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> and thou hast solemnly mocked God this very day by
                    praying for ‘the inspiration of his Holy Spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the first collect in The
                            Order for Holy Communion, BCP: ‘Almighty God, unto whom all hearts are
                            open…’; note the assumption here that most in the audience had already
                            shared in a eucharistic liturgy.</p>
                    </note> when thou didst not believe
                    there was any such thing to be received.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Yet on the authority of God’s Word and our own Church I must repeat
                    the question, ‘Hast thou received the Holy Ghost?’ If thou hast not thou art not
                    yet a Christian; for a Christian is a man that is ‘anointed with the Holy Ghost
                    and with power’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 10:38.</p>
                    </note> Thou art not yet made a
                    partaker of pure religion and undefiled.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:27.</p>
                    </note> Dost <pb n="150"/>thou
                    know what religion is? That it is a participation of the divine nature, the life
                    of God in the soul of man:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:4: ἵνα διὰ τούτων γένησθε θείας
                            κοινωνοὶ φύσεως, a phrase which sums up the catholic tradition of human
                            participation in ‘the divine nature’. Cf. St. Irenaeus, <hi rend="italic">Adversus Haereses</hi>, III.xi.1, xix.6; IV.xxv.3-4;
                            and also J. T. Nielsen, <hi rend="italic">Adam and Christ in the
                                Theology of Irenaeus of Lyons</hi> (Assen, Van Gorcum, 1968); see
                            also Origen’s <hi rend="italic">De Principiis</hi>, I.i.8-9; III.vi.1;
                            IV.iv.9-10; and Hal Koch, <hi rend="italic">Pronoia und Paideusis…</hi>
                            (Berlin, Walter de Gruyter, 1932), ch.iii. See also, espec., Balas, <hi rend="italic">Metousia Theou:</hi> (pp. 72-73 above). This theme had
                            come to the Wesleys through such favourite sources in the Epworth
                            rectory as Lorenzo Scupoli, <hi rend="italic">Pugna Spiritualis…</hi>
                            (1589), reckoned by both Susanna and John to have been the work of Juan
                            de Castañiza; cf. Richard Lucas’s English translation, <hi rend="italic">The Spiritual Combat</hi> (1698), and many translations thereafter;
                            see No. 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.5 and n.; and Henry Scougal, <hi rend="italic">The Life of God in the Soul of Man</hi> (cf. Wesley’s
                            abridgement in 1744; see also Winthrop S. Hudson’s edn. [Philadelphia,
                            The Westminster Press, 1948]). Other crucial sources in their Oxford
                            days included Jeremy Taylor, Thomas à Kempis, William Law (cf. Wesley’s
                            references in <hi rend="italic">A Plain Account of Christian
                                Perfection</hi>, §4), and Richard Lucas (Wesley read his <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi> in Mar. 1730, and other
                            works in 1733).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">It is not incidental that
                            John Wesley’s carefully crafted account of his Aldersgate experience
                            (JWJ, May 24, 1738) begins with the opening of his New Testament to 2
                            Pet. 1:4 (the longest Greek quotation in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>). He condenses both the original text and his
                            translation of it so as to emphasize ‘the exceeding great and precious
                            promises, even that ye should be partakers of the divine nature’ (cf.
                            this with the AV and with the translation in the <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>). For further discussion, cf. Reginald Kissack,
                            ‘Wesley’s Conversion’, WHS, XXII.1-6.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For
                            other references to the participation theme in the Wesley corpus, cf.
                            Nos. 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, III.1; 43, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, I.4; 135, ‘On Guardian Angels’,
                            II.2; 146, ‘The One Thing Needful’, III.1. Cf. also, in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, his commentaries on Matt. 7:12; John
                            20:17; Rom. 3:23, 5:21; 1 John 2:5, 4:21. See also his letter to Richard
                            Morgan, Jan. 14, 1734; to ‘John Smith’, June 25, 1746; and to William
                            Dodd, Mar. 12, 1756. Wesley emphasized this theme in his selections for
                            the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, e.g., XIX.193-97, 269-72;
                            XXXIX.44-61; L.369-73. He even took care to preserve a MS sermon of John
                            Gambold’s among his own papers, from 1738 until his death, on ‘The Holy
                            Spirit’ (see below, Vol. 4, Appendix B). Its dominant theme is
                            participation.</p>
                    </note> ‘Christ formed in the heart’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            4:19.</p>
                    </note> ‘Christ in thee, the hope of glory’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 1:27.</p>
                    </note>
                    happiness and holiness; heaven begun upon earth;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A line which appears
                            frequently in Charles Wesley’s hymns. Cf., e.g., his hymn on Ps. 65, st.
                            4, ll. 7-8 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, VIII.142):</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Heaven begun on earth we feel,</l>
                            <l>The heaven of Jesu’s
                                love.</l>
                            <l>Cf. also the hymn on Ps. 31, Pt. II, st. 12, ll. 7-8
                                    (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, VIII.64):</l>
                            <l>Enjoy a
                                paradise of love</l>
                            <l>A heaven on earth begun.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also J. Wakelin, <hi rend="italic">Christ and
                                Nicodemus</hi>, ver. xxx, l. 1 (2nd edn., 1760, p. 19): ‘A little
                            heav’n begun on earth.’</p>
                    </note> ‘a kingdom of God within thee’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            17:21.</p>
                    </note> ‘not meat and drink’, no outward thing, ‘but
                    righteousness <pb n="151"/>and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        14:17.</p>
                    </note> an everlasting kingdom brought into thy soul, a ‘peace of
                    God that passeth all understanding’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> a ‘joy unspeakable
                    and full of glory’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. Knowest thou that ‘in Jesus Christ neither circumcision availeth
                    anything, nor uncircumcision; but faith that worketh by love;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:6.</p>
                    </note> but a
                    new creation?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:15.</p>
                    </note> Seest thou the necessity of that inward change,
                    that spiritual birth, that life from the dead, that holiness? And art thou
                    thoroughly convinced that ‘without it no man shall see the Lord’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            12:14.</p>
                    </note> Art thou labouring after it? ‘Giving all diligence to
                    make thy calling and election sure’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘Working out thy
                    salvation with fear and trembling’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> ‘Agonizing to enter in
                    at the strait gate’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 13:24.</p>
                    </note> Art thou <emph>in
                        earnest</emph> about thy soul? And canst thou tell the Searcher of hearts,
                    ‘Thou, O God, art the thing that I long for!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 6:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘Lord, thou knowest
                    all things! Thou knowest that I <emph>would</emph> love thee!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                    21:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. Thou hopest to be saved. But what reason hast thou to give of the hope
                    that is in thee?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> Is it because thou hast
                    done no harm? Or because thou hast done much good? Or because thou art not like
                    other men,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Luke 18:11.</p>
                    </note> but wise, or learned, or honest, and morally
                    good? Esteemed of men, and of a fair reputation? Alas, all this will never bring
                    thee to God. It is in his account lighter than vanity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 62:9.</p>
                    </note> Dost
                    thou ‘know Jesus Christ whom he hath sent’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 17:3.</p>
                    </note> Hath he taught
                    thee that ‘by grace we are saved through faith? And that not of ourselves: it is
                    the gift of God; not of works, lest any man should boast’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:8, 9.</p>
                    </note>
                    Hast thou received the faithful saying as the whole foundation of thy hope, that
                    ‘Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 1:15.</p>
                    </note>
                    Hast thou learned what that meaneth, ‘I came not to call the righteous, but
                    sinners to repentance’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 2:17.</p>
                    </note> ‘I am not sent but to the
                    lost sheep’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 15:24; note Charles Wesley’s omission of the concluding phrase,
                            ‘of the house of Israel’.</p>
                    </note> Art thou (he that heareth, let him
                    understand!) lost, dead, <emph>damned already</emph>? Dost thou know thy
                    deserts? Dost thou feel thy wants? Art thou ‘poor in spirit’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:3.</p>
                    </note>
                    Mourning for God and refusing to be comforted?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:4.</p>
                    </note> Is the prodigal
                    ‘come to himself’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 15:17.</p>
                    </note> and well content to be
                    therefore <pb n="152"/>thought ‘beside himself’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 3:21.</p>
                    </note> by
                    those who are still feeding upon the husks which he hath left?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                        15:16-17.</p>
                    </note> Art thou willing to ‘live godly in Christ Jesus’? And
                    dost thou therefore ‘suffer persecution’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> Do ‘men say all
                    manner of evil against thee falsely, for the Son of man’s sake’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            5:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. O that in all these questions ye may hear the voice that wakes the
                    dead, and feel that hammer of the Word which ‘breaketh the rock in pieces’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer.
                        23:29.</p>
                    </note> ‘If ye will hear his voice today, while it is called
                    today, harden not your hearts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 3:8, 15, etc.</p>
                    </note> Now ‘awake, thou
                    that sleepest’ in spiritual death, that thou sleep not in death eternal! Feel
                    thy lost estate, and ‘arise from the dead.’ Leave thine old companions in sin
                    and death. Follow thou Jesus, and ‘let the dead bury their dead.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        8:22.</p>
                    </note> ‘Save thyself from this untoward generation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        2:40.</p>
                    </note> ‘Come out from among them, and be thou separate, and touch
                    not the unclean thing; and the Lord shall receive thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 6:17.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘Christ shall give thee light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. This promise I come, lastly, to explain. And how encouraging a
                    consideration is this, that whosoever thou art who obeyest his call, thou canst
                    not seek his face in vain. If thou even now ‘awakest and arisest from the dead’,
                    he hath bound himself to ‘give thee light’. ‘The Lord shall give thee grace and
                        glory;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 84:11 (AV).</p>
                    </note> the light of his grace here, and the
                    light of his glory when thou receivest the ‘crown that fadeth not away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            5:4.</p>
                    </note> ‘Thy light shall break forth as the morning,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            58:8.Cf. Isa. 58:8.</p>
                    </note> and thy darkness be as the noonday.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        58:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘God, who commanded the light to shine out of darkness’,
                    shall ‘shine in thy heart, to give the knowledge of the glory of God in the face
                    of Jesus Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> ‘On them that fear the
                    Lord shall the Sun of righteousness arise with healing in his wings.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mal.
                            4:2.</p>
                    </note> And ‘in that day it shall be said unto thee’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Zeph.
                            3:16.</p>
                    </note> ‘Arise, shine; for thy light is come, and the glory of
                    the Lord is risen upon thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 60:1.</p>
                    </note> For Christ shall reveal
                    himself in thee. And he is ‘the true light’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 1:9; 1 John 2:8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. God is light,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:5.</p>
                    </note> and will give himself to
                    every awakened sinner that waiteth for him. And thou shalt then be a temple of
                    the living God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:16.</p>
                    </note> and Christ shall ‘dwell in
                    thy heart by faith’. And, <pb n="153"/>‘being rooted and grounded in love’, thou
                    shalt ‘be able to comprehend with all saints what is the breadth, and length,
                    and depth, and height’ of that ‘love of Christ which passeth knowledge, that
                    thou mayest be filled with all the fullness of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                    3:17-19.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Ye see your calling, brethren. We are called to be ‘an habitation of God
                    through his Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:22.</p>
                    </note> and through his Spirit
                    dwelling in us ‘to be saints’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 1:7; 1 Cor. 1:2.</p>
                    </note> here, ‘and
                    partakers of the inheritance of the saints in light’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> So
                    ‘exceeding great are the promises which are given unto us’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:4.</p>
                    </note>
                    actually given unto us who believe. For by faith ‘we receive, not the spirit of
                    the world, but the Spirit which is of God’—the sum of all the promises—‘that we
                    may know the things that are freely given to us of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                    2:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. The Spirit of Christ is that great gift of God which at sundry times and
                    in divers manners<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 1:1.</p>
                    </note> he hath promised to man, and
                    hath fully bestowed since the time that Christ was glorified. Those promises
                    before made to the fathers he hath thus fulfilled: ‘I will put my Spirit within
                    you, and cause you to walk in my statutes.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ezek. 36:27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘I will
                    pour water upon him that is thirsty, and floods upon the dry ground: I will pour
                    my Spirit upon thy seed, and my blessing upon thine offspring.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa.
                                44:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Ye may all be living witnesses of these things, of remission of sins,
                    and the gift of the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 2:38; 10:43; note the implied rejection
                            here of the patristic notion of ‘the seal of the Spirit’ in baptism (cf.
                            2 Cor. 1:22; Eph. 1:13; 4:30).</p>
                    </note> ‘If thou canst believe, all
                    things are possible to him that believeth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:23.</p>
                    </note> ‘Who among you is
                    there that feareth the Lord’, and yet ‘walketh on in darkness, and hath no
                        light?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 50:10.</p>
                    </note> I ask thee in the name of Jesus, believest
                    thou that ‘his arm is not shortened at all’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 50:2; 59:1.</p>
                    </note> That he is
                    still ‘mighty to save’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 63:1.</p>
                    </note> That he is ‘the same
                    yesterday, today, and for ever’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165" n="165">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:8.</p>
                    </note> That ‘he hath
                        <emph>now</emph> power on earth to forgive sins’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 9:6,
                        etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘Son, be of good cheer; thy sins are forgiven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn167" n="167">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            9:2.</p>
                    </note> God, for Christ’s sake, hath <pb n="154"/>forgiven thee.
                    Receive this, ‘not as the word of man; but as it is, indeed, the word of
                        God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168" n="168">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Thess. 2:13.</p>
                    </note> and thou art ‘justified freely through
                        faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn169" n="169">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt be sanctified also through faith
                    which is in Jesus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn170" n="170">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 26:18.</p>
                    </note> and shalt set to thy
                        seal,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn171" n="171">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            John 3:33.</p>
                    </note> even thine, ‘that God hath given unto us eternal
                    life, and this life is in his Son’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn172" n="172">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.1 John 5:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Men and brethren, let me freely speak unto you,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn173" n="173">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:29.</p>
                    </note> and
                    ‘suffer ye the word of exhortation’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn174" n="174">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 13:22.</p>
                    </note> even from one the
                    least esteemed in the church. Your conscience beareth you witness in the
                        HolyGhost<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn175" n="175">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 9:1.</p>
                    </note> that these things are so, ‘if so be ye have
                    tasted that the Lord is gracious’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn176" n="176">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> ‘This is eternal life, to
                    know the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom he hath sent.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn177" n="177">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 17:3.</p>
                    </note>
                    This experimental knowledge,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn178" n="178">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, ‘personal’,
                            ‘existential’. Cf. Bishop Joseph Hall, Epistle VII, ‘To Mr. William
                            Bedell’, in <hi rend="italic">Select Works</hi> (London, 1811), IV.138;
                            and Bishop Laurence Womock, <hi rend="italic">The Examination of
                                Tilenus</hi> (1661),p. 85. This distinction between ‘speculative’
                            and ‘practical’ religion is pervasive in the writings of both Wesley
                            brothers. Note the implied either/or here; this, too, will soften as the
                            Revival matures.</p>
                    </note> and this alone, is true Christianity. He is
                    a Christian who hath received the Spirit of Christ. He is not a Christian who
                    hath not received him. Neither is it possible to have received him and not know
                    it. For ‘at that day’ (when he cometh, saith the Lord) ‘ye shall know that I am
                    in my Father, and you in me, and I in you.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John 14:20.</p>
                        </note> This is that
                        ‘Spirit of truth, whom the world cannot receive, because it seeth him not,
                        neither knoweth him. But ye know him; for he dwelleth with you, and shall be
                        in you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn179" n="179">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John 14:17. Note the radical either/or here: either a clear and
                                full assurance of justifying faith or none at all. Southey,
                                I.150-53, observes that it was this stark disjunction between full
                                assurance and none at all that prompted many of the hysterical
                                symptoms reported in the early years of the Revival. Bernard G.
                                Holland confirms this thesis and extends it in ‘The Conversions of
                                John and Charles Wesley’, WHS, XXIII.53, 65-71, but also points to
                                the fact that both brothers rather quickly modified this
                                all-or-nothing emphasis by allowing for <emph>degrees</emph> of
                                assurance. This softening may be seen in John Wesley’s letter to Dr.
                                Rutherford, Mar. 28, 1768; and in Nos. 89, ‘The More Excellent Way’,
                                §§7, 8; and 106, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, I.11 (and for John’s
                                numerous references to the plerophory or ‘full assurance of faith’
                                cf. No. 117, ‘On the Discoveries of Faith’, §15 and n.).</p>
                            <p rend="footnote text">Melville Horne, once an active Methodist
                                itinerant, reports a ‘final’ word from John Wesley on this subject
                                (either from a letter or a conversation that must be dated somewhere
                                close to 1789): ‘When fifty years ago my brother Charles and I, in
                                the simplicity of our hearts, told the good people of England that
                                unless they knew their sins were forgiven, they were under the wrath
                                and curse of God, I marvel, Melville, they did not stone us!’; cf.
                                Melville Horne, <hi rend="italic">An Investigation of the Definition
                                    of Justifying Faith…</hi> (1809), p. 3; and Thomas Coke’s reply
                                to it in <hi rend="italic">A Series of Letters Addressed to the
                                    Methodist Connexion…</hi> (1810). See also Southey, I.216-17;
                                and Semmel, <hi rend="italic">Methodist Revolution</hi>, p.
                            100.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="7">
                    <pb n="155"/>7. The world cannot receive him, but utterly rejecteth the
                    promise of the Father, contradicting and blaspheming. But every spirit which
                    confesseth not this is not of God. Yea, ‘this is that spirit of antichrist,
                    whereof ye have heard that it should come into the world; and even now it is in
                    the world.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn180" n="180">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:3.</p>
                    </note> He is antichrist whosoever denies the
                    inspiration of the Holy Ghost, or that the indwelling Spirit of God is the
                    common privilege of all believers, the blessing of the gospel, the unspeakable
                    gift, the universal promise, the criterion of a real Christian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn181" n="181">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For a careful
                            statement of the general teaching about the gifts of the Holy Spirit as
                            extraordinary and exceptional, cf. Arthur Bedford, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Doctrine of Assurance…</hi> (1738). For another claim that such
                            gifts are the common privilege of all believers, cf. Moore, I.269,
                            reporting a conversation between John Wesley and Joseph Butler in
                            Bristol, Aug. 18, 1739, about faith and assurance. The bishop’s
                            complaint was candid: ‘Sir, the pretending to extraordinary revelations
                            and gifts of the Holy Ghost is a horrid thing, a very horrid thing.’
                            Wesley’s reply was meant to be disarming: ‘My lord, …I pretend to no
                            extraordinary revelations or gifts of the Holy Ghost—none but what every
                            Christian may receive, and ought to expect and pray for….’ See p. 13, n.
                            47 above; see also No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                            Christianity</hi>, §4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. It nothing helps them to say, ‘We do not deny the
                        <emph>assistance</emph> of God’s Spirit, but only this
                        <emph>inspiration</emph>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn182" n="182">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Moore also prints (II.277-322) a twelve-letter
                            exchange between Wesley and a pseudonymous ‘John Smith’. (See <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi> II, Vol. 26 of this edn.) Though an acute
                            theologian, ‘Smith’ almost certainly was not Thomas Seeker as Tyerman
                                (<hi rend="italic">JW</hi>), (I.409-10); Sugden (I.82); and Telford
                                (<hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, II.42) have suggested. Wesley’s
                            letter of Mar. 22, 1748, to ‘Smith’ indicates that he was a pastor of a
                            parish (‘If a single parish takes up your whole time and care, and you
                            spend and are spent upon it, well’). ‘Smith’ was deeply disturbed by
                            what he took to be a Wesleyan doctrine of assurance as ‘perceptible
                            inspiration’ (cf. Letter III, Nov. 27, 1745, and Letter V, Feb. 26,
                            1746). Wesley’s reply (Letter VI, June 25, 1746) rehearses once again
                            the claim that the gifts of the Spirit are meant for all truly converted
                            Christians. See also, below, Nos. 10 and 11, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit’, Discourses I and II.</p>
                    </note> this “receiving the Holy Ghost”
                    and being <emph>sensible</emph> of it. It is only this <emph>feeling</emph> of
                    the Spirit, this being <emph>moved</emph> by the Spirit, or filled with it,
                    which we deny to have any place in sound religion.’ But in ‘only’ denying this
                    you deny the whole Scriptures, the whole truth and promise and testimony of
                    God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. Our own excellent Church knows nothing of this devilish distinction; but
                    speaks plainly of ‘feeling the Spirit of Christ’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Article 17 [‘Of Predestination
                                and Election’: ‘…and such as feel in themselves the working of the
                                Spirit of Christ…’].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> of <pb n="156"/>being ‘moved by
                    the Holy Ghost’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Office of consecrating Priests [BCP, The
                                Ordering of Deacons].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and knowing and ‘feeling there
                    is no other name than that of Jesus whereby we can receive any salvation’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Visitation
                                of the Sick [<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, Of the
                        Sick].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> She teaches us also to pray for the ‘inspiration of
                    the Holy Spirit’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Collect before the Holy Communion [<hi rend="italic">ibid. </hi>].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> yea, that we may be
                    ‘filled with the Holy Ghost’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Order of Confirmation [<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi> However, the words do not occur there but in
                                Collects, St. Stephen’s Day].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Nay, and every
                    presbyter of hers professes to ‘receive the Holy Ghost by the imposition of
                        hands’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn183" n="183">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Ordering of Priests.</p>
                    </note> Therefore to deny any of these
                    is in effect to renounce the Church of England, as well as the whole Christian
                    revelation.</p>
                <p n="10">10. But ‘the wisdom of God’ was always ‘foolishness with men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn184" n="184">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            1:21-25.</p>
                    </note> No marvel, then, that the great mystery of the
                    gospel should be now also ‘hid from the wise and prudent’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn185" n="185">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 11:25.</p>
                    </note> as
                    well as in the days of old; that it should be almost universally denied,
                    ridiculed, and exploded as mere frenzy, and all who dare avow it still branded
                    with the names of madmen and enthusiasts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn186" n="186">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For samplings of eighteenth-century
                            denunciations of enthusiasm, cf. Lee, <hi rend="italic">Early Methodist
                                Enthusiasm</hi>, chs. 2-3.</p>
                    </note> This is that ‘falling
                        away’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn187" n="187">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Thess. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> which was to come—that general apostasy of all
                    orders and degrees of men which we even now find to have overspread the earth.
                    ‘Run to and fro in the streets of Jerusalem, and see if you can find a
                        man,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn188" n="188">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jer. 5:1.</p>
                    </note> a man that loveth the Lord his God with all his
                    heart, and serveth him with all his strength. How does our own land mourn (that
                    we look no farther) under the overflowings of ungodliness!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn189" n="189">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 18:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                    What villainies of every kind are committed day by day; yea, too often with
                    impunity by those who sin with a high hand, and glory in their shame!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn190" n="190">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil.
                        3:19.</p>
                    </note> Who can reckon up the oaths, curses, profaneness,
                    blasphemies; the lying, slandering, evil speaking; the sabbath-breaking,
                    gluttony, drunkenness, revenge; the whoredoms, adulteries, and various
                    uncleanness; the frauds, injustice, oppression, extortion, which overspread our
                    land as a flood?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn191" n="191">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 69:2, and No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, IV.11. See also Rom.
                        1:18-32.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. And even among those who have kept themselves pure from those grosser
                    abominations, how much anger and pride, <pb n="157"/>how much sloth and
                    idleness, how much softness and effeminacy, how much luxury and self-indulgence,
                    how much covetousness and ambition, how much thirst of praise,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn192" n="192">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For John Wesley’s references
                            to the common thirst for fame and glory (<hi rend="italic">gloria
                                sitis</hi>), see No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.7 and n.</p>
                    </note> how much love of the world,
                    how much fear of man is to be found! Meanwhile, how little of true religion! For
                    where is he that loveth either God or his neighbour, as he hath given us
                    commandment? On the one hand are those who have not so much as the form of
                    godliness; on the other, those who have the form only:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn193" n="193">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 3:5, and No. 2,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    there stands the open, there the painted sepulchre.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn194" n="194">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 23:27, and I.7 and
                            n., above.</p>
                    </note> So that, in very deed, whosoever were earnestly to
                    behold any public gathering together of the people (I fear those in our churches
                    are not to be excepted) might easily perceive ‘that the one part were Sadducees,
                    and the other Pharisees’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn195" n="195">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 23:6.</p>
                    </note> the one having almost as
                    little concern about religion as if there were ‘no resurrection, neither angel
                    nor spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn196" n="196">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 23:8.</p>
                    </note> and the other making it a mere lifeless form, a
                    dull round of external performances without either true faith, or the love of
                    God, or joy in the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn197" n="197">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. Would to God I could except us of this place. ‘Brethren, my heart’s
                    desire and prayer to God for you is that ye may be saved’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn198" n="198">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    from this overflowing of ungodliness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn199" n="199">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 18:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> and that here may
                    its proud waves be stayed!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn200" n="200">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Job 38:11.</p>
                    </note> But is it so indeed? God
                    knoweth, yea, and our own conscience, it is not. We have not kept ourselves
                        pure.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn201" n="201">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Tim. 5:22.</p>
                    </note> Corrupt are we also and abominable; and few are
                    there that understand any more, few that worship God in spirit and in
                        truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn202" n="202">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 4:24.</p>
                    </note> We too are ‘a generation that set not our hearts
                    aright, and whose spirit cleaveth not steadfastly unto God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn203" n="203">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 78:9
                        (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He hath appointed us indeed to be ‘the salt of the earth.
                    But if the salt have lost its savour, it is thenceforth good for nothing but to
                    be cast out, and to be trodden under foot of men.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn204" n="204">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. And ‘shall I not visit for these things? saith the Lord. Shall not my
                    soul be avenged on such a nation as this?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn205" n="205">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 5:9, 29.</p>
                    </note> Yea, we know not
                    how soon he may say to the sword, ‘Sword, go through this land!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn206" n="206">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ezek.
                            14:17.</p>
                    </note> He hath given us long space to repent. He lets us
                    alone this year also. But he warns and awakens us by thunder. His <pb n="158"/>judgments are abroad in the earth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn207" n="207">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 105:7 (AV). III.13-15 are echoes of the
                            compound crises in Europe in general and England in particular; Charles
                            Wesley could expect most of his hearers to share his alarm, even if for
                            different reasons. Sir Robert Walpole’s cynical reign had ended only two
                            months before, and a dangerous new future loomed ahead with the War of
                            the Austrian Succession (1739-48) which had pageengulfed an ineptly led
                            Britain; Charles Edward Stuart (‘Bonnie Prince Charlie’) was waiting in
                            the wings. In 1745-46 England and, much more tragically, Scotland became
                            ‘a field of blood’ (as at Culloden, Apr. 15, 1746). Cf. Robertson, <hi rend="italic">England Under the Hanoverians</hi>, pp. 80-111; and
                            Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Whig Supremacy</hi>, pp.
                        220-51.</p>
                    </note> And we have all reason to expect that heaviest of all,
                    even ‘that he should come unto us quickly, and remove our candlestick out of its
                    place, except we repent and do the first works’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn208" n="208">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 2:5.</p>
                    </note>
                    unless we return to the principles of the Reformation, the truth and simplicity
                    of the gospel. Perhaps we are now resisting the last effort of divine grace to
                    save us. Perhaps we have wellnigh ‘filled up the measure of our iniquities’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn209" n="209">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            23:32.</p>
                    </note> by rejecting the counsel of God against ourselves, and
                    casting out his messengers.</p>
                <p n="14">14. O God, ‘in the midst of wrath remember mercy’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn210" n="210">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Hab. 3:2.</p>
                    </note> Be
                    glorified in our reformation, not in our destruction. Let us ‘hear the rod, and
                    him that appointed it’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn211" n="211">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mic. 6:9.</p>
                    </note> Now that ‘thy judgments
                    are abroad in the earth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn212" n="212">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Chr. 16:14; Ps.105:7.</p>
                    </note> let ‘the
                    inhabitants of the world learn righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn213" n="213">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 26:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="15">15. My brethren, it is high time for us to awake out of sleep; before ‘the
                    great trumpet of the Lord be blown’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn214" n="214">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 27:13.</p>
                    </note> and our land become a
                    field of blood.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn215" n="215">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 27:8.</p>
                    </note> O may we speedily see the
                    things that make for our peace, before they are hid from our eyes!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn216" n="216">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                            19:42.</p>
                    </note> ‘Turn thou us, O good Lord, and let thine anger cease
                    from us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn217" n="217">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 85:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘O Lord, look down from heaven, behold and
                    visit this vine’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn218" n="218">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 80:14.</p>
                    </note> and cause us to know the
                    time of our visitation.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn219" n="219">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Jer. 8:12, etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘Help us, O God of
                    our salvation, for the glory of thy name; O deliver us, and be merciful to our
                    sins, for thy name’s sake.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn220" n="220">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 79:9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘And so will we not go
                    back from thee: O let us live, and we shall call upon thy name. Turn us again, O
                    Lord God of hosts, show the light of thy countenance, and we shall be
                        whole.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn221" n="221">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 80:18-19 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
                <p>‘Now unto him that is able to do exceeding abundantly above all that we can ask
                    or think, according to the power that worketh in us, unto him be glory in the
                    church by Christ Jesus throughout all ages, world without end. Amen.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn222" n="222">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            3:20-21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>