<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 9: The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon009</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 9: The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="248" to="266"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <pb n="248"/>
            </p>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>In this sermon Wesley returns to the theme of ‘faith alone’, now in the context
                    of a borrowed typology about the three states of man: ‘natural’, ‘legal’, and
                    ‘evangelical’ (a scheme that presupposes man’s original state as that of
                    innocence). His ‘classical’ source for such a scheme is in St. Augustine’s <hi rend="italic">Enchiridion</hi>, xxxi (117-19). His ‘modern’ source here
                    would have been Thomas Boston’s <hi rend="italic">Human Nature in Its Fourfold
                        State</hi> (Edinburgh, 1720)—henceforth ‘Boston’. Wesley’s interest in such
                    typologies may be seen in an early letter to his mother, February 14, 1735, and
                    an interesting entry in Benjamin Ingham’s diary for March 17, 1734: ‘7:00 a.m.
                    Breakfast with John Robson and John Wesley; religious talk of three different
                    states of man: natural, Jewish (or fearful), and evangelical—the two last only,
                    salvable.’</p>
                <p>At this point in the development of his soteriology after 1738, the term
                    ‘natural’ was understood by John Wesley (as it had been by Charles in <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>) as a condition of moral
                    anomie. This sermon, then, is John’s positive version of Charles’s earlier
                    sermon. Later (as in No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, III.4), he will
                    revise his view and assert that ‘there is no man that is in a state of mere
                    nature, no man, unless he has quenched the Spirit, that is wholly void of the
                    grace of God. No man living is entirely destitute of what is vulgarly called
                    “natural conscience”. But this is not natural: it is more properly termed
                    “preventing grace”. Every man has a greater or less measure of this….’ But
                    notice that in I.2, 4-5, he pursues the self-excusing ‘natural man’ into the
                    depths of his unconscious motives as if there were a conscience at their core.
                    Sin is not defined as deliberate violations of known laws of God (as in No. 13,
                        <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9 and n.): ‘it
                    extends to every temper, desire, thought, and motion of the heart.’ This differs
                    also from his views in No. 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>.</p>
                <p>Wesley’s main concern, however, is with the contrast between the harrowed
                    conscience and spiritual despair of those who in their ‘legal state’ have been
                    ‘awakened’ (but continue as guilt-ridden and unhappy, <pb n="249"/>despite their
                    best efforts at good works and religious observances) and the peace, joy, and
                    good conscience of those who have <hi rend="italic">heard</hi> the gospel and
                    are assured of God’s justifying grace. Here he is echoing Thomas Boston’s moving
                    description of ‘Peace with God and Peace of Conscience’ (<hi rend="italic">op.
                        cit.</hi>, State III, Head II). Thus, this sermon is Wesley’s interpretation
                    of the contrast delineated in Romans 7 and 8, with Romans 7 taken as a
                    description of despair in the ‘legal state’ and Romans 8 as St. Paul’s
                    celebration of ‘evangelical’ grace. Thus, the sermon concludes with an
                    invitation to those living under the Law to accept God’s proffered pardon and to
                    ‘rejoice and love like the angels of God’.</p>
                <p>It is worth noting that of the six sermons that follow after the bloc of
                    ‘university sermons,’ five (Nos. 5, 6, 8, 9, and 10) have their texts from
                    Romans. This is not accidental, for these are the sermons in which Wesley has
                    distilled the essence of his gospel of justification. He had already preached
                    from Romans 8:15 thirteen times: three times in 1739, once in 1740, three times
                    in 1741, four times in 1742, and twice in 1743—all in the early years of the
                    Revival. He seems to have neglected it thereafter.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 8:15</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ye have not received the spirit of bondage again unto fear;
                        but ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry, Abba,
                        Father.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. St. Paul here speaks to those who are the children of God by faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                        3:26.</p>
                    </note> Ye, saith he, who are indeed his children, have drunk into
                    his Spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Cor. 10:4.</p>
                    </note> ‘Ye have not received the spirit of bondage again
                    unto fear;’ but ‘because ye are sons, God hath sent forth the Spirit of his Son
                    into your hearts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> ‘Ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby
                    we cry, Abba, Father.’</p>
                <p n="2">
                    <pb n="250"/>2. The spirit of bondage and fear is widely distant from this
                    loving Spirit of adoption. Those who are influenced only by slavish fear cannot
                    be termed the sons of God. Yet some of them may be styled his servants,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The earliest
                            instance in the published sermons of the distinction between the faith
                            of ‘servants’ and of ‘sons’/’children’. It had already appeared in the
                                <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi> (May 13, 1746). It will be further
                            developed after this to become a Wesleyan commonplace (as in No. 106,
                            ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, espec. I:10 and n.).</p>
                    </note> and ‘are not far
                    from the kingdom of heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:34.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. But it is to be feared the bulk of mankind, yea, of what is called ‘the
                    Christian world’, have not attained even this; but are still afar off, ‘neither
                    is God in all their thoughts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 10:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> A few names may be
                    found of those who love God; a few more there are that fear him. But the greater
                    part have neither the fear of God before their eyes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 3:18.</p>
                    </note> nor
                    the love of God in their hearts.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Perhaps most of you, who by the mercy of God now partake of a better
                    spirit, may remember the time when ye were as they, when ye were under the same
                    condemnation. But at first ye knew it not, though ye were wallowing daily in
                    your sins and in your blood; till in due time ye ‘received the spirit of
                        fear’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:15; 2 Tim. 1:7.</p>
                    </note> (ye <hi rend="italic">received</hi>; for
                    this also is the gift of God);’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 111:10, ‘The fear of the Lord is the
                            beginning of wisdom.’</p>
                    </note> and afterwards fear vanished away, and
                    the spirit of love filled your hearts.</p>
                <p n="5">5. One who is in the first state of mind, without fear or love, is in
                    Scripture termed ‘a natural man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:14. Cf. Boston, State II, Head II, ‘The
                            State of Nature’. For other references to ‘natural man’, see No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, I.1 and n.; and espec. No. 2,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>. See also Nos. 17, ‘The
                            Circumcision of the Heart’, §2; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that
                            are Born of God’, I.3-10; 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>,
                            II.1-2; 45, ‘The New Birth’, I.4; 63, ‘The General Spread of the
                            Gospel’, §§9-10; 130, ‘On Living without God’, §6.</p>
                    </note> One who is
                    under the spirit of bondage and fear is sometimes said to be ‘under the
                        law’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            6:14, 15.</p>
                    </note> (although that expression more frequently signifies
                    one who is under the Jewish dispensation, who thinks himself obliged to observe
                    all the rites and ceremonies of the Jewish law). But one who has exchanged the
                    spirit of fear for the spirit of love is properly said to be ‘under grace’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Now because it highly imports us to know what spirit we are of, I shall endeavour
                    to point out distinctly, first, the state of a ‘natural man’; secondly, that of
                    one who is ‘under the law’; and thirdly, of one who is ‘under grace’.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">
                    <pb n="251"/>I. 1. And, first, the state of a ‘natural man’. This the
                    Scripture represents as a state of sleep. The voice of God to him is, ‘Awake,
                    thou that sleepest.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:14. See No. 3, ‘<hi rend="italic">Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest</hi>’, on this text.</p>
                    </note> For his soul is
                    in a deep sleep. His spiritual senses are not awake; they discern neither
                    spiritual good nor evil. The eyes of his understanding are closed;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            1:18.</p>
                    </note> they are sealed together, and see not. Clouds and
                    darkness continually rest upon them;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This echoes a line in Addison’s famous drama, <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi>, V.i:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>The wide, the unbounded prospect lies before me;</l>
                            <l>But shadows, clouds, and darkness rest upon it.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley quotes these lines in other sermons. See
                            below, No. 117, ‘On the Discoveries of Faith’, §8 and n.</p>
                    </note> for
                    he lies in the valley of the shadow of death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 23:4.</p>
                    </note> Hence, having no inlets
                    for the knowledge of spiritual things,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This same phrase—reflecting the same
                            epistemology—as above in Charles’s sermon, No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, I.11. Cf. also No. 10, ‘The
                            Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p>
                    </note> all the avenues of his
                    soul being shut up, he is in gross, stupid ignorance of whatever he is most
                    concerned to know. He is utterly ignorant of God, knowing nothing concerning him
                    as he ought to know. He is totally a stranger to the law of God, as to its true,
                    inward, spiritual meaning. He has no conception of that evangelical holiness
                    without which no man shall see the Lord;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:14.</p>
                    </note> nor of the happiness
                    which they only find whose ‘life is hid with Christ in God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:3; once again, the
                            correlation between ‘holiness’ and ‘happiness’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And for this very reason, because he is fast <hi rend="italic">asleep</hi>, he is in some sense at <hi rend="italic">rest</hi>. Because he
                    is <hi rend="italic">blind</hi>, he is also <hi rend="italic">secure</hi>: he
                    saith, ‘Tush, …there shall no harm happen unto me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 10:6 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> The
                    darkness which covers him on every side keeps him in a kind of peace—so far as
                    peace can consist with the works of the devil, and with an earthly, devilish
                        mind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Jas. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> He <hi rend="italic">sees</hi> not that he stands
                    on the edge of the pit; therefore he <hi rend="italic">fears</hi> it not. He
                    cannot tremble at the danger he does not know. He has not understanding enough
                    to fear. Why is it that he is in no dread of God? Because he is totally ignorant
                    of him: if not ‘saying in his heart, There is no God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 14:1; 53:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    or that he ‘sitteth on the circle of the heavens’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 40:22.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘and humbleth’ not ‘himself <pb n="252"/>to behold the things’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 113:6 (AV).</p>
                    </note>
                    which are done on earth; yet satisfying himself as well, to all Epicurean
                    intents and purposes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The typical eighteenth-century estimate of
                            ‘Epicurism’ is reflected in Samuel Johnson’s definition: ‘sensual
                            enjoyment; gross pleasure’. Wesley had this in mind when he labelled
                            Horace an ‘Epicurean poet’, in No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, I. (III.)9. But he also knew of Cicero’s more
                            positive views in <hi rend="italic">De Natura Deorum (On the Nature of
                                the Gods)</hi>, i. 19, and also the interesting passage on
                            Epicureanism in Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> (1728),
                            where a distinction is made between ‘rigid Epicureans’ and the ‘loose or
                            remiss’ ones. The former ‘thought it above the majesty of the deity to
                            concern himself with human affairs’. The latter ‘placed all their
                            happiness in pleasures of the body….’ For some of Wesley’s other
                            references to ‘elegant Epicurism’, cf. Nos. 50, ‘The Use of Money’,
                            II.2; 78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, I.5; and 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’,
                            I.13.</p>
                    </note> by saying, ‘God is merciful;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 116:5. In ascribing to
                            either the ‘natural’ or ‘legal’ man any idea of God as being merciful,
                            etc., Wesley seems to have confounded the Epicureans with the Gnostics
                            whom Plotinus had denounced along with the Christians—the latter,
                            though, for rather different reasons; cf. Plotinus, ‘Against the
                            Gnostics’ in the Ninth Tractate of <hi rend="italic">Enneads</hi> II;
                            see A. H. Armstrong, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Cambridge History of
                                Later Greek and Early Medieval Philosophy</hi> (1967), pp. 205-6,
                            243-45.</p>
                    </note> confounding and swallowing up at once in that
                    unwieldy idea of mercy all his holiness and essential hatred of sin, all his
                    justice, wisdom, and truth. He is in no dread of the vengeance denounced against
                    those who obey not the blessed law of God, because he understands it not. He
                    imagines the main point is to <hi rend="italic">do thus</hi>, to be <hi rend="italic">outwardly</hi> blameless—and sees not that it extends to every
                    temper, desire, thought, motion of the heart. Or he fancies that the obligation
                    hereto is ceased, that Christ came to ‘destroy the law and the prophets’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:17.</p>
                    </note> to save his people <hi rend="italic">in</hi>, not <hi rend="italic">from</hi> their sins, to bring them to heaven without
                        holiness;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            oblique criticism of Christian antinomians (e.g., Agricola, the
                            Moravians, William Cudworth, James Relly); see No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro.</p>
                    </note> notwithstanding his own
                    words, ‘Not one jot or tittle of the law shall pass away till all things are
                        fulfilled,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:18.</p>
                    </note> and, ‘Not everyone that saith unto me, Lord,
                    Lord, shall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doth the will of my
                    Father which is in heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 7:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. He is secure, because he is utterly ignorant of himself. Hence he talks
                    of ‘repenting by and by’; he does not indeed exactly know when; but some time or
                    other before he dies—taking it for granted that this is quite in his own
                        power.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In
                            his Oxford days, Wesley had borrowed, abridged, and preached a sermon of
                            Benjamin Calamy’s against ‘death-bed repentance’ to the prisoners in the
                            Castle; see Vol. 4, Appendix C.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="253"/>For what should hinder his doing it if he will? If he does but once
                    set a resolution, no fear but he will make it good.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the flat rejection here
                            of any notion of moral freedom (and the power not to sin) in ‘the <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> man’. The <hi rend="italic">posse non
                                peccare</hi>, then, is a divine gift of justifying and regenerating
                            grace. For other references to liberty and will, cf. No. 60, ‘The
                            General Deliverance’, I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. But this ignorance never so strongly glares as in those who are termed
                    ‘men of learning’. If a natural man be one of these, he can talk at large of his
                    rational faculties, of the freedom of his will and the absolute necessity of
                    such freedom in order to constitute man a moral agent.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 63, ‘The General
                            Spread of the Gospel’, §11.</p>
                    </note> He reads and argues, and proves
                    to a demonstration that every man may do as he will, may dispose his own heart
                    to evil or good as it seems best in his own eyes. Thus the god of this world
                    spreads a double veil of blindness over his heart, lest by any means ‘the light
                    of the glorious gospel of Christ should shine’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:4.</p>
                    </note> upon it.</p>
                <p n="5">5. From the same ignorance of himself and God there may sometimes arise in
                    the natural man a kind of joy in congratulating himself upon his own wisdom and
                    goodness. And what the world calls joy he may often possess. He may have
                    pleasure in various kinds, either in gratifying the desires of the flesh, or the
                    desire of the eye, or the pride of life<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 2:16. See also below, III.7; and cf.
                            No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note>—particularly if
                    he has large possessions, if he enjoy an affluent fortune.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The first instance in the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> of this sense of ‘affluent’ is from ‘Junius’,
                            and dated 1769. Samuel Johnson cites it from Pope and Prior. Thus, it
                            was a ‘modern’ usage in Wesley’s time and a sample of his interest in
                            current speech.</p>
                    </note> Then he may ‘clothe himself in purple and
                    fine linen, and fare sumptuously every day’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:19.</p>
                    </note> And <hi rend="italic">so long as</hi> he thus <hi rend="italic">doth well unto
                        himself</hi>, ‘men will’ doubtless ‘speak good of’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 6:26.</p>
                    </note> him.
                    They will say he is a happy man; for indeed this is the sum of worldly
                    happiness—to dress, and visit, and talk, and eat, and drink, and rise up to
                        play.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Exod. 32:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. It is not surprising if one in such circumstances as these, dozed<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">It seems almost
                            certain here that Wesley is using the participial adjective of ‘dosed’,
                            of which <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> cites examples from 1659 to
                            1849.</p>
                    </note> with the opiates of flattery and sin, should imagine,
                    among his other waking dreams, that he walks in great <hi rend="italic">liberty</hi>. How easily may he persuade himself that he is at liberty from
                    all ‘vulgar errors’ and from the ‘prejudice’ of education, judging <pb n="254"/>exactly right, and keeping clear of all extremes. ‘I am free (may he say) from
                    all the <hi rend="italic">enthusiasm</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 37, ‘The Nature of
                        Enthusiasm’.</p>
                    </note> of weak and narrow souls; from <hi rend="italic">superstition</hi>, the disease of fools and cowards, always righteous
                    overmuch; and from <hi rend="italic">bigotry</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 38, ‘A Caution against
                            Bigotry’.</p>
                    </note> continually incident to those who have not a free
                    and generous way of thinking.’ And too sure it is that he is altogether free
                    from the ‘wisdom which cometh from above’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 3:17.</p>
                    </note> from holiness, from
                    the religion of the heart, from the whole mind which was in Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil.
                            2:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. For all this time he is the servant of sin. He commits sin, more or
                    less, day by day. Yet he is not troubled; he ‘is in no bondage’ (as some speak),
                    he feels no condemnation. He contents himself (even though he should profess to
                    believe that the Christian revelation is of God) with: ‘Man is frail. We are all
                    weak. Every man has his infirmity.’ Perhaps he quotes Scripture: ‘Why, does not
                    Solomon say, “The righteous man falls into sin seven times a day”?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An ironic
                            metaphrase of Prov. 24:16, where the original refers to the righteous
                            man’s falling (lit. ‘stumbling’) into adversity and being delivered. But
                            seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Puritan exegetes had come to
                            understand נפל as connoting a fall into sin. Thus Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, and Henry, <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>, (‘The just man falls, sometimes falls seven times,
                            perhaps into sin, …but he rises again, by repentance finds mercy with
                            God, and regains his peace’). In <hi rend="italic">A Plain Account of
                                Christian Perfection</hi>, §12, Wesley will dispute the point again:
                            ‘Here [Prov. 24:16] is no mention of “falling into sin” at all. What is
                            here mentioned is “falling into temporal affliction”.’); in <hi rend="italic">Predestination Calmly Considered</hi>, §§69-79, he
                            will argue the question of ‘perseverance’ with Dr. John Gill
                            (1697-1771), a Baptist minister at Horsleydown and author of <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of the Saints’ Final Perseverance
                                Asserted and Vindicated</hi> (1752). Cf. also No. 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.9; and see the homily on
                            ‘An Information for Them That Take Offence at Certain Places in the Holy
                            Scripture’, Pt. II, <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p. 335.</p>
                    </note>
                    And doubtless they are all hypocrites or enthusiasts who pretend to be better
                    than their neighbours.’ If at any time a serious thought fix upon him, he
                    stifles it as soon as possible with, ‘Why should I fear, since God is merciful,
                    and Christ died for sinners?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> Thus he remains a willing
                    servant of sin, content with the bondage of corruption;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:21.</p>
                    </note> inwardly
                    and outwardly unholy, and satisfied therewith; not only not conquering sin, but
                    not striving to conquer, particularly that sin which doth so easily beset
                        him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Such is the state of every ‘natural man’; whether he be a gross,
                    scandalous transgressor, or a more reputable and decent <pb n="255"/>sinner,
                    having the form though not the power of godliness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 3:5, from whence it
                            would follow that ‘the almost Christian’, as Wesley had already
                            described him, was ‘a natural man’, ‘<hi rend="italic">utterly</hi>
                            ignorant of God, …<hi rend="italic">totally</hi> a stranger to the law
                            of God’ (above, I.1).</p>
                    </note> But how can such an one be ‘convinced
                    of sin’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 8:46.</p>
                    </note> How is he brought to <hi rend="italic">repent</hi>? To be ‘under the law’? To receive the ‘spirit of bondage unto
                    fear’? This is the point which is next to be considered.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p n="1">II. 1. By some awful providence, or by his Word applied with the
                    demonstration of his Spirit, God touches the heart of him that lay asleep in
                    darkness and in the shadow of death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 107:10; Luke 1:79.</p>
                    </note> He is terribly
                    shaken out of his sleep, and awakes into a consciousness of his danger. Perhaps
                    in a moment, perhaps by degrees, the eyes of his understanding are opened,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            1:18.</p>
                    </note> and now first (the veil being in part removed) discern
                    the real state he is in. Horrid light breaks in upon his soul; such light as may
                    be conceived to gleam from the bottomless pit, from the lowest deep, from a lake
                    of fire burning with brimstone.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 19:20.</p>
                    </note> He at last sees the loving,
                    the merciful God is also ‘a consuming fire’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 4:24; Heb. 12:29.</p>
                    </note> that he is
                    a just God and a terrible, rendering to every man according to his works,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Prov. 24:12; cf.
                            Ps. 62:12.</p>
                    </note> entering into judgment with the ungodly for every
                    idle word, yea, and for the imaginations of the heart. He now clearly perceives
                    that the great and holy God is ‘of purer eyes than to behold iniquity’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Hab.
                            1:13.</p>
                    </note> that he is an avenger of everyone who rebelleth against
                    him, and repayeth the wicked to his face;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Deut. 7:10.</p>
                    </note> and that ‘it is a
                    fearful thing to fall into the hands of the living God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:31; note here an
                            abrupt shift in mood and rhetoric.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. The inward, spiritual meaning of the law of God now begins to glare upon
                    him. He perceives the ‘commandment is exceeding broad’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:96.</p>
                    </note> and
                    ‘there is nothing hid from the light thereof.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 19:6.</p>
                    </note> He is convinced that
                    every part of it relates not barely to outward sin or obedience, but to whit
                    passes in the secret recesses of the soul, which no eye but God’s can penetrate.
                    If he now hears, ‘Thou shalt not kill,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:13, etc.</p>
                    </note> God speaks in
                    thunder, ‘He that hateth his brother is a murderer;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:15.</p>
                    </note> he
                    that saith unto his brother, ‘Thou fool, is obnoxious to hellfire.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:22,
                            and see No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, II.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> If the
                    law say, ‘Thou shalt not <pb n="256"/>commit adultery,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:14, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                    the voice of the Lord sounds in his ears, ‘He that looketh on a woman to lust
                    after her hath committed adultery with her already in his heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:28.</p>
                    </note> And thus in every point he feels the Word of God ‘quick and
                    powerful, sharper than a two-edged sword’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 4:12.</p>
                    </note> It pierces ‘even to
                    the dividing asunder of his soul and spirit, his joints and marrow’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> And so much the more because he is conscious
                        <hi rend="italic">to himself</hi> of having neglected so great
                        salvation;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> of having ‘trodden under foot the Son of God’
                    who would have saved him from his sins, and ‘counted the blood of the covenant
                    an unholy’, a common, unsanctifying ‘thing’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:29.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. And as he knows ‘all things are naked and opened unto the eyes of him
                    with whom we have to do,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 4:13.</p>
                    </note> so he sees himself naked,
                    stripped of all the fig-leaves which he had sewed together, of all his poor
                    pretences to religion or virtue, and his wretched excuses for sinning against
                    God. He now sees himself like the ancient sacrifices, τετραχηλισμένον,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A lexical oddity.
                            Sugden, <hi rend="italic">Standard Sermons</hi>, I.187, has confused it
                            with the τομώτερος in Heb. 4:12. Wesley’s term does not appear in
                            Liddell and Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, Arndt
                            and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, nor Lampe,
                                <hi rend="italic">A Patristic Greek Lexicon</hi>. Its meaning is
                            clear enough—‘drawn and quartered’—but not its source.</p>
                    </note> ‘cleft
                    in sunder’, as it were, from the neck downward, so that all within him stands
                    confessed. His heart is bare, and he sees it is all sin, ‘deceitful above all
                    things, desperately wicked’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 17:9.</p>
                    </note> that it is altogether corrupt
                    and abominable, more than it is possible for tongue to express; that there
                    dwelleth there no good thing,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 7:18.</p>
                    </note> but unrighteousness and
                    ungodliness only; every motion thereof, every temper and thought, being only
                    evil continually.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gen. 6:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And he not only sees, but feels in himself, by an emotion of soul which
                    he cannot describe, that for the sins of his heart, were his life without blame
                    (which yet it is not, and cannot be; seeing ‘an evil tree cannot bring forth
                    good fruit’),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:18; Luke 6:43.</p>
                    </note> he deserves to be cast into ‘the
                    fire that never shall be quenched’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:43.</p>
                    </note> He feels that ‘the wages’,
                    the just reward, ‘of sin’, of his sin above all, ‘is death;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:23.</p>
                    </note> even the
                    second death,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 21:8.</p>
                    </note> the death which dieth not, the destruction of
                    body and soul in hell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 10:28.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">
                    <pb n="257"/>5. Here ends his pleasing dream, his delusive rest, his false
                    peace, his vain security. His joy now vanishes as a cloud; pleasures once loved
                    delight no more. They pall upon the taste; he loathes the nauseous sweet;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Samuel
                            Johnson’s quotation from Denham (under ‘nauseous’):</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Those trifles wherein children take delight,</l>
                            <l>Grow nauseous to the young man’s appetite.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </note> he is weary to bear them. The shadows of happiness flee away,
                    and sink into oblivion; so that he is stripped of all, and wanders to and fro
                    seeking rest, but finding none.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 12:43; Luke 11:24.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. The fumes of those opiates being now dispelled, he feels the anguish of
                    a wounded spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, III.4.</p>
                    </note> He finds that sin let
                    loose upon the soul (whether it be pride, anger, or evil desire; whether
                    self-will, malice, envy, revenge, or any other) is perfect misery. He feels
                    sorrow of heart for the blessings he has lost, and the curse which is come upon
                    him; remorse for having thus destroyed himself, and despised his own mercies;
                    fear, from a lively sense of the wrath of God, and of the consequences of his
                    wrath; of the punishment which he has justly deserved, and which he sees hanging
                    over his head; fear of death, as being to him the gate of hell, the entrance of
                    death eternal; fear of the devil, the executioner of the wrath and righteous
                    vengeance of God; fear of men, who if they were able to kill his body, would
                    thereby plunge both body and soul into hell;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 10:28.</p>
                    </note> fear, sometimes
                    arising to such a height that the poor, sinful, guilty soul is terrified with
                    everything, with nothing, with shades,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., ghosts; cf. Johnson, <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>, No. 10, and his citations from Dryden and
                            Tickell.</p>
                    </note> with a leaf shaken of the wind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Lev. 26:36.</p>
                    </note>
                    Yea, sometimes it may even border upon distraction, making a man ‘drunken,
                    though not with wine’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 29:9; 51:21.</p>
                    </note> suspending the
                    exercise of the memory, of the understanding, of all the natural faculties.
                    Sometimes it may approach to the very brink of despair; so that he who trembles
                    at the name of death may yet be ready to plunge into it every moment, to ‘choose
                    strangling rather than life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 7:15.</p>
                    </note> Well may such a man
                    ‘roar’, like him of old, ‘for the very disquietness of his heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 38:8
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Well may he cry out, ‘The spirit of a man may sustain
                    his infirmities; but a wounded spirit who can bear?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov.
                    18:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">
                    <pb n="258"/>7. Now he truly desires to break loose from sin, and begins to
                    struggle with it. But though he strive with all his might he cannot conquer; sin
                    is mightier than he. He would fain escape; but he is so fast in prison that he
                    cannot get forth. He resolves against sin, but yet sins on; he sees the snare,
                    and abhors—and runs into it. So much does his boasted reason avail—only to
                    enhance his guilt, and increase his misery! Such is the freedom of his will—free
                    only to evil; free to ‘drink in iniquity like water’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 15:16.</p>
                    </note> to
                    wander farther and farther from the living God, and do more ‘despite to the
                    Spirit of grace’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:29.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. The more he strives, wishes, labours to be free, the more does he feel
                    his chains, the grievous chains of sin, wherewith Satan binds and ‘leads him
                    captive at his will’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:26.</p>
                    </note> His servant he is,
                    though he repine ever so much; though he rebel, he cannot prevail. He is still
                    in bondage and fear by reason of sin: generally of some outward sin, to which he
                    is peculiarly disposed either by nature, custom, or outward circumstances; but
                    always of some inward sin, some evil temper or unholy affection. And the more he
                    frets against it, the more it prevails; he may bite, but cannot break his chain.
                    Thus he toils without end, repenting and sinning, and repenting and sinning
                    again, till at length the poor sinful, helpless wretch is even at his wit’s end,
                    and can barely groan, ‘O wretched man that I am, who shall deliver me from the
                    body of this death?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:14, 15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. This whole struggle of one who is ‘under the law’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:24.</p>
                    </note> under
                    the ‘spirit of fear and bondage’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> is beautifully described by
                    the Apostle in the foregoing chapter, speaking in the person of an awakened man.
                    ‘I (saith he) was alive without the law once.’ I had much life, wisdom,
                    strength, and virtue—so I thought. ‘But when the commandment came, sin revived,
                    and I died.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Rom. 7,] ver. 9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> When the
                    commandment, in its spiritual meaning, came to my heart with the power of God my
                    inbred sin was stirred up, fretted, inflamed, and all my virtue died away. ‘And
                    the commandment, which was ordained to life, I found to be unto death. For sin,
                    taking occasion by the commandment, deceived me, and by it slew me.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                10-11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> It came <pb n="259"/>upon me unawares, slew
                    all my hopes, and plainly showed, in the midst of life I was in death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See BCP, Burial
                            (477).</p>
                    </note> ‘Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy,
                    and just, and good:’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> I no longer lay the
                    blame on this, but on the corruption of my own heart. I acknowledge that ‘the
                    law is spiritual; but I am carnal, sold under sin.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 14. [Cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> here on ‘the whole process of a man
                                reasoning, groaning, striving, and escaping from the legal to the
                                evangelical state’.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> I now see both the spiritual
                    nature of the law, and my own carnal devilish heart, ‘sold under sin’, totally
                    enslaved (like slaves bought with money, who were absolutely at their master’s
                    disposal). ‘For that which I do, I allow not; for what I would, I do not; but
                    what I hate, that I do.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Such is the bondage
                    under which I groan; such the tyranny of my hard master. ‘To will is present
                    with me, but how to perform that which is good I find not. For the good that I
                    would I do not; but the evil which I would not, that I do.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                18-19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘I find a law’, an inward constraining power,
                    ‘that when I would do good, evil is present with me. For I delight in’ (or
                    consent to) ‘the law of God, after the inward man.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 21-22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    (In my mind: so the Apostle explains himself in the words that immediately
                    follow; and so ὁ ἔσω ἄνθρωπος, ‘the inward man’, is understood in all other
                    Greek writers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., in ver. 23, where St. Paul speaks of τῷ νόμῳ τοῦ νοός μου. As for
                            ‘other Greek writers’, Wesley would have known of this same usage, in
                            Plato, <hi rend="italic">Republic</hi> IX. 589<hi rend="italic">a</hi>,
                            and IV. 439<hi rend="italic">d</hi>, as well as Plotinus, <hi rend="italic">Enneads</hi> I.i.10.</p>
                    </note>) ‘But I see another
                    law in my members’, another constraining power, ‘warring against the law of my
                    mind’, or inward man, ‘and bringing me into captivity to the law’, or power, ‘of
                        sin,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> dragging me as it were at my conqueror’s
                    chariot-wheels into the very thing which my soul abhors. ‘O wretched man that I
                    am, who shall deliver me from the body of this death!’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Who shall deliver me from this helpless, dying
                    life; from this bondage of sin and misery! Till this is done, ‘I myself’ (or
                    rather, ‘that I’, αὐτὸς ἐγώ, that man I am now personating<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley had inherited the still
                            controverted question of whether St. Paul, in Rom. 7, is speaking of his
                            continuing moral struggles as believer (eased and ‘covered’ by grace) or
                            of his earlier state of ineffectual moral earnestness before his
                            conversion. The Lutherans and Calvinists by and large took it as
                            confirmation of the <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi>.
                            Wesley understands that St. Paul is here ‘personating’ a hypothetical
                            man in ‘the legal state’; he holds to this later in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Rom. 7:7-8. On the other side, cf. Karl
                            Barth, <hi rend="italic">Epistle to the Romans</hi> (Oxford, Oxford
                            University Press, 1933), p. 270: ‘What Paul is here asserting [that
                            7:21-25 is his own experience] was well understood by the Reformers; it
                            is misunderstood by those modern theologians who read him through the
                            spectacles of their own piety.’ But see W. Sanday and A. C. Headlam, <hi rend="italic">The Epistle to the Romans</hi>, in The <hi rend="italic">International Critical Commentary</hi> (New York,
                            Charles Scribner’s Sons, 1895), XXXIII.186; also John Knox in <hi rend="italic">The Interpreter’s Bible</hi>, IX.498-500. Obviously,
                            one’s exegesis here follows from one’s soteriology and not from any
                            decisive evidence within the Greek text.</p>
                    </note>) ‘with the mind’, or
                    inward man, ‘serve the law of <pb n="260"/>God’; my mind, my conscience, is on
                    God’s side: ‘but with the flesh’, with my body, ‘the law of sin,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                25.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> being hurried away by a force I cannot
                    resist.</p>
                <p n="10">10. How lively a portraiture is this of one ‘under the law’! One who feels
                    the burden he cannot shake off; who pants after liberty, power, and love, but is
                    in fear and bondage still! Until the time that God answers the wretched man
                    crying out, ‘Who shall deliver me’ from this bondage of sin, from this body of
                    death?—‘The grace of God, through Jesus Christ thy Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 1:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. Then it is that this miserable bondage ends, and he is no more
                    ‘under the law, but under grace’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:14. See also Boston, State III, ‘The State
                            of Grace’, and note the similarities between that text and
                        this.</p>
                    </note> This state we are thirdly to consider; the state of one who
                    has found ‘grace’, or favour in the sight of God, even the Father, and who has
                    the ‘grace’, or power of the Holy Ghost, reigning in his heart; who has
                    received, in the language of the Apostle, ‘the Spirit of adoption, whereby he
                    now cries, Abba, Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘He cried unto the Lord in his trouble, and God delivers him out of his
                        distress.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 107:6.</p>
                    </note> His eyes are opened in quite another manner
                    than before, even to see a loving, gracious God. While he is calling, ‘I beseech
                    thee show me thy glory,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 33:18.</p>
                    </note> he hears a voice in his
                    inmost soul, ‘I will make all my goodness pass before thee, and I will proclaim
                    the name of the Lord; I will be gracious to whom I will be gracious, and I will
                    show mercy to whom I will show mercy.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 33:19.</p>
                    </note> And it is not long
                    before ‘the Lord descends in the cloud, and proclaims the name of the
                        Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Exod. 34:5.</p>
                    </note> Then he sees (but not with eyes of flesh and
                    blood) ‘The Lord, the Lord God; <pb n="261"/>merciful and gracious,
                    long-suffering, and abundant in goodness and truth; keeping mercy for thousands,
                    and forgiving iniquities and transgression and sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 34:6-7. Note this
                            rare instance of Wesley’s ‘spiritualizing’ of what stands as a
                            historical record in Exod. 33-34.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Heavenly, healing light now breaks in upon his soul. He ‘looks on him
                    whom he had pierced’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Zech. 12:10.</p>
                    </note> and ‘God, who out of
                    darkness commanded light to shine, shineth in <hi rend="italic">his</hi> heart.’
                    He sees ‘the light of the glorious love of God, in the face of Jesus
                        Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> He hath a divine ‘evidence of things not
                        seen’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            11:1.</p>
                    </note> by sense, even of ‘the deep things of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                            2:10.</p>
                    </note> more particularly of the love of God, of his pardoning
                    love to him that believes in Jesus. Overpowered with the sight, his whole soul
                    cries out, ‘My Lord, and my God!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 20:28.</p>
                    </note> For he sees all his
                    iniquities laid on him who ‘bare them in his own body on the tree’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            2:24.</p>
                    </note> he beholds the Lamb of God taking away his sins. How
                    clearly now does he discern ‘that God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto
                    himself; …making him sin for us, who knew no sin, that we might be made the
                    righteousness of God through him!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:19, 21.</p>
                    </note> And that he himself
                    is reconciled to God by that blood of the covenant!</p>
                <p n="4">4. Here end both the guilt and power of sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A hyperbole here, since
                            Wesley will continue to recognize (as in No. 8, ‘The First-fruits of the
                            Spirit’, II.4-13) that even in regeneration (as here) ‘sin <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> but no longer <hi rend="italic">reigns</hi>’ (cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>, I.6 and n.). What <hi rend="italic">is</hi> taken
                            away is guilt and ‘condemnation’.</p>
                    </note> He can now say, ‘I am
                    crucified with Christ. Nevertheless I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me.
                    And the life which I now live in the flesh’, even in this mortal body, ‘I live
                    by faith in the Son of God, who loved me and gave himself for me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            2:20.</p>
                    </note> Here end remorse and sorrow of heart, and the anguish
                    of a wounded spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, II.6.</p>
                    </note> ‘God turneth his
                    heaviness into joy.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 4:9.</p>
                    </note> He ‘made sore’, and now
                    ‘his hands bind up’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 5:18.</p>
                    </note> Here ends also that
                    bondage unto fear; for ‘his heart standeth fast, believing in the Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 112:7
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He cannot fear any longer the wrath of God; for he
                    knows it is now turned away from him, and looks upon him no more as an angry
                    judge, but as a loving Father. He cannot fear the devil, knowing he has ‘no <pb n="262"/>power, except it be given him from above’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 19:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    He fears not hell, being an heir of the kingdom of heaven. Consequently, he has
                    no fear of death, by reason whereof he was in time past for so many years
                    ‘subject to bondage’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 2:15.</p>
                    </note> Rather, knowing that ‘if the
                    earthly house of this tabernacle be dissolved, he hath a building of God, a
                    house not made with hands, eternal in the heavens, he groaneth earnestly,
                    desiring to be clothed upon with that house which is from heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            5:1-2.</p>
                    </note> He groans to shake off this house of earth, that
                    ‘mortality may be swallowed up of life’; knowing that ‘God hath wrought him for
                    the selfsame thing; who hath also given him the earnest of his Spirit.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            5:4-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. And ‘where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is liberty;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                            3:17.</p>
                    </note> liberty not only from guilt and fear, but from sin,
                    from that heaviest of all yokes, that basest of all bondage. His labour is not
                    now in vain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:58.</p>
                    </note> The snare is broken, and he is
                        delivered.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 124:7.</p>
                    </note> He not only strives, but likewise prevails;
                    he not only fights, but conquers also. ‘Henceforth he doth not serve sin…. He is
                    dead unto sin and alive unto God…. Sin doth not now reign, even in his mortal
                    body’, nor doth he ‘obey it in the desires thereof’. He does not ‘yield his
                    members as instruments of unrighteousness unto sin, but as instruments of
                    righteousness unto God’. For ‘being now made free from sin, he is become the
                    servant of righteousness.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Rom.]6:6[,11-13, 18].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Thus ‘having peace with God, through our Lord Jesus Christ’, ‘rejoicing
                    in hope of the glory of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:1-2.</p>
                    </note> and having power over
                    all sin, over every evil desire and temper, and word and work, he is a living
                    witness of the ‘glorious liberty of the sons of God’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:21.</p>
                    </note>
                    all of whom, being partakers of ‘like precious faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 1:1.</p>
                    </note> bear
                    record with one voice, ‘We have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we cry,
                    Abba, Father!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. It is this Spirit which continually ‘worketh in them, both to will and
                    to do of his good pleasure’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:13.</p>
                    </note> It is he that sheds the
                    love of God abroad in their hearts,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 5:5.</p>
                    </note> and the love of all
                    mankind; thereby purifying their hearts from the love of the world, from the
                    lust of <pb n="263"/>the flesh, the lust of the eye, and the pride of life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            2:16.</p>
                    </note> It is by him they are delivered from anger and pride,
                    from all vile and inordinate affections.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Col. 3:5.</p>
                    </note> In consequence,
                    they are delivered from evil words and works, from all unholiness of
                    conversation; doing no evil to any child of man, and being zealous of all good
                        works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Titus 2:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. To sum up all. The ‘natural man’ neither fears nor loves God; one ‘under
                    the law’ fears, one ‘under grace’ loves him. The first has no light in the
                    things of God, but walks in utter darkness. The second sees the painful light of
                    hell; the third, the joyous light of heaven. He that sleeps in death has a false
                    peace. He that is awakened has no peace at all. He that believes has true peace,
                    the peace of God, filling and ruling his heart. The heathen, baptized or
                        unbaptized,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Baptized or unbaptized’: a strange usage, since
                            elsewhere Wesley uses the term ‘heathen’ in its generally accepted sense
                            of those never having made any sort of Christian profession (or Jewish
                            or Moslem, for that matter); cf. his argument with John Taylor over the
                            cultural status of ‘the heathens’ in <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of
                                Original Sin</hi>, Pt. I, II.2-5; see also Nos. 63, ‘The General
                            Spread of the Gospel’, §1; 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, I.9; and No. 2,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.1. But for the
                            salvability of ‘heathens’, cf. Large <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, in
                                <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, London, 1862, I.669-73; and No. 91,
                            ‘On Charity’, I.3 and n.</p>
                    </note> hath a fancied liberty, which is
                    indeed licentiousness; the Jew (or one under the Jewish dispensation) is in
                    heavy, grievous bondage; the Christian enjoys the true glorious liberty of the
                    sons of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:21.</p>
                    </note> An unawakened child of the devil<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        13:10.</p>
                    </note> sins willingly; one that is awakened sins unwillingly; a
                    child of God ‘sinneth not, but keepeth himself, and the wicked one toucheth him
                        not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 John 5:18.</p>
                    </note> To conclude: the natural man neither conquers
                    nor fights; the man under the law fights with sin, but cannot conquer; the man
                    under grace fights and conquers, yea is ‘more than conqueror, through him that
                    loveth him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:37.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. From this plain account of the threefold state of man—the ‘natural’,
                    the ‘legal’, and the ‘evangelical’—it appears that it is not sufficient to
                    divide mankind into sincere and insincere.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, I.9 and n.</p>
                    </note> A man may be sincere in any of
                    these states; not only when he has the ‘Spirit of adoption’, but while he has
                    the ‘spirit of bondage unto fear’. Yea, while he has neither this fear, nor
                    love. For undoubtedly there may be sincere heathens as well as sincere <pb n="264"/>Jews or Christians. This circumstance, then, does by no means prove
                    that a man is in a state of acceptance with God.</p>
                <p>‘Examine yourselves’, therefore, not only whether ye are sincere, but ‘whether ye
                    be in the faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> Examine narrowly, for it
                    imports you much. What is the ruling principle in your soul? Is it the love of
                    God? Is it the fear of God? Or is it neither one nor the other? Is it not rather
                    the love of the world? The love of pleasure? Or gain? Of ease; or reputation? If
                    so, you are not come so far as a Jew. You are but a <hi rend="italic">heathen</hi> still. Have you heaven in your heart? Have you the Spirit of
                    adoption, ever crying, ‘Abba, Father’? Or do you cry unto God as ‘out of the
                    belly of hell’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jonah 2:2.</p>
                    </note> overwhelmed with sorrow and
                    fear? Or are you a stranger to this whole affair, and cannot imagine what I
                    mean? Heathen, pull off the mask. Thou hast never put on Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                        3:27.</p>
                    </note> Stand barefaced. Look up to heaven; and own before him that
                    liveth for ever and ever, thou hast no part either among the sons or servants of
                    God.</p>
                <p>Whosoever thou art, dost thou commit sin, or dost thou not? If thou dost, is it
                    willingly, or unwillingly? In either case God hath told thee whose thou art—‘He
                    that committeth sin is of the devil.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:8.</p>
                    </note> If thou committest it
                    willingly thou art his faithful servant. He will not fail to reward thy labour.
                    If unwillingly, still thou art his servant<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An apparent exception to Wesley’s normal
                            distinction between wilful and unwilled sins; it fits the mood of this
                            particular exhortation and need not signify a basic shift.</p>
                    </note>
                    God deliver thee out of his hands!</p>
                <p>Art thou daily fighting against all sin; and daily more than conqueror? I
                    acknowledge thee for a child of God. O stand fast in thy glorious liberty. Art
                    thou fighting, but not conquering; striving for the mastery, but not able to
                    attain? Then thou art not yet a believer in Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note Wesley’s reversion, in
                            this ‘application’, to his earlier emphasis on a complete deliverance
                            from sin and the state of full assurance, or none at all.</p>
                    </note> But
                    follow on; and thou shalt know the Lord. Art thou not fighting at all, but
                    leading an easy, indolent, fashionable life? O how hast thou dared to name the
                    name of Christ! Only to make it a reproach among the heathen? Awake, thou
                    sleeper! Call upon thy God, before the deep swallow thee up.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 69:15
                        (AV).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Perhaps one reason why so many think of themselves more highly than they
                    ought to think,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:3.</p>
                    </note> why they do not discern
                    what state they are in, is because these several states of soul are often <pb n="265"/>mingled together, and in some measure meet in one and the same
                    person. Thus experience shows that the legal state, or state of fear, is
                    frequently mixed with the natural; for few men are so fast asleep in sin but
                    they are sometimes more or less awakened. As the Spirit of God does not ‘wait
                    for the call of man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Micah 5:7.</p>
                    </note> so at some times he <hi rend="italic">will</hi> be heard. He puts them in fear, so that for a season
                    at least the heathen ‘know themselves to be but men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 9:20.</p>
                    </note> They
                    feel the burden of sin, and earnestly desire to flee from the wrath to
                        come.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:7; Luke 3:7.</p>
                    </note> But not long. They seldom suffer the
                    arrows of conviction to go deep into their souls;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matthew Henry’s exegesis
                                (<hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>) of Ps. 38:2 (‘the arrows of the
                            Almighty [are] the terrors of the Lord [which cause] a very melancholy
                            frightful apprehension of the wrath of God…’) and also of Ps. 45:5
                            (‘convictions are like the arrows of a bow…’).</p>
                    </note> but quickly
                    stifle the grace of God, and return to their wallowing in the mire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet.
                            2:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>In like manner the evangelical state, or state of love, is frequently mixed with
                    the legal. For few of those who have the spirit of bondage and fear remain
                    always without hope.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley is more positive than this in the <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, May 13, 1746:</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> But can it be conceived that God has any
                            regard to the sincerity of an unbeliever?</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> Yes, so much that if he persevere therein, God
                            will infallibly give him faith. </p>
                    </note> The wise and gracious God
                    rarely suffers this; for he remembereth that we are but dust.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 103:14.</p>
                    </note> And
                    he willeth not that ‘the flesh should fail before him, or the spirit which he
                    hath made’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 57:16.</p>
                    </note> Therefore, at such times as he seeth good he
                    gives a dawning of light unto them that sit in darkness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:79.</p>
                    </note> He
                    causes a part of his goodness to pass before them,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 33:19.</p>
                    </note>
                    and shows he is a ‘God that heareth the prayer’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 15:29.</p>
                    </note>
                    They see the promise which is by faith in Christ Jesus, though it be yet afar
                    off; and hereby they are encouraged to ‘run with patience the race which is set
                    before them’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Another reason why many deceive themselves is because they do not
                    consider how far a man may go and yet be in a natural, or at best a legal
                        state.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This and the following two paragraphs are a sort of reprise of No. 2,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>.</p>
                    </note> A man may be
                    of a compassionate and a benevolent temper; he may be affable, courteous,
                    generous, friendly; he may have some degree of meekness, patience, temperance,
                    and of many other moral virtues; he may feel many desires of shaking off all
                    vice, and attaining higher degrees of virtue; he may abstain from much
                    evil—perhaps from all that is <pb n="266"/>grossly contrary to justice, mercy,
                    or truth; he may do much good, may feed the hungry, clothe the naked,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            25:35-36.</p>
                    </note> relieve the widow and fatherless;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 146:9.</p>
                    </note> he
                    may attend public worship, use prayer in private, read many books of
                    devotion—and yet for all this he may be a mere natural man, knowing neither
                    himself nor God; equally a stranger to the spirit of fear and to that of love;
                    having neither repented nor believed the gospel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165" n="165">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Mark
                    1:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>But suppose there were added to all this a deep conviction of sin, with much fear
                    of the wrath of God; vehement desires to cast off every sin, and to fulfil all
                        righteousness;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> frequent rejoicing in hope,
                    and touches of love often glancing upon the soul: yet neither do these prove a
                    man to be ‘under grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn167" n="167">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:14.</p>
                    </note> to have true, living,
                    Christian faith, unless the Spirit of adoption abide in his heart, unless he can
                    continually cry, ‘Abba, Father!’</p>
                <p n="4">4. Beware, then, thou who art called by the name of Christ, that thou come
                    not short of the mark of thy high calling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168" n="168">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:14.</p>
                    </note> Beware thou rest
                    not, either in a natural state, with too many that are accounted ‘good
                    Christians’, or in a legal state, wherein those who are ‘highly esteemed of
                        men’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn169" n="169">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Luke 16:15.</p>
                    </note> are generally content to live and die. Nay, but
                    God hath prepared better things for thee, if thou follow on till thou attain.
                    Thou art not called to fear and tremble, like devils,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn170" n="170">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Jas. 2:19.</p>
                    </note>
                    but to rejoice and love, like the angels of God. ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy
                    God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul, and with all thy mind, and with
                    all thy strength.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn171" n="171">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 12:30, etc.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt ‘rejoice
                        evermore.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn172" n="172">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:16.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt ‘pray without ceasing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn173" n="173">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess.
                            5:17.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt ‘in everything give thanks.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn174" n="174">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess.
                            5:18.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt do the will of God ‘on earth, as it is done
                    in heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn175" n="175">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 6:10; Luke 11:2.</p>
                    </note> O ‘prove’ thou ‘what is that good
                    and acceptable and perfect will of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn176" n="176">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> Now ‘present’ thyself
                    ‘a living sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn177" n="177">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> ‘Whereunto thou hast
                    already attained’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn178" n="178">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:16; 1 Tim. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> ‘hold
                        fast’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn179" n="179">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Thess. 5:21; Heb. 4:14.</p>
                    </note> by ‘reaching forth unto those things
                    which are before’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn180" n="180">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:13.</p>
                    </note> until ‘the God of peace…make
                    thee perfect in every good work, working in thee that which is well-pleasing in
                    his sight, through Jesus Christ, to whom be glory for ever and ever! Amen!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn181" n="181">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            13:20-21. For Wesley’s use of ascriptions, cf. No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, III.9 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>