<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 4: Scriptural Christianity</title>
                <title type="subtitle">A Sermon preached at St. Mary's, Oxford, before the
                    University, <date when="1744-08-24">August 24, 1744</date>
                </title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-23</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon004</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 4: Scriptural Christianity</title>
                            <date when="1742-04-04"/>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="109" to="116"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="159" to="180"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <pb n="109"/>
            </p>
            <introduction>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 1-4]</hi>
                </p>
                <p>As we have seen, these first four sermons in this first volume of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> were ‘prefixed’ to the other eight on the advice of
                    friends, and also as proof of the consistency of Wesley’s new preaching, whether
                    before the University of Oxford or to the masses in Moorfields. But they also
                    serve another function, unavowed but crucial: they mark out the successive
                    stages of Wesley’s alienation from any further career as a reformer within the
                    university, as he made the radical shift in his commitment to the Revival as his
                    new vocation.</p>
                <p>Along with other ordained Oxford M.A.s, the brothers Wesley were subject to
                    occasional appointment as preachers in the <hi rend="italic">rota</hi> of
                    university services on Sundays and saints’ days (most of them in the Church of
                    St. Mary the Virgin, but others in St. Peter’s in the East and certain college
                        chapels).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Oxford University Statutes, tr. by G. R. M. Ward (1845), Vol. I, ‘The
                            Laudian Statutes’ (1636), Title XVI, chs. 1-7.</p>
                    </note> Attendance
                    upon these services was a stated obligation of ‘all doctors, masters, graduates,
                    and scholars’, who were enjoined to ‘be present at them from their beginning to
                    their end…’; no one was ‘permitted to wander abroad to another church, or
                    churches, under pain of chastisement…’, etc. (ch. 10). Even though these
                    injunctions were often honoured in the breach, such occasions were still
                    splendid sounding boards for eloquent preachers with earnest messages.</p>
                <p>John Wesley’s first ‘university sermon’ had been delivered in St. Mary’s on
                    November 15, 1730, ‘On Gen. 1:27’ (see No. 141, Vol. IV); a second on July 23,
                    1732 (‘A Consecration Sermon’, not extant); a third on January 1, 1733 (‘The
                    Circumcision of the Heart’; see No. 17 below). This last may be reckoned as a
                    landmark in the development of Wesley’s theology, and must also have made a
                    favourable general impression, for in the next two and a half years he was
                    invited to deliver <pb n="110"/>
                    <hi rend="italic">six</hi> more university
                    sermons: March 26, 1733 (Easter); April 1, 1733 (Low Sunday); May 13, 1733
                    (Whitsunday); February 10, 1734; June 11, 1734 (St. Barnabas’s); September 21,
                    1735 (St. Matthew’s). This is out of all proportion to any typical rotation, and
                    even if Wesley was serving as substitute for other appointed preachers, that
                    would have required the approval of the Vice-Chancellor (cf. <hi rend="italic">Statutes</hi>, XVI, ch. 6). The least that this can mean is that John
                    Wesley was more widely appreciated at Oxford as a preacher than the popular
                    stereotypes have suggested.</p>
                <p>This fact sheds some light on the arrangement by the university officials for
                    Wesley to preach again in Oxford soon after his return from Georgia (probably in
                    expectation of his resumption of his duties there); the new appointment was set
                    for the Festival of St. Barnabas, June 11, 1738. By that time, of course, Wesley
                    had undergone the radical change of heart and mind described in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for May 24, about which his Oxford colleagues
                    would have known nothing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Intro., above, p.4; see also Schmidt, <hi rend="italic">Wesley</hi>, I.141-95, for a careful analysis of the
                            theological developments involved in this ‘conversion’; JWJ, Feb. 7-May
                            28, sheds light on Wesley’s mood as he revised his sermon for this
                            crucial new occasion.</p>
                    </note> Meanwhile, he had already tested his
                    ‘new gospel’ (‘salvation by faith alone’) in several churches in and near
                    London, and his presentation of it had almost invariably stirred up more offence
                    than conversions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, Feb. 5 (Milbank, Westminster); Feb. 12 (St. Andrew’s,
                            Holborn); Feb. 26 (thrice in London, the first, in St. Lawrence Jewry,
                            being the most blessed ‘because it gave the most offence’); Mar. 6
                            (after being counselled by Böhler to ‘preach faith <hi rend="italic">till</hi> you have it; and then, <hi rend="italic">because</hi> you
                            have it, you <hi rend="italic">will</hi> preach faith’); Mar. 17, 26,
                            and 27; Apr. 2, 25, 26; May 7, 9, 14, and 21 (this last being also the
                            day of Charles Wesley’s experience of assurance).</p>
                    </note> In most of
                    these instances, as he records with a trace of self-righteousness, he had been
                    thenceforth barred from this pulpit and that. The Aldersgate experience had not
                    produced a new doctrine, but a new resolution to make the most of his
                    opportunities to expound the one to which he had already come.</p>
                <p>He was by now very well aware of the controversial character of his message, and
                    he could not have expected a sympathetic hearing at Oxford. ‘Salvation by Faith’
                    was, however, the first public occasion after his ‘Aldersgate’ experience for a
                    positive evangelical manifesto. It is worth noting that its Moravian substance
                    is qualified by echoes from the Edwardian <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, as in
                    the claim that salvation involved a power not to commit sin (<hi rend="italic">posse non peccare</hi>). There is also an obvious Anglican nuance in the
                    definition of saving faith presented here.</p>
                <p>When his turn as university preacher came round again (<date when="1741-07-25">July 25, 1741</date>), the Revival was in full swing and Wesley had found
                    in its <pb n="111"/>leadership an alternative career. He had not only begun to
                    shift his loyalties from Oxford to his own Societies; he had also become one of
                    Oxford’s harsher critics.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This may be seen in the Latin and English versions
                            of a sermon on Isa. 1:21 which he had first prepared in 1739, probably
                            in connection with his exercises for the B.D. degree which, as Fellow of
                            Lincoln College, he was expected to take in due course (see below, Nos.
                            150, 151).</p>
                    </note> John Gambold had already advised him that he would
                    face a hostile audience, but Wesley was in no mood to mollify them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See JWJ, June 18,
                            1741: ‘All here [Gambold had said of the Oxford community] are so
                            prejudiced that they will mind nothing you say.’ Wesley’s reaction: ‘I
                            know that. However, I am to deliver my own soul, whether they will hear
                            or whether they will forbear’ (one of Wesley’s standard formulae of
                            alienation). A fortnight later even Wesley and Gambold had come to a
                            parting of their ways (cf. JWJ, July 2). Earlier, he had finally got
                            round to reading ‘that celebrated book, Martin Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Comment on the Epistle to the Galatians</hi>’; his
                            negative reaction to it was intemperate (see JWJ, June 15).</p>
                    </note>
                    Indeed, the whole <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> record for June and July
                    reflects a mounting tension, as if Wesley was aware of the crisis. On June 28 he
                    preached ‘at Charles Square [London], to the largest congregation that, I
                    believe, was ever seen there, on “Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian”
                    [cf. Acts 26:28]’. This was the sermon that, revised and with its new
                    ‘application’ explicitly aimed at Oxford, he delivered on the festival day of
                    St. James the Apostle, July 25.</p>
                <p>Its theme—the radical difference between nominal and real Christianity—was
                    already a familiar one in Puritan preaching;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, proem and n.</p>
                    </note> it was, however, already
                    conventional to ignore the text’s plain reference to Agrippa’s being almost
                    persuaded to become a Christian rather than to his already being a nominal one.
                    Wesley draws out the distinctions between the two stages of Christian experience
                    (‘almost’ and ‘altogether’). Part I paints a vivid picture of the high-minded
                    hypocrite (the ‘almost Christian’) and concludes with Wesley’s confession ‘that
                    this had been his own state in all his days at Oxford’ (I.13). Part II
                    delineates the ‘altogether Christian’ according to his new conceptions, and
                    openly expresses doubt that there are many such in Oxford even now (II.7-9).
                    There are no records of this sermon’s reception on this occasion, but it would
                    not have been lost on his Methodist readers that their leader had bearded the
                    Anglican establishment in one of its citadels and had survived.</p>
                <p>In the following year Charles Wesley came up for an appointment as preacher in
                    St. Mary’s on <date when="1742-04-04">April 4, 1742</date>. His evangelical
                    conversion had preceded his brother’s, either on <date when="1738-05-03">May 3,
                        1738</date> (when ‘it pleased God to open his <hi rend="italic">eyes</hi> so
                    that he saw clearly what was the nature of [saving] <pb n="112"/>faith…’) or on
                        <date when="1738-05-19">May 19</date> (when he ‘had found rest to his
                        soul’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            both CWJ and JWJ for these dates and experiences.</p>
                    </note> In any
                    case, Charles was more exuberant in temperament and rhetoric than his elder
                        brother.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            above, p. 2, n. 6: ‘…in connection I beat you; but in strong, pointed
                            sentences you beat me.’</p>
                    </note> He had already preached a sermon on
                    justification ‘before the university [July 1739] with great boldness…’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">CWJ, Sunday, July
                            1, 1739; this is followed (on Monday) by a note that the Vice-Chancellor
                            and ‘all were against [that] sermon as liable to be misunderstood’. Had
                            this been Charles’s reinforcing sequel to John’s <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>?</p>
                    </note> His bidding prayer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In the
                            unpublished MS of a sermon on Rom. 3:27-28.</p>
                    </note> indicates that
                    this preaching service had been held in Christ Church Cathedral rather than St.
                    Mary’s. On June 30, 1740, he reports having spent a week in Oxford ‘preaching
                    repentance’ but also in discovering that ‘learned Gallio cared for none of these
                        things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 18:17 for this analogy between a Roman proconsul’s and Oxford’s
                            indifference.</p>
                    </note> Now, he was scheduled to preach in St. Mary’s
                    itself—for the first and last time.</p>
                <p>Charles’s message, with a barrage of invidious questions for its climax, fell
                    largely on deaf ears; this is reported by a visitor who was in the audience:
                    Thomas Salmon, a popular historian.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The times of the day the University go to this
                            church are ten in the morning and two in the afternoon, on Sundays and
                            holidays, the sermon usually lasting about half an hour. But when I
                            happened to be at Oxford, in 1742, Mr. Wesley, the Methodist, of Christ
                            Church, entertained his audience two hours, having insulted and abused
                            all degrees from the highest to the lowest, was in a manner hissed out
                            of the pulpit by the lads;’ Thomas Salmon, <hi rend="italic">A
                                Foreigner’s Companion through the Universities of Cambridge and
                                Oxford</hi> (1748), p. 25, and quoted in CWJ, Apr. 15,
                        1750.</p>
                    </note> Charles Wesley’s denial of Salmon’s report appears in his
                        <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> for April 15, 1750, and is emphatic;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘And it would
                            have been high time for them to do so, if the historian [Salmon] said
                            true. But, unfortunately for him, I measured the time by my watch and it
                            was within the hour; I abused neither high nor low, as my sermon in
                            print will prove; neither was I hissed out of the pulpit or treated with
                            the least incivility, either by young or old….’</p>
                    </note> he may have
                    been right about the time, since the sermon as printed can be read aloud in
                    thirty minutes. On the other hand, Charles’s accusations must surely have
                    aroused resentment in his auditory, and Salmon would have been a competent judge
                    of that. In any case this sermon would have persuaded any Methodist reader of
                    Charles’s wholehearted identification with his brother’s cause and theirs. <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> is then a lively evangelical
                    statement, a personal identification with the Revival and a valedictory to
                    Oxford.</p>
                <p>By August 1744 the Revival was gaining momentum, the network (‘connexion’) of the
                    Methodist Societies had extended over into Wales <pb n="113"/>and had come under
                    serious persecution by English mobs, the first ‘conference’ had just been held
                    (June 25-29), and John Wesley had found his true mission in life. Even so, his
                    turn as university preacher came up yet again for August 24 (another festival,
                    this one for St. Bartholomew). This, of course, was an anniversary of the
                    notorious Massacre of Paris (in 1572) and, again, of the Great Ejectment of the
                    Nonconformists in England in 1662, in which both of Wesley’s grandfathers had
                    suffered. Benjamin Kennicott’s explanation of Wesley’s appointment was that ‘as
                    no clergyman [could] avoid his turn, so the university can refuse none;
                    otherwise Mr. Wesley would not have preached.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">At this time, Kennicott was an undergraduate
                            at Wadham College, but he was destined to set Old Testament studies in
                            England upon a new level with his great <hi rend="italic">Vetus
                                Testamentum cum Variis Lectionibus</hi> (Vol. 1, 1776; Vol. 2,
                            1780). His account of Wesley’s sermon appeared in <hi rend="italic">WMM</hi>, 1866, 47-48.</p>
                    </note> Actually, though, that rule was
                    flexible; there was ample precedent for substitutions. One must wonder,
                    therefore, how the appointment came about. Was it a gesture of academic freedom?
                    Did Wesley have a stronger base in Oxford than would appear from the record?
                    There is no indication that he had claimed his turn as by right, but it would
                    never have crossed his mind to avoid it. Thus, the stage was set for a
                    confrontation—and another valedictory.</p>
                <p>Parts I-III of <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> constitute a
                    positive account of Wesley’s conception of the ‘order of salvation’ (Part I), an
                    interesting missiological perspective (Part II), and an early statement of
                    Wesley’s eschatological ideas (Part III)—the sum of these parts is evangelical
                    and Anglican. The mood changes in Part IV where he comes to his ‘plain and
                    practical application’. Here the judgment is passed, with scant charity, that
                    Oxford’s hypocrisies are an intolerable offence to God and a general hindrance
                    to the Christian mission. Kennicott’s uncharitable suspicion was that this final
                    salvo ‘was what [Wesley] had been preparing for all along…’:</p>
                <quote>[In the conclusion] he fired his address with so much zeal and unbounded
                    satire as quite spoiled what otherwise might have been turned to great
                    advantage…. I liked some of his freedom: such as calling the generality of young
                    townsmen ‘a generation of triflers’…. But considering how many shining lights
                    are here that are the glory of the Christian cause, his sacred censure was much
                    too flaming and strong and his charity much too weak…. Having summed up the
                    measure of our iniquities, he concluded with a lifted up eye in this most solemn
                    form, ‘It is time for <hi rend="italic">thee</hi>, Lord, to lay to <hi rend="italic">thine</hi> hand’—words full of such presumption and seeming
                    imprecation that they gave an universal shock…. Had these things been omitted
                    and his censures moderated, I think his discourse, as to style and delivery,
                    would have been uncommonly pleasing to others as well as to myself. He is
                    allowed to be a man of great parts, and that by the excellent Dean <pb n="114"/>of Christ Church;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John Conybeare, who succeeded Joseph Butler as
                            Bishop of Bristol, and author of <hi rend="italic">Defence of Revealed
                                Religion…</hi> (1732), one of the eighteenth century’s more famous
                            replies to Tindal and other deists.</p>
                    </note> for the day he preached
                    the dean generously said of him, ‘John Wesley will always be thought a man of
                    sound sense, though an enthusiast!’ However, the Vice-Chancellor<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Walter Hodges,
                            Provost of Oriel.</p>
                    </note> sent for the sermon, and I hear that the
                    heads of college intend to shew their resentment.</quote>
                <p>Another eyewitness report of the same event was recorded by William Blackstone,
                    already a Fellow of All Souls and on his way to the fame he would earn as author
                    of his <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Laws of England</hi> (1765-69). In
                    a letter to a family friend (Aug. 28) the young Blackstone reports on Wesley’s
                    sermon, which seems to have become the talk of the town:</p>
                <quote>We were last Friday [Aug. 24] entertained at St. Mary’s by a curious sermon
                    from Wesley the Methodist. Among other equally modest particulars, he informed
                    us, 1st, that there was not one Christian among all the Heads of Houses; 2ndly,
                    that pride, gluttony, avarice, luxury, sensuality and drunkenness were general
                    characteristics of all Fellows of Colleges, who were useless to a proverbial
                    uselessness. Lastly, that the younger part of the University were a generation
                    of triflers, all of them perjured and none of them of any religion at all. His
                    notes were demanded by the Vice-Chancellor, but on mature deliberation it has
                    been thought proper to punish him by a mortifying neglect….<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the facsimile of the
                            letter in John Fletcher Hurst, <hi rend="italic">The History of
                                Methodism</hi>, II.604-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That ‘mortifying neglect’ began at once. Charles Wesley records that ‘we [John
                    Wesley, Charles Wesley, Messrs. Piers and Meriton] walked back in form, the
                    little band of us four; for of the rest durst none join himself to us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. CWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Methodists, then and later, could see no proper warrant for anyone to have taken
                    offence at such a sermon; after all, Wesley had simply preached the gospel and
                    applied it ‘close and home’. Thomas Jackson’s later comment on it is
                    typical:</p>
                <quote>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> contains a beautiful and
                    forcible description of spiritual religion, with the manner by which it is
                    acquired by individuals and then spreads from one to another until it shall
                    cover the earth. The concluding application to the heads of colleges and halls,
                    to the fellows and tutors and to the body of undergraduates, assumes their
                    general and wide departure from the true Christian character, and [their]
                    abandonment to formality, worldliness, levity, and sloth. It contains nothing
                    sarcastic and irritating, nothing that was designed to give unnecessary pain or
                    offence; but is marked throughout by seriousness, fidelity, and tender
                        affection.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">The Life of the Rev. Charles Wesley</hi> (1841),
                            I.403.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>
                    <pb n="115"/>John Wesley himself was much more of a realist and also more aware
                    of his own intention:</p>
                <quote>I preached, I suppose the last time, at <placeName>St. Mary’s</placeName>. Be
                    it so. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully delivered my own
                    soul.</quote>
                <quote>The Beadle came to me afterwards and told me the Vice-Chancellor had sent him
                    for my notes. I sent them without delay, not without admiring the wise
                    providence of God. Perhaps few men of note would have given a sermon of mine the
                    reading if I had put it into their hands; but by this means it came to be read,
                    probably more than once, by every man of eminence in the University.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">JWJ, Aug. 24,
                            1744.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>That he never regretted the affair or its consequences would appear from a
                    complacent recollection of it in 1781 in ‘A Short History of the People called
                    Methodists’:</p>
                <quote>Friday, August 24, St. Bartholomew’s Day, I preached for the last time before
                    the University of Oxford. I am now clear of the blood of these men. I have fully
                    delivered my own soul. And I am well pleased that it should be the very day on
                    which, in the last century,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, the Great Ejectment in
                            1662.</p>
                    </note> near two thousand burning and shining lights were put
                    out at one stroke. Yet what a wide difference is there between their case and
                    mine! They were turned out of house and home, and all that they had; whereas I
                    am only hindered from preaching, without any other loss; and that in a kind of
                    honourable manner; it being determined that when my next turn to preach came
                    they would pay another person to preach for me. And so they did twice or thrice,
                    even to the time that I resigned my fellowship.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">§30. See Vol. 9 of this edn. and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 420.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p>What would have been most obvious to his Methodist readers was the heroic stature
                    of their leader who had preached ‘plain truth’ to academic people to their face
                    and at the cost of rejection by them. What clearer proof could there be of his
                    fidelity to the gospel under all circumstances and of his total commitment in
                    his ministry among them? It was no small matter for a tenured don to have
                    forsaken his privileged status in a class-conscious English society in exchange
                    for ‘The Foundery’, ‘The New Room’, and a career among the masses. They knew,
                    all too well, how rudely the Methodists had been treated, to the point of savage
                    persecution, condoned by magistrates and clergy alike in the years between 1739
                    and 1746; they could still foresee dangerous days ahead. <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> as published was an evangelical proclamation;
                    it was also an act of defiance.</p>
                <p>These ‘prefixed’ sermons, therefore, serve a particular junction in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> as a bloc: they proclaim the Wesleyan message in
                    prophetic terms, and they signify Wesley’s transference of his allegiance from
                    the <pb n="116"/>Academy to his new vocation as a preacher of ‘plain truth for
                    plain people’. Together they dispel any impression of inconsistency. His message
                    in St. Mary’s had been the same as it was now in Moorfields. Thus, these sermons
                    could serve as a multifaceted introductory quartet to the larger endeavour of
                        <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi>.</p>
                <p>The edited text of <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi> is based upon the
                    first edition of 1738. For a stemma illustrating its publishing history through
                    its thirty-one editions in Wesley’s lifetime, together with substantive variant
                    readings, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                    10.</p>
                <p>The text for <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi> is based upon its first
                    edition, 1741. For a stemma and table of variant readings through the
                    twenty-eight extant editions during Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix.
                    See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 50.</p>
                <p>The first edition of <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi> followed
                    here, was published shortly after the sermon itself was preached in 1742. For a
                    stemma and variant readings from the fifty-two extant editions in Charles
                    Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 59.</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi> was also published shortly after
                    its delivery in 1744 and ran through at least fifteen editions in Wesley’s
                    lifetime. For a stemma of these editions and a list of variant readings, see
                    Vol. IV, Appendix. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 92.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="159"/>            
            <head>Scriptural Christianity</head>
            <head type="subhead">A Sermon preached at St. Mary's, Oxford,<lb/>before the
                    University,<lb/>
                <date when="1744-08-24">August 24, 1744</date>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Half-title reproduced from <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, 1746. The drop-title prefixed to the
                        individual editions of the sermon was simply ‘Acts iv.31’.</p>
                </note>
            </head>
            <div type="foreword">
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">To the Reader.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>It was not my design when I wrote ever to print the latter part of the following
                    sermon. But the false and scurrilous accounts<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See above, ‘Intro. Com.’, pp.
                        113-15.</p>
                    </note> of it which have been published almost in every corner of
                    the nation constrain me to publish the whole, just as it was preached, that men
                    of reason may judge for themselves.<lb/>October 20, 1744<lb/>John Wesley<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This foreword was
                            omitted from the collected editions of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Acts 4:31</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. The same expression occurs in the second chapter, where we read, ‘When
                    the day of Pentecost was fully come, they were all’ (the apostles, with the
                    women, and the mother of Jesus, and his brethren) ‘with one accord in one place.
                    And suddenly there came a sound from heaven, as of a rushing mighty wind…. And
                    there appeared unto them cloven tongues, like as of fire, and it sat upon each
                    of them. And they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                2:1-4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> One immediate effect whereof was, they ‘began
                    to speak with other tongues’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> insomuch that both the
                    ‘Parthians, Medes, <pb n="160"/>Elamites’, and the other strangers who ‘came
                    together’ ‘when this was noised abroad’, ‘heard them speak’ in their several
                    ‘tongues, the wonderful works of God.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 6 [9, 11].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. In this chapter we read that when the apostles and brethren had been
                    praying and praising God, ‘the place was shaken where they were assembled
                    together, and they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                4:31.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Not that we find any visible appearance here,
                    such as had been in the former instance: nor are we informed that the <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> gifts of the Holy Ghost were then given to
                    all or any of them, such as ‘the gifts of healing, of working other miracles, of
                    prophecy, of discerning spirits’, the speaking with ‘divers kinds of tongues’,
                    and ‘the interpretation of tongues’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 12:9-10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Whether these gifts of the Holy Ghost were designed to remain in the
                    church throughout all ages, and whether or not they will be restored at the
                    nearer approach of the ‘restitution of all things’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 3:21.</p>
                    </note> are
                    questions which it is not needful to decide. But it is needful to observe this,
                    that even in the infancy of the church God divided them with a sparing hand.
                    ‘Were all’ even then ‘prophets?’ Were ‘all workers of miracles? Had all the
                    gifts of healing? Did all speak with tongues?’ No, in no wise. Perhaps not one
                    in a thousand. Probably none but the teachers in the church, and only some of
                        them.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1
                                Cor. 12:28-30.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> It was therefore for a more excellent
                    purpose than this that ‘they were all filled with the Holy Ghost.’</p>
                <p n="4">4. It was to give them (what none can deny to be essential to all
                    Christians in all ages)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Another claim that the ordinary gifts of the Holy
                            Spirit are designed for ordinary Christians; see above, p. 155, n.
                            181.What is important here is Wesley’s view that the gifts of the Spirit
                            are to be normed by the ‘fruits’; cf. Nos. 10, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit, I’, II.12; 37, ‘The Nature of Enthusiasm’, §§19-26; 89, ‘The
                            More Excellent Way’, §2; and his letters to Dr. Middleton, Jan. 4, 1749;
                            to Dr. Warburton, Nov. 26, 1762, and to George Fleury, May 18, 1771. See
                            also, <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Acts 19:2.</p>
                    </note> ‘the mind
                    which was in Christ’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> those holy ‘fruits of the
                        Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                            5:22.</p>
                    </note> which whosoever hath not ‘is none of his’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:9.</p>
                    </note> to fill them with ‘love, joy, peace, long-suffering,
                    gentleness, goodness’; to endue them with ‘faith’ (perhaps it might be rendered
                    ‘fidelity’), with ‘meekness and temperance’; to enable them to ‘crucify the
                    flesh with its affections and lusts’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 5:22-24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> its
                    passions and desires; and, in consequence of that <hi rend="italic">inward
                        change</hi>, <pb n="161"/>to fulfil all <hi rend="italic">outward</hi>
                    righteousness, ‘to walk as Christ also walked’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:6.</p>
                    </note> in the ‘work of
                    faith, the patience of hope, the labour of love’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Thess.
                    1:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Without busying ourselves then in curious, needless inquiries touching
                    those <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> gifts of the Spirit, let us take a
                    nearer view of these his <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi> fruits, which we are
                    assured will remain throughout all ages: of that great work of God among the
                    children of men which we are used to express by one word, ‘Christianity’; not as
                    it implies a set of opinions, a system of doctrines, but as it refers to men’s
                    hearts and lives. And this Christianity it may be useful to consider under three
                    distinct views:</p>
                <p>I. As beginning to exist in individuals.</p>
                <p>II. As spreading from one to another.</p>
                <p>III. As covering the earth.</p>
                <p>I design to close these considerations with a plain practical application.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>I. And first, let us consider Christianity in its rise, as beginning to exist in
                    individuals.</p>
                <p n="1">[1.] Suppose then one of those who heard the Apostle Peter preaching
                    ‘repentance and remission of sins’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 24:47.</p>
                    </note> was ‘pricked to the
                        heart’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 2:37.</p>
                    </note> was convinced of sin, repented, and then ‘believed
                    in Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                            2:16.</p>
                    </note> By this ‘faith of the operation of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col.
                        2:12.</p>
                    </note> which was the very ‘substance’, or subsistence, ‘of things
                    hoped for’, the demonstrative ‘evidence of invisible things’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb.
                                11:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> he instantly ‘received the Spirit of adoption,
                    whereby he (now) cried Abba, Father.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Now first
                    it was that he could ‘call Jesus Lord, by the Holy Ghost’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor.
                                12:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘the Spirit itself bearing witness with his
                    spirit that he was a child of God’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 8:16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Now it was
                    that he could truly say, ‘I live not, but Christ liveth in me; and the life
                    which I now live in the flesh I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me
                    and gave himself for me.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Gal. 2:20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. This then was the very essence of his faith, a divine ἔλεγχος<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Evidence
                                or conviction. [See Heb. 11:1; cf. No. 3, ‘<hi rend="italic">Awake,
                                    Thou That Steepest’</hi>, I.11 and n.].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> of the
                    love of God the Father, through the Son of his love, to him <pb n="162"/>a
                    sinner, now ‘accepted in the beloved’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> And ‘being justified by
                    faith, he had peace with God’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 5:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> yea, ‘the peace of God
                    ruling in his heart’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> a peace ‘which, passing
                    all understanding’ (πάντα νοῦν, all barely rational conception), ‘kept his heart
                    and mind’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Phil. 4:7. Wesley’s translation of νοῦς here as ‘barely rational
                            conception’ is faithful to his own general distinction between mere
                            reason and spiritual intuition, but it is misleading, even in this
                            verse. Cf. Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">A Greek-English
                                Lexicon</hi>, 1957 (entries on νοῦς and its cognates); see also
                            Liddell and Scott, <hi rend="italic">A Greek-English Lexicon</hi> (9th
                            edn., 1940). Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Epistle of Barnabas</hi>, 6:10,
                            where νοῦς means an ‘understanding’ of divine ‘secrets’. Thus, the
                            ‘peace’ of Phil. 4:7 is a divine bestowal, surpassing the utmost
                            outreach of ‘rational conception’.</p>
                    </note> from all doubt and fear,
                    through the ‘knowledge of him in whom he had believed’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> He
                    could not therefore ‘be afraid of any evil tidings’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 112:7 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                    for his ‘heart stood fast, believing in the Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:1; 1 Thess.
                            3:8.</p>
                    </note> He feared not what man could do unto him, knowing ‘the
                    very hairs of his head were all numbered’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 10:30.</p>
                    </note> He feared not all
                    the powers of darkness, whom God was daily ‘bruising under his feet’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            16:20.</p>
                    </note> Least of all was he afraid to die; nay, he ‘desired to
                    depart and be with Christ’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Phil. 1:23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> who ‘through death
                    had destroyed him that had the power of death, even the devil, and delivered
                    them who through fear of death were all their lifetime’, till then, ‘subject to
                        bondage’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 2:14-15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘His soul’ therefore ‘magnified the Lord, and his spirit rejoiced in God
                    his Saviour.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:46-47.</p>
                    </note> He rejoiced in him ‘with joy
                        unspeakable’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:8.</p>
                    </note> who ‘had reconciled him to
                    God, even the Father’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:18; 1 Cor. 15:24, etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘in
                    whom he had redemption through his blood, the forgiveness of sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:14; cf.
                            Eph. 1:7.</p>
                    </note> He rejoiced in that ‘witness of God’s Spirit with
                    his spirit that he was a child of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note> and more abundantly
                    ‘in hope of the glory of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:2.</p>
                    </note> in hope of the glorious image
                    of God, the full ‘renewal of his soul in righteousness and true holiness’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:23,
                            24.</p>
                    </note> and in hope of that ‘crown of glory’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:4.</p>
                    </note> that
                    ‘inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, and that fadeth not away’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        1:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. ‘The love of God’ was also ‘shed abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghost
                    which was given unto him.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 5:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Because he was a son,
                        <pb n="163"/>God had sent forth the Spirit of his Son into his heart, crying
                    Abba, Father!’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 4:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And that filial love
                    of God was continually increased by the ‘witness he had in himself’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John
                                5:10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> of God’s pardoning love to him, by ‘beholding
                    what manner of love it was which the Father had bestowed upon him, that he
                    should be called a child of God’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 3:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> So that God was
                    the desire of his eyes, and the joy of his heart; his portion in time and in
                        eternity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 16:5; 73:25-26 (AV).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. He that thus ‘loved God’ could not but ‘love his brother also’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        4:21.</p>
                    </note> and ‘not in word only, but in deed and in truth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John
                            3:18.</p>
                    </note> ‘If God’, said he, ‘so loved us, we ought also to love
                    one another;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 4:11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> yea, every soul of
                    man, as the ‘mercy’ of God ‘is over all his works’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ps. 145:9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    Agreeably hereto, the affection of this lover of God embraced all mankind for
                    his sake; not excepting those whom he had never seen in the flesh, or those of
                    whom he knew nothing more than that they were ‘the offspring of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        17:29.</p>
                    </note> for whose souls his Son had died; not excepting the <hi rend="italic">evil</hi> and <hi rend="italic">unthankful</hi>, and least of
                    all his enemies, those who ‘hated, or persecuted, or despitefully used’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            5:44.</p>
                    </note> him for his Master’s sake. These had a peculiar place
                    both in his heart and his prayers. He loved them ‘even as Christ loved us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                        5:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. And ‘love is not puffed up’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 13:4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> It
                    abases to the dust every soul wherein it dwells. Accordingly he was ‘lowly of
                        heart’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 11:29.</p>
                    </note> little and mean and vile in his own eyes. He
                    neither sought nor received the ‘praise of men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 12:43.</p>
                    </note> ‘but
                    that which cometh of God only’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 5:44. Cf. also Nos. 17, ‘The Circumcision
                            of the Heart’, I.1, II.1-2; 26, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’, I.3; 136, ‘On
                            Mourning for the Dead’, ¶14; 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That
                                Sleepest’</hi>, III.11 and n.; and 14, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.7 and n.</p>
                    </note> He was meek and
                    long-suffering, gentle to all, and easy to be entreated.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:17.</p>
                    </note>
                    Faithfulness and truth never forsook him; they were ‘bound about his neck, and
                    wrote on the table of his heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 3:3.</p>
                    </note> By the same Spirit he was
                    enabled to be ‘temperate in all things’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 9:25.</p>
                    </note> ‘refraining his soul
                    even as a weaned child’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 131:3 (BCP), and Ps. 131:2 (AV); a rare
                            instance of Wesley’s combining the AV and BCP Psalters.</p>
                    </note> He
                    was ‘crucified to the world, and the world crucified to him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:
                    14.</p>
                    </note>—superior to ‘the desire of the flesh, the <pb n="164"/>desire of
                    the eye, and the pride of life.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:16. Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’,
                            II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> By the same almighty love was he saved both from
                    passion and pride, from lust and vanity, from ambition and covetousness, and
                    from every temper which was not in Christ.</p>
                <p n="7">7. It may be easily believed, he who had this love in his heart would ‘work
                    no evil to his neighbour’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 15:3.</p>
                    </note> It was impossible for him
                    knowingly and designedly to do harm to any man. He was at the greatest distance
                    from cruelty and wrong, from any unjust or unkind action. With the same care did
                    he ‘set a watch before his mouth, and keep the door of his lips’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            141:3.</p>
                    </note> lest he should offend in tongue either against
                    justice, or against mercy or truth. He ‘put away all lying’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:25.</p>
                    </note>
                    falsehood, and fraud; ‘neither was guile found in his mouth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:22.</p>
                    </note> He
                    ‘spake evil of no man’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 3:2.</p>
                    </note> nor did an unkind word ever
                    come out of his lips.</p>
                <p n="8">8. And as he was deeply sensible of the truth of that word, ‘without me ye
                    can do nothing’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 15:5.</p>
                    </note> and consequently of the need he had to be
                    ‘watered’ of God ‘every moment’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 27:3.</p>
                    </note> so he ‘continued daily’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:42,
                            46.</p>
                    </note> in all the ordinances of God, the stated channels of his
                    grace to man: ‘in the apostles’ doctrine’ or teaching, receiving that food of
                    the soul with all readiness of heart; ‘in the breaking of bread’, which he found
                    to be ‘the communion of the body of Christ’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 10:16.</p>
                    </note> and ‘in the
                        prayers’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:42.</p>
                    </note> and praises offered up by the great congregation.
                    And thus he daily ‘grew in grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:18.</p>
                    </note> increasing in strength,
                    in the knowledge and love of God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. But it did not satisfy him barely to abstain from doing evil. His soul
                    was athirst to do good. The language of his heart continually was, ‘My Father
                    worketh hitherto, and I work.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 5:17.</p>
                    </note> My Lord ‘went about doing
                        good’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            10:28; note the echoes here from the first two <hi rend="italic">General
                                Rules</hi>.</p>
                    </note> and shall not I ‘tread in his steps’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            2:21.</p>
                    </note> ‘As he had opportunity’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:10.</p>
                    </note>
                    therefore, if he could do no good of a higher kind, he fed the hungry, clothed
                    the naked, helped the fatherless or stranger, visited and assisted them that
                    were sick or in prison.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 25:35-39.</p>
                    </note> He ‘gave all his
                    goods to feed the poor’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:3.</p>
                    </note> He rejoiced to labour
                    or to suffer for them; and whereinsoever he might profit another, there
                    especially to ‘deny himself’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 16:24, etc.</p>
                    </note> He <pb n="165"/>counted nothing too dear to part with for them, as well remembering the word
                    of his Lord, ‘Inasmuch as ye have done it unto one of the least of these my
                    brethren, ye have done it unto me.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 25:40.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. Such was Christianity in its rise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the close correspondence between this
                            description of apostolic Christianity and Wesley’s own conception of the
                                <hi rend="italic">ordo salutis</hi> in its successive stages from
                            repentance to experienced holiness.</p>
                    </note> Such was a Christian in
                    ancient days. Such was every one of those who, ‘when they heard’ the
                    threatenings of ‘the chief priests and elders’, ‘lifted up their voice to God
                    with one accord, …and were all filled with the Holy Ghost…. The multitude of
                    them that believed were of one heart and of one soul’ (so did the love of him in
                    whom they had believed constrain them to love one another). ‘Neither said any of
                    them that ought of the things which he possessed was his own; but they had all
                    things common.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 4:23-24, 31-32; for ‘ought’ see below, p. 171, n. 117.</p>
                    </note>
                    So fully were they crucified to the world and the world crucified to them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal.
                            6:14.</p>
                    </note> ‘And they continued steadfastly…’ ‘with one accord…’
                    ‘in the apostles’ doctrine, and in the breaking of bread, and in prayers.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:1,
                        42.</p>
                    </note> ‘And great grace was upon them all; neither was there any
                    among them that lacked: for as many as were possessors of lands or houses sold
                    them, and brought the prices of the things that were sold, and laid them down at
                    the apostles’ feet; and distribution was made unto every man according as he had
                        need.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 4:31-5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Let us take a view, in the second place, of this Christianity as
                    spreading from one to another, and so gradually making its way into the world.
                    For such was the will of God concerning it, who ‘did not light a candle to put
                    it under a bushel, but that it might give light to all that were in the house’.
                    And this our Lord had declared to his first disciples, ‘Ye are the salt of the
                    earth, …the light of the world,’ at the same time that he gave that general
                    command, ‘Let your light so shine before men that they may see your good works,
                    and glorify your Father which is in heaven.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 5:13-16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And, indeed, supposing a few of these lovers of mankind to see ‘the
                    whole world lying in wickedness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:19.</p>
                    </note> can we believe they <pb n="166"/>would be unconcerned at the sight? At the misery of those for whom
                    their Lord died? Would not their bowels yearn over them, and their hearts ‘melt
                    away for very trouble’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 107:26; 6:7 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Could they
                    then stand idle all the day long?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 20:6.</p>
                    </note> Even were there no
                    command from him whom they loved? Rather, would they not labour, by all possible
                    means, to ‘pluck some of these brands out of the burning’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Amos 4:11; Zech. 3:2. An
                            autobiographical note here: Wesley and his mother had regarded <hi rend="italic">him</hi> as ‘a brand plucked out of the burning’ since
                            the Epworth rectory fire of 1709. Cf. Wesley’s personal account of Miss
                            Sophy Hopkey, 1736-37 (MSS. III.5, MA; also quoted in Curnock, I.328),
                            and other frequent references in the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> and
                                <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>; also Nos. 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                            X’, §17; 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.12; 80, ‘On
                            Friendship with the World’, §10; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, II.1; 110,
                                <hi rend="italic">Free Grace</hi>, §18.</p>
                    </note> Undoubtedly they
                    would: they would spare no pains to bring back whomsoever they could of those
                    poor ‘sheep that had gone astray’ ‘to the great Shepherd and Bishop of their
                        souls.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Pet. 2:25.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. So the Christians of old did. They laboured, having opportunity, to ‘do
                    good unto all men’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 6:10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> warning them to ‘flee
                    from the wrath to come’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:7; Luke 3:7.</p>
                    </note> now, now, to
                    ‘escape the damnation of hell’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 23:33.</p>
                    </note> They declared, ‘The times
                    of ignorance God winked at; but now he calleth all men everywhere to repent.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                17:30. [‘Winked at’ is the AV rendering; Wesley’s text for his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> has it ‘overlooked’.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    They cried aloud, ‘Turn ye, turn ye from your evil ways;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ezek. 33:11.</p>
                    </note> ‘so
                    iniquity shall not be your ruin’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ezek. 18:30.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> They ‘reasoned’
                    with them ‘of temperance and righteousness’, or justice, of the virtues opposite
                    to their reigning sins, and ‘of judgment to come’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 24:25.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> of
                    the wrath of God which would surely be executed on evil-doers in that day when
                    he should judge the world.</p>
                <p n="4">4. They endeavoured herein to speak to every man severally as he had need.
                    To the careless, to those who lay unconcerned in darkness and in the shadow of
                        death,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            107:10; Luke 1:79.</p>
                    </note> they thundered, ‘Awake, thou that
                    sleepest; …arise from the dead, and Christ shall give thee light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:14. An
                            echo of Charles Wesley’s sermon; cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest’</hi>.</p>
                    </note> But to those who were already
                    awakened out of sleep, and groaning under a sense of the wrath of God, their
                    language was, ‘We have an advocate with the Father; …he is the <pb n="167"/>propitiation for our sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:1-2. Here, very early, is Wesley’s
                            distinction between preaching stern judgment to the unawakened or
                            complacent and the gospel word of pardon and consolation to those under
                            conviction of sin. Cf. his fuller exposition of this in his letter of
                            Dec. 20, 1751, ‘Of Preaching Christ’, see <hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>
                            II, Vol. 26 of this edn.</p>
                    </note> Meantime those who had believed they
                    ‘provoked to love and to good works’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:24.</p>
                    </note> to ‘patient continuance
                    in well-doing’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> and to ‘abound more and more’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 4:1.</p>
                    </note> in
                    that ‘holiness, without which no man can see the Lord’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb.
                                12:14.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. And their labour was not in vain in the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:58.</p>
                    </note>
                    His ‘word ran and was glorified’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 3:1.</p>
                    </note> It ‘grew mightily and
                        prevailed’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 19:20.</p>
                    </note> But so much the more did offences prevail
                    also. The world in general were offended, ‘because they testified of it that the
                    works thereof were evil’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John 7:7.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The men of pleasure
                    were offended, not only because these men were ‘made’, as it were, ‘to reprove
                    their thoughts’ (‘He professeth’, said they, ‘to have the knowledge of God; he
                    calleth himself the child of the Lord;’ ‘his life is not like other men’s; his
                    ways are of another fashion; he abstaineth from our ways, as from filthiness; he
                    maketh his boast that God is his Father’);<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Wisd. 2:13-16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> but
                    much more because so many of their companions were taken away and would no more
                    ‘run with them to the same excess of riot’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Pet. 4:4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The men
                    of reputation were offended, because as the gospel spread they declined in the
                    esteem of the people; and because many no longer dared to ‘give them flattering
                        titles’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Job 32:21, 22.</p>
                    </note> or to pay man the homage due to God only. The
                    men of trade called one another together and said, ‘Sirs, ye know that by this
                    craft we have our wealth. But ye see and hear that these men have persuaded and
                    turned away much people; …so that this our craft is in danger to be set at
                        nought.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 19:25-27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Above all the men
                    of religion, so called—the men of <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> religion, ‘the
                    saints of the world’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In a letter to his father, Dec. 10, 1734, Wesley
                            identifies the author of this phrase as Juan de Valdés: ‘I never come
                            from among these “saints of the world” (as J. Valdesso calls them)
                            faint, dissipated, and shorn of all my strength, but I say, “God deliver
                            us from an half-Christian”’ (see above, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Almost Christian</hi>, proem and n.) His diaries indicate that he
                            first read Valdés in Oct. 1733, again in Nov. 1734 with the Holy Club,
                            and to Sophy Hopkey, Nov. 1, 1736.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">For the
                            phrase in Valdés, cf. ‘Consideraziones’ LXXVI and LXXXI in <hi rend="italic">Reformistas Antiguos Españoles</hi>, Torno XVII: <hi rend="italic">Ziento I Diez Consideraziones</hi> (1550), pp. 258,
                            261, 285; cf. also George Herbert’s translation, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Hundred and Ten Considerations of Signior J. Valdesso</hi> (1638).
                            For Wesley’s other uses of this metaphor, cf. Nos. 18, ‘The Marks of the
                            New Birth’, IV.4; 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, I.5; 61, ‘The Mystery
                            of Iniquity’, §28; 94, ‘On Family Religion’, III.18; and see JWJ, Jan.
                            4, 1739; and <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Mark 2:16. For his comments
                            on ‘the religion of the world’, cf. No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’,
                            II.4 and n.</p>
                    </note>—were offended, <pb n="168"/>and ready at every
                    opportunity to cry out, ‘Men of Israel, help!’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 21:28.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘We have
                    found these men pestilent fellows, movers of sedition throughout the world.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                24:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘These are the men that teach all men
                    everywhere against the people and against the law.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                    21:28.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Thus it was that the heavens grew black with clouds, and the storm
                    gathered amain. For the more Christianity spread, ‘the more hurt was done’, in
                    the account of those who received it not; and the number increased of those who
                    were more and more enraged at these ‘men who (thus) turned the world upside
                        down’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 17:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> insomuch that they more and more cried
                    out, ‘Away with such fellows from the earth; it is not fit that they should
                        live;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 22:22.</p>
                    </note> yea, and sincerely believed that ‘whosoever’
                    should ‘kill them would do God service’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 16:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Meanwhile they did not fail to ‘cast out their name as evil’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke
                                6:22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> so that this ‘sect was everywhere spoken
                        against’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 28:22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Men said all manner
                    of evil of them’, even as had been done of ‘the prophets that were before
                        them’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 5:11, 12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And whatever any would affirm,
                    others would believe; so that offences grew as the stars of heaven for
                        multitude.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 1:10.</p>
                    </note> And hence arose, at the time foreordained of the
                    Father, persecution in all its forms. Some, for a season, suffered only shame
                    and reproach; some, ‘the spoiling of their goods’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 10:34.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    some ‘had trial of mocking and scourging’; some ‘of bonds and imprisonment’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb.
                                11:36.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and others ‘resisted unto blood’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        12:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Now it was that the pillars of hell were shaken, and the kingdom of God
                    spread more and more. Sinners were everywhere ‘turned from darkness to light,
                    and from the power of Satan unto God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 26:18.</p>
                    </note> He gave his children
                    ‘such a mouth, and such wisdom, as all their adversaries could not resist’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            21:15.</p>
                    </note> And their lives were of equal force with their words.
                    But above all, their sufferings spake to all the world. They ‘approved
                    themselves’ the servants of God ‘in afflictions, in necessities, in distresses;
                    in <pb n="169"/>stripes, in imprisonments, in tumults, in labours’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor.
                                6:4-5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘in perils in the sea, in perils in the
                    wilderness; in weariness and painfulness, in hunger and thirst, in cold and
                        nakedness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 11:26-27.</p>
                    </note> And when, having ‘fought the good
                        fight’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Tim. 6:12.</p>
                    </note> they were ‘led as…sheep to the slaughter’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        8:32.</p>
                    </note> and ‘offered upon the sacrifice and service of their
                        faith’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Phil. 2:17.</p>
                    </note> then the blood of each found a voice, and the
                    heathen owned, ‘He being dead, yet speaketh.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. Thus did Christianity spread itself in the earth. But how soon did the
                    tares appear with the wheat!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 13:25-40.</p>
                    </note> And ‘the mystery of
                        iniquity’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Thess. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> work as well as ‘the mystery of godliness’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                        3:16.</p>
                    </note> How soon did Satan find a seat, even ‘in the temple of
                        God’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Thess. 2:4.</p>
                    </note> Till ‘the woman fled into the wilderness’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        12:6.</p>
                    </note> and ‘the faithful were (again) minished from the children
                    of men.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 12:1 (BCP). Cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> for other
                            eighteenth-century usages of ‘minished’.</p>
                    </note> Here we tread a
                    beaten path: the still increasing corruptions of the succeeding generations have
                    been largely described from time to time, by those witnesses God raised up, to
                    show that he had ‘built his church upon a rock, and the gates of hell should
                    not’ wholly ‘prevail against her.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 16:18.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. But shall we not see greater things than these?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For a fuller summary of
                            Wesley’s eschatology, cf. No. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great
                                Assize</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Yea, greater than have been yet from the
                    beginning of the world? Can Satan cause the truth of God to fail? Or his
                    promises to be of none effect? If not, the time will come when Christianity will
                    prevail over all, and cover the earth. Let us stand a little, and survey (the
                    third thing which was proposed) this strange sight, a <hi rend="italic">Christian world</hi>. ‘Of this the prophets of old inquired and searched.
                    diligently:’ of this ‘the Spirit which was in them testified’:<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Pet.
                                1:10, 11, etc.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘It shall come to pass in the last
                    days, that the mountain of the Lord’s house shall be established in the top of
                    the mountains, and shall be exalted above the hills, and all nations shall flow
                    unto it…. And they shall beat their swords into ploughshares, and their spears
                    into pruning-hooks. Nation shall not lift up sword against nation; neither shall
                    they learn war any more.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa. 2:2, 4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘In that day there
                        <pb n="170"/>shall be a root of Jesse, which shall stand for an ensign of
                    the people. To it shall the Gentiles seek, and his rest shall be glorious. And
                    it shall come to pass in that day, that the Lord shall set his hand again to
                    recover the remnant of his people; …and he shall set up an ensign for the
                    nations, and shall assemble the outcasts of Israel, and gather together the
                    dispersed of Judah, from the four corners of the earth.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa.
                                11:10-12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘The wolf shall (then) dwell with the
                    lamb, and the leopard shall lie down with the kid; and the calf, and the young
                    lion, and the fading together; and a little child shall lead them…. They shall
                    not hurt nor destroy (saith the Lord) in all my holy mountain: for the earth
                    shall be full of the knowledge of the Lord, as the waters cover the sea.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa. 11:6,
                                9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. To the same effect are the words of the great Apostle, which it is
                    evident have never yet been fulfilled: ‘Hath God cast away his people? God
                    forbid…. But through their fall, salvation is come to the Gentiles. And if the
                    diminishing of them be the riches of the Gentiles, how much more their
                    fullness?… For I would not, brethren, that ye should be ignorant of this
                    mystery; …that blindness in part is happened to Israel, until the fullness of
                    the Gentiles be come in: and so all Israel shall be saved.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 11:1,
                                11-12, 25-6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Suppose now the fullness of time to be come, and the prophecies to be
                    accomplished—what a prospect is this! All is ‘peace, quietness, and assurance
                        forever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 32:17.</p>
                    </note> Here is no din of arms, no ‘confused noise’,
                    no ‘garments rolled in blood’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 9:5.</p>
                    </note> ‘Destructions are come to
                    a perpetual end:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 9:6.</p>
                    </note> wars are ceased from the earth.
                    Neither is there any intestine jar<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matthew Prior, ‘An Ode…on the late glorious
                            success of Her Majesty’s arms…’ (1706): ‘Their own intestine feuds and
                            mutual jars…’. See also Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Comedy of
                                Errors</hi>, I.i.11-12:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>the mortal and intestine jars</l>
                            <l>’Twixt thy seditious countrymen and us…</l>
                        </lg>
                    </note> remaining: no brother rising up against brother; no country or city
                    divided against itself, and tearing out its own bowels. Civil discord is at an
                    end for evermore, and none is left either to destroy or hurt his neighbour. Here
                    is no oppression to ‘make (even) the wise man mad’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 7:7.</p>
                    </note>
                    no extortion to ‘grind the face of the poor’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 3:15.</p>
                    </note> no robbery or
                    wrong; no rapine or injustice; for all are ‘content with such <pb n="171"/>things as they possess’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 13:5.</p>
                    </note> Thus ‘righteousness and
                    peace have kissed each other’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ps. 85:10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> they have ‘taken root
                    and filled the land’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 80:9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> righteousness
                    flourishing out of the earth, and ‘peace looking down from heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            80:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And with righteousness or justice, mercy is also found. The earth is no
                    longer ‘full of cruel habitations’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 74:21 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘The Lord hath
                    destroyed both the bloodthirsty’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 5:6 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> and malicious, the
                    envious and revengeful man. Were there any provocation, there is none that now
                    knoweth to ‘return evil for evil’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 5:15, etc.</p>
                    </note> but indeed there
                    is none doth evil, no not one;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 3:10.</p>
                    </note> for all are ‘harmless as
                        doves’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:16.</p>
                    </note> and being ‘filled with peace and joy in
                        believing’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 15:13.</p>
                    </note> and united in one body,
                    by one Spirit, they all ‘love as brethren’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 3:8.</p>
                    </note> they are all ‘of one
                    heart, and of one soul, neither saith any of them that ought of the things which
                    he possesseth is his own’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 4:32; in Shakespeare, Milton, and Pope ‘ought’
                            and ‘aught’ appear indiscriminately (in their original
                        texts).</p>
                    </note> There is none among them that lacketh; for every man
                    loveth his neighbour as himself. And all walk by one rule: ‘Whatever ye would
                    that men should do unto you, even so do unto them.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                    7:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. It follows that no unkind word can ever be heard among them—no ‘strife
                    of tongues’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 31:20 (AV).</p>
                    </note> no contention of any kind, no railing, or
                    evil speaking—but everyone ‘opens his mouth with wisdom, and in his tongue there
                    is the law of kindness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 31:26.</p>
                    </note> Equally incapable are
                    they of fraud or guile: their ‘love is without dissimulation’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:9.</p>
                    </note>
                    their words are always the just expression of their thoughts, opening a window
                    into their breast,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A standard metaphor in illuminist mysticism; here
                            it reflects Wesley’s own intuitionism (cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.). It occurs again in No. 100, ‘On Pleasing All
                            Men’, II. 7, where Christians are exhorted, in speaking ‘<hi rend="italic">the</hi> truth’, to ‘open the window of their
                            breasts’. Cf. also Edward Young (the elder), ‘The Nature and Use of
                            Self-Denial’ (which Wesley published in the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                                Lib.</hi>, XLVI.133-34): ‘Were our breasts but for a while that “sea
                            of glass, clear as crystal” to one another (as St. John in his
                            Revelation tells us, they always are unto God); were our breasts so laid
                            open for awhile, that each could see the natural propensions of
                            another’s heart, in the same form that they now…stand; how should we be
                            glad to run away from ourselves, and be ashamed to own our own
                            appearances!’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">In No. 90, ‘An Israelite
                            Indeed’, II.10, Wesley cites ‘that arrogant King of Castile (Alphonso X
                            [1221-84]) as having said that God ought to have made man with a window
                            in his breast (so as to inhibit dissimulation; see Nos. 138A, 138B, ‘On
                            Dissimulation’). Originally, however, the jibe had come from Momus, the
                            Greek god of wit and ridicule; cf. Joseph Addison in <hi rend="italic">The Guardian</hi>, No. 106, July 13, 1713. The same point had been
                            made by Bishop Robert Sanderson, ‘Fifth Sermon <hi rend="italic">Ad
                                Populum’</hi>, (1624), in <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, Vol. I, p.
                            277, with an involved reference to Lucian, <hi rend="italic">Hermotimus</hi> (Loeb, 430:297-99).</p>
                    </note> that whosoever
                    desires may look into their hearts and see that only love and God are there.</p>
                <p n="6">
                    <pb n="172"/>6. Thus, where ‘the Lord God omnipotent taketh to himself his
                    mighty power, and reigneth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 19:6.</p>
                    </note> doth he ‘subdue all
                    things to himself,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:21.</p>
                    </note> cause every heart to
                    overflow with love, and fill every mouth with praise. ‘Happy are the people that
                    are in such a case; yea, blessed are the people who have the Lord for their
                        God.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ps. 144:15 [BCP].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Arise, shine (saith the Lord),
                    for thy light is come, and the glory of the Lord is risen upon thee…. Thou hast
                    known that I the Lord am thy Saviour and thy Redeemer, the mighty God of Jacob….
                    I have made thy officers peace, and thy exactors righteousness. Violence shall
                    no more be heard in thy land, wasting nor destruction within thy borders; but
                    thou shalt call thy walls “Salvation”, and thy gates “Praise”…. Thy people are
                    all righteous; they shall inherit the land for ever, the branch of my planting,
                    the work of my hands, that I may be glorified.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa. 60:1, 16-18[,
                            21].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘The sun shall no more be thy light by day; neither
                    for brightness shall the moon give light unto thee: but the Lord shall be unto
                    thee an everlasting light, and thy God thy glory.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Isa.
                    60:19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>IV. Having thus briefly considered Christianity as beginning, as going on, and as
                    covering the earth, it remains only that I should close the whole with a plain
                    practical application.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And first I would ask, Where does this Christianity now exist? Where, I
                    pray, do the Christians live?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s lifelong interest in primitive
                            Christianity and its restoration is well analysed by Schmidt, Wesley,
                                <hi rend="italic">passim</hi>. Wesley had been deeply impressed by
                            Johannes Arndt’s <hi rend="italic">True Christianity</hi> (Eng. tr.,
                            1712, 1714) and its pietistic visions of renewal; there are echoes of
                            the theme in Charles Wesley’s hymn, ‘Primitive Christianity’, first
                            published in <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, 1743 (11:90-94 of
                            this edn.). Wesley had read Antoinette Bourignon’s <hi rend="italic">Light of the World</hi> (Eng. tr. 1696); cf. her childhood queries
                            and pleas: ‘Where are the Christians? Let us go to the country where the
                            Christians live’ (Intro., xvi). Cf. Wesley’s reply to the Duke of Weimar
                            (?) to a query as to the purposes of his journey to Herrnhut: ‘I
                            answered, “To see the place where the Christians live”’ (JWJ, July 22,
                            1738; cf. also Curnock’s n., II.15). One of Wesley’s favourite church
                            histories was Claude Fleury, <hi rend="italic">An Historical Account of
                                the Manners and Behaviour of the Christians…</hi> (1698); indeed, he
                            would presently edit and publish an abridged translation of it (<hi rend="italic">The Manners of the Ancient Christians</hi>) in 1749;
                            see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 157.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">This primitivist orientation goes with Wesley’s conviction that the
                            Constantinian emancipation of Christianity was a sort of fall of the
                            church; see No. 61, ‘The Mystery of Iniquity’, §27 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    Which is the <pb n="173"/>country, the inhabitants whereof are ‘all (thus)
                    filled with the Holy Ghost’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:4.</p>
                    </note> Are all ‘of one heart and of
                    one soul’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 4:32. Cf. also Charles Wesley, ‘Primitive Christianity’, Pt. I,
                            ll. 15-16:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>They all were of one heart and soul,</l>
                            <l>And only love inspired the whole.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also No. 63, ‘The General Spread of the Gospel’,
                            §20.</p>
                    </note> Cannot suffer one among them to ‘lack anything’, but
                    continually give ‘to every man as he hath need’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 4:34-35.</p>
                    </note>
                    Who one and all have the love of God filling their hearts, and constraining them
                    to love their neighbour as themselves? Who have all ‘put on bowels of mercies,
                    humbleness of mind, gentleness, long-suffering’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:12.</p>
                    </note>
                    Who offend not in any kind, either by word or deed, against justice, mercy, or
                    truth, but in every point do unto all men as they would these should do unto
                        them?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 7:12; Luke 6:31.</p>
                    </note> With what propriety can we term any a
                    Christian country which does not answer this description? Why then, let us
                    confess we have never yet seen a Christian country upon earth.</p>
                <p n="2">2. I beseech you, brethren, by the mercies of God, if ye do account <hi rend="italic">me</hi> a madman or a fool,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The Oxford Methodists had already been
                            labelled with this commonplace eighteenth-century epithet in <hi rend="italic">Fog’s Weekly Journal</hi>, Nov. 5, 1732. John
                            Hutchinson would apply it to England’s most distinguished scientist,
                            Isaac Newton, in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (3rd edn. 1748-49), V.142.
                            William Law had used it (though not of the Methodists) in <hi rend="italic">A Practical Treatise Upon Christian Perfection</hi>
                            (1726), <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1762), III.99: ‘A good man who
                            enjoys the use of his reason is offended at madmen and fools because
                            they both act contrary to the reason of things. The madman fancies
                            himself, and everything about him, to be different from what they are;
                            the fool knows nothing of the value of things, is ridiculous in his
                            choices and prefers a shell before the most useful things in life;’ see
                            also <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, III.245. John Locke, <hi rend="italic">Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> (1690), ch.
                            xi, §§12-13, had distinguished between madmen (men who ‘reason right
                            from…wrong propositions’) and fools (who ‘reason scarce at all’). <hi rend="italic">The Tatter</hi>, No. 127 (Jan. 28-31, 1709), quotes
                            Terence, <hi rend="italic">Hic homines ex stultis facit insanos</hi>
                            (‘This fellow has the art of converting fools into madmen’).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley made his peace with this epithet as with the
                            others; cf. <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Hymns</hi> (1780), Hymn
                            388, l. 25: ‘Fools and madmen let us be’; see also Sermons 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III.14; and 125, ‘On a
                            Single Eye’, III.5. But in No. 11, <hi rend="italic">The Witness of the
                                Spirit</hi>, II, IV.2, Wesley himself speaks of the ‘French prophets
                            [i.e., the Camisards] and enthusiasts’ as ‘madmen’.</p>
                    </note> yet ‘as a
                    fool bear with me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 11:16.</p>
                    </note> It <pb n="174"/>is
                    utterly needful that someone should use great plainness of speech toward you. It
                    is more especially needful at <hi rend="italic">this</hi> time; for who knoweth
                    but it is the <hi rend="italic">last</hi>? Who knoweth how soon the righteous
                    judge may say, ‘I will no more be entreated for this people’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 8:8, 9, 29-31;
                            Jer. 7:16, etc.; and Ps. 77:7 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘Though Noah, Daniel,
                    and Job, were in this land, they should but deliver their own souls.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ezek.
                            14:20.</p>
                    </note> And who will use this plainness if I do not? Therefore
                    I, even I, will speak. And I adjure you, by the living God, that ye steel not
                    your breasts against receiving a blessing at <hi rend="italic">my</hi> hands. Do
                    not say in your heart, <hi rend="italic">Non persuadebis, etiamsi
                        persuaseris</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘You cannot persuade me, even though you have been
                            persuasive.’ This aphorism appears, in Greek, in Aristophanes, <hi rend="italic">Plutus</hi> (which Wesley had read), l. 600. By
                            Wesley’s time it had been turned into a sort of Latin proverb; cf.
                            South, <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1823), I.170: ‘Where the heart is
                            bent upon…a vicious cause [even a miracle] would end in a <hi rend="italic">non persuadebit etiamsi persuaseris</hi>….’ See also
                            Sanderson, <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, II.188. Joseph Addison (one
                            of Wesley’s favourite essayists) had used it in <hi rend="italic">The
                                Freeholder</hi>, No. 32 (Apr. 9, 1712): ‘“Make us believe that if
                            you can”, which is in Latin, if I may be allowed the pedantry, <hi rend="italic">Non persuadebis etiamsi persuaseris</hi>.’ For a later
                            usage (1773), cf. Oliver Goldsmith, <hi rend="italic">She Stoops to
                                Conquer</hi>, III.i.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">It reappears in
                            Wesley in a letter to Francis Okeley, Oct. 4, 1758; in English it turns
                            up in the Preface to the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi>, Pt. III. In
                            Nos. 83, ‘On Patience’, §11; and 88, ‘On Dress’, §8, it appears as a
                            somewhat incongruous paraphrase of Agrippa’s comment to St. Paul in Acts
                            26:28 (the text of No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                            Christian</hi>).</p>
                    </note> or, in other words, Lord, thou shalt not
                    ‘send by whom thou wilt send’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 4:13; John 3:34; 5:38; 6:29; 7:28; 14:26;
                            17:3, all of which served as warrants for Wesley’s self-understanding of
                            his own ‘extraordinary ministry’ and that of his preachers. The theme
                            reappears in Nos. 38, ‘A Caution against Bigotry’, I.14; 104, ‘On
                            Attending the Church Service’, §21; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, V.5; 121,
                            ‘Prophets and Priests’, §3. See also Charles Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Hymns on the Four Gospels</hi>, No. 1705 (on John 4:39), st. 1, l.
                            6: ‘The Almighty sends by whom he will’ (cf. <hi rend="italic">Poet.
                                Wks.</hi>, XI.361).</p>
                    </note> Let me rather perish in my blood than
                    be saved by this man!</p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘Brethren, I am persuaded better things of you, though I thus
                        speak.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 6:9.</p>
                    </note> Let me ask you, then, in tender love, and in
                    the spirit of meekness, Is this city a <hi rend="italic">Christian</hi> city? Is
                    Christianity, <hi rend="italic">scriptural</hi> Christianity, found here? Are
                    we, considered as a community of men, so ‘filled with the Holy Ghost’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:4;
                            4:31.</p>
                    </note> as to enjoy in our hearts, and show forth in our lives,
                    the genuine fruits of that Spirit? Are all the magistrates, all heads and
                    governors of colleges and halls, and their respective societies (not to speak of
                    the inhabitants of the town), ‘of one heart and of one soul’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 4:32.</p>
                    </note> Is
                    ‘the love of God shed abroad in our hearts’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:5.</p>
                    </note> Are our tempers the
                    same that were <pb n="175"/>in him? And are our lives agreeable thereto? Are we
                    ‘holy as he which hath called us is holy, in all manner of conversation’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            1:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. I entreat you to observe that here are no <hi rend="italic">peculiar
                        notions</hi> now under consideration; that the question moved is not
                    concerning <hi rend="italic">doubtful opinions</hi> of one kind or another; but
                    concerning the undoubted, fundamental branches (if there be any such) of our <hi rend="italic">common Christianity</hi>. And for the decision thereof I
                    appeal to your own conscience, guided by the Word of God. He therefore that is
                    not condemned by his own heart, let him go free.</p>
                <p n="5">5. In the fear, then, and in the presence of the great God before whom both
                    you and I shall shortly appear, I pray you that are in authority over us, whom I
                    reverence for your office’ sake, to consider (and not after the manner of
                    dissemblers with God), are you ‘filled with the Holy Ghost’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 2:4; 4:31.</p>
                    </note>
                    Are ye lively portraitures of him whom ye are appointed to represent among men?
                    ‘I have said, Ye are gods,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 82:6; cf. John 10:34.</p>
                    </note> ye magistrates
                    and rulers; ye are by office so nearly allied to the God of heaven! In your
                    several stations and degrees ye are to show forth unto us ‘the Lord our
                        Governor’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 8:1 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Are all the thoughts of your hearts, all
                    your tempers and desires, suitable to your high calling? Are all your words like
                    unto those which come out of the mouth of God? Is there in all your actions
                    dignity and love? A greatness which words cannot express, which can flow only
                    from an heart full of God—and yet consistent with the character of ‘man that is
                    a worm, and the son of man that is a worm’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 25:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Ye venerable men who are more especially called to form the tender minds
                    of youth, to dispel thence the shades of ignorance and error, and train them up
                    to be wise unto salvation, are you ‘filled with the Holy Ghost’? With all those
                    ‘fruits of the Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:22.</p>
                    </note> which your important
                    office so indispensably requires? Is your heart whole with God? Full of love and
                    zeal to set up his kingdom on earth? Do you continually remind those under your
                    care that the one rational end of all our studies is to know, love, and serve
                    ‘the only true God, and Jesus Christ whom he hath sent’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 17:3.</p>
                    </note> Do you
                    inculcate upon them day by day that ‘love alone never faileth’? Whereas,
                    ‘whether there be tongues, they shall fail’, or <pb n="176"/>philosophical
                    ‘knowledge, it shall vanish away’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:8.</p>
                    </note> and that without love all
                    learning is but splendid ignorance,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In his earlier university sermon on Luke 10:42
                            (1734), No. 146, ‘The One Thing Needful’, III.1, Wesley had described
                            learning as ‘that fairest earthly fruit’.</p>
                    </note> pompous folly,
                    vexation of spirit. Has all you teach an actual tendency to the love of God, and
                    of all mankind for his sake? Have you an eye to this end in whatever you
                    prescribe touching the kind, the manner, and the measure of their studies;
                    desiring and labouring that wherever the lot of these young soldiers of Christ
                    is cast they may be so many ‘burning and shining lights’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 5:35.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘adorning the gospel of Christ in all things’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 2:10.</p>
                    </note> And permit me to
                    ask, Do you put forth all your strength in the vast work you have undertaken? Do
                    you labour herein with all your might? Exerting every faculty of your soul?
                    Using every talent which God hath lent you, and that to the uttermost of your
                        power?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            these questions with those that had been put to Wesley himself on Feb.
                            8, 1736, by the Moravian leader, A. G. Spangenberg (see JWJ for the
                            reported conversation): ‘Do you know yourself? Have you the witness
                            within yourself? Does the Spirit of God bear witness with your spirit
                            that you are a child of God?’ Wesley records that he ‘was surprised and
                            knew not what to answer’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Let it not be said that I speak here as if all under your care were
                    intended to be clergymen. Not so; I only speak as if they were all intended to
                    be Christians. But what example is set them by us who enjoy the beneficence of
                    our forefathers; by fellows, students, scholars; more especially those who are
                    of some rank and eminence? Do ye, brethren, abound in the fruits of the Spirit,
                    in lowliness of mind, in self-denial and mortification, in seriousness and
                    composure of spirit, in patience, meekness, sobriety, temperance, and in
                    unwearied, restless endeavours to do good in every kind unto all men, to relieve
                    their outward wants, and to bring their souls to the true knowledge and love of
                        God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            list clearly reminiscent of the goals of the earlier Holy
                        Club.</p>
                    </note> Is this the general character of fellows of colleges? I
                    fear it is not. Rather, have not pride and haughtiness of spirit, impatience and
                    peevishness, sloth and indolence, gluttony and sensuality, and even a proverbial
                    uselessness, been objected to us, <hi rend="italic">perhaps</hi> not always by
                    our enemies, nor <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi> without ground? O that God would
                    roll away this reproach from us,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Josh. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> that the very memory of
                    it might perish for ever!</p>
                <p n="8">
                    <pb n="177"/>8. Many of us are more immediately consecrated to God, called
                    to ‘minister in holy things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 9:13.</p>
                    </note> Are we then patterns to
                    the rest, ‘in word, in conversation, in charity; in spirit, in faith, in
                        purity’?<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Tim. 4:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Is there written on
                    our forehead and on our heart, ‘Holiness to the Lord’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 28:36.</p>
                    </note>
                    From what motives did we enter upon this office? Was it indeed with a single eye
                    ‘to serve God, trusting that we were inwardly moved by the Holy Ghost to take
                    upon us this ministration, for the promoting of his glory, and the edifying of
                    his people’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Ordering of Deacons, Bishop’s examination, Q. 1
                        (511).</p>
                    </note> And have we ‘clearly determined, by God’s grace, to give
                    ourselves wholly to this office? Do we forsake and set aside, as much as in us
                    lies, all worldly cares and studies? Do we apply ourselves wholly to this one
                    thing, and draw all our cares and studies this way’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Ordering of Priests,
                            Bishop’s exhortation (532).</p>
                    </note> Are we ‘apt to teach’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim.
                            2:24.</p>
                    </note> Are we ‘taught of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 6:45.</p>
                    </note> that
                    we may be able to teach others also? Do we know God? Do we know Jesus Christ?
                    Hath God ‘revealed his Son in us’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> And hath he ‘made us able
                    ministers of the new covenant’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165" n="165">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 3:6.</p>
                    </note> Where then are ‘the
                    seals of our apostleship’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 9:2.</p>
                    </note> Who that ‘were dead in
                    trespasses and sins’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn167" n="167">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:1.</p>
                    </note> have been quickened by our
                    word? Have we a burning zeal to save souls from death,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168" n="168">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 5:20.</p>
                    </note> so
                    that for their sake we often forget even to eat our bread?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn169" n="169">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 102:4.</p>
                    </note> Do
                    we speak plain, ‘by manifestation of the truth commending ourselves to every
                    man’s conscience in the sight of God’?<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor. 4:2.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Are we
                    dead to the world and the things of the world, ‘laying up all our treasure in
                        heaven’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn170" n="170">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 6:20.</p>
                    </note> ‘Do we lord it over God’s heritage’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn171" n="171">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            5:3.</p>
                    </note> Or are we the least, the ‘servants of all’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn172" n="172">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark
                            9:35.</p>
                    </note> When we bear the reproach of Christ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn173" n="173">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:26.</p>
                    </note> does
                    it sit heavy upon us, or do we rejoice therein? When we are ‘smitten on the one
                    cheek’, do we resent it? Are we impatient of affronts? Or do we ‘turn the other
                    also’; ‘not resisting the evil’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn174" n="174">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:39.</p>
                    </note> but ‘overcoming evil
                    with good’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn175" n="175">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:21.</p>
                    </note> Have we a bitter zeal, inciting us to strive
                    sharply and passionately <pb n="178"/>with them ‘that are out of the way’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn176" n="176">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        5:2.</p>
                    </note> Or is our zeal the flame of love? So as to direct all our
                    words with sweetness, lowliness, and meekness of wisdom?</p>
                <p n="9">9. Once more: what shall we say concerning the youth of this place? Have
                        <hi rend="italic">you</hi> either the form or the power of Christian
                    godliness? Are you humble, teachable, advisable; or stubborn, self-willed,
                    heady, and high-minded? Are you obedient to your superiors as to parents; or do
                    you despise those to whom you owe the tenderest reverence? Are you diligent in
                    your easy business, pursuing your studies with all your strength? Do you ‘redeem
                    the time’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn177" n="177">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 5:16; Col. 4:5; see also No. 93, ‘On Redeeming the
                        Time’.</p>
                    </note> crowding as much work into every day as it can contain?
                    Rather, are ye not conscious to yourselves that you waste away day after day,
                    either in reading what has no tendency to Christianity, or in gaming, or in—you
                    know not what?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn178" n="178">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The background here would have been the Statutes of the University, <hi rend="italic">Parecbolae sive Excerpta è Corpore Statutorum
                                Universitatis Oxoniensis…</hi> (1729). See also G. R. M. Ward, tr.,
                                <hi rend="italic">Oxford University Statutes</hi>, Vol. I: <hi rend="italic">Containing the Caroline Code or Laudian Statutes,
                                Promulgated, A.D. 1636. Titulus XV, De Moribus Conformandis</hi>
                            (‘Concerning Appropriate Behaviour’), spells out prohibited behaviour in
                            detail: e.g., §4, <hi rend="italic">De Domibus Oppidanorum non
                                frequentandis</hi> (‘Concerning Types of Houses in the City Not to
                            be Frequented’); §5, <hi rend="italic">De Oenopolis, sive Taberniis
                                Vinariis, Popinis, et Diversionis non frequentandis</hi>
                            (‘Concerning Wine-Shops or Taverns, Eating Houses and Diversions Not to
                            be Frequented’); §6, <hi rend="italic">De Nocturna Vagatione
                                reprimenda</hi> (‘Concerning the Restraint of Nocturnal
                            Excursions’); §7, <hi rend="italic">De Ludis Prohibitis</hi>
                            (‘Concerning Prohibited Amusements’); §8, <hi rend="italic">De famosis
                                Libellis cohibendis</hi> (‘Concerning the Repression of Scandalous
                            Books’), etc. See Nos. 150, 151, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’.</p>
                    </note> Are
                    you better managers of your fortune than of your time? Do you, out of principle,
                    take care to ‘owe no man anything’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn179" n="179">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:8.</p>
                    </note> Do you ‘remember the sabbath
                    day to keep it holy’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn180" n="180">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:8.</p>
                    </note> to spend it in the more
                    immediate worship of God? When you are in his house do you consider that God is
                    there? Do you behave ‘as seeing him that is invisible’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn181" n="181">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:27.</p>
                    </note> Do
                    you know how to ‘possess your bodies in sanctification and honour’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn182" n="182">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess.
                            4:4.</p>
                    </note> Are not drunkenness and uncleanness found among you?
                    Yea, are there not of you who ‘glory in their shame’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn183" n="183">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:19.</p>
                    </note> Do
                    not many of you ‘take the name of God in vain’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn184" n="184">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:7.</p>
                    </note>
                    perhaps habitually, without either remorse or fear? Yea, are there not a
                    multitude of you that are forsworn? I fear, a swiftly increasing multitude. Be
                    not surprised, brethren: before God and this congregation I own myself to have
                    been of that number; solemnly swearing to ‘observe all those customs’ which I
                    then <pb n="179"/>knew nothing of, ‘and those statutes’ which I did not so much
                    as read over, either then, or for some years after.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn185" n="185">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Not till Nov. 1726 (as the
                            early diaries show), after his graduation as AB and his election as
                            Fellow of Lincoln (Mar. 17, 1726).</p>
                    </note> What is perjury, if this
                    is not? But if it be, O what a weight of sin, yea, sin of no common dye, lieth
                    upon us! And doth not ‘the Most High regard it’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn186" n="186">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 73:11;
                        94:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. May it not be one of the consequences of this that so many of you are
                    a generation of <hi rend="italic">triflers</hi>; triflers with God, with one
                    another, and with your own souls? For how few of you spend, from one week to
                    another, a single hour in private prayer? How few have any thought of God in the
                    general tenor of your conversation? Who of you is in any degree acquainted with
                    the work of his Spirit? His supernatural work in the souls of men? Can you bear,
                    unless now and then in a church, any talk of the Holy Ghost? Would you not take
                    it for granted if one began such a conversation that it was either ‘hypocrisy’
                    or ‘enthusiasm’? In the name of the Lord God Almighty I ask, What religion are
                        <hi rend="italic">you</hi> of? Even the talk of Christianity ye cannot, will
                    not, bear! O my brethren! What a Christian city is this? ‘It is time for thee,
                    Lord, to lay to thine hand!&lt;note place="foot" n="’184"&gt;Ps. 119:126 (BCP).
                    Wesley’s own answer here had already been given (in No. 150, ‘Hypocrisy in
                    Oxford’): ‘How has this city become an harlot!’ (Isa. 1:21).</p>
                <p n="11">11. For indeed what probability—what possibility rather (speaking after
                    the manner of men)—is there that Christianity, scriptural Christianity, should
                    be again the religion of this place? That all orders of men among us should
                    speak and live as men ‘filled with the Holy Ghost’? By whom should this
                    Christianity be restored? By those of you that are in authority? Are you
                    convinced then that this is scriptural Christianity? Are you desirous it should
                    be restored? And do ye not count your fortune, liberty, life, dear unto
                    yourselves, so ye may be instrumental in the restoring it? But suppose ye have
                    this desire, who hath any power proportioned to the effect? Perhaps some of you
                    have made a few faint attempts, but with how small success! Shall Christianity
                    then be restored by young, unknown, inconsiderable men? I know not whether ye
                    yourselves could suffer it. Would not some of you cry out, ‘Young man, in so
                    doing thou reproachest us!’ But there is no danger of your being put to the
                    proof, so hath ‘iniquity overspread us like a flood’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn187" n="187">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 69:2; see also No.
                            3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, III.10 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> Whom then shall God send? The famine, the pestilence <pb n="180"/>(the last messengers of God to a guilty land), or the sword?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn188" n="188">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer. 14:12,
                            etc.; Ezek. 6:11, etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘The armies of the’ Romish
                        ‘aliens’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn189" n="189">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:34; the ‘Romish aliens’ were, of course, the French.
                            Britain was already deeply involved in the anti-Bourbon coalition led by
                            Frederick II, and had already celebrated the victory of Dettingen the
                            year before. But after the naval defeat at Toulon and the appearance of
                            a French fleet off Dungeness (both in Feb. 1744), fears of a French
                            invasion had aroused the country. War had been declared, officially, in
                            March. A year later came ‘the Rising of ’45’ under ‘Bonnie Prince
                            Charlie’ (Stuart), aided by the French.</p>
                    </note> to reform us into our
                    first love? Nay, rather ‘let us fall into thy hand, O Lord, and let us not fall
                    into the hand of man.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn190" n="190">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Sam. 24:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
                <p>Lord, save, or we perish!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn191" n="191">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 8:25.</p>
                    </note> Take us out of the mire,
                    that we sink not! O help us against these enemies! For vain is the help of man.
                    Unto thee all things are possible.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn192" n="192">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Mark 14:36.</p>
                    </note> According to the
                    greatness of thy power, preserve thou those that are appointed to die. And
                    preserve us in the manner that seemest thee good; not as we will, but as thou
                        wilt!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn193" n="193">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 26:39.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>