<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 25: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse V</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon025</idno>                   
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 25: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse V</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="550" to="571"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic">Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic">there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="468"/>the former part of [ch. 7]
                    he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic">and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="550"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Fifth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 5:17-20</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Think not that I am come to destroy the law or the prophets: I
                        am not come to destroy, but to fulfil.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For verily I say unto you, Till heaven and earth pass, one jot
                        or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law, till all be
                        fulfilled.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least
                        commandments, and shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the
                        kingdom of heaven; but whosoever shall do and teach them, the same shall be
                        called great in the kingdom of heaven.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For verily I say unto you, That except your righteousness shall
                        exceed the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case
                        enter into the kingdom of heaven.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Among the multitude of reproaches which fell upon him who was ‘despised
                    and rejected of men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 53:3.</p>
                    </note> it could not fail to be one
                    that he was a teacher of novelties, an introducer of a <hi rend="italic">new
                        religion</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Such a charge, if true, would have been devastating in Wesley’s eyes,
                            since he regarded novelty in doctrine as prima facie evidence of error;
                            cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, III.9 (‘Whatever
                            doctrine is <hi rend="italic">new</hi> must be <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi>’); and his letter to Mary Stokes, Aug. 10, 1772: a thing
                            that is ‘wholly new is therefore wholly wrong’. In No. 17, ‘The
                            Circumcision of the Heart’, §1, he had emphatically denied that he was
                            ‘a setter forth of new doctrine’ and would warn against doctrinal
                            innovations in later sermons; cf. Nos. 78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, I.7
                            ff.; and 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III.8; and
                            see also a very late letter to Walter Churchey, June 20, 1789: ‘In
                            religion I am for as few innovations as possible.’ In all this he was
                            reflecting the basic Anglican attitude toward <hi rend="italic">tradition</hi> (‘Christian antiquity’); the same perspective had
                            been echoed by Stillingfleet, Addison, South, and others—harking back to
                            the Vincentian Canon, ‘<hi rend="italic">Consensus veterum: quod ab
                                omnibus, quod ubique, quod semper creditum</hi>’ (‘the ancient
                            consensus: what has been believed by all, everywhere and always’). Cf.
                                <hi rend="italic">The Commonitory of Vincent of Lerins</hi> (A.D.
                            435), §6 [ch. II].</p>
                    </note> This might be affirmed with the more
                    colour because many of the expressions he had used were not common among the
                    Jews: either they did not use them at all, or not in the same sense, not in so
                    full and strong a meaning. Add to this that the worshipping <pb n="551"/>God ‘in
                    spirit and in truth’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 4:23, 24.</p>
                    </note> must always appear a new
                    religion to those who have hitherto known nothing but outside worship, nothing
                    but the ‘form of godliness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And ’tis not improbable some might hope it was so, that he was
                    abolishing the old religion and bringing in another, one which they might
                    flatter themselves would be an easier way to heaven. But our Lord refutes in
                    these words both the vain hopes of the one and the groundless calumnies of the
                    other.</p>
                <p>I shall consider them in the same order as they lie, taking each verse for a
                    distinct head of discourse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, ‘think not that I am come to destroy the law or the
                    prophets. I am not come to destroy, but to fulfil.’</p>
                <p>The ritual or ceremonial law delivered by Moses to the children of Israel,
                    containing all the injunctions and ordinances which related to the old
                    sacrifices and service of the temple, our Lord indeed did come to destroy, to
                    dissolve and utterly abolish. To this bear all the apostles witness: not only
                    Barnabas and Paul, who vehemently withstood those who taught that Christians
                    ought ‘to keep the law of Moses’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 15:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> not only St.
                    Peter, who termed the insisting on this, on the observance of the ritual law,
                    a[s] ‘tempting God, and putting a yoke upon the neck of the disciples which
                    neither our fathers (saith he) nor we were able to bear’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                15:10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> but ‘all the apostles, elders, and brethren,
                    […] being assembled with one accord’, declared that to command them to keep this
                    law was to ‘subvert their souls’; and that ‘it seemed good to the Holy Ghost and
                    to them to lay no such burden upon them.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 24, etc. [Acts
                            15:22-28.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> This ‘handwriting of ordinances our Lord did
                    blot out, take away, and nail to his cross.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 2:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. But the moral law, contained in the Ten Commandments, and enforced by
                    the prophets, he did not take away. It was not the design of his coming to
                    revoke any part of this. This is a law which never can be broken, which ‘stands
                    fast as the faithful witness in heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 89:36 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> The moral stands on
                    an entirely different foundation from the ceremonial or ritual law, which was
                    only designed for a temporary restraint upon a disobedient and stiff-necked
                    people; <pb n="552"/>whereas this was from the beginning of the world, being
                    ‘written not on tables of stone’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 3:3.</p>
                    </note> but on the hearts of all
                    the children of men when they came out of the hands of the Creator. And however
                    the letters once wrote by the finger of God<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 31:18; Deut. 9:10.</p>
                    </note> are
                    now in a great measure defaced by sin, yet can they not wholly be blotted out
                    while we have any consciousness of good and evil. Every part of this law must
                    remain in force, upon all mankind, and in all ages; as not depending either on
                    time or place, or any other circumstances liable to change, but on the nature of
                    God and the nature of man, and their unchangeable relation to each other.</p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘I am not come to destroy, but to fulfil.’ Some have conceived our Lord
                    to mean, I am come to fulfil this by my entire and perfect obedience to it. And
                    it cannot be doubted but he did in this sense fulfil every part of it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A special point of
                            Blackall’s in Discourse XIX, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                        I.174-77.</p>
                    </note> But this does not appear to be what he intends here,
                    being foreign to the scope of his present discourse. Without question his
                    meaning in this place is (consistently with all that goes before and follows
                    after): I am come to establish it in its fullness, in spite of all the glosses
                    of men; I am come to place in a full and clear view whatsoever was dark or
                    obscure therein; I am come to declare the true and full import of every part of
                    it; to show the length and breadth, the entire extent of every commandment
                    contained therein, and the height and depth, the inconceivable purity and
                    spirituality of it in all its branches.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A move beyond the prevailing interpretations,
                            as in Tillotson, Henry, and Poole; cf. Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, where Jesus’s word is paraphrased thus, ‘I am
                            come to fulfil [the Moral Law] by yielding myself a personal obedience
                            to it, by giving a fuller and stricter interpretation of it.’ Henry’s
                            comment here is to the same effect. For Wesley’s view of the exalted
                            status of ‘the Moral Law’, see below, Nos. 34-36, but especially the
                            passage on ‘the nature of the Law’ in No. 34, ‘The Original, Nature,
                            Properties, and Use of the Law’, II.1-6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And this our Lord has abundantly performed in the preceding and
                    subsequent parts of the discourse before us, in which he has not introduced a
                    new religion into the world, but the same which was from the beginning: a
                    religion the substance of which is, without question, ‘as old as the
                        creation’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>, I.4(4-10):
                            ‘Our [Christian] manner of life and mode of conduct, together with our
                            religious principles, have not been just now invented by us, but from
                            the first creation of man were established by the innate ideas of those
                            men of old whom God loved….’ Matthew Tindal had given this old idea a
                            deistic twist in his <hi rend="italic">Christianity as Old as
                                Creation</hi> (1730); Wesley harks back to the original—the moral
                            law <hi rend="italic">is</hi> ‘coeval with man’ but is, and has always
                            been, <hi rend="italic">supernatural</hi> in its origins and
                            sanctions.</p>
                    </note> being coeval <pb n="553"/>with man, and having
                    proceeded from God at the very time when ‘man became a living soul’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                        2:7.</p>
                    </note> (The substance, I say, for some circumstances of it now
                    relate to man as a fallen creature); a religion witnessed to both by the law and
                    by the prophets in all succeeding generations. Yet was it never so fully
                    explained nor so throughly understood till the great Author of it himself
                    condescended to give mankind this authentic comment on all the essential
                    branches of it; at the same time declaring it should never be changed, but
                    remain in force to the end of the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. ‘For verily I say unto you’ (a solemn preface, which denotes both
                    the importance and certainty of what is spoken), ‘Till heaven and earth pass,
                    one jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass from the law till all be
                        fulfilled.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘One jot’—it is literally, <hi rend="italic">not one iota</hi>, not the most
                    inconsiderable vowel; ‘or one tittle’, μία κεραία, one corner, or point of a
                    consonant. It is a proverbial expression which signifies that no one commandment
                    contained in the moral law, nor the least part of one, however inconsiderable it
                    might seem, should ever be disannulled.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., ‘cancelled’; cf. III.8, below, for a
                            similar usage. See also <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘Shall in no wise pass from the law;’ οὐ μὴ παρέλθῃ ἀπὸ τοῦ νόμοῦ. The double
                    negative here used strengthens the sense so as to admit of no contradiction. And
                    the word παρέλθῃ, it may be observed, is not barely <hi rend="italic">future</hi>, declaring what <hi rend="italic">will</hi> be; but has
                    likewise the force of an <hi rend="italic">imperative</hi>, ordering what <hi rend="italic">shall</hi> be. It is a word of authority, expressing the
                    sovereign will and power of him that spake, of him whose word is the law of
                    heaven and earth, and stands fast for ever and ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 40:8. For Wesley’s
                            overconfident way with future indicative and imperative forms in Greek,
                            cf. No. 16, ‘The Means of Grace’, III.7 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘One jot or one tittle shall in no wise pass till heaven and earth pass;’ or as
                    it is expressed immediately after, ἕως ἂν πάντα γένηται, ‘till all’ (or rather,
                        <hi rend="italic">all things</hi>) ‘be fulfilled’, till the consummation of
                    all things. Here is therefore no room for that poor evasion (with which some
                    have delighted themselves greatly) that ‘no part of the law was to pass away
                    till <hi rend="italic">all the law</hi> was fulfilled; but it has been fulfilled
                    by Christ, and therefore now must pass, <pb n="554"/>for the gospel to be
                        established.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s paraphrase of the substance of the
                            antinomian argument cast in the form of a syllogism.</p>
                    </note> Not so;
                    the word ‘all’ does not mean all the law, but all things in the universe; as
                    neither has the term ‘fulfilled’ any reference to the law, but to all things in
                    heaven and earth.</p>
                <p n="2">2. From all this we may learn that there is no contrariety at all between
                    the law and the gospel; that there is no need for the law to pass away in order
                    to the establishing of the gospel. Indeed neither of them supersedes the other,
                    but they agree perfectly well together. Yea, the very same words, considered in
                    different respects, are parts both of the law and of the gospel. If they are
                    considered as commandments, they are parts of the law: if as promises, of the
                    gospel. Thus, ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 6:5; Matt.
                            22:37, etc.</p>
                    </note> when considered as a commandment, is a branch of
                    the law; when regarded as a promise, is an essential part of the gospel—the
                    gospel being no other than the commands of the law proposed by way of
                        promises.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            prime rule for Wesley’s hermeneutics: no command apart from a promise of
                            grace; no promise without an implied moral responsibility. Its probable
                            source: Thomas Drayton, <hi rend="italic">The Proviso or Condition of
                                the Promises</hi> (1657), pp. 1-2. Cf. also Nos. 27, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, VII’, II.12; 76, ‘On Perfection’, II.1-2, 11; and 101, ‘The Duty
                            of Constant Communion’, II.3. See also Wesley’s letter to Ebenezer
                            Blackwell (?), Dec. 20, 1751.</p>
                    </note> Accordingly poverty of spirit,
                    purity of heart, and whatever else is enjoined in the holy law of God, are no
                    other, when viewed in a gospel light, than so many great and precious
                        promises.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 1:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. There is therefore the closest connection that can be conceived between
                    the law and the gospel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For a fuller development of this thesis, see below,
                            Nos. 34-36.</p>
                    </note> On the one hand the law continually makes way for
                    and points us to the gospel; on the other the gospel continually leads us to a
                    more exact fulfilling of the law. The law, for instance, requires us to love
                    God, to love our neighbour, to be meek, humble, or holy. We feel that we are not
                    sufficient for these things, yea, that ‘with man this is impossible.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            19:26.</p>
                    </note> But we see a promise of God to give us that love, and
                    to make us humble, meek, and holy. We lay hold of this gospel, of these glad
                    tidings: it is done unto us according to our faith, and ‘the righteousness of
                    the law is fulfilled in us’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:4.</p>
                    </note> through faith which is in
                    Christ Jesus.</p>
                <p>We may yet farther observe that every command in Holy Writ is <pb n="555"/>only a
                    covered promise. For by that solemn declaration, ‘This is the covenant I will
                    make after those days, saith the Lord; I will put my laws in your minds, and
                    write them in your hearts,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:16.</p>
                    </note> God hath engaged to give
                    whatsoever he commands. Does he command us then to ‘pray without ceasing’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess.
                            5:17.</p>
                    </note> To ‘rejoice evermore’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:16.</p>
                    </note> To be ‘holy as he
                    is holy’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Pet. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> It is enough. He will work in us this very thing.
                    It shall be unto us according to his word.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:38.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. But if these things are so, we cannot be at a loss what to think of
                    those who in all ages of the church have undertaken to change or supersede some
                    commands of God, as they professed, by the peculiar direction of his Spirit.
                    Christ has here given us an infallible rule whereby to judge of all such
                    pretentions. Christianity, as it includes the whole moral law of God, both by
                    way of injunction and of promise, if we will hear him, is designed of God to be
                    the last of all his dispensations. There is no other to come after this. This is
                    to endure till the consummation of all things. Of consequence all such new
                    revelations are of Satan, and not of God; and all pretences to another more
                    perfect dispensation fall to the ground of course. ‘Heaven and earth shall pass
                    away; but this word shall not pass away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 21:33.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. ‘Whosoever therefore shall break one of these least commandments,
                    and shall teach men so, he shall be called the least in the kingdom of heaven;
                    but whosoever shall do and teach them, the same shall be called great in the
                    kingdom of heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:19.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Who, what are they that make ‘the preaching of the law’ a character of reproach?
                    Do they not see on whom their reproach must fall? On whose head it must light at
                    last? Whosoever on this ground despiseth us, despiseth him that sent us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                            10:16.</p>
                    </note> For did ever any man preach the law like him? Even
                    when he ‘came not to condemn but to save the world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:17;
                        12:47.</p>
                    </note> when he came purposely to bring ‘life and immortality to
                    light through the gospel’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 1:10.</p>
                    </note> Can any ‘preach the law’
                    more expressly, more rigorously, than Christ does in these words? And who is he
                    that shall amend them? Who is he that shall instruct the Son of God how to
                    preach? Who will teach him a better way of delivering the message which he hath
                    received of the Father?</p>
                <p n="2">
                    <pb n="556"/>2. ‘Whosoever shall break one of these least commandments’, or
                    one of the least of these commandments. ‘These commandments’, we may observe, is
                    a term used by our Lord as equivalent with ‘the law’, or the ‘law and the
                    prophets’, which is the same thing, seeing the prophets added nothing to the
                    law, but only declared, explained, or enforced it, as they were moved by the
                    Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Pet. 1:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘Whosoever shall break one of these least commandments’, especially if it be done
                    wilfully or presumptuously. <hi rend="italic">One</hi>—for ‘he that keepeth the
                    whole law and’ thus ‘offends in one point, is guilty of all:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> the
                    wrath of God abideth on him<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:36.</p>
                    </note> as surely as if he had broken
                    every one. So that no allowance is made for one darling lust;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A seventeenth- and
                            eighteenth-century cliché repeated by John Bunyan, John Dryden, Francis
                            Atterbury, Samuel Annesley, Robert Bolton, Thomas Fuller, Richard Lucas,
                            Robert South, and others, with such variations as ‘darling sins’, ‘bosom
                            sins’, etc. Cf. Matthew Mead, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian
                                Discovered</hi>, p. 107: ‘There is a natural man, let him go never
                            so far, let him go never so much in matters of religion; but still he
                            hath his Dalilah, his bosom-lust;’ on p. 130 he repeats the point:
                            ‘…every lust, every darling, every beloved sin…’. For other usages in
                            Wesley, cf. Nos. 48, ‘Self-denial’, II.2-3; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s
                            Coming’, §1; and 142, ‘The Wisdom of Winning Souls’, II.7. In No. 135,
                            ‘On Guardian Angels’, proem, ¶2, Wesley speaks of ‘darling bodies’; in
                            No. 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, I.3, he speaks of ‘parent
                        sins’.</p>
                    </note> no reserve for one idol; no excuse for refraining from all
                    besides, and only giving way to one bosom sin. What God demands is an entire
                    obedience; we are to have an eye to all his commandments; otherwise we lose all
                    the labour we take in keeping some, and our poor souls for ever and ever.</p>
                <p>‘One of these least’, or one of the least of these ‘commandments’. Here is
                    another excuse cut off, whereby many, who cannot deceive God, miserably deceive
                    their own souls. ‘This sin, saith the sinner, is it not a little one? Will not
                    the Lord spare me in this thing? Surely he will not be extreme to mark this,
                    since I do not offend in the greater matters of the law.’ Vain hope! Speaking
                    after the manner of men we may term these great, and those little commandments.
                    But in reality they are not so. If we use propriety of speech there is no such
                    thing as a little sin, every sin being a transgression of the holy and perfect
                    law, and an affront of the great majesty of heaven.</p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘And shall teach men so’—In some sense it may be said that whosoever
                    openly breaks any commandment teaches others to do <pb n="557"/>the same; for
                    example speaks, and many times louder than precept. In this sense it is apparent
                    every open drunkard is a teacher of drunkenness; every sabbath-breaker is
                    constantly teaching his neighbour to profane the day of the Lord. But this is
                    not all; an habitual breaker of the law is seldom content to stop here. He
                    generally teaches other men to do so too, by word as well as example; especially
                    when he hardens his neck, and hateth to be reproved. Such a sinner soon
                        commences<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This is the academic usage of ‘commence’; i.e., ‘graduates to the
                            status of…’. Cf. No. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>,
                            III.4, where Wesley again uses ‘commence’ in this sense.</p>
                    </note> an
                    advocate for sin: he defends what he is resolved not to forsake. He excuses the
                    sin which he will not leave, and thus directly teaches every sin which he
                    commits.</p>
                <p>‘He shall be called least in the kingdom of heaven’—that is, shall have no part
                        therein.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heylyn’s point: ‘<hi rend="italic">minimus in regno caelorum</hi>’ has
                            here the force of <hi rend="italic">minimé</hi> and imports an exclusion
                            from the gospel dispensation (<hi rend="italic">Theological
                                Lectures</hi>, I.76). Wesley repeats his own phrase here in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p>
                    </note> He is a stranger to the kingdom
                    of heaven which is on earth; he hath no portion in that inheritance; no share of
                    that righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note> Nor by
                    consequence can he have any part in the glory which shall be revealed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. But if those who even thus break and teach others to break one of the
                    least of these commandments shall be called least in the kingdom of heaven,
                    shall have no part in the kingdom of Christ and of God; if even these ‘shall be
                    cast into outer darkness’, where is ‘wailing and gnashing of teeth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        8:12.</p>
                    </note> then where will they appear whom our Lord chiefly and
                    primarily intends in these words? They who, bearing the character of teachers
                    sent from God, do nevertheless themselves break his commandments, yea and openly
                    teach others so to do, being corrupt both in life and doctrine?</p>
                <p n="5">5. These are of several sorts. Of the first sort are they who live in some
                    wilful, habitual sin. Now if an ordinary sinner teaches by his example, how much
                    more a sinful minister, even if he does not attempt to defend, excuse, or
                    extenuate his sin! If he does he is a murderer indeed, yea, the murderer-general
                    of his congregation!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This stark metaphor occurs in a letter written at
                            the same time with this sermon (to ‘John Smith’, Mar. 25, 1747): ‘a
                            lifeless, unconverting minister is the murderer-general of his
                            congregation.’ Cf. the much later No. 104, ‘On Attending the Church
                            Service’, §§19 ff., where unworthy ministers are viewed less harshly.
                            See also Art. XXVI, ‘Of the unworthiness of the ministers, which hinders
                            not the effect of the sacraments’.</p>
                    </note> He peoples the regions of
                    death. He is the choicest <pb n="558"/>instrument of the prince of darkness.
                    When he goes hence ‘hell from beneath is moved to meet him at his coming.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            14:9.</p>
                    </note> Nor can he sink into the bottomless pit<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 9:11;
                            20:1. Cf. also No. 32, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XII’, I.7 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    without dragging a multitude after him.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Next to these are the good-natured, good sort of men: who live an easy,
                    harmless life, neither troubling themselves with outward sin, nor with inward
                    holiness; men who are remarkable neither one way nor the other, neither for
                    religion nor irreligion; who are very regular both in public and private, but
                    don’t pretend to be any stricter than their neighbours. A minister of this kind
                    breaks not one, or a few only, of the least commandments of God, but all the
                    great and weighty branches of his law which relate to the power of godliness,
                    and all that require us to ‘pass the time of our sojourning in fear’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            1:17.</p>
                    </note> to ‘work out our salvation with fear and
                        trembling’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> to have our ‘loins always girt and our lights
                        burning’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 12:35.</p>
                    </note> to ‘strive or “agonize” to enter in at the
                    strait gate’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 13:24. The Greek imperative is ἀγωνίζεσθε, and Wesley is fond of
                            stressing the metaphor of ‘agonizing’ as a characteristic of Christian
                            moral discipline, since it had the double meaning of ‘struggle’ (as in
                            athletics) and also of ‘suffering’ (as in martyrdom). Cf. No. 17, ‘The
                            Circumcision of the Heart’, II.7 and n.</p>
                    </note> And he ‘teaches men
                        so’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> by the whole form of his life and the general
                    tenor of his preaching, which uniformly tends to soothe those in their pleasing
                    dream who imagine themselves Christians and are not; to persuade all who attend
                    upon his ministry to sleep on and take their rest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An ironic echo of Matt. 26:45
                            and Mark 14:41.</p>
                    </note> No marvel, therefore, if both he and they
                    that follow him wake together in everlasting burnings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 33:14. Another favourite
                            metaphor; cf. below, IV.13 and n.; and No. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                            XIII’, III.12, where Wesley links it with ‘everlasting glory’; see also
                            Downey, <hi rend="italic">Eighteenth Century Pulpit</hi>, p.
                        162.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. But above all these, in the highest rank of the enemies of the gospel of
                    Christ are they who openly and explicitly ‘judge the law’ itself, and ‘speak
                    evil of the law’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 4:11.</p>
                    </note> who teach men to break
                    (λῦσαι, to dissolve, to loose, to untie the obligation of) not one only—whether
                    of the least or of the greatest—but all the <pb n="559"/>commandments at a
                    stroke; who teach, without any cover, in so many words: ‘What did our Lord do
                    with the law? He abolished it.’ ‘There is but one duty, which is that of
                    believing.’ ‘All commands are unfit for our times.’ ‘From any demand of the law
                    no man is obliged now to go one step, to give away one farthing, to eat or omit
                    one morsel.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Again, a catena of quotations or paraphrases from the favourite dicta
                            of the antinomians running back to Tobias Crisp and John Saltmarsh
                            (targets of Richard Baxter’s), to the Moravians and even to schismatic
                            Methodists like James Wheatley, William Cudworth, <hi rend="italic">et
                                al.</hi> In the <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi> of 1744, the question
                            is asked: ‘<hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> 19. What is antinomianism? <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> The doctrine which makes void the law through
                            faith.’ This is followed by ‘<hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> 20. What are the
                            main pillars thereof?’ The answer lists six of them (No. 1, ‘That Christ
                            abolished the moral law’); one might compare that list with the
                            quotations Wesley has collected here. Cf. also below, Nos.
                        34-36.</p>
                    </note> This is indeed carrying matters with a high hand.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Num. 33:3
                            (especially in the Wycliffe translation); see also <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> (‘high’, 17<hi rend="italic">b</hi>).</p>
                    </note> This is
                    withstanding our Lord to the face, and telling him that he understood not how to
                    deliver the message on which he was sent. ‘O Lord, lay not this sin to their
                        charge!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 7:60.</p>
                    </note> ‘Father, forgive them; for they know not what they
                        do!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            23:34.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. The most surprising of all the circumstances that attend this strong
                    delusion is that they who are given up to it really believe that they honour
                    Christ by overthrowing his law, and that they are magnifying his office while
                    they are destroying his doctrine! Yea, they honour him just as Judas did when he
                    ‘said, Hail, Master, and kissed him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:49.</p>
                    </note> And he may as justly say to
                    every one of them, ‘Betrayest thou the Son of man with a kiss?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        22:48.</p>
                    </note> It is no other than betraying him with a kiss to talk of
                    his blood and take away his crown; to set light by any part of his law under
                    pretence of advancing his gospel. Nor indeed can anyone escape this charge who
                    preaches faith in any such manner as either directly or indirectly tends to set
                    aside any branch of obedience; who preaches Christ so as to disannul or weaken
                    in any wise the least of the commandments of God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. It is impossible indeed to have too high an esteem for ‘the faith of
                    God’s elect’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 1:1.</p>
                    </note> And we must all declare, ‘By grace ye are saved
                    through faith: …not of works, lest any man should boast.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:8-9.</p>
                    </note> We must
                    cry aloud to every penitent sinner, ‘Believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, and thou
                    shalt be saved.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 16:31.</p>
                    </note> But at the same time we must take care to let
                    all men know we esteem no faith but <pb n="560"/>that ‘which worketh by
                        love’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                            5:6. Cf. No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.6 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> and that we are not ‘saved by faith’ unless so far as we
                    are delivered from the power as well as the guilt of sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A bald claim of salvation from
                            the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> of sin. Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, I.6: ‘sin <hi rend="italic">remains</hi>
                            but no longer <hi rend="italic">reigns</hi>’, and n.</p>
                    </note> And when
                    we say, ‘Believe, and thou shalt be saved,’ we do not mean, ‘Believe, and thou
                    shalt step from sin to heaven, without any holiness coming between, faith
                    supplying the place of holiness;’ but, believe and thou shalt be holy; believe
                    in the Lord Jesus, and thou shalt have peace and power together. Thou shalt have
                    power from him in whom thou believest to trample sin under thy feet; power to
                    love the Lord thy God with all thy heart,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note> and to
                    serve him with all thy strength. Thou shalt have power ‘by patient continuance
                    in well-doing’ to ‘seek for glory and honour and immortality’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> Thou
                    shalt both ‘do and teach’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> all the commandments of God,
                    from the least even to the greatest. Thou shalt teach them by thy life as well
                    as thy words, and so ‘be called great in the kingdom of heaven’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. Whatever other way we teach to the kingdom of heaven, to glory,
                    honour, and immortality,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> be it called ‘the way of
                    faith’ or by any other name, it is in truth the way to destruction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            7:13.</p>
                    </note> It will not bring a man peace at the last.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Was this phrase
                            Wesley’s own coinage? If not, what was its common source with J. H.
                            Newman, who would use it for the close of his best known prayer in
                            ‘Wisdom and Innocence’, 1843: ‘Then in thy mercy, grant us a safe
                            lodging and a holy rest, and peace at the last’? See Newman, <hi rend="italic">Sermons Bearing on Subjects of the Day</hi> (London
                            and New York, Longmans, Green, and Co., 1918), p. 307.</p>
                    </note> For
                    thus saith the Lord, ‘Verily I say unto you, except your righteousness shall
                    exceed the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter
                    into the kingdom of heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">scribes</hi>, mentioned so often in the New Testament as
                    some of the most constant and vehement opposers of our Lord, were not
                    secretaries, or men employed in writing only, as that term might incline us to
                    believe. Neither were they <hi rend="italic">lawyers</hi>, in our common sense
                    of the word (although the word νομικοί is so rendered in our translation).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley here takes
                            the English law and English lawyers, as he knew them, as the popular
                            paradigm for νομικός. Actually, amongst Greek-speaking Jews, the term
                            would have denoted a man who was learned both in the written Torah and
                            the unwritten legal interpretations of <hi rend="italic">Halakah</hi>;
                            cf. <hi rend="italic">The Jewish Encyclopedia</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Their
                    employment had no affinity <pb n="561"/>at all to that of a lawyer among us.
                    They were conversant with the laws of God, and not with the laws of man. These
                    were their study: it was their proper and peculiar business to read and expound
                    the law and the prophets, particularly in the synagogues. They were the
                    ordinary, stated preachers among the Jews; so that if the sense of the original
                    word was attended to we might render it, the divines.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 104, ‘On Attending the
                            Church Service’, §12, where Wesley again equates ‘scribe’ with ‘divine’
                            (i.e., theologian) and then defines ‘divine’ as meaning a public teacher
                            (and, by inference, the term ‘divinity’ as the church’s public
                            teaching); cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</p>
                    </note> For these were the
                    men who made divinity their profession; and they were generally (as their name
                    literally imports) men of letters; men of the greatest account for learning that
                    were then in the Jewish nation.</p>
                <p n="2">2. The Pharisees were a very ancient sect or body of men among the Jews:
                    originally so called from the Hebrew word פרש, which signifies to ‘separate’ or
                        ‘divide’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The literal meaning of the Hebrew verb, <hi rend="italic">perush</hi>,
                            is to ‘disperse’ or ‘scatter’; in a figurative sense it meant to
                            separate. The Pharisees (<hi rend="italic">perushim</hi>, <hi rend="italic">perishaya</hi>) were those who had separated
                            themselves from those who did not strictly observe both Torah and <hi rend="italic">Halakah</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Not that they made any formal
                    separation from or division in the national church. They were only distinguished
                    from others by greater strictness of life, by more exactness of conversation.
                    For they were zealous of the law in the minutest points, paying tithes of mint,
                    anise, and cummin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 23:23.</p>
                    </note> And hence they were had
                    in honour of all the people and generally esteemed the holiest of men.</p>
                <p>Many of the scribes were of the sect of the Pharisees. Thus St. Paul himself, who
                    was educated for a scribe, first at the university of Tarsus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of
                            Our Own Spirit’, §14 and n.</p>
                    </note> and after that in Jerusalem at
                    the feet of Gamaliel<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 22:3.</p>
                    </note> (one of the most learned
                    scribes or doctors of the law that were then in the nation), declares of himself
                    before the council, ‘I am a Pharisee, the son of a Pharisee;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                23:6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and before King Agrippa, ‘after the straitest
                    sect of our religion I lived a Pharisee.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Acts] 26:5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And the
                    whole body of the scribes generally esteemed and acted in concert with the
                    Pharisees. Hence we find our Saviour so frequently coupling them together, as
                    coming in many respects under the same consideration. In this place they seem to
                    be mentioned together <pb n="562"/>as the most eminent professors of religion:
                    the former of whom were accounted the wisest, the latter the holiest of men.</p>
                <p n="3">3. What ‘the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees’ really was it is
                    not difficult to determine. Our Lord has preserved an authentic account which
                    one of them gave of himself. And he is clear and full in describing his own
                    righteousness, and cannot be supposed to have omitted any part of it. He ‘went
                    up’ indeed ‘into the temple to pray’, but was so intent upon his own virtues
                    that he forgot the design upon which he came.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 18:10; this parable was one of
                            Wesley’s favourites in the Revival’s early days. He used it thirteen
                            times between 1739-47, but only five times thereafter for a total of
                            eighteen times in all. For a sample of conventional wisdom about the
                            Pharisees in Wesley’s time, see Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>: ‘a celebrated sect among the ancient
                            Jews…separated from the rest by the austerity of their life, by their
                            professing a greater degree of holiness…’.</p>
                    </note> For ’tis
                    remarkable he does not properly pray at all. He only tells God how wise and good
                    he was. ‘God, I thank thee that I am not as other men are, extortioners, unjust,
                    adulterers; or even as this publican. I fast twice in the week: I give tithes of
                    all that I possess.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:11-12.</p>
                    </note> His righteousness
                    therefore consisted of three parts: first, saith he, ‘I am not as other men
                    are.’ I am not an ‘extortioner’, not ‘unjust’, not an ‘adulterer’; not ‘even as
                    this publican’. Secondly, ‘I fast twice in the week;’ and thirdly, ‘give tithes
                    of all that I possess.’</p>
                <p>‘I am not as other men are.’ This is not a small point. It is not every man that
                    can say this. It is as if he had said, I do not suffer myself to be carried away
                    by that great torrent, custom.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A favourite phrase; cf. IV.7 and IV. 12, below. Cf.
                            also Nos. 52, <hi rend="italic">The Reformation of Manners</hi>, I.6;
                            88, ‘On Dress’, §21; and 94, ‘On Family Religion’, III.18. In No. 97,
                            ‘On Obedience to Pastors’, III.11, Wesley defines its synonym, ‘fashion’
                            as ‘that tyrant of fools’; in No. 108, ‘On Riches’, II.3, he calls it
                            ‘the mistress of fools’. See also his letter to Miss March, June 29,
                            1767: ‘Fashion and custom are nothing to you: you have a more excellent
                            rule.’ Also his letter to John Fletcher, Mar. 20, 1786; to Mary Bishop,
                            Nov. 22, 1769. The idea is also found in Law’s <hi rend="italic">Serious
                                Call</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.170): ‘the vogue and
                            fashion of the world by which we have been carried away as in a
                            torrent’. Cf. also, Edward Stillingfleet, Sermon II, in <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi> (1696), I.66-67:
                            ‘custom of the world…a torrent of wickedness’; James Garden, <hi rend="italic">Comparative Theology</hi> (1700), p. 70: ‘that vulgar
                            maxim: Custom is a second nature’—which Bartlett, <hi rend="italic">Familiar Quotations</hi>, attributes to Caesar Augustus, <hi rend="italic">Rules for the Preservation of Health</hi>, 18. Cf.
                            also Guillaume de Salluste, Seigneur du Bartas (1544-90), <hi rend="italic">Divine Weekes and Workes, Second Week, Third Day, Part
                                2</hi>: ‘Only that he may conform/To tyrant custom.’ So also
                            Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>, I. iii. 231: ‘The tyrant
                            custom…’. Addison made ‘custom’ the topic of an essay for the <hi rend="italic">Spectator</hi>; cf. No. 447, Aug. 2, 1712 (see No. 81,
                            ‘In What Sense we are to Leave the World’, §17 and n.). See also No. 31,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, II.5, where Wesley uses the phrase, ‘the
                            torrent of example’.</p>
                    </note> I live not by custom but by reason; not
                    by the examples of men but the word <pb n="563"/>of God. ‘I am not an
                    extortioner, not unjust, not an adulterer;’ however common these sins are, even
                    among those who are called the people of God (extortion, in particular, a kind
                    of legal injustice, not punishable by any human law, the making gain of
                    another’s ignorance or necessity, having filled every corner of the land); ‘nor
                    even as this publican’, not guilty of any open or presumptuous sin, not an
                    outward sinner, but a fair, honest man, of blameless life and conversation.</p>
                <p n="4">4. ‘I fast twice in the week.’ There is more implied in this than we may at
                    first be sensible of. All the stricter Pharisees observed the weekly fasts,
                    namely, every Monday and Thursday. On the former day they fasted in memory of
                    Moses receiving on that day (as their tradition taught) the two tables of stone
                    written by the finger of God;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 31:18; Deut. 9:10.</p>
                    </note> on the
                    latter in memory of his casting them out of his hand when he saw the people
                    dancing round the golden calf.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 32:19; Deut. 9:17.</p>
                    </note> On these days
                    they took no sustenance at all till three in the afternoon, the hour at which
                    they began to offer up the evening sacrifice in the temple. Till that hour it
                    was their custom to remain in the temple—in some of the corners, apartments, or
                    courts thereof—that they might be ready to assist at all the sacrifices and to
                    join in all the public prayers. The time between they were accustomed to employ
                    partly in private addresses to God, partly in searching the Scriptures, in
                    reading the law and the prophets, and in meditating thereon. Thus much is
                    implied in, ‘I fast twice in the week’, the second branch of the righteousness
                    of a Pharisee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>,
                        ‘Pharisees’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘I give tithes of all that I possess.’ This the Pharisees did with the
                    utmost exactness. They would not except the most inconsiderable thing, no, not
                    mint, anise, or cummin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 23:23.</p>
                    </note> They would not keep
                    back the least part of what they believed properly to belong to God, but gave a
                    full tenth of their whole substance yearly, and of all their increase,
                    whatsoever it was.</p>
                <p>Yea, the stricter Pharisees (as has been often observed by those who are versed
                    in the ancient Jewish writings), not content with giving one tenth of their
                    substance to God in his priests and Levites, gave another tenth to God in the
                    poor, and that continually. They gave the same proportion of all they had in
                    alms <pb n="564"/>as they were accustomed to give in tithes. And this likewise
                    they adjusted with the utmost exactness, that they might not keep back any part,
                    but might fully render unto God the things which were God’s,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 22:21; Mark
                            12:17.</p>
                    </note> as they accounted this to be. So that upon the whole
                    they gave away from year to year an entire fifth of all that they possessed.</p>
                <p n="6">6. This was ‘the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees’: a
                    righteousness which in many respects went far beyond the conception which many
                    have been accustomed to entertain concerning it. But perhaps it will be said it
                    was all false and feigned; for they were all a company of hypocrites. Some of
                    them doubtless were; men who had really no religion at all, no fear of God, or
                    desire to please him; who had no concern for the honour that cometh of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John
                            5:44.</p>
                    </note> but only for the praise of men. And these are they whom
                    our Lord so severely condemns, so sharply reproves, on many occasions. But we
                    must not suppose, because many Pharisees were hypocrites, therefore all were so.
                    Nor indeed is hypocrisy by any means essential to the character of a Pharisee.
                    This is not the distinguishing mark of their sect. It is rather this (according
                    to our Lord’s account)—they ‘trusted in themselves that they were righteous, and
                    despised others’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:9.</p>
                    </note> This is their genuine badge.
                    But the Pharisee of this kind cannot be a hypocrite. He must be, in the common
                    sense, sincere; otherwise he could not ‘trust in himself that he is righteous’.
                    The man who was here commending himself to God unquestionably thought himself
                    righteous. Consequently, he was no hypocrite—he was not conscious to himself of
                    any insincerity. He now spoke to God just what he thought, namely, that he was
                    abundantly better than other men.</p>
                <p>But the example of St. Paul, were there no other, is sufficient to put this out
                    of all question. He could not only say, when he was a Christian, ‘Herein do I
                    exercise myself, to have always a conscience void of offence toward God and
                    toward men;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 24:16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> but even concerning
                    the time when he was a Pharisee, ‘Men and brethren, I have lived in all good
                    conscience before God until this day.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Acts] 23:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> He was
                    therefore sincere when he was a Pharisee, as well as <pb n="565"/>when he was a
                    Christian. He was no more an hypocrite when he persecuted the church than when
                    he preached the faith which once he persecuted. Let this then be added to ‘the
                    righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees’—a sincere belief that they are
                    righteous, and in all things ‘doing God service’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 16:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. And yet, ‘Except your righteousness’, saith our Lord, ‘shall exceed the
                    righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter into the
                    kingdom of heaven.’ A solemn and weighty declaration! And which it behoves all
                    who are called by the name of Christ seriously and deeply to consider. But
                    before we inquire how our righteousness may exceed theirs, let us examine
                    whether at present we come up to it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Blackall had devoted two entire discourses to this
                            question (XXII-XXIII, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.212-18), and his
                            answer is summed up (p. 216): ‘This was [the Pharisees’] righteousness.
                            Some things they did which, as to the matter of them, were good, but
                            then they spoiled them by a wrong intention…; they sought their own
                            glory thereby, not the glory of God…. [They had] no design…to recommend
                            themselves to his grace and favour…. That our righteousness may exceed
                            theirs, it is necessary not only that we do the thing that is good, but
                            that we do it with a right intention; i.e., that we design it to the
                            glory of God, and that we do it out of a principle of obedience to the
                            will of God….’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>First, a Pharisee was ‘not as other men are’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:11.</p>
                    </note> In externals he was
                    singularly good. Are we so? Do we dare to be singular at all?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 31, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, XI’, III.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> Do we not rather swim with the
                    stream? Do we not many times dispense with religion and reason together because
                    we would not ‘look particular’? Are we not often more afraid of being out of the
                        fashion<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            above, IV.3 and n.</p>
                    </note> than of being out of the way of salvation?
                    Have we courage to stem the tide? To run counter to the world? ‘To obey God
                    rather than man’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 5:29.</p>
                    </note> Otherwise the Pharisee
                    leaves us behind at the very first step. ’Tis well if we overtake him any
                    more.</p>
                <p>But to come closer. Can we use his first plea with God, which is in substance, ‘I
                    do no harm.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            IV.11, below; and No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, II.4 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> I live in no outward sin. I do nothing for which my own heart
                    condemns me.’ Do you not? Are you sure of that? Do you live in no practice for
                    which your own heart condemns you? If you are not an adulterer, if you are not
                    unchaste either in word or deed, are you not unjust? The grand measure of
                    justice, as well as of mercy, is, Do unto others as thou wouldst they should do
                    unto thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 7:12; Luke 6:31.</p>
                    </note> Do you walk by this rule? Do you <pb n="566"/>never do unto any what you would not they should do unto you? Nay,
                    are you not grossly unjust? Are you not an extortioner? Do you not make a gain
                    of anyone’s ignorance or necessity? Neither in buying nor selling? Suppose you
                    are engaged in trade, do you demand, do you receive, no more than the real value
                    of what you sell? Do you demand, do you receive, no more of the ignorant than of
                    the knowing; of a little child than of an experienced trader? If you do, why
                    does not your heart condemn you? You are a barefaced extortioner. Do you demand
                    no more than the usual price of the goods of any who is in pressing want? Who
                    must have, and that without delay, the things which you only can furnish him
                    with? If you do, this also is flat extortion. Indeed you do not come up to the
                    righteousness of a Pharisee.</p>
                <p n="8">8. A Pharisee, secondly (to express his sense in our common way), used all
                    the means of grace. As he fasted <hi rend="italic">often</hi> and <hi rend="italic">much</hi>, ‘twice in every week’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:12; cf. Matt.
                            9:14.</p>
                    </note> so he attended all the sacrifices. He was constant in
                    public and private prayer, and in reading and hearing the Scriptures. Do you go
                    as far as this? Do you fast <hi rend="italic">much</hi> and <hi rend="italic">often</hi>? Twice in the week? I fear not! Once, at least: ‘On all Fridays
                    in the year.’ (So our church clearly and peremptorily enjoins all her members to
                    do, to observe all these as well as the vigils and the forty days of Lent as
                    ‘days of fasting, or abstinence’.)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, ‘Tables and Rules’: ‘All the Fridays in the
                            year except Christmas Day and The Epiphany, or any Friday which may
                            intervene between these feasts.’</p>
                    </note> Do you fast twice in the
                    year? I am afraid some among us cannot plead even this! Do you neglect no
                    opportunity of attending and partaking of the Christian sacrifice? How many are
                    they who call themselves Christians and yet are utterly regardless of it; yet do
                    not eat of that bread or drink of that cup for months, perhaps years together?
                    Do you every day either hear the Scriptures or read them and meditate thereon?
                    Do you join in prayer with the great congregation?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 35:18; also
                        22:25.</p>
                    </note> Daily, if you have opportunity? If not, whenever you can,
                    particularly on that day which you ‘remember to keep it holy’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:8.</p>
                    </note> Do you
                    strive to <hi rend="italic">make</hi> opportunities? Are you ‘glad when they say
                    unto you, we will go into the house of the Lord’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 122:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    Are you zealous of, and diligent in, private prayer? Do you suffer no day to
                    pass without it? Rather are not some of you so far from spending therein (with
                    the Pharisee) several hours in one day that <pb n="567"/>you think one hour full
                    enough, if not too much? Do you spend an hour in a day, or in a week, in praying
                    to your Father which is in secret?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 6:6, 18.</p>
                    </note> Yea, an hour in a
                    month? Have you spent one hour together in private prayer ever since you was
                    born? Ah, poor Christian! Shall not the Pharisee rise up in the judgment against
                    thee and condemn thee?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 12:41, 42; Luke 11:31, 32.</p>
                    </note> His
                    righteousness is as far above thine as the heaven is above the earth.</p>
                <p n="9">9. The Pharisee, thirdly, ‘paid tithes’ and gave alms ‘of all that he
                    possessed’. And in how ample a manner! So that he was (as we phrase it) ‘a man
                    that did much good’. Do we come up to him here? Which of us is so abundant as he
                    was in good works? Which of us gives a fifth of all his substance to God? Both
                    of the principal and of the increase? Who of us out of (suppose) an hundred
                    pounds a year, gives twenty to God and the poor; out of fifty, ten: and so in a
                    larger or a smaller proportion? When shall our righteousness, in using all the
                    means of grace, in attending all the ordinances of God, in avoiding evil and
                    doing good, equal at least the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees?</p>
                <p n="10">10. Although if it only equalled theirs what would that profit? ‘For
                    verily I say unto you, except your righteousness shall exceed the righteousness
                    of the scribes and Pharisees, ye shall in no case enter into the kingdom of
                    heaven.’ But how can it exceed theirs? Wherein does the righteousness of a
                    Christian exceed that of a scribe or Pharisee?</p>
                <p>Christian righteousness exceeds theirs, first, in the extent of it. Most of the
                    Pharisees, though they were rigorously exact in many things, yet were emboldened
                    by the traditions of the elders to dispense with others of equal importance.
                    Thus they were extremely punctual in keeping the fourth commandment—they would
                    not even ‘rub an ear of corn’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 6:1.</p>
                    </note> on the sabbath day—but not
                    at all in keeping the third, making little account of light, or even false
                    swearing. So that their righteousness was partial—whereas the righteousness of a
                    real Christian is universal. He does not observe one, or some parts, of the law
                    of God, and neglect the rest; but keeps all his commandments, loves them all,
                    values them above gold or precious stones.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 17:4; 18:16.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. It may be indeed that some of the scribes and Pharisees <pb n="568"/>endeavoured to keep all the commandments, and consequently were, as touching
                    the righteousness of the law, that is, according to the letter of it,
                        blameless.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:6.</p>
                    </note> But still the righteousness of a Christian
                    exceeds all this righteousness of a scribe or Pharisee by fulfilling the spirit
                    as well as the letter of the law, by inward as well as outward obedience. In
                    this, in the spirituality of it, it admits of no comparison. This is the point
                    which our Lord has so largely proved in the whole tenor of this discourse. Their
                    righteousness was external only; Christian righteousness is in the inner man.
                    The Pharisee ‘cleansed the outside of the cup and the platter’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            23:25; Luke 11:39.</p>
                    </note> the Christian is clean within. The
                    Pharisee laboured to present God with a good life; the Christian with a holy
                    heart. The one shook off the leaves, perhaps the fruits of sin; the other ‘lays
                    the axe to the root’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 3:9.</p>
                    </note> as not being content with
                    the outward form of godliness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 3:5.</p>
                    </note> how exact soever it be,
                    unless the life, the spirit, the power of God unto salvation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> be
                    felt in the inmost soul.</p>
                <p>Thus to do no harm, to do good, to attend the ordinances of God (the
                    righteousness of a Pharisee)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">But also the righteousness of the <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi> of the Methodist Societies (as also above, IV.7;
                            and No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, II.4 and n.). What were the
                            Methodists supposed to make of these denigrations of their disciplinary
                            rules? This much at least: Wesley himself was clear of any charge of
                            ‘mere moralism’ and wanted none of it for his people.</p>
                    </note> are all
                    external; whereas, on the contrary, poverty of spirit, mourning, meekness,
                    hunger and thirst after righteousness, the love of our neighbour, and purity of
                        heart<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 5:3-8.</p>
                    </note> (the righteousness of a Christian) are all
                    internal. And even peacemaking (or doing good) and suffering for righteousness’
                        sake,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 5:9-10.</p>
                    </note> stand entitled to the blessings annexed to them
                    only as they imply these inward dispositions, as they spring from, exercise, and
                    confirm them. So that whereas the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees was
                    external only, it may be said in some sense that the righteousness of a
                    Christian is internal only—all his actions and sufferings being as nothing in
                    themselves, being estimated before God only by the tempers from which they
                    spring.</p>
                <p n="12">12. Whosoever therefore thou art who bearest the holy and <pb n="569"/>venerable name of a Christian, see, first, that thy righteousness fall not
                    short of the righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees. Be not thou ‘as other
                    men are’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            18:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    <lg>
                        <l>Dare to stand alone, to be</l>
                        <l>Against example, singularly good!</l>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Apparently a conflation of two lines of verse from Samuel Wesley,
                                Jun.: the first from ‘The Battle of the Sexes’, st. xxxv, l. 3
                                (‘Against example resolutely good’), in <hi rend="italic">Poems on
                                    Several Occasions</hi> (1736; hereafter cited as <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>), p. 38; the second from ‘To the Memory
                                of the Rt. Rev. Francis Gastrell’, l. 226 (‘Adverse against a world,
                                and singly good’), <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 135. But see
                                also, Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Regained</hi>, iii.57 (‘His
                                lot who dares be singularly good’). Cf. No. 88, ‘On Dress’,
                            §23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </lg>
                </p>
                <p>If thou ‘follow a multitude’ at all it must be ‘to do evil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 23:2.</p>
                    </note> Let
                    not custom or fashion<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, IV.3 and n.</p>
                    </note> be thy guide, but
                    reason and religion. The practice of others is nothing to thee: ‘Every man must
                    give an account of himself to God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 14:12.</p>
                    </note> Indeed if thou canst
                    save the soul of another, do; but at least save one, thy own. Walk not in the
                    path of death because it is broad, and many walk therein.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:13.</p>
                    </note>
                    Nay, by this very token thou mayst know it. Is the way wherein thou now walkest
                    a broad, well-frequented, fashionable way? Then it infallibly leads to
                    destruction. O be not thou ‘damned for company’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark Le Pla, <hi rend="italic">A Paraphrase on the Song of the Three Children</hi>,
                                <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, st. 42:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>You who from vice, as from infection fly,</l>
                            <l>And care not to be damned for company.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">See also Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection
                                of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>, II.132.</p>
                    </note>—‘cease from
                        evil’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> fly from sin as from the face of a serpent.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev.
                            12:14.</p>
                    </note> At least, do no harm. ‘He that committeth sin is of
                    the devil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 3:8.</p>
                    </note> Be not thou found in that number. Touching outward
                    sins, surely the grace of God is even now sufficient for thee. ‘Herein’ at least
                    ‘exercise thyself to have a conscience void of offence toward God and toward
                        men.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 24:16.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Secondly, let not thy righteousness fall short of theirs with regard to the
                    ordinances of God. If thy labour or bodily strength will not allow of thy
                    fasting ‘twice in the week’, however, deal faithfully with thy own soul, and
                    fast as often as thy strength will <pb n="570"/>permit. Omit no public, no
                    private opportunity of pouring out thy soul in prayer. Neglect no occasion of
                    eating that bread and drinking that cup which is the communion of the body and
                    blood of Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 11:28; 10:16.</p>
                    </note> Be diligent in
                    searching the Scriptures: read as thou mayst, and meditate therein day and
                    night. Rejoice to embrace every opportunity of hearing ‘the word of
                        reconciliation’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> declared by the
                    ‘ambassadors of Christ, the stewards of the mysteries of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 4:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    In using all the means of grace, in a constant and careful attendance on every
                    ordinance of God, live up to (at least, till thou canst go beyond) ‘the
                    righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees’.</p>
                <p>Thirdly, fall not short of a Pharisee in doing good. Give alms of all thou dost
                    possess. Is any hungry? Feed him. Is he athirst? Give him drink. Naked? Cover
                    him with a garment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 25:35-38.</p>
                    </note> If thou hast this
                    world’s goods, do not limit thy beneficence to a scanty proportion. Be merciful
                    to the uttermost of thy power. Why not, even as this Pharisee? ‘Now make thyself
                    friends’, while the time is, ‘of the mammon of unrighteousness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An anticipation
                            of the third of Wesley’s three rules for ‘the use of money’; cf. below,
                            Nos. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §§23-28, and 50, ‘The Use of
                            Money’, III.1-7 and n.</p>
                    </note> that when thou failest’, when this
                    earthly tabernacle is dissolved, ‘they may receive thee into everlasting
                        habitations.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. But rest not here. Let thy ‘righteousness exceed the righteousness of
                    the scribes and Pharisees’. Be not thou content to ‘keep the whole law, and
                    offend in one point’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘Hold thou fast all his
                    commandments, and all false ways do thou utterly abhor.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 119:128
                        (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Do all the things whatsoever he hath commanded, and that
                    with all thy might. Thou canst do all things through Christ strengthening
                        thee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 4:13.</p>
                    </note> though without him thou canst do nothing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John
                            15:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>Above all, let thy righteousness exceed theirs in the purity and spirituality of
                    it. What is the exactest form of religion to thee? The most perfect outside
                    righteousness? Go thou higher and deeper <pb n="571"/>than all this. Let thy
                    religion be the religion of the heart.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. JWJ, Aug. 12, 1771: ‘The very thing which
                            Mr. Stinstra calls fanaticism is no other than heart-religion—in other
                            words, “righteousness and peace and joy in the Holy Ghost”’; cf. John
                            Stinstra, <hi rend="italic">A Pastoral Letter Against Fanaticism…</hi>
                            (1753). See also Wesley’s letter to James Knox, May 30, 1765: ‘You saw
                            what heart-religion meant, and the gate of it, justification…. True
                            religion is not a negative or an external thing, but the life of God in
                            the soul of man [Scougal], the image of God stamped upon the
                            heart.’</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, Wesley’s Preface, §6, (p.
                            106); and Nos. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6; 16, ‘The Means of
                            Grace’, I.5; 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.12; 36, ‘The Law
                            Established through Faith, II’, I.5; 37, ‘The Nature of Enthusiasm’,
                            §§1, 10; 102, ‘Of Former Times’, §11. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">Remarks
                                on a Defence of…Aspasio Vindicated</hi>: ‘the grand points—the
                            religion of the heart and salvation by faith’. See also Harald Höffding,
                                <hi rend="italic">A History of Modern Philosophy</hi>,
                        I.252.</p>
                    </note> Be thou poor in spirit; little and base and mean and vile
                    in thy own eyes; amazed and humbled to the dust at the love of God which is in
                    Christ Jesus thy Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:39.</p>
                    </note> Be serious: let the whole
                    stream of thy thoughts, words, and works, be such as flows from the deepest
                    conviction that thou standest on the edge of the great gulf, thou and all the
                    children of men, just ready to drop in, either into everlasting glory, or
                    everlasting burnings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 33:14; cf. Jonathan Edwards, ‘Sinners in
                            the Hands of an Angry God’ (ten years earlier), <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1843), IV.318-19. For the phrase, ‘everlasting glory’,
                            cf. BCP, Burial (481), as well as the Collect for St. Peter’s Day (312).
                            It occurs frequently in Kempis, <hi rend="italic">Imitation</hi>, e.g.,
                            IV. iii. 2. Cf. above, III.6 and n.; and Nos. 26, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                            VI’, III.8; and 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.12.</p>
                    </note> Be
                    meek: let thy soul be filled with mildness, gentleness, patience, long-suffering
                    toward all men; at the same time that all which is in thee is athirst for God,
                    the living God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 42:2.</p>
                    </note> longing to awake up after
                    his likeness, and to be satisfied with it. Be thou a lover of God and of all
                    mankind. In this spirit do and suffer all things. Thus ‘exceed the righteousness
                    of the scribes and Pharisees’, and thou shalt be ‘called great in the kingdom of
                    heaven’.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>