<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 52: The Reformation of Manners</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 52: The Reformation of Manners</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="300" to="323"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:300"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>One of the prime concerns of the religious societies introduced into Restoration
                    England by Dr. Anthony Horneck and others had been ‘the reformation of
                    manners’—the reinforcement of police control of public vice, drunkenness,
                    prostitution, etc., with assistance from concerned citizens, together with
                    active aid programmes in relief of the ill, the destitute, and the unemployed
                    (rf. Josiah Woodward, <hi rend="italic">An Account of the Societies for the
                        Reformation of Manners, in London, Westminster, and other parts of the
                        Kingdom…against prophaneness and debauchery, for the effecting a National
                        Reformation…</hi> [1699]). This project was underwritten by a network of
                    neighbourhood ‘societies’, first organized in 1677 and then reorganized in 1691.
                    The programmes of their annual meetings regularly included special sermons by
                    eminent ministers; cf. the one hundred and twenty-eight sermons by William Wake,
                    Isaac Watts, John Tillotson, Samuel Chandler, Joseph Burroughs, and others,
                    listed in <hi rend="italic">Early Nonconformity, 1566-1800: A Catalogue of Books
                        in Dr. Williams’ Library, London</hi> (Boston, Mass., G. K. Hall and Co.,
                    1968). And, on February 13, 1698, the sermon had been preached (in the morning
                    at St. James’s, Westminster, and in the afternoon in St. Bride’s, London) by the
                    rector of Epworth parish, Lincolnshire, the Revd. Samuel Wesley, Sen. It was
                    later published in <hi rend="italic">The Methodist Magazine</hi> (1814), pp.
                    648-65, 727-36, and should be compared with this present sermon, sixty-eight
                    years later, for their notable similarity.</p>
                <p>This movement of social reform seems to have ceased functioning by 1730 but was
                    then revived in 1757 under the leadership of one ‘W. Welsh’ (see JWJ, February
                    2, 1766), and in 1763 John Wesley was invited to preach the ‘Annual Sermon’.
                    This took place on January 30, not at one of the fashionable city churches, but
                    in Wesley’s own ‘Chapel in West Street, Seven Dials’, for a society whose one
                    hundred and sixty members numbered seventy Dissenters and only twenty ‘regular’
                    Anglicans.</p>
                <p>This is another of Wesley’s sermons <hi rend="italic">ad aulam</hi> (‘formal), in
                    a ‘plain’ but ‘polite’ style—and, it might be noted, on the same text as his
                    father <pb n="02:301"/>had used before him. In its substance it is one of the
                    least evangelical of any of Wesley’s sermons after 1738; its definition of ‘the
                    church’ in §2 sounds more ‘congregational’ than ‘connexional’; its conclusions
                    are moralistic and hortatory. Its descriptions of public vice and crime in
                    mid-century London are confirmed, in part at least, by contemporary observers
                    (e.g., Boswell, Hogarth, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>) and by George Rudé, <hi
                        rend="italic">Hanoverian London, 1714-1808</hi>, ch. 5, and Dorothy George,
                        <hi rend="italic">London Life in the Eighteenth Century</hi>.</p>
                <p>It was printed as a fairly expensive pamphlet (‘sixpence’) in 1763, and was then
                    inserted into the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771), Vol. IV; its third
                    edition in Wesley’s lifetime is dated 1778. For its publishing history and
                    variant readings, see Appendix, Vol. 4 in this edn.; and <hi rend="italic"
                        >Bibliog</hi>, No. 254.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Reformation of Manners</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Psalm 94:16</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Who will rise up with me against the wicked?</hi><note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">BCP,
                        Psalter.</p></note>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <p>1. In all ages men who neither feared God nor regarded man<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 18:2.</p></note> have
                    combined together and formed confederacies to carry on the works of
                        darkness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            13:12; Eph. 5:11.</p></note> And herein they have shown themselves wise
                    in their generation;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Luke 16:18, which is also the text for No. 147,
                            ‘Wiser than the Children of Light’ (one of the early MS
                        sermons).</p></note> for by this means they more effectually promoted the
                    kingdom of their father the devil<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See John 8:44.</p></note> than otherwise they could
                    have done. On the other hand, men who did fear God and desire the happiness of
                    their fellow-creatures have in every age found it needful to join together in
                    order to oppose the works of darkness, to spread the knowledge of God their
                    Saviour, and to promote his kingdom upon earth. Indeed he himself has instructed
                    them so to do. From the time that men were upon the earth he hath taught them to
                    join together in his service, and has united them in one body by one
                        spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Eph. 4:4.</p></note> And for this very end he <pb n="02:302"/>has joined
                    them together, ‘that he might destroy the works of the devil’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:8.</p></note> first in
                    them that are already united, and by them in all that are round about them.</p>
                <p>2. This is the original design of the church of Christ. It is a body of men
                    compacted together in order, first, to save each his own soul, then to assist
                    each other in working out their salvation, and afterwards, as far as in them
                    lies, to save all men from present and future misery, to overturn the kingdom of
                    Satan, and set up the kingdom of Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. this definition of ‘the church’ with those
                            in No. 74, ‘Of the Church’; also No. 92, ‘On Zeal’, II.5; <hi
                                rend="italic">Popery Calmly Considered</hi>, I.6; <hi rend="italic"
                                >Α Collection of Forms of Prayer</hi> (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Bibliog</hi>, No. 1; Vol. 8 of this edn.); his letter to Gilbert
                            Joyce, May 22, 1750; his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 16:18,
                            and on Eph. 3:10 (where the church is defined as ‘the theatre of divine
                            wisdom’).</p></note> And this ought to be the continued care and
                    endeavour of every member of his church. Otherwise he is not worthy to be called
                    a member thereof, as he is not a living member of Christ.</p>
                <p>3. Accordingly this ought to be the constant care and endeavour of all those who
                    are united together in these kingdoms, and are commonly called ‘the Church of
                    England’. They are united together for this very end, to oppose the devil and
                    all his works, and to wage war against the world and the flesh, his constant and
                    faithful allies. But do they in fact answer the end of their union? Are all who
                    style themselves ‘members of the Church of England’ heartily engaged in opposing
                    the works of the devil and fighting against the world and the flesh? Alas, we
                    cannot say this. So far from it that a great part—I fear, the greater part of
                    them—are themselves ‘the world’, the people that know not God to any saving
                    purpose; are indulging day by day instead of ‘mortifying the flesh, with its
                    affections and desires’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:13; Gal. 5:24 (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Notes</hi>).</p></note> and doing themselves those works of the
                        devil<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:8.</p></note> which they are peculiarly engaged to destroy.</p>
                <p>4. There is therefore still need, even in this ‘Christian country’ (as we <hi
                        rend="italic">courteously</hi> style Great Britain)<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. this sarcastic touch with
                            the suggestion in No. 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, §8,
                            that ‘a little well-placed raillery will pierce deeper than solid
                            argument, [especially] when we have to do with those who are strangers
                            to religion.’</p></note> yea, in this ‘Christian church’ (if we may give
                    that title to the bulk of our nation) of some to ‘rise up against the wicked’,
                    and join together ‘against the evil-doers’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12"
                        n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 94:16 (BCP).</p></note> Nay, there was
                    never more need than there is at this <pb n="02:303"/>day for ‘them that fear
                    the Lord’ to ‘speak often together’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Mal. 3:16.</p></note> on this very head—how
                    they may ‘lift up a standard against’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 59:19.</p></note> the iniquity which
                    overflows the land. There is abundant cause for all the servants of God to join
                    together against the works of the devil with united hearts and counsels and
                    endeavours, to make a stand for God, and to repress, as much as in them lies,
                    these ‘floods of ungodliness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Pss. 18:3 (BCP), and 18:4 (AV); see also 2 Sam.
                            22:5.</p></note></p>
                <p>5. For this end a few persons in London, towards the close of the last century,
                    united together, and after a while were termed ‘The Society for Reformation of
                        Manners’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Not one but many, cf. Josiah Woodward, <hi rend="italic">Account of
                                the…Societies…</hi>. Queen Mary’s Letter of Approval is dated July
                            9, 1691; King William’s Charge to the Societies was dated Feb. 24, 1697.
                            The original society was composed of ‘Members of Parliament, Justices of
                            the Peace, and considerable citizens of London’ (p. 10). There was ‘a
                            second society of tradesmen and others’ (p. 11), and ‘a third society of
                            constables…’ (pp. 11-12). ‘A fourth…is of supporters of the magistrates’
                            (pp. 12-13). ‘There are eight other related and mixed bodies of
                            housekeepers and officers in the several quarters of London,
                            Westminster, and Southwark.’ (pp. 14-15). ‘Nine and thirty religious
                            societies in London, Westminster, and other parts of the nation’ (p.
                            15). Cf. Robert South’s comment about the religious societies in <hi
                                rend="italic">Sermons Preached Upon Several Occasions</hi> (1st
                            edn., 1737; Philadelphia, Sorin and Ball, 1844), II.105: ‘Their leverage
                            of influence is the sense of shame that decent people have in the face
                            of the disapproval of polite society.’</p></note> And incredible good
                    was done by them for near forty years. But then, most of the original members
                    being gone to their reward, those who succeeded them grew faint in their mind,
                    and departed from the work; so that a few years ago the Society ceased, nor did
                    any of the kind remain in the kingdom.</p>
                <p>6. It is a society of the same nature which has been lately formed. I purpose to
                    show, first, the <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> of their design, and the <hi
                        rend="italic">steps</hi> they have hitherto taken; (2), the <hi
                        rend="italic">excellency</hi> of it, with the various <hi rend="italic"
                        >objections</hi> which have been raised against it; (3), <hi rend="italic"
                        >what manner of men</hi> they ought to be who engage in such a design; and
                    (4), with what <hi rend="italic">spirit</hi> and in what <hi rend="italic"
                        >manner</hi> they should proceed in the prosecution of it. I shall conclude
                    with an <hi rend="italic">application</hi> both to them and to all that fear
                    God.</p>
            </div>
            <div><p>I. 1. I am, first, to show the <hi rend="italic">nature</hi> of their design,
                    and the <hi rend="italic">steps</hi> they have hitherto taken.</p>
                <p>It was on a Lord’s Day in August 1757 that in a small company who were met for
                    prayer and religious conversation mention was made of the gross and open
                    profanation of that sacred day, by <pb n="02:304"/>persons buying and selling,
                    keeping open shop, tippling in alehouses, and standing or sitting in the
                    streets, roads, or fields, vending their wares as on common days; especially in
                        Moorfields,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >A large open moor north of the walled city, split by the new ‘City
                            Road’ which led out from the Moorgate (opened in 1415). It was divided
                            into ‘Moorfields’, ‘Middle Moorfields’ (later ‘Finsbury Pavement’), and
                            ‘Upper Moorfields’. In Upper Moorfields there were the Royal Artillery
                            grounds, Bunhill Fields, the Quaker Burying Ground, and, after 1739,
                            Wesley’s London headquarters (in the Foundery). It was a favourite
                            resort for the London poor and ‘middling sort’, and thus a happy hunting
                            ground for mountebanks and petty criminals. It was also the site of many
                            of the great outdoor preaching services held by the Wesleys and
                            Whitefield.</p></note> which was then full of them every Sunday, from
                    one end to the other. It was considered what method could be taken to redress
                    these grievances. And it was agreed that six of them should in the morning wait
                    upon Sir John Fielding<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The blind half-brother and successor to Henry
                            Fielding (author of <hi rend="italic">Tom Jones</hi>) as the chief
                            magistrate at the Bow Street Courts. A man of ‘turbulent disposition’,
                            he was zealous in his war on crime and criminals and interested in
                            various philanthropic causes. William Cole said of him, in <hi
                                rend="italic">The Cambridge Chronicle</hi>, June 7, 1766, that
                            ‘though stark blind and of no great reputation for strict integrity, he
                            was generally esteemed as a very useful member of society.’</p></note>
                    for instruction. They did so. He approved of the design, and directed them how
                    to carry it into execution.</p>
                <p>2. They first delivered petitions to the right honourable the Lord Mayor and the
                    Court of Aldermen, to the Justices sitting at Hicks’s Hall,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Sir Baptist Hickes, first
                            Viscount of Campden and first ‘shopkeeper’ ennobled by James I, ‘had
                            built at his own cost a sessions-house for the Middlesex magistrates in
                            St. John’s Street, Clerkenwell. It was known as Hick’s Hall and was in
                            use as a low court from 1612 to 1788’ (see <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>),
                            and served the boroughs of Holborn, St. Pancras, and
                        Moorfields.</p></note> and those in Westminster Hall.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">A part of the Palace of
                            Westminster, built by William Rufus and altered by Richard II. It has
                            been used for many purposes and is now incorporated into the New Palace
                            (or Houses of Parliament). In Wesley’s time it was in use as ‘a low
                            court’ (e.g., Common Pleas and the King’s Bench) and also as a sort of
                            shopping centre.</p></note> And they received from all these honourable
                    benches much encouragement to proceed.</p>
                <p>3. It was next judged proper to signify their design to many persons of eminent
                    rank, and to the body of the clergy, as well as the ministers of other
                    denominations, belonging to the several churches and meetings in and about the
                    cities of London and Westminster. And they had the satisfaction to meet with a
                    hearty consent and universal approbation from them.</p>
                <p>4. They then printed and dispersed, at their own expense, several thousand books
                    of instruction to constables and other <pb n="02:305"/>parish officers,
                    explaining and enforcing their several duties. And to prevent as far as possible
                    the necessity of proceeding to an actual execution of the laws, they likewise
                    printed and dispersed in all parts of the town dissuasives from
                    sabbath-breaking, extracts from Acts of Parliament against it, and notices to
                    the offenders.</p>
                <p>5. The way being paved by these precautions, it was in the beginning of the year
                    1758 that, after notices delivered again and again, which were as often set at
                    naught, actual informations were made to magistrates against persons profaning
                    the Lord’s day. By this means they first cleared the streets and fields of those
                    notorious offenders who, without any regard either to God or the king, were
                    selling their wares from morning to night. They proceeded to a more difficult
                    attempt, the preventing <hi rend="italic">tippling</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Johnson, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi>: ‘To waste life over the cup.’ See also,
                            Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Anthony and Cleopatra</hi>, I.iv.16,
                            18-20:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Let us grant it is not amiss to…sit</l>
                            <l>And keep the turn of tippling with a slave,</l>
                            <l>To reel the streets at noon.</l>
                        </lg></note></p> on the Lord’s day, spending the time in alehouses which
                ought to be spent in the more immediate worship of God. Herein they were exposed to
                abundance of reproach, to insult and abuse of every kind; having not only the
                tipplers and those who entertained them, the alehouse keepers, to contend with, but
                rich and honourable men, partly the landlords of those alehouse keepers, partly
                those who furnished them with drink, and in general all who gained by their sins.
                Some of these were not only men of substance but men in authority; nay, in more
                instances than one they were the very persons before whom the delinquents were
                brought. And the treatment they gave those who laid the informations naturally
                encouraged ‘the beasts of the people’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                        rend="footnote text">I.e., the London mob; from Ps. 68:30 (BCP). Cf. also,
                        No. 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, IV.2; JWJ, June 5, 1765; <hi rend="italic"
                            >Free Thoughts on Public Affairs</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>,
                        No. 325; Vol. 15 of this edn.); <hi rend="italic">Thoughts Upon
                        Liberty</hi>, §23 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 337; Vol. 15 of this
                        edn.). For Wesley’s frequent references to ‘the great vulgar’, cf. No. 31,
                        ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, I.6 and n.</p></note> to follow their example,
                and to use them as fellows not fit to live upon the earth. Hence they made no
                scruple, not only to treat them with the basest language, not only to throw at them
                mud or stones or whatever came to hand, but many times to beat them without mercy,
                and to drag them over the stones, or through the <pb n="02:306"/>kennels.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">I.e., ‘gutters’. Cf.
                        Johnson’s definition (‘the water-course of a street’) and his example from
                        Arbuthnot (‘He came in so dirty as if he had been dragged through the
                        kennel’). Cf. also JWJ, June 16, 1763.</p></note> And that they did not
                murder them was not for want of will; but the bridle was in their teeth. <p>6.
                    Having therefore received help from God, they went on to restrain <hi
                        rend="italic">bakers</hi> likewise from spending so great a part of the
                    Lord’s day in exercising the work of their calling.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">The first two edns. added here
                            the footnote: ‘They did not mean by this the restraining them from
                            baking provision for the poor.’ This was omitted from the edn. in
                            Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771), IV.90.</p></note> But many
                    of these were more noble than the victuallers. They were so far from resenting
                    this, or looking upon it as an affront, that several who had been hurried down
                    the stream of custom<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.2 and
                            n.</p></note> to act contrary to their own conscience, sincerely thanked
                    them for their labour, and acknowledged it as a real kindness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">Alexander Mather, later
                            Wesley’s trusted assistant, tells how in 1753 he was employed by William
                            Marriott, master baker in the Moorfields area, but served notice that he
                            would leave because of an uneasy conscience about the universal practice
                            of ‘the baking of pans’ on Sundays. Marriott and a neighbouring baker
                            canvassed all the master bakers in the area to secure a general
                            agreement to give up the practice, but to no avail. He then told his own
                            customers that he himself would bake no more on Sundays. And yet his
                            business flourished the more, and he became one of the mainstays of
                            Wesley’s Foundery society. See <hi rend="italic">AM</hi> (1780),
                            IIΙ.96-98.</p></note></p>
                <p>7. In clearing the streets, fields, and alehouses of sabbath-breakers, they fell
                    upon another sort of offenders as mischievous to society as any, namely, <hi
                        rend="italic">gamesters</hi> of various kinds. Some of these were of the
                    lowest and vilest class, commonly called ‘gamblers’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">The noun ‘gambler’ was a slang
                            word of recent coinage, thus defined in Johnson’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Gambler</hi> (a cant word, I
                            suppose, for <hi rend="italic">game</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                                >gamester</hi>), a knave whose practice it is to invite the unwary
                            to game and cheat them.’</p></note> who make a trade of seizing on young
                    and unexperienced men, and tricking them out of all their money. And after they
                    have beggared them, they frequently teach them the same mystery of
                        iniquity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 2 Thess. 2:7.</p></note> Several nests of these they have rooted
                    out, and constrained not a few of them honestly to earn their bread by the sweat
                    of their brow and the labour of their hands.</p>
                <p>8. Increasing in number and strength, they extended their views, and began not
                    only to repress <hi rend="italic">profane swearing</hi>, but to remove out of
                    our streets another public nuisance and scandal of the Christian name—<hi
                        rend="italic">common prostitutes</hi>. Many of these were stopped in their
                    mid-career of audacious wickedness. And in order to go to the root of the
                    disease, many of the <hi rend="italic">houses</hi> that <pb n="02:307"
                    />entertained them have been detected, prosecuted according to law, and totally
                    suppressed. And some of the poor, desolate women themselves, though fallen
                    to</p>
                <l>The lowest line of human infamy,</l><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Apparently, a conflation of a line from Prior’s ‘Henry
                        and Emma’ (line 498) and one from Samuel Wesley, Jun., ‘The Prisons Opened’
                            (<hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>, 1736, p. 180), l. 110. Prior: ‘O line
                        extreme of human infamy’; Wesley: ‘O lowest depth of human misery’. But see
                        also John Van Brugh, ‘the lowest ebb of human infamy’ (<hi rend="italic">The
                            Provoked Wife</hi> [1697], Act III). Cf. also No. 115, ‘Dives and
                        Lazarus’, I.2, where Wesley uses the same line as here, applied there to
                        beggars.</p></note>
                <p>have acknowledged the gracious providence of God, and broke off their sins by
                    lasting repentance. Several of these have been placed out, and several received
                    into the Magdalen Hospital.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A home for reformed ex-prostitutes, founded in 1758
                            by Jonas Hanway and Robert Dingley. Its first location was in Goodman’s
                            Fields. Dr. William Dodd preached the inaugural sermon and acted as its
                            chaplain.</p></note></p>
                <p>9. If a little digression may be allowed, who can sufficiently admire the wisdom
                    of divine providence in the disposal of the times and seasons so as to suit one
                    occurrence to another? For instance. Just at a time when many of these poor
                    creatures, being stopped in their course of sin, found a desire of leading a
                    better life, as it were in answer to that sad question, ‘But if I quit the way I
                    now am in, what can I do to live? For I am not mistress of any trade; and I have
                    no friends that will receive me:’ I say, just at this time, God has prepared the
                    Magdalen Hospital. Here those who have no trade, nor any friends to receive
                    them, are received with all tenderness. Here they may live, and that with
                    comfort, being provided with all things that are needful ‘for life and
                        godliness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 2 Pet. 1:3.</p></note></p>
                <p>10. But to return. The number of persons brought to justice</p>
                <p>From August 1757 to August 1762, is 9,596</p>
                <p>From thence to the present time,</p>
                <p>For unlawful gaming, and profane swearing, 40</p>
                <p>or sabbath-breaking, 400</p>
                <p>Lewd women, and keepers of ill houses, 550</p>
                <p>For offering to sale obscene prints, 2</p>
                <p>In all, 10,588</p><!--Need to make a table for this, maybe?-->
                <p>11. In the admission of members into the society no regard is had to any
                    particular sect or party. Whoever is found upon inquiry to be a good man is
                    readily admitted. And none who has selfish or pecuniary views will long continue
                    therein; not only because he <pb n="02:308"/>can gain nothing thereby, but
                    because he would quickly be a loser, inasmuch as he must commence subscriber as
                    soon as he is a member. Indeed the vulgar cry is ‘These are all <hi
                        rend="italic">Whitfelites</hi>.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A clue to the popular pronunciation of
                            ‘Whitefield’.</p></note> But it is a great mistake. About twenty of the
                    constantly subscribing members are all that are in connexion with Mr.
                    Whitefield. About fifty are in connexion with Mr. Wesley. About twenty, who are
                    of the established Church, have no connexion with either; and about seventy are
                    Dissenters, who make in all an hundred and sixty. There are indeed many more who
                    assist in the work by occasional subscriptions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>II. 1. These are the <hi rend="italic">steps</hi> which have been hitherto taken
                    in prosecution of this design. I am, in the second place, to show the <hi
                        rend="italic">excellency</hi> thereof, notwithstanding the <hi rend="italic"
                        >objections</hi> which have been raised against it. Now this may appear from
                    several considerations. And, first, from hence—that the making an open stand
                    against all the ungodliness and unrighteousness which overspread our land as a
                    flood is one of the noblest ways of confessing Christ in the face of his
                    enemies. It is giving glory to God, and showing mankind that even in these dregs
                    of time,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">‘Dregs
                            of time’. A variation of Dryden’s familiar phrase, ‘dregs of life’ (in
                                <hi rend="italic">Aureng-Zebe</hi>, IV.1)? But see also Samuel
                            Wesley, Sen., who cites only ‘the father of old’ as saying, ‘To what
                            dregs of time are we reserved.’ Wesley uses it again in No. 102, ‘Of
                            Former Times’, §2. Cf. also Law, <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>
                                (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.25); and <hi rend="italic"
                                >Christian Perfection</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            III.117).</p></note></p>
                <lg>
                    <l>There are, who faith prefer,</l>
                    <l>Though few, and piety to God.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi
                            rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, vi.143-44:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>All are not of thy train; there be, who faith</l>
                        <l>Prefer, and piety to God, …</l>
                    </lg><note><p rend="footnote text">See also No. 79, ‘On Dissipation’, §15; and
                                <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §52 (11:64 in this
                            edn.)</p></note>
                    <p>And what more excellent than to render to God the honour due unto his
                            name?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                                >Pss. 29:2; 96:8 (BCP).</p></note> To declare by a stronger proof
                        than words, even by suffering, and running all hazards, ‘Verily there is a
                        reward for the righteous; doubtless there is a God that judgeth the
                            earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"
                                >Ps. 58:10 (BCP).</p></note></p>
                    <p>2. How excellent is the design to prevent in any degree the dishonour done to
                        his glorious name, the contempt which is poured on his authority, and the
                        scandal brought upon our holy religion by the gross, flagrant wickedness of
                        those who are still called by the name of Christ! To stem in any degree the
                        torrent of <hi n="02:309"/> vice, to repress the floods of ungodliness, to
                        remove in any measure those occasions of blaspheming the worthy name whereby
                        we are called,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                                rend="footnote text">See Jas. 2:7.</p></note> is one of the noblest
                        designs it can possibly enter into the heart of man<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 2:9.</p></note>
                        to conceive.</p>
                    <p>3. And as this design thus evidently tends to bring ‘glory to God in the
                        highest’, so it no less manifestly conduces to the establishing ‘peace upon
                            earth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text"
                                >Luke 2:14.</p></note> For as all sin directly tends both to destroy
                        our peace with God by setting him at open defiance, to banish peace from our
                        own breasts, and to set every man’s sword against his neighbour; so whatever
                        prevents or removes sin does in the same degree promote peace, both peace in
                        our own soul, peace with God, and peace with one another. Such are the
                        genuine fruits of this design, even in the present world. But why should we
                        confine our views to the narrow bounds of time and space? Rather pass over
                        these into eternity. And what fruit of it shall we find there? Let the
                        Apostle speak: ‘Brethren, if one of you err from the truth, and one convert
                        him’ (not to this or that opinion, but to God!) ‘let him know that he who
                        converteth a sinner from the error of his way shall save a soul from death,
                        and hide a multitude of sins.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                                    ><p rend="endnote text">Jas. 5:19-20.</p></note></hi></p>
                    <p>4. Nor is it to individuals only, whether those who betray others into sin or
                        those that are liable to be betrayed and destroyed by them, that the benefit
                        of this design redounds, but to the whole community whereof we are members.
                        For is it not a sure observation, ‘righteousness exalteth a nation’? And is
                        it not as sure on the other hand that ‘sin is a reproach to <hi
                            rend="italic">any</hi> people’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"
                                ><p rend="footnote text">Prov. 14:34.</p></note> Yea, and bringeth
                        down the curse of God upon them? So far therefore as righteousness in any
                        branch is promoted, so far is the national interest advanced. So far as sin,
                        especially open sin, is restrained, the curse and reproach are removed from
                        us. Whoever therefore they are that labour herein, they are general
                        benefactors. They are the truest friends of their king and country. And in
                        the same proportion as their design takes place, there can be no doubt but
                        God will give national prosperity, in accomplishment of his faithful word,
                        ‘Them that honour me, I will honour.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41"
                            n="41"><p rend="footnote text">1 Sam. 2:30.</p></note></p>
                    <p><pb n="02:310"/>5. But it is objected, ‘However excellent a design this is,
                        it does not concern <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. For are there not persons to
                        whom the repressing these offences and punishing the offenders properly
                        belong? Are there not constables and other parish officers, who are bound by
                        oath to this very thing?’ There are. Constables and church wardens in
                        particular are engaged by solemn oaths to give due information against
                        profaners of the Lord’s day, and all other scandalous sinners. But if they
                        leave it undone, if notwithstanding their oaths they trouble not themselves
                        about the matter, it concerns all that fear God, that love mankind, and that
                        wish well to their king and country, to pursue this design with the very
                        same vigour as if there were no such officers existing. It being just the
                        same thing, if they are of no use, as if they had no being.</p>
                    <p>6. ‘But this is only a pretence; their real design is to get money by giving
                        informations.’ So it has frequently and roundly been affirmed, but without
                        the least shadow of truth. The contrary may be proved by a thousand
                        instances: no member of the Society takes any part of the money which is by
                        the law allotted to the informer. They never did from the beginning, nor
                        does any of them ever receive anything to suppress or withdraw their
                        information. This is another mistake, if not wilful slander, for which there
                        is not the least foundation.</p>
                    <p>7. ‘But the design is impracticable. Vice is risen to such an head that it is
                        impossible to suppress it; especially by such means. For what can an handful
                        of poor people do in opposition to all the world?’ ‘With men this is
                        impossible, but not with God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                                rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 19:26.</p></note> And they trust, not
                        in themselves, but him. Be then the patrons of vice ever so strong, to him
                        they are no more than grasshoppers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"
                                ><p rend="footnote text">See Jer. 46:23.</p></note> And all means
                        are alike to him. It is the same thing with God ‘to deliver by many or by
                            few’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text"
                                >Cf. 1 Sam. 14:6.</p></note> The small number therefore of those who
                        are on the Lord’s side is nothing, neither the great number of those that
                        are against him. Still he doth whatever pleaseth him. And ‘there is no
                        counsel or strength against the Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45"
                            n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 21:30.</p></note></p>
                    <p>8. ‘But if the end you aim at be really to reform sinners, you choose the
                        wrong means. It is the Word of God must effect this, and not human laws. And
                        it is the work of ministers, not of magistrates. Therefore the applying to
                        these can only produce an outward reformation. It makes no change in the
                        heart.’</p>
                    <p><pb n="02:311"/>It is true the Word of God is the chief ordinary means
                        whereby he changes both the hearts and lives of sinners; and he does this
                        chiefly by the ministers of the gospel. But it is likewise true that the
                        magistrate is ‘the minister of God’; and that he is designed of God ‘to be a
                        terror to evil-doers’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                                rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 13:3, 4.</p></note> by executing human
                        laws upon them. If this does not change the heart, yet to prevent outward
                        sin is one valuable point gained. There is so much the less dishonour done
                        to God, less scandal brought on our holy religion, less curse and reproach
                        upon our nation, less temptation laid in the way of others. Yea, and less
                        wrath heaped up by the sinners themselves against the day of wrath.<note
                            place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                                2:5.</p></note></p>
                    <p>9. ‘Nay, rather more; for it makes many of them hypocrites, pretending to be
                        what they are not. Others, by exposing them to shame, and putting them to
                        expense, are made impudent and desperate in wickedness; so that in reality
                        none of them are any better, if they are not worse than they were
                        before.’</p>
                    <p>This is a mistake all over. For (1), where are these hypocrites? We know none
                        who have pretended to be what they were not. (2). The exposing obstinate
                        offenders to shame, and putting them to expense, does not make them
                        desperate in offending, but afraid to offend. (3). Some of them, far from
                        being worse, are substantially better, the whole tenor of their lives being
                        changed. Yea, (4), some are inwardly changed, even ‘from darkness to light,
                        and from the power of Satan unto God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48"
                            n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 26:18.</p></note></p>
                    <p>10. ‘But many are not convinced that buying or selling on the Lord’s day is a
                        sin.’</p>
                    <p>If they are not convinced, they ought to be: it is high time they should. The
                        case is as plain as plain can be. For if an open, wilful breach both of the
                        law of God and the law of the land is not sin, pray what is? And if such a
                        breach both of divine and human laws is not to be punished because a man is
                        not convinced it is a sin, there is an end of all execution of justice, and
                        all men may live as they list.</p>
                    <p>11. ‘But <hi rend="italic">mild</hi> methods ought to be tried first.’ They
                        ought. And so they are. A mild admonition is given to every offender before
                        the law is put in execution against him; nor is any man prosecuted till he
                        has express notice that this will be the case unless he will prevent that
                        prosecution by removing the cause of it. In every case the mildest method is
                        used which the nature of the case will bear; <pb n="02:312"/>nor are severer
                        means ever applied but when they are absolutely necessary to the end.</p>
                    <p>12. ‘Well, but after all this stir about reformation, what real good has been
                        done?’ Unspeakable good; and abundantly more than anyone could have expected
                        in so short a time, considering the small number of the instruments, and the
                        difficulties they had to encounter. Much evil has been already prevented,
                        and much has been removed. Many sinners have been outwardly reformed; some
                        have been inwardly changed. The honour of him whose name we bear, so openly
                        affronted, has been openly defended. And it is not easy to determine how
                        many and how great blessings even this little stand, made for God and his
                        cause against his daring enemies, may already have derived upon our whole
                        nation. On the whole, then, after all the objections that can be made,
                        reasonable men may still conclude, a more excellent design could scarce ever
                        enter into the heart of man.</p></note>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>III. 1. But <hi rend="italic">what manner of men</hi> ought they to be who engage
                    in such a design? Some may imagine any that are willing to assist therein ought
                    readily to be admitted; and that the greater the number of members, the greater
                    will be their influence. But this is by no means true; matter of fact undeniably
                    proves the contrary. While the former Society for Reformation of Manners
                    consisted of chosen members only, though neither many, rich, nor powerful, they
                    broke through all opposition, and were eminently successful in every branch of
                    their undertaking. But when a number of men, less carefully chosen, were
                    received into that Society, they grew less and less useful till, by insensible
                    degrees, they dwindled into nothing.</p>
                <p>2. The <hi rend="italic">number</hi> therefore of the members is no more to be
                    attended to than the riches or eminence. This is a work of God. It is undertaken
                    in the name of God, and for his sake. It follows that men who neither love nor
                    fear God have no part or lot in this matter.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49"
                        n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 8:21.</p></note> ‘Why takest thou my
                    covenant in thy mouth,’ may God say to any of these, ‘whereas thou’ thyself
                    ‘hatest to be reformed, and have cast my words behind thee?’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 50:16-17
                        (BCP).</p></note> Whoever therefore lives in any known sin is not fit to
                    engage in reforming sinners. More especially if he is guilty in any instance, or
                    in the least degree, of <hi n="02:313"/> profaning the name of God, of buying,
                    selling, or doing any unnecessary work on the Lord’s day, or offending in any
                    other of those instances which this society is peculiarly designed to reform.
                    No; let none who stands himself in need of this reformation presume to meddle
                    with such an undertaking. First let him ‘pull the beam out of his own eye’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            7:5.</p></note> Let him be himself <hi rend="italic">unblameable</hi> in
                    all things.</p>
                <p>3. Not that this will suffice. Everyone engaging herein should be more than a
                    harmless man.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. No. 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §18, where Wesley
                            speaks of ‘hellish harmlessness’; see also No. 32, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                            XII’, II.2 and n.</p></note> He should be a man of <hi rend="italic"
                        >faith</hi>; having at least such a degree of that ‘evidence of things not
                        seen’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            11:1.</p></note> as to ‘aim not at the things that are seen, which are
                    temporal, but at those that are not seen, which are eternal’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:18.</p></note>
                    such a faith as produces a steady <hi rend="italic">fear of God</hi>, with a
                    lasting resolution by his grace to abstain from all that he has forbidden, and
                    to do all that he has commanded. He will more especially need that particular
                    branch of faith, ‘confidence in God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 3:4.</p></note> It is this faith which
                    ‘removes mountains’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 17:20; 1 Cor. 13:2.</p></note> which
                    ‘quenches the violence of fire’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:34.</p></note> which breaks through all
                    opposition, and enables ‘one’ to stand against and ‘chase a thousand’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Deut. 32:30;
                            Josh. 23:10.</p></note> knowing in whom his strength lies, and even when
                    he has ‘the sentence of death in himself, trusting in him who raiseth the
                        dead’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                            Cor. 1:9.</p></note></p>
                <p>4. He that has faith and confidence in God will of consequence be a man of <hi
                        rend="italic">courage</hi>. And such it is highly needful every man should
                    be who engages in this undertaking. For many things will occur in the
                    prosecution thereof which are terrible to nature; indeed so terrible that all
                    who ‘confer with flesh and blood’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:16.</p></note> will be afraid to
                    encounter them. Here therefore true courage has its proper place, and is
                    necessary in the highest degree. And this, faith only can supply. A believer can
                    say,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>I fear no denial;</l>
                    <l>No danger I fear:</l>
                    <l>Nor start from the trial;</l>
                    <l>For Jesus is near.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">John and
                            Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p.
                            137 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, II.197). Orig., ‘While Jesus is
                            near’.</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p><pb n="02:314"/>5. To courage, <hi rend="italic">patience</hi> is nearly allied;
                    the one regarding future, the other present evils. And whoever joins in carrying
                    on a design of this nature will have great occasion for this. For
                    notwithstanding all his unblameableness, he will find himself just in Ishmael’s
                    situation, ‘his hand against every man, and every man’s hand against him’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                        16:12.</p></note> And no wonder. If it be true that ‘all who will live godly
                    shall suffer persecution,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 3:12.</p></note> how eminently must this
                    be fulfilled in them who, not content to live godly themselves, compel the
                    ungodly to do so too, or at least to refrain from notorious ungodliness! Is not
                    this declaring war against all the world? Setting all the children of the
                        devil<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:10.</p></note> at defiance? And will not Satan himself, ‘the prince of
                    this world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >John 12:31; 14:30; 16:11.</p></note> ‘the ruler of the darkness’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            6:12.</p></note> thereof, exert all his subtlety and all his force in
                    support of his tottering kingdom? Who can expect the ‘roaring lion’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        5:8.</p></note> will tamely submit to have the prey plucked out of his
                    teeth? ‘Ye have,’ therefore, ‘need of patience, that when ye have done the will
                    of God ye may receive the promise.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:36.</p></note></p>
                <p>6. And ye have need of <hi rend="italic">steadiness</hi>, that ye may ‘hold fast
                    this profession of your faith without wavering’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:23.</p></note>
                    This also should be found in all that unite in this society; which is not a task
                    for a ‘double-minded man’, for one that ‘is unstable in his ways’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        1:8.</p></note> He that is as a reed shaken with the wind<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 11:7.</p></note> is not
                    fit for this warfare, which demands a firm purpose of soul, a constant,
                    determined resolution. One that is wanting in this may ‘set his hand to the
                    plough’; but how soon will he ‘look back’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72"
                        n="72"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 9:62.</p></note> He may indeed
                    ‘endure for a time; but when persecution or tribulation’, public or private
                    troubles, ‘arise because of the work, immediately he is offended’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark
                            4:17.</p></note></p>
                <p>7. Indeed it is hard for any to persevere in so unpleasing a work unless <hi
                        rend="italic">love</hi> overpowers both pain and fear. And therefore it is
                    highly expedient that all engaged therein have ‘the love of God shed abroad in
                    their hearts’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Rom. 5:5.</p></note> that they should all be able to declare, ‘we
                    love him, because he first loved us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 4:19.</p></note> The presence of him whom
                    their soul loveth<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See S. of S. 3:1, etc.</p></note> will then make
                    their labour light. <hi n="02:315"/> They can then say, not from the wildness of
                    an heated imagination, but with the utmost truth and soberness,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>With thee conversing, I forget</l>
                    <l>All time, and toil, and care;</l>
                    <l>Labour is rest, and pain is sweet,</l>
                    <l>While thou, my God, art here.</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                    <p rend="footnote text">John and Charles Wesley, ‘On a Journey’, <hi
                            rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1740), p. 127 (<hi
                            rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.304). Orig., ‘If thou, …’. Cf. Milton,
                            <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, iv.639-40:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>With thee conversing, I forget all time,</l>
                        <l>All seasons and their change; all please alike.</l>
                    </lg><p rend="footnote text">See also Nos. 82, ‘On Temptation’, III.4; 84, <hi
                            rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III.6; Wesley’s letter to
                        Hester Ann Roe, Oct. 6, 1776; and JWJ, Mar. 3, 1753, where he quotes the
                        last two lines of this verse.</p></note>
                <p>8. What adds a still greater sweetness even to labour and pain is the Christian
                        <hi rend="italic">love of our neighbour</hi>. When they ‘love their
                    neighbour’, that is, every soul of man, ‘as themselves’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Lev. 19:18,
                        etc.</p></note> as their own souls; when ‘the love of Christ
                        constrains’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 2 Cor. 5:14.</p></note> them to love one another, ‘even as he loved
                        us’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 5:2.</p></note> when as he ‘tasted death for every man’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                        2:9.</p></note> so they are ‘ready to lay down their life for their
                        brethren’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 John 3:16. Notice the definition here of ‘brethren’ as ‘<hi
                                rend="italic">every man</hi>…’ and compare it with the similar
                            definition of ‘neighbour’, cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.8 and
                            n.</p></note> (including in that number <hi rend="italic">every
                    man</hi>, every soul for which Christ died), what prospect of danger will then
                    be able to fright them from their labour of love! What suffering will they not
                    be ready to undergo to save one soul from everlasting burnings!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        33:14.</p></note> What continuance of labour, disappointment, pain, will
                    vanquish their fixed resolution! Will they not be</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>’Gainst all repulses steeled, nor ever tired</l>
                    <l>With toilsome day, or ill-succeeding night?</l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text">Samuel Wesley,
                        Jun., ‘The Battle of the Sexes’, xxi.3-4 (<hi rend="italic">Poems</hi>,
                        1736, p. 31); cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred
                            Poems</hi> (1744), III.27.</p></note>
                <p>So love both ‘hopeth and endureth all things’. So ‘charity never faileth.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            13:7-8.</p></note></p>
                <p>9. Love is necessary for all the members of such a society on another account
                    likewise; even because it ‘is not puffed up’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86"
                        n="86"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:4.</p></note> it <pb n="02:316"
                    />produces not only courage and patience, but <hi rend="italic">humility</hi>.
                    And Oh! how needful is this for all who are so employed! What can be of more
                    importance than that they should be little, and mean, and base, and vile in
                    their own eyes? For otherwise, should they think themselves anything, should
                    they impute anything to themselves, should they admit anything of a pharisaic
                    spirit, ‘trusting in themselves that they were righteous, and despising
                        others’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Luke 18:9.</p></note> nothing could more directly tend to overthrow the
                    whole design. For then they would not only have all the world, but also God
                    himself to contend with; seeing he ‘resisteth the proud, and giveth grace’ only
                    ‘to the humble’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Pet. 5:5.</p></note> Deeply conscious therefore should every member
                    of this society be of his own foolishness, weakness, helplessness; continually
                    hanging with his whole soul upon him who alone hath wisdom and strength, with an
                    unspeakable conviction that ‘the help which is done upon earth, God doth it
                        himself;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Ps. 121:2; Eccles. 3:14.</p></note> and that it is he <hi
                        rend="italic">alone</hi> ‘who worketh in us, both to will and to do of his
                    good pleasure’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Phil. 2:13.</p></note></p>
                <p>10. One point more whoever engages in this design should have deeply impressed on
                    his heart, namely, that ‘the wrath of man worketh not the righteousness of
                        God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                            1:20.</p></note> Let him therefore ‘learn of’ him ‘who was meek’ as well
                    as lowly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 11:29.</p></note> And let him abide in meekness as well as
                    humility: ‘with all lowliness and meekness’, let him ‘walk worthy of the
                    vocation wherewith he is called’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:1, 2.</p></note> Let them be ‘gentle
                    toward all men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >2 Tim. 2:24.</p></note> good or bad, for his own sake, for their sake,
                    for Christ’s sake. Are any ‘ignorant and out of the way’? Let him ‘have
                    compassion’ upon them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 5:2.</p></note> Do they even <hi rend="italic"
                        >oppose</hi> the word and the work of God; yea, set themselves in battle
                    array against it? So much the more hath he need ‘in meekness to instruct those
                    who’ thus ‘oppose themselves’, if haply they may ‘awake out of the snare of the
                    devil’, and no more be ‘taken captive at his will’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim.
                    2:25-26.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>IV. 1. From the qualifications of those who are proper to engage in such an
                    undertaking as this I proceed to show, fourthly, with what <hi rend="italic"
                        >spirit</hi> and in what <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> it ought to be
                    pursued. First, with what spirit. Now this first regards the <hi rend="italic"
                        >motive</hi> which is to be <pb n="02:317"/>preserved in every step that is
                    taken. For ‘if’ at any time ‘the light which is in thee be darkness, how great
                    is that darkness!’ But ‘if thine eye be single, thy whole body shall be full of
                        light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 6:22-23.</p></note> This is therefore continually to be
                    remembered, and carried into every word and action. Nothing is to be spoke or
                    done, either great or small, with a view to any temporal advantage; nothing with
                    a view to the favour or esteem, the love or the praise of men. But the
                    intention, the eye of the mind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For Wesley’s other uses of this metaphor, see No.
                            12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §11 and n.</p></note> is always to
                    be fixed on the glory of God and good of man.</p>
                <p>2. But the spirit with which everything is to be done regards the <hi
                        rend="italic">temper</hi>, as well as the motive. And this is no other than
                    that which has been described above. For the same courage, patience, steadiness,
                    which qualify a man for the work, are to be exercised therein. ‘Above all’ let
                    him ‘take the shield of faith’; this will quench a thousand fiery darts.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            6:16.</p></note> Let him exert all the faith which God has given him, in
                    every trying hour. And ‘let all his doings be done in love;’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 16:14 (<hi
                                rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p></note> never let this be wrested from
                    him. Neither must many waters quench this love, nor the floods of ingratitude
                    drown it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            S. of S. 8:7.</p></note> ‘Let’ likewise that lowly ‘mind be in him which
                    was also in Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p></note> Yea, and let him ‘be
                    clothed with humility’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 5:5.</p></note> filling his heart, and
                    adorning his whole behaviour. At the same time let him ‘put on bowels of
                    mercies, gentleness, long-suffering’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:12.</p></note> avoiding the least
                    appearance of malice, bitterness, anger, or resentment; knowing it is our
                    calling, not to be ‘overcome of evil, but to overcome evil with good’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            12:21.</p></note> In order to preserve this humble, gentle love, it is
                    needful to do all things with <hi rend="italic">recollection</hi> of spirit, <hi
                        rend="italic">watching</hi> against all <hi rend="italic">hurry</hi> or
                    dissipation of thought, as well as against pride, wrath, or surliness. But this
                    can be no otherwise preserved than by ‘continuing instant in prayer’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        12:12.</p></note> both before and after he comes into the field, and during
                    the whole action; and by doing all in <hi rend="italic">the spirit of
                        sacrifice</hi>, offering all to God, through the Son of his love.</p>
                <p>3. As to the outward <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of acting, a general rule is,
                    let it be expressive of these inward tempers. But to be more particular. (1).
                    Let every man beware not to ‘do evil that good may come’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:8.</p></note>
                    <pb n="02:318"/>Therefore, ‘putting away all lying’, let ‘every man speak the
                    truth to his neighbour’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:25.</p></note> Use no <hi rend="italic"
                        >fraud</hi> or <hi rend="italic">guile</hi>, either in order to detect or to
                    punish any man, but ‘by simplicity and godly sincerity’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 1:12.</p></note>
                    ‘commend yourself to men’s consciences in the sight of God.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:2.</p></note>
                    It is probable that by your adhering to these rules fewer offenders will be
                    convicted. But so much the more will the blessing of God accompany the whole
                    undertaking.</p>
                <p>4. But let innocence be joined with <hi rend="italic">prudence</hi>, properly so
                    called. Not that offspring of hell which ‘the world’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >calls</hi> prudence, which is mere craft, cunning dissimulation; but with
                    that ‘wisdom from above’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:17. Cf. No. 109, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Trouble and Rest of Good Men</hi>, II.3, where Wesley defines
                            ‘controversy’ as ‘the offspring of hell’. Cf. also, Nos. 138A and 138B,
                            ‘On Dissimulation’.</p></note> which our Lord peculiarly recommends to
                    all who would promote his kingdom upon earth. ‘Be ye therefore wise as
                    serpents’, while ye are ‘harmless as doves’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112"
                        n="112"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:16.</p></note> This wisdom will
                    instruct you how to suit your words and whole behaviour to the persons with whom
                    you have to do, to the time, place, and all other circumstances. It will teach
                    you to cut off occasion of offence, even from those who seek occasion, and to do
                    things of the most offensive nature in the least offensive manner that is
                    possible.</p>
                <p>5. Your <hi rend="italic">manner of speaking</hi>, particularly to offenders,
                    should be at all times deeply <hi rend="italic">serious</hi> (lest it appear
                    like insulting or triumphing over them), rather inclining to <hi rend="italic"
                        >sad</hi>; showing that you pity them for what they do, and sympathize with
                    them in what they suffer. Let your <hi rend="italic">air</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">tone</hi> of voice, as well as words, be <hi rend="italic"
                        >dispassionate</hi>, <hi rend="italic">calm</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                        >mild</hi>; yea, where it would not appear like dissimulation, even <hi
                        rend="italic">kind</hi> and <hi rend="italic">friendly</hi>. In some cases,
                    where it will probably be received as it is meant, you may <hi rend="italic"
                        >profess</hi> the <hi rend="italic">goodwill</hi> you bear them; but at the
                    same time (that it may not be thought to proceed from fear, or any wrong
                    inclination) professing your <hi rend="italic">intrepidity</hi> and inflexible
                        <hi rend="italic">resolution</hi> to oppose and punish vice to the
                    uttermost.</p>
                <p>V. 1. It remains only to make some application of what has been said, partly to
                    you who are already engaged in this work, partly to all that fear God, and more
                    especially to them that love as well as fear him.</p>
                <p><pb n="02:319"/>With regard to you who are already engaged in this work, the
                    first advice I would give you is calmly and deeply to consider the nature of
                    your undertaking. Know what you are about; be throughly acquainted with what you
                    have in hand. Consider the objections which are made to the whole of your
                    undertaking. And before you proceed, be satisfied that those objections have no
                    real weight. Then may every man act as he is fully persuaded in his own
                        mind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rom. 14:5.</p></note></p>
                <p>2. I advise you, secondly, be not in haste to increase your number. And in adding
                    thereto regard not wealth, rank, or any outward circumstance. Only regard the
                    qualifications above described. Inquire diligently whether the person proposed
                    be of an <hi rend="italic">unblameable carriage</hi>, and whether he be a man of
                        <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>, <hi rend="italic">courage</hi>, <hi
                        rend="italic">patience</hi>, <hi rend="italic">steadiness</hi>, whether he
                    be a <hi rend="italic">lover</hi> of God and man. If so, he will add to your
                    strength as well as number. If not, you will lose by him more than you gain. For
                    you will displease God. And be not afraid to purge out from among you any who do
                    not answer the preceding character. By thus lessening your number you will
                    increase your strength; you will be ‘vessels meet for your master’s use’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim.
                            2:21.</p></note></p>
                <p>3. I would, thirdly, advise you narrowly to observe from what <hi rend="italic"
                        >motive</hi> you at any time act or speak. Beware that your intention be not
                    stained with any regard either to profit or praise. Whatever you do, ‘do it to
                    the Lord,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Col. 3:23.</p></note> as the servants of Christ.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:6.</p></note> Do not
                    aim at pleasing yourself in any point, but pleasing him whose you are, and whom
                    you serve.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 27:23.</p></note> Let your eye be single<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 6:22.</p></note>
                    from first to last; eye God alone in every word and work.</p>
                <p>4. I advise you, in the fourth place, see that you do everything in a right <hi
                        rend="italic">temper</hi>, with lowliness and meekness, with patience and
                    gentleness, worthy the gospel of Christ. Take every step trusting in God, and in
                    the most tender, loving spirit you are able. Meantime <hi rend="italic">watch
                        always</hi> against all hurry and dissipation of spirit, and <hi
                        rend="italic">pray always</hi> with all earnestness and perseverance that
                    your faith fail not. And let nothing interrupt that <hi rend="italic">spirit of
                        sacrifice</hi> which you make of all you have and are, of all you suffer and
                    do, that it may be an offering of a sweet smelling savour to God<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            5:2.</p></note> through Jesus Christ.</p>
                <p><pb n="02:320"/>5. As to the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of acting and
                    speaking, I advise you to do it with all innocence and simplicity, prudence, and
                    seriousness. Add to these all possible calmness and mildness; nay, all the
                    tenderness which the case will bear. You are not to behave as butchers or
                    hangmen, but as surgeons rather, who put the patient to no more pain than is
                    necessary in order to the cure. For this purpose each of <hi rend="italic"
                        >you</hi> likewise has need of ‘a lady’s hand with a lion’s heart’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi
                                rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of English Proverbs</hi>, ‘Surgeon’,
                            where the first citation is dated 1589, attributed to L. Wright, <hi
                                rend="italic">Display of Dutie</hi>, 37(a): ‘In a good chirurgian a
                            hawkes eye, a lyons heart, and a ladies hand.’ See also Thomas Adams
                                (<hi rend="italic">fl.</hi> 1612-53; called by Robert Southey ‘the
                            prose Shakespeare of Puritan theologians’), <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sermons</hi> (1861), I.43: ‘We say of the chirurgian that he should
                            have a lady’s hand and a lion’s heart; but the Christian soldier should
                            have a lady’s heart and a lion’s hand.’ Cf. also Wesley’s letter to his
                            brother Charles, dated twenty-five days earlier than this sermon, Jan.
                            5, 1763, where he also uses this proverb.</p></note> So shall many even
                    of them you are constrained to punish ‘glorify God in the day of
                        visitation’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:12.</p></note></p>
                <p>6. I exhort all of you who fear God, as ever you hope to find mercy at his hands,
                    as you dread being found (though you knew it not) ‘even to fight against
                        God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            5:39.</p></note> do not on any account, reason, or pretence whatsoever,
                    either directly or indirectly, oppose or hinder so merciful a design, and one so
                    conducive to his glory. But this is not all. If you are lovers of mankind, if
                    you long to lessen the sins and miseries of your fellow-creatures, can you
                    satisfy yourselves, can you be clear before God, by barely not opposing it? Are
                    not <hi rend="italic">you</hi> also bound by the most sacred ties, ‘as you have
                    opportunity to do good to all men’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:10.</p></note> And is not here an
                    opportunity of doing good to many, even good of the highest kind? In the name of
                    God, then, embrace the opportunity. Assist in doing this good, if no otherwise,
                    yet by your earnest prayers for them who are immediately employed therein.
                    Assist them, according to your ability, to defray the expense which necessarily
                    attends it, and which, without the assistance of charitable persons, would be a
                    burden they could not bear. Assist them, if you can without inconvenience, by
                    quarterly or yearly subscriptions. At least, assist them <hi rend="italic"
                        >now</hi>: use the present hour, doing what God puts into your heart. Let it
                    not be said that you saw your brethren labouring for God and would not help them
                    with one of your fingers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 23:4.</p></note> In this way, however,
                    ‘come to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord against the mighty.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Judg.
                            5:23.</p></note></p>
                <p><pb n="02:321"/>7. I have an higher demand upon you who love, as well as fear,
                    God. He whom you fear, whom you love, has qualified <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
                    for promoting his work in a more excellent way.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 89 by this
                            title.</p></note> Because you love God you love your brother also.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 John
                            4:21.</p></note> You love not only your friends, but your enemies;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            5:43-44.</p></note> not only the friends, but even the enemies of God.
                    You have ‘put on, as the elect of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129"
                        n="129"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:12.</p></note> ‘lowliness,
                    gentleness, long-suffering’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:2.</p></note> You have faith in God, and
                    in Jesus Christ whom he hath sent<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See John 17:3.</p></note>—faith which overcometh
                    the world. And hereby you conquer both evil shame and that fear of man which
                    ‘bringeth a snare’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Prov. 29:25.</p></note> so that you can ‘stand with
                    boldness before them that despise you and make no account of your labours’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wisd.
                            5:1.</p></note> Qualified then as you are, and armed for the fight, will
                        <hi rend="italic">you</hi> be ‘like the children of Ephraim, who being
                    harnessed, and carrying bows, turned back in the day of battle’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 78:10
                            (BCP).</p></note> Will <hi rend="italic">you</hi> leave a few of your
                    brethren to stand alone against all the hosts of the aliens? O say not, ‘This is
                    too heavy a cross: I have not strength or courage to bear it.’ True; not of
                    yourself. But you that believe ‘can do all things through Christ
                        strengthening’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:13.</p></note> you. ‘If thou canst believe,
                    all things are possible to him that believeth.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn136" n="136"><p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:23.</p></note> No
                    cross is too heavy for <hi rend="italic">him</hi> to bear, knowing that they
                    that ‘suffer with him, shall reign with him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137"
                        n="137"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:12.</p></note> Say not, ‘Nay,
                    but I cannot bear to be <hi rend="italic">singular</hi>.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 31, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, XI’, III.4 and n.</p></note> Then you cannot enter into the
                    kingdom of heaven. No one enters there but through the ‘narrow way’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                            7:14.</p></note> And all that walk in this are singular. Say not, ‘But I
                    cannot endure the reproach, the odious name of an <hi rend="italic"
                        >informer</hi>.’ And did any man ever save his soul that was not ‘a by-word,
                    and a proverb of reproach’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Tobit 3:4.</p></note> Neither canst thou ever save
                    thine, unless thou art willing that men should ‘say all manner of evil of
                        thee’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 5:11.</p></note> Say not, ‘But if I am active in this work I shall
                    lose not only my reputation, but my friends, my customers, my business, my
                    livelihood, so that I shall be brought to poverty.’ Thou shalt not; thou canst
                    not; it is absolutely impossible unless God himself chooseth it. For ‘his
                    kingdom ruleth over all,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 103:19.</p></note> and ‘the very hairs of thy
                    head are all <pb n="02:322"/>numbered.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143"
                        n="143"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:30.</p></note> But if the wise, the
                    gracious God choose it for thee, wilt thou murmur or complain? Wilt thou not
                    rather say, ‘The cup which my Father hath given me, shall I not drink it?’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144"><p rend="footnote text">John
                        18:11.</p></note> If you ‘suffer for Christ, happy are you; the spirit of
                    glory and of Christ shall rest upon you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145"
                        n="145"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 4:14.</p></note> Say not: ‘I
                    would suffer all things, but my wife will not consent to it. And certainly a man
                    ought to “leave father and mother”, and all, “and cleave to his wife”.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146"><p rend="footnote text">Mark 10:7; cf.
                            Gen. 2:24.</p></note> True, all—but God; all—but Christ. But he ought
                    not to leave <hi rend="italic">him</hi> for his wife. He is not to ‘leave any
                    duty undone’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Matt. 23:23.</p></note> for the dearest relative. Our Lord himself
                    hath said in this very sense, ‘If any man loveth father, or mother, or wife, or
                    children, more than me, he is not worthy of me!’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn148" n="148"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 10:37.</p></note>
                    Say not: ‘Well, I would forsake all for Christ. But one duty must not hinder
                    another. And this would frequently hinder my attending public worship.’
                    Sometimes it probably would. ‘Go’, then, ‘and learn what that meaneth, I will
                    have mercy and not sacrifice.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 9:13.</p></note> And whatever is lost by
                    showing this mercy, God will repay sevenfold into thy bosom.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn150" n="150"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 79:12.</p></note>
                    Say not: ‘But I shall hurt my own soul. I am a young man; and by taking up loose
                    women I should expose myself to temptation.’ Yes, if you did this in your own
                    strength, or for your own pleasure. But that is not the case. You trust in God:
                    and you aim at pleasing him only. And if he should call you even into the midst
                    of a burning fiery furnace,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Dan. 3:6, 11, 15.</p></note> ‘though thou walkest
                    through the fire thou shalt not be burnt, neither shall the flames kindle upon
                        thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 43:2.</p></note> ‘True; if <hi rend="italic">he called me</hi> into
                    the furnace. But I do not see that I am called to this.’ Perhaps thou art not
                    willing to see it. However, if thou wast not called before, I call thee <hi
                        rend="italic">now</hi>, in the name of Christ, ‘Take up thy cross and follow
                        him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 16:24, etc.</p></note> Reason no more with flesh and blood, but
                    now resolve to cast in thy lot with the most despised, the most infamous of his
                    followers, the filth and offscouring of the world.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn154" n="154"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 4:13.</p></note>
                    I call thee in particular who didst once strengthen their hands, but since art
                    drawn back. Take courage! Be strong! Fulfil their joy by returning with heart
                    and hand. Let it appear thou ‘departedst for a season, that they might receive
                    thee again for ever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Philem. 15.</p></note> O be ‘not <pb n="02:323"
                    />disobedient to the heavenly calling’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156"
                        n="156"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 26:19.</p></note> And as for all of
                    you who know whereunto ye are called, count ye all things loss,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil.
                            3:8.</p></note> so ye may save one soul for which Christ died. And
                    therein ‘take no thought for the morrow’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158"
                        n="158"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:34.</p></note> but ‘cast all your
                    care on him that careth for you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn159" n="159"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 5:7.</p></note> ‘Commit your souls’,
                    bodies, substance, all to him, ‘as unto a merciful and faithful Creator’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                            4:19.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>« « « « « « «</p>
                <p>The original edition, as also that of 1778, appended:</p>
                <quote><p><hi rend="italic">The form of a Donation by Will.</hi></p>
                    <p>Item. I, A. B., do hereby give and bequeath the sum of _____ unto the
                        Treasurer for the time being of a voluntary society commonly called or known
                        by the name of ‘The Society for Reformation of Manners’ (which Society doth
                        now usually meet in St. Martins le Grand, near Newgate Street, London) the
                        same to be paid within _____ months after my decease, and to be applied to
                        the uses and purposes of the said Society.</p>
                    <p>Subscriptions and donations are taken in by Messrs.</p>
                    <p>Williams and Bellamy, near the Mansion House, London.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Edward Webber, near the East India House.</p>
                    <p>Mr. William Park, in Holiwell Street, Strand.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Crook, Great Turn-Stile, Holbourn.</p>
                    <p>Mr. Osgood, in St. Martin’s Court, near Leicester Fields.</p></quote>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>« « « « « « «</p>
                <p>Appendix to the <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, edition of 1771:</p>
                <quote>N.B. After this Society had subsisted several years, and done unspeakable
                    good, it was wholly destroyed by a verdict given against it in the King’s Bench,
                    with three hundred pounds damages. I doubt a severe account remains for the
                    witnesses, the jury, and all who were concerned in that dreadful affair. <note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn161" n="161"><p rend="footnote text">In JWJ, Feb. 2,
                            1766, Wesley wrote: ‘I dined with W. Welsh, the father of the late
                            Society for Reformation of Manners. But that excellent design is at a
                            full stop. They have indeed convicted the wretch who by wilful perjury
                            carried the cause against them in Westminster Hall; but they could never
                            recover the expense of that suit. Lord, how long shall the ungodly
                            triumph?’</p></note>
                    <note place="foot"><p rend="footnote text">A fresh beginning in the same cause,
                            and under the same name, was made by William Wilberforce in 1787, and it
                            flourished even more effectively than its predecessors, well into the
                            latter half of the nineteenth century. See R. A. Soloway, <hi
                                rend="italic">Prelates and People: Ecclesiastical Social Thought in
                                England, 1783-1852</hi> (Toronto, Univ. of Toronto Press, 1969),
                            354-56.</p></note></quote>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
