<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 23: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse III</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon023</idno>                   
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 23: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse III</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="510" to="530"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic">Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic">there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="468"/>the former part of [ch. 7]
                    he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic">and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="510"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Third</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 5:8-12</p>
                <p n="">
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see
                        God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p n="">
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are the peacemakers: for they shall be called the
                        children of God.</hi>
                </p>
                <p n="">
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are they which are persecuted for righteousness’
                        sake: for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.</hi>
                </p>
                <p n="">
                    <hi rend="italic">Blessed are ye when men shall revile you, and persecute
                        you, and shall say all manner of evil against you falsely for my
                    sake.</hi>
                </p>
                <p n="">
                    <hi rend="italic">Rejoice, and be exceeding glad; for great is your reward
                        in heaven: for so persecuted they the prophets which were before
                    you.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. How excellent things are spoken of the love of our neighbour! It is
                    ‘the fulfilling of the law’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘the end of the
                        commandment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 1:5.</p>
                    </note> Without this all we have, all we do, all we
                    suffer, is of no value in the sight of God. But it is that love of our neighbour
                    which springs from the love of God; otherwise itself is nothing worth. It
                    behoves us therefore to examine well upon what foundation our love of our
                    neighbour stands: whether it is really built upon the love of God; whether ‘we’
                    do ‘love him because he first loved us;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 4:19.</p>
                    </note> whether we are ‘pure in
                        heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            5:8.</p>
                    </note> For this is the foundation which shall never be moved:
                    ‘Blessed are the pure in heart: for they shall see God.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘The pure in heart’ are they whose hearts God hath ‘purified even as he
                    is pure’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            John 3:3.</p>
                    </note> who are purified through faith in the blood of
                    Jesus from every unholy affection; who, being ‘cleansed from all filthiness of
                    flesh and spirit, perfect holiness in the’ loving ‘fear of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                        7:1.</p>
                    </note> They are, through the power of his grace, purified from
                    pride by the deepest poverty of spirit; from anger, from every <pb n="511"/>unkind or turbulent passion, by meekness and gentleness; from every desire but
                    to please and enjoy God, to know and love him more and more, by that hunger and
                    thirst after righteousness which now engrosses their whole soul:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Blackall,
                            Discourse IX, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.79: ‘By heart it is most
                            obvious to understand the soul with all its faculties, the
                            understanding, the will and the affections…. The “pure in heart” are
                            they who…as strictly forbear all <hi rend="italic">inward</hi> acts of
                            sin…as they would be to forbear and avoid the open practice of
                            wickedness….’ See also, Hammond, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                                Catechism</hi>, pp. 99-100, for a similar view and another Anglican
                            source far Wesley’s ideas about holy living.</p>
                    </note> so that now they
                    love the Lord their God with all their heart, and with all their soul, and mind,
                    and strength.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. But how little has this ‘purity of heart’ been regarded by the false
                    teachers of all ages! They have taught men barely to abstain from such outward
                    impurities as God hath forbidden by name. But they did not strike at the heart;
                    and by not guarding against, they in effect countenanced inward corruptions.</p>
                <p>A remarkable instance of this our Lord has given us in the following words: ‘Ye
                    have heard that it was said by them of old time, Thou shalt not commit
                        adultery.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Matt. 5,] ver. 27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And in
                    explaining this those blind leaders of the blind<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 15:14.</p>
                    </note> only insist on men’s
                    abstaining from the outward act. ‘But I say unto you, whosoever looketh on a
                    woman to lust after her hath committed adultery with her already in his
                        heart.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 28.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> For God requireth truth in the inward
                        parts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 51:6 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He searcheth the heart and trieth the
                        reins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 7:10; see Jer. 11:20.</p>
                    </note> And ‘if thou incline unto iniquity
                    with thy heart, the Lord will not hear thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 66:16 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. And God admits no excuse for retaining anything which is an occasion of
                    impurity. Therefore ‘if thy right eye offend thee, pluck it out and cast it from
                    thee; for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and
                    not that thy whole body should be cast into hell.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 29.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> If
                    persons as dear to thee as thy right eye be an occasion of thy thus offending
                    God, a means of exciting unholy desire in thy soul, delay not—forcibly separate
                    from them. ‘And if thy right hand offend thee, cut it off, and cast it from
                    thee; for it is profitable for thee that one of thy members should perish, and
                    not that thy whole body should be cast into hell.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 30.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> If
                    any who <pb n="512"/>seem as necessary to thee as thy right hand be an occasion
                    of sin, of impure desire, even though it were never to go beyond the heart,
                    never to break out in word or action, constrain thyself to an entire and final
                    parting: cut them off at a stroke; give them up to God. Any loss, whether of
                    pleasure, or substance, or friends, is preferable to the loss of thy soul.</p>
                <p>Two steps only it may not be improper to take before such an absolute and final
                    separation. First, try whether the unclean spirit may not be driven out by
                    fasting and prayer,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 17:21; Mark 9:29.</p>
                    </note> and by carefully
                    abstaining from every action and word and look which thou hast found to be an
                    occasion of evil. Secondly, if thou art not by this means delivered, ask counsel
                    of him that watcheth over thy soul,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the assumption here that every Christian
                            should have his or her own ‘spiritual director’.</p>
                    </note> or at least
                    of some who have experience in the ways of God, touching the time and manner of
                    that separation. But confer not with flesh and blood,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> lest
                    thou be ‘given up to a strong delusion to believe a lie’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess.
                    2:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Nor may marriage itself, holy and honourable as it is, be used as a
                    pretence for giving a loose to our desires.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 138A, ‘On Dissimulation’, II and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> Indeed ‘It hath been said, Whosoever will put away his
                    wife, let him give her a writing of divorcement.’ And then all was well, though
                    he alleged no cause but that he did not like her, or liked another better. ‘But
                    I say unto you, That whosoever shall put away his wife, saving for the case of
                    fornication’ (that is adultery, the word πορνεία signifying unchastity in
                    general, either in the married or unmarried state) ‘causeth her to commit
                    adultery’ if she marry again; ‘and whosoever shall marry her that is put away
                    committeth adultery.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 31-32.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>All polygamy is clearly forbidden in these words, wherein our Lord expressly
                    declares that for any woman who has a husband alive, to marry again is adultery.
                    By parity of reason it is adultery for any man to marry again so long as he has
                    a wife alive. Yea, although they were divorced—unless that divorce had been for
                    the cause of adultery. In that only case there is no Scripture which forbids to
                    marry again.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            point long debated by Anglican casuists; cf. More and Cross, <hi rend="italic">Anglicanism</hi>, pp. 661-66. The governing canon was
                            No. 107 of 1604 (<hi rend="italic">Constitutions and Canons
                                Ecclesiastical</hi>, E. Cardwell, <hi rend="italic">Synodalia</hi>,
                            I.307-8); it would seem to prevent remarriage of divorced persons in any
                            case. Lancelot Andrewes had declared against remarriage,
                            ‘notwithstanding [one party] hath profaned marriage with another’; cf.
                                <hi rend="italic">A Discourse…Against Second Marriage, After
                                Sentence of Divorce…</hi> (1601), in <hi rend="italic">Minor
                                Works</hi> (in LACT), pp 106-7. Hammond, in his <hi rend="italic">Practical Catechism</hi>, II. vii, had made no allowance for
                            remarriage after divorce, even ‘in the case of fornication’. But Bishops
                            John Cosin and Joseph Hall had allowed for the remarriage of the
                            innocent party in the case of a divorce on the grounds of adultery; cf.
                            Cosin’s <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (in LACT), IV.489-93, and Hall, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (ed. Peter Hall, 1837),
                    VII.474.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">
                    <pb n="513"/>6. Such is the purity of heart which God requires, and works
                    in those who believe on the Son of his love. And ‘blessed’ are they who are thus
                    ‘pure in heart; for they shall see God’. He will ‘manifest himself unto them’,
                    not only ‘as he doth not unto the world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 14:22.</p>
                    </note> but as he doth not
                    always to his own children. He will bless them with the clearest communications
                    of his Spirit, the most intimate ‘fellowship with the Father and with the
                        Son’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            John 1:3.</p>
                    </note> He will cause his presence to go continually before
                    them, and the light of his countenance to shine upon them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 4:6, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                    It is the ceaseless prayer of their heart, ‘I beseech thee, show me thy
                        glory:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 33:18.</p>
                    </note> and they have the petition they ask of him.
                    They now see him by faith (the veil of the flesh being made, as it were,
                        transparent<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p>
                    </note>)
                    even in these his lowest works, in all that surrounds them, in all that God has
                    created and made. They see him in the height above, and in the depth beneath;
                    they see him filling all in all.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>The pure in heart see all things full of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">De Anima</hi>,
                            I.5, 411a, ll. 9-10, attributes this idea to the philosopher Thales; cf.
                                <hi rend="italic">The Basic Works of Aristotle</hi>, tr. by Richard
                            McKeon (New York, Random House, 1941), p. 553. Cicero, <hi rend="italic">De Legibus</hi>, II. xi. 26, also says that it was Thales’s
                            opinion, ‘<hi rend="italic">Homines existimare oportere deos omnia
                                cernere, deorum omnia esse plena</hi>’ (‘Men ought to believe that
                            everything they see is full of gods’). Cf. also Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Eclogues</hi>, iii.60: ‘<hi rend="italic">Jovis omnia
                                plena</hi>’, which Wesley quotes exactly in No. 118, ‘On the
                            Omnipresence of God’, II.3. Cf. also, I.11, below; and No. 69, ‘The
                            Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, I.2. See also Q. Aurelius Symmachus,
                                <hi rend="italic">Epistularum ad Diversos</hi>, Lib. X (Pareus edn.,
                            1617, p. 441): <hi rend="italic">Omnia quidem Deo plena sunt…</hi>
                            [Seeck edn., 1888, pp. 281-82].</p>
                    </note> They see him in the firmament
                    of heaven, in the moon walking in brightness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 31:26.</p>
                    </note> in the sun when he
                    rejoiceth as a giant to run his course.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 19:5 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> They see him
                    ‘making the clouds his chariots, and walking upon the wings of the wind’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            104:3.</p>
                    </note> They see him ‘preparing rain for the earth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            147:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘and blessing the increase of it’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 65:11
                        (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘giving grass for the cattle, and green herb for the use
                    of man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            104:14.</p>
                    </note> They see the Creator of all wisely <pb n="514"/>
                    governing all, and ‘upholding all things by the word of his power’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        1:3.</p>
                    </note> ‘O Lord, our Governor, how excellent is thy name in all the
                        world!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            8:1, 9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. In all his providences relating to themselves, to their souls or bodies,
                    the pure in heart do more particularly see God. They see his hand ever over them
                    for good; giving them all things in weight, and measure, numbering the hairs of
                    their head,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 10:30.</p>
                    </note> making a hedge round about them and all that
                    they have,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Job 1:10.</p>
                    </note> and disposing all the circumstances of their life
                    according to the depth both of his wisdom and mercy.</p>
                <p n="8">8. But in a more especial manner they see God in his ordinances.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 16, ‘The
                            Means of Grace’.</p>
                    </note> Whether they appear in the great
                    congregation to ‘pay him the honour due unto his name, and worship him in the
                    beauty of holiness’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 96:8, 9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> or ‘enter into
                    their closets’ and there pour out their souls before their ‘Father which is in
                        secret’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:6.</p>
                    </note> whether they search the oracles of God, or hear
                    the ambassadors of Christ proclaiming glad tidings of salvation; or by eating of
                    that bread and drinking of that cup<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 11:28.</p>
                    </note> ‘show forth his death
                    till he come’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 11:26.</p>
                    </note> in the clouds of heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:64; Mark
                        14:62.</p>
                    </note> In all these his appointed ways they find such a near
                    approach as cannot be expressed. They see him, as it were, face to face, and
                    ‘talk with him as a man talking with his friend’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod. 33:11.</p>
                    </note>—a
                    fit preparation for those mansions above wherein they shall ‘see him as he
                        is’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. But how far were they from seeing God, who having ‘heard that it had
                    been said by them of old time, Thou shalt not forswear thyself, but shalt
                    perform unto the Lord thine oaths’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 33.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> interpreted
                    it thus: thou shalt not forswear thyself when thou swearest by the Lord Jehovah;
                    thou ‘shalt perform unto the Lord <hi rend="italic">these</hi> thine oaths’—but
                    as to other oaths, he regardeth them not.</p>
                <p>So the Pharisees taught. They not only allowed all manner of swearing in common
                    conversation; but accounted even forswearing a little thing, so they had not
                    sworn by the peculiar name of God.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="515"/>But our Lord here absolutely forbids all common swearing as well as
                    all false swearing; and shows the heinousness of both by the same awful
                    consideration, that every creature is God’s, and he is everywhere present, in
                    all, and over all.</p>
                <p>‘I say unto you, Swear not at all; neither by heaven, for it is God’s throne’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                34.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—and therefore this is the same as to swear by
                    him who sitteth upon the circle of the heavens<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 40:22.</p>
                    </note>—‘nor by the earth,
                    for it is his footstool,’ and he is as intimately present in earth as heaven;
                    ‘neither by Jerusalem, for it is the city of the great King’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                35.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and ‘God is well known in her palaces.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 48:2
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘Neither shalt thou swear by thy head, because thou
                    canst not make one hair white or black;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 36.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> because even
                    this, it is plain, is not thine but God’s, the sole disposer of all in heaven
                    and earth. ‘But let your communication’—your conversation, your discourse with
                    each other—‘be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay’—a bare serious affirming or denying—‘for
                    whatsoever is more than these cometh of evil’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 37.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—ἐκ τοῦ
                    πονηροῦ ἐστιν, (‘is of the evil one’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §10
                            and n.</p>
                    </note> proceedeth from the devil and is a mark of his
                    children).</p>
                <p n="10">10. That our Lord does not here forbid the ‘swearing in judgment and
                        truth’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Thirty-nine Articles, Art. XXXIX, ‘Of a Christian Man’s Oath’, to which
                            Wesley subscribed so wholeheartedly that he reproduced it, intact, in
                            his later abridgement of the Articles. The issue here had been posed by
                            the Anabaptist’s stubborn refusal to take such oaths, chiefly on the
                            grounds of this New Testament prohibition. See Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Radical Reformation</hi>, pp. 125, 185, 194 ff.,
                            594, 785; for the later controversy in England over this article itself,
                            cf. Barbour and Roberts, <hi rend="italic">Early Quaker Writings</hi>,
                            p. 354, and the ‘testimonies against the oath’ by George Fox (p. 406)
                            and William Penn (pp. 448-50). But see also the section on ‘Oaths’ in
                            More and Cross, <hi rend="italic">Anglicanism</hi>, pp. 672-76, where
                            Tillotson, Taylor, and Beveridge are quoted in support of the position
                            here taken by Wesley.</p>
                    </note> when we are required so to do by a
                    magistrate may appear: (1). From the occasion of this part of his discourse, the
                    abuse he was here reproving, which was false swearing and common swearing, the
                    swearing before a magistrate being quite out of the question. (2) From the very
                    words wherein he forms the general conclusion, ‘Let your communication’, or
                    discourse, ‘be, Yea, yea; Nay, nay.’ (3). From his own example; <pb n="516"/>for
                    he answered himself upon oath when required by a magistrate. When ‘the High
                    Priest said unto him, I adjure thee by the living God that thou tell us whether
                    thou be the Christ, the Son of God,’ Jesus immediately answered in the
                    affirmative, ‘Thou hast said’ (i.e., the truth). ‘Nevertheless’ (or rather,
                        ‘Moreover’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s translation in <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 26:63-64;
                            but cf. Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, for Jesus’s reply to
                            Caiaphas, ‘Thou hast said the Truth…,’ and Henry’s comment, ‘It is as
                            thou hast said’ (<hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>).</p>
                    </note>) ‘I say
                    unto you, Hereafter shall ye see the Son of man sitting on the right hand of
                    power, and coming in the clouds of heaven.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 26:63-64.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> (4).
                    From the example of God, even the Father, who ‘willing the more abundantly to
                    show unto the heirs of promise the immutability of his counsel, confirmed it by
                    an oath.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 6:17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> (5). From the example of St. Paul, who
                    we ‘think had the Spirit of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 7:40.</p>
                    </note> and well understood the
                    mind of his Master. ‘God is my witness’, saith he to the Romans, ‘that without
                    ceasing I make mention of you always in my prayers;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 1:9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> to
                    the Corinthians, ‘I call God to record upon my soul, that to spare you I came
                    not as yet unto Corinth;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor. 1:23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and to the
                    Philippians, ‘God is my record, how greatly I long after you in the bowels of
                    Jesus Christ.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Phil. 1:8.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> (Hence it undeniably
                    appears that if the Apostle knew the meaning of his Lord’s words, they do not
                    forbid swearing on weighty occasions, even to one another—how much less before a
                    magistrate!) And lastly, from that assertion of the great Apostle concerning
                    solemn swearing in general (which it is impossible he could have mentioned
                    without any touch of blame if his Lord had totally forbidden it): ‘Men verily
                    swear by the greater’ (by one greater than themselves), ‘and an oath for
                    confirmation is to them the end of all strife.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 6:16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. But the great lesson which our blessed Lord inculcates here, and which
                    he illustrates by this example, is that God is in all things,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. I.6, above, and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> and that we are to see the Creator in the glass of every
                        creature;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This will be the central theme of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Survey of
                                the Wisdom of God…</hi> in its three successive edns. (1763, 1770,
                            1777).</p>
                    </note> that we should use and look upon nothing as separate
                        <pb n="517"/>from God, which indeed is a kind of practical atheism;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A phrase from
                            John Norris, ‘Concerning Practical Atheism’, in <hi rend="italic">Practical Discourses</hi>, IV.100-24. Wesley habitually used
                            ‘practical atheism’, ‘idolatry’, and ‘dissipation’ as working synonyms.
                            Cf. below, III.4, as well as Nos. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering
                                Thoughts</hi>, III.1; 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, II.7;
                            69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, III.2; 108, ‘On Riches’,
                            II.1; 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §20; 120, ‘The Unity
                            of the Divine Being’, §§19, 20; 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’, §12; 128,
                            ‘The Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, I.3, 4; and 130, ‘On Living
                            without God’, §§1, 6, 7. Cf. also Nos. 79, ‘On Dissipation’, §1; and 78,
                            ‘Spiritual Idolatry’. See also Charles Hickman, <hi rend="italic">Sermon
                                Before the Queen at Whitehall, Sunday, October 2, 1692</hi>, p. 7:
                            ‘When men have conquered their conscience…they may for a while enjoy
                            their sins in peace and live as if there were no God in the
                        world.’</p>
                    </note> but with a true magnificence of thought survey heaven and
                    earth and all that is therein as contained by God in the hollow of his hand, who
                    by his intimate presence holds them all in being, who pervades and actuates the
                    whole created frame, and is in a true sense the soul of the universe.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Viz.</hi>, the ‘<hi rend="italic">anima mundi</hi>’, one of the
                            oldest notions of both Platonists and Stoics; it will presently be
                            re-echoed by Wordsworth in <hi rend="italic">The Prelude</hi>,
                            I.401-4:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>Wisdom and Spirit of the Universe!</l>
                            <l>Thou Soul that art the Eternity of thought!</l>
                            <l>And giv’st to forms and images a breath</l>
                            <l>And everlasting motion!</l>
                        </lg>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Thus far our Lord has been more directly employed in teaching the
                    religion of the heart. He has shown what Christians are to be. He proceeds to
                    show what they are to do also: how inward holiness is to exert itself in our
                    outward conversation. ‘Blessed’, saith he, ‘are the peacemakers; for they shall
                    be called the children of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘The peacemakers’—the word in the original is οἱ εἰρηνοποιοί. It is well
                    known that εἰρήνη in the sacred writings implies all manner of good—every
                    blessing that relates either to the soul or the body, to time or eternity.
                    Accordingly, when St. Paul in the titles of his epistles wishes ‘grace and
                    peace’ to the Romans or the Corinthians it is as if he had said, ‘As a fruit of
                    the free, undeserved love and favour of God, may you enjoy all blessings,
                    spiritual and temporal, all the good things “which God hath prepared for them
                    that love him.”’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Hence we may easily learn in how wide a sense the term ‘peacemakers’ is
                    to be understood. In its literal meaning it implies those lovers of God and man
                    who utterly detest and abhor all strife and debate, all variance and contention;
                    and accordingly <pb n="518"/>labour with all their might either to prevent this
                    fire of hell from being kindled, or when it is kindled from breaking out, or
                    when it is broke out from spreading any farther.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In this entire section
                            (II.2-7) Wesley continues the hermeneutical tradition reflected in
                            Blackall, Discourse XII, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.105-14, and in
                            Hammond, <hi rend="italic">Practical Catechism</hi>, pp.
                        101-3.</p>
                    </note> They endeavour to calm the stormy spirits of men, to quiet
                    their turbulent passions, to soften the minds of contending parties, and if
                    possible reconcile them to each other. They use all innocent arts, and employ
                    all their strength, all the talents which God has given them, as well to
                    preserve peace where it is as to restore it where it is not. It is the joy of
                    their heart to promote, to confirm, to increase mutual goodwill among men, but
                    more especially among the children of God, however distinguished by things of
                    smaller importance; that as they have all ‘one Lord, one faith’, as they are all
                    ‘called in one hope of their calling’, so they may all ‘walk worthy of the
                    vocation wherewith they are called’: ‘with all lowliness and meekness, with
                    long-suffering, forbearing one another in love; endeavouring to keep the unity
                    of the Spirit in the bond of peace.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:1-5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. But in the full extent of the word a ‘peacemaker’ is one that as he hath
                    opportunity ‘doth good unto all men’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:10. Cf. John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical Discourses</hi>, I.126: ‘The “peacemakers” are persons of
                            “peaceable dispositions”. And this requires: “First, that the
                            [peacemaker] be free from all inordinate self-love; it being impossible
                            that he who prefers his own little private concerns before the public
                            interest should be at peace with the public when that tender part comes
                            once to be touched. No, such an one will balance self against the world,
                            will not care what becomes of the public when it stands in competition;
                            but will embroil all the world in war and mischief, if he can, for the
                            least self-advantage…”.’</p>
                    </note> one that being filled with the love
                    of God and of all mankind cannot confine the expressions of it to his own
                    family, or friends, or acquaintance, or party; or to those of his own opinions;
                    no, nor those who are partakers of like precious faith;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 1:1.</p>
                    </note> but
                    steps over all these narrow bounds that he may do good to every man; that he may
                    some way or other manifest his love to neighbours and strangers, friends and
                    enemies. He doth good to them all as he hath opportunity, that is, on every
                    possible occasion; ‘redeeming the time’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:16; Col. 4:5.</p>
                    </note> in order
                    thereto, ‘buying up every opportunity’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:10.</p>
                    </note> improving every hour,
                    losing no moment wherein he may profit another. He does good, not of one
                    particular kind, but good in general: in every possible way, employing herein
                    all his talents of every kind, all his powers and faculties of body and soul,
                    all his fortune, his interest, his <pb n="519"/>reputation; desiring only that
                    when his Lord cometh he may say, ‘Well done, good and faithful servant!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        25:23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. He doth good, to the uttermost of his power, even to the bodies of all
                    men. He rejoices to ‘deal his bread to the hungry’, and to ‘cover the naked with
                    a garment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 58:7; Ezek. 18:7, 16.</p>
                    </note> Is any a stranger? He takes him
                    in, and relieves him according to his necessities. Are any sick or in prison? He
                    visits them, and administers such help as they stand most in need of. And all
                    this he does, not as unto man, but remembering him that hath said, ‘Inasmuch as
                    ye have done it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye have done it unto
                        me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            25:40.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. How much more does he rejoice if he can do any good to the soul of any
                    man! This power indeed belongeth unto God. It is he only that changes the heart,
                    without which every other change is lighter than vanity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 62:9.</p>
                    </note>
                    Nevertheless it pleases him who worketh all in all<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 12:6.</p>
                    </note> to
                    help man chiefly by man; to convey his own power and blessing and love through
                    one man to another. Therefore, although it be certain that ‘the help which is
                    done upon earth, God doth it himself,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 74:13 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> yet has no man
                    need on this account to stand idle in his vineyard. The peacemaker cannot: he is
                    ever labouring therein, and as an instrument in God’s hand preparing the ground
                    for his Master’s use, or sowing the seed of the kingdom, or watering what is
                    already sown, if haply God may give the increase.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 3:6-7.</p>
                    </note>
                    According to the measure of grace which he has received he uses all diligence
                    either to reprove the gross sinner, to reclaim those who run on headlong in the
                    broad way of destruction<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:13.</p>
                    </note>, or ‘to give light to
                    them that sit in darkness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 1:79.</p>
                    </note> and are ready to ‘perish for
                    lack of knowledge’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Hos. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> or to ‘support the
                        weak’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            20:35; 1 Thess. 5:14.</p>
                    </note> to ‘lift up the hands that hang down,
                    and the feeble knees’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:12.</p>
                    </note> or to bring back and heal
                    that which was ‘lame and turned out of the way’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:13.</p>
                    </note> Nor is
                    he less zealous to confirm those who are already striving to enter in at the
                    strait gate;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Luke 13:24.</p>
                    </note> to strengthen those that stand, that they may
                    ‘run with patience the race which is set before them’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> to
                    ‘build up in their most holy <pb n="520"/>faith’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jude 20.</p>
                    </note> those
                    that know in whom they have believed;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> to exhort them to stir
                    up the gift of God which is in them,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> that daily ‘growing in
                        grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Pet. 3:18.</p>
                    </note> ‘an entrance may be ministered unto them
                    abundantly into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus
                        Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Pet. 1:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Blessed are they who are thus continually employed in the work of faith
                    and the labour of love; ‘for they shall be called’—that is ‘shall be’ (a common
                        Hebraism<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Generally true but with important exceptions, as in Gen. 2:23; Isa.
                            35:8; 47:1; 54:5; 58:12; 62:2, 4, 12; Jer. 7:32; 19:6; 23:6; 33:16. But
                            cf. Heylyn, <hi rend="italic">Theological Lectures</hi>, I.71: ‘“to be
                            called” is a frequent Hebraism signifying only an assertion that such a
                            thing really <hi rend="italic">is</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">becomes</hi>, what is said to be “called”.’</p>
                    </note>)—‘the
                    children of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> God shall continue unto them
                    the Spirit of adoption,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> yea, shall pour it more
                    abundantly into their hearts. He shall bless them with all the blessings of his
                    children. He shall acknowledge them as sons before angels and men; ‘and if sons,
                    then heirs; heirs of God, and joint heirs with Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. One would imagine such a person as has been above described, so
                    full of genuine humility, so unaffectedly serious, so mild and gentle, so free
                    from all selfish design, so devoted to God, and such an active lover of men,
                    should be the darling of mankind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Suetonius, <hi rend="italic">Lives of the
                                Caesars</hi> (‘The Deified Titus’, I): ‘Titus, with the same surname
                            as his father, was the delight and darling of mankind’ (‘<hi rend="italic">deliciae humani generis</hi>’).</p>
                    </note> But our
                    Lord was better acquainted with human nature in its present state. He therefore
                    closes the character of this man of God with showing him the treatment he is to
                    expect in the world. ‘Blessed’, saith he, ‘are they which are persecuted for
                    righteousness’ sake; for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. In order to understand this throughly, let us first inquire who are they
                    that are persecuted.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Here Wesley departs from both Blackall and Hammond,
                            who stress that ‘the persecuted’ are those who offend the world by their
                            ‘strict and close adherence to the profession and practice of the
                            Christian Church’; Cf. Blackall, Discourse XV, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.134-41.</p>
                    </note> And this we may easily learn from
                    St. Paul: ‘As of old he that was born after the flesh persecuted him <pb n="521"/>that was born after the Spirit, even so it is now.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal.
                                4:29.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Yea’, saith the Apostle, ‘and all that will
                    live godly in Christ Jesus shall suffer persecution.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Tim.
                                3:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The same we are taught by St. John: ‘Marvel
                    not, my brethren, if the world hate you. We know that we have passed from death
                    unto life, because we love the brethren.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 3:13-14.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> As if
                    he had said, The brethren, the Christians, cannot be loved but by them who have
                    passed from death unto life. And most expressly by our Lord: ‘If the world hate
                    you, ye know that it hated me before it hated you. If ye were of the world, the
                    world would love its own; but because ye are not of the world, …therefore the
                    world hateth you. Remember the word that I said unto you, The servant is not
                    greater than the Lord. If they have persecuted me, they will also persecute
                        you.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John 15:18-20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p>By all these Scriptures it manifestly appears who they are that are persecuted,
                    namely the righteous: ‘he that is born after the Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:29.</p>
                    </note> ‘all
                    that will live godly in Christ Jesus’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> they that are ‘passed
                    from death unto life’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:14.</p>
                    </note> those who ‘are not of the
                        world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            15:19.</p>
                    </note> all those who are meek and lowly in heart, that mourn
                    for God, that hunger after his likeness; all that love God and their neighbour,
                    and therefore as they have opportunity do good unto all men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. If it be, secondly, inquired why they are persecuted, the answer is
                    equally plain and obvious. It is ‘for righteousness’ sake’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:10.</p>
                    </note> because
                    they are righteous; because they are ‘born after the Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 4:29.</p>
                    </note> because
                    they ‘will live godly in Christ Jesus’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> because they ‘are not
                    of the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 15:19.</p>
                    </note> Whatever may be pretended, this is the real
                    cause; be their infirmities more or less, still if it were not for this they
                    would be borne with, and the world would love its own. They are persecuted
                    because they are ‘poor in spirit’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:3.</p>
                    </note> that is, say the world,
                    ‘poor-spirited, mean, dastardly souls, good for nothing, not fit to live in the
                    world’; because they <pb n="522"/>‘mourn’: ‘They are such dull, heavy, lumpish
                        creatures,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Address to the Clergy</hi>, II.1 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 216, Vol. 14 of this edn.), where
                            Wesley speaks of ‘dull, heavy, blockish ministers’.</p>
                    </note> enough to
                    sink anyone’s spirits that sees them! They are mere death’s-heads; they kill
                    innocent mirth, and spoil company wherever they come;’ because they are <hi rend="italic">meek</hi>: ‘Tame, passive fools, just fit to be trampled
                    upon;’ because they ‘hunger and thirst after righteousness’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:6.</p>
                    </note> ‘A
                    parcel of hot-brained enthusiasts, gaping after they know not what, not content
                    with rational religion, but running mad after raptures and inward feelings;’
                    because they are ‘merciful’, lovers of all, lovers of the evil and unthankful:
                    ‘Encouraging all manner of wickedness; nay, tempting people to do mischief by
                    impunity; and men who, it is to be feared, have their own religion still to
                    seek; very loose in their principles;’ because they are ‘pure in heart’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘Uncharitable creatures that damn all the world but those
                    that are of their own sort! Blasphemous wretches that pretend to make God a
                    liar, to live without sin!’ Above all because they are ‘peacemakers’, because
                    they take all opportunities of doing good to all men. This is the grand reason
                    why they have been persecuted in all ages, and will be till the restitution of
                    all things.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 3:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘If they would but keep their religion to themselves it would be tolerable. But
                    it is this spreading their errors, this infecting so many others, which is not
                    to be endured. They do so much mischief in the world that they ought to be
                    tolerated no longer. It is true the men do some things well enough; they relieve
                    some of the poor. But this, too, is only done to gain the more to their party;
                    and so in effect to do the more mischief.’ Thus the men of the world sincerely
                    think and speak. And the more the kingdom of God prevails, the more the
                    peacemakers are enabled to propagate lowliness, meekness, and all other divine
                    tempers, the more mischief is done—in their account. Consequently the more are
                    they enraged against the authors of this, and the more vehemently will they
                    persecute them.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Let us, thirdly, inquire who are they that persecute them. St. Paul
                    answers, ‘He that is born after the flesh’; everyone who is not ‘born of the
                        Spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal 4:29.</p>
                    </note> or at least desirous so to be; all that do not
                    at <pb n="523"/>least labour to ‘live godly in Christ Jesus’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> all
                    that are not ‘passed from death unto life’, and consequently cannot ‘love the
                        brethren’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:14.</p>
                    </note> ‘the world’, that is, according to our
                    Saviour’s account, ‘they who know not him that sent me’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 15:21. Ὁ κόσμος as
                            the community of those at enmity with God is a special New Testament
                            usage (cf. 7 in Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English
                                Lexicon</hi>), but it was one of Wesley’s favourites; the notable
                            exception, of course, is in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on John
                            3:16, 17. Generally, however, he followed the mystical tradition of <hi rend="italic">contemptus mundi</hi> (Kempis, De Renty, Law); cf.
                            Nos. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.5 and n., for
                            Wesley’s comments on ‘saints of the world’; and 22, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, II’, II.4 and n., for ‘religion of the world’; see also No. 80,
                            ‘On Friendship with the World’, §5. For Wesley’s satanocratic views
                            about the world, cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §10 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> they who know not God, even the loving, pardoning God, by
                    the teaching of his own Spirit.</p>
                <p>The reason is plain. The spirit which is in the world is directly opposite to the
                    Spirit which is of God. It must therefore needs be that those who are of the
                    world will be opposite to those who are of God. There is the utmost contrariety
                    between them in all their opinions, their desires, designs, and tempers. And
                    hitherto ‘the leopard and the kid’ cannot ‘lie down in peace together.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            11:6.</p>
                    </note> The proud, because he is proud, cannot but persecute
                    the lowly; the light and airy, those that mourn: and so in every other kind, the
                    unlikeness of disposition (were there no other) being a perpetual ground of
                    enmity. Therefore (were it only on this account) all the servants of the devil
                    will persecute the children of God.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Should it be inquired, fourthly, how they will persecute them, it may be
                    answered in general, just in that manner and measure which the wise Disposer of
                    all sees will be most for his glory, will tend most to his children’s growth in
                    grace and the enlargement of his own kingdom. There is no one branch of God’s
                    government of the world which is more to be admired than this. His ear is never
                    heavy to the threatenings of the persecutor or the cry of the persecuted. His
                    eye is ever open and his hand stretched out to direct every the minutest
                    circumstance. When the storm shall begin, how high it shall rise, which way it
                    shall point its course, when and how it shall end, are all determined by his
                    unerring wisdom.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 67, ‘On Divine Providence’, §23 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> The ungodly are only a sword of his; an instrument which he
                    uses as it pleaseth him, and which itself, <pb n="524"/>when the gracious ends
                    of his providence are answered, is cast into the fire.</p>
                <p>At some rare times, as when Christianity was planted first, and while it was
                    taking root in the earth, as also when the pure doctrine of Christ began to be
                    planted again in our nation, God permitted the storm to rise high, and his
                    children were called to resist unto blood.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:4. Cf. Tertullian, <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>, 50, §13: ‘<hi rend="italic">…semen est
                                sanguis Christianorum</hi>’ (‘nothing whatever is accomplished by
                            your cruelties…. They are the bait that wins men for our sect. We
                            multiply whenever we are mown down by you; <hi rend="italic">the blood
                                of Christians is seed</hi>’). This evolved into the familiar
                            aphorism: ‘The blood of the martyrs is the seed of the
                        Church.’</p>
                    </note> There was a peculiar reason why he suffered this with
                    regard to the apostles—that their evidence might be the more unexceptionable.
                    But from the annals of the church we learn another and a far different reason
                    why he suffered the heavy persecutions which rose in the second and third
                    centuries: namely, because the mystery of iniquity did so strongly work, because
                    of the monstrous corruptions which even then reigned in the church; these God
                    chastised, and at the same time strove to heal, by those severe but necessary
                    visitations.</p>
                <p>Perhaps the same observation may be made with regard to the grand persecution in
                    our own land.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Any Englishman of the time would have recognized this as a reference to
                            ‘Bloody Mary’ Tudor (1553-58), since John Foxe’s <hi rend="italic">Book
                                of Martyrs</hi> (first Eng. edn. in 1563) had indelibly fixed the
                            image of Roman Catholic zeal and cruelty in English minds; John Knox’s
                            contemptuous epithet (‘that wicked Jezebel of England’) had focused
                            their feelings on Mary. Her cruelties, however, were scarcely more
                            ruthless than those of her acclaimed half-sister, ‘Good Queen Bess’. But
                            in JWJ for Mar. 13, 1747, Wesley records having read Daniel Neal’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Puritans</hi> (1732-38) and being
                            ‘amaze[d]’: ‘First, at the execrable spirit of persecution which drove
                            [the Puritans] out of the Church, and with which Queen Elizabeth’s
                            clergy were as deeply tinctured as ever Queen Mary’s were.’ On Apr. 26,
                            1786, he recounts his ‘discovery’ of Queen Elizabeth’s cruel treatment
                            of Maty Stuart: ‘But what then was Queen Elizabeth? As just and merciful
                            as Nero and as good a Christian as Mahomet.’ In his old age, however, he
                            wrote to Henry Fisher (Nov. 7, 1781): ‘I do not remember that Queen
                            Elizabeth or King James (bad as they were) burnt any heretics.’ Here he
                            conveniently ignored the ‘forty English martyrs’ (later to be canonized
                            in Rome in 1968). The Roman martyrology reckons 183 persons martyred for
                            their faith during Elizabeth’s reign. Cf. No. 92, ‘On Zeal’, §1. The
                            last Englishman burnt for heresy (by James I) was Edward Wightman (in
                            Lichfield, Apr. 1612), a month after Bartholomew Legate had been burnt
                            in Smithfield; the Roman Catholics martyred by Charles II were formally
                            charged with sedition.</p>
                    </note> God had dealt very graciously with our
                    nation; he had poured out various blessings upon us. He had given us peace
                    abroad and at home; and a king wise and good beyond his years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The boy-king, Edward VI
                            (1547-53), who succeeded his father, Henry VIII, at the age of ten.
                            Under guidance by the Lords Protector (first the Earl of Somerset and
                            then the Earl of Northumberland), Edward aided the Protestant reform,
                            chiefly by his encouragement of reformers like Thomas Cranmer, John
                            Hooper, Nicholas Ridley. The results included the <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> (1547), clerical marriage, and communion in both
                            kinds (1548), a ‘reformed’ BCP (1549), followed by an even more
                            ‘reformed’ version (1552), a Protestant Catechism and Christian Primer
                            (1553). Wesley rightly infers that the young king had taken a personal
                            interest in these reform measures. With his early death and the
                            counter-reform measures of Queen Mary, the Protestant cause had been
                            imperilled but also had become heroic. For a rather different
                            perspective, see Carolly Erickson, <hi rend="italic">Bloody Mary</hi>,
                            pp. 226-84, 450 ff.</p>
                    </note> And above all he had caused <pb n="525"/>the pure light of his gospel to arise and shine amongst us. But what return
                    did he find? ‘He looked for righteousness; but behold a cry!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 5:7.</p>
                    </note> A cry
                    of oppression and wrong, of ambition and injustice, of malice and fraud and
                    covetousness. Yea, the cry of those who even then expired in the flames entered
                    into the ears of the Lord of sabaoth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 5:4.</p>
                    </note> It was then God arose to
                    maintain his own cause against those that held the truth in
                        unrighteousness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 1:18.</p>
                    </note> Then he sold them into
                    the hands of their persecutors, by a judgment mixed with mercy, an affliction to
                    punish and yet a medicine to heal the grievous backslidings of his people.</p>
                <p n="6">6. But it is seldom God suffers the storm to rise so high as torture or
                    death or bonds or imprisonment. Whereas his children are frequently called to
                    endure those lighter kinds of persecution: they frequently suffer the
                    estrangement of kinsfolk, the loss of the friends that were as their own
                        soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Deut. 13:6.</p>
                    </note> They find the truth of their Lord’s word
                    (concerning the event, though not the design of his coming): ‘Suppose ye that I
                    am come to give peace on earth? I tell you, Nay, but rather division.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke
                                12:51.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And hence will naturally follow loss of
                    business or employment, and consequently of substance. But all these
                    circumstances likewise are under the wise direction of God, who allots to
                    everyone what is most expedient for him.</p>
                <p n="7">7. But the persecution which attends all the children of God is that our
                    Lord describes in the following words: ‘Blessed are ye, when men shall revile
                    you, and persecute you (shall persecute by reviling you), and say all manner of
                    evil against you falsely, for my sake.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:11.</p>
                    </note> This cannot fail: it
                    is the very badge of our discipleship; it is one of the seals of our calling. It
                    is a sure portion entailed on all the children of God; if we have it not we are
                    bastards and not <pb n="526"/>sons. Straight through ‘evil report’ as well as
                    ‘good report’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:8.</p>
                    </note> lies the only way to the kingdom. The meek,
                    serious, humble, zealous lovers of God and man are of good report among their
                    brethren; but of evil report with the world, who count and treat them ‘as the
                    filth […] and offscouring of all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 4:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Indeed some have supposed that before the fullness of the Gentiles shall
                    come in<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rom. 11:25.</p>
                    </note> the scandal of the cross will cease; that God
                    will cause Christians to be esteemed and loved, even by those who are as yet in
                    their sins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Joseph Mede, <hi rend="italic">Commentationum Apocalypticarum</hi>,
                            in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.530-32; and ‘Remains’, XI, XII, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 602-5.</p>
                    </note> Yea, and sure it is that
                    even now he at some times suspends the contempt as well as the fierceness of
                    men. ‘He makes a man’s enemies to be at peace with him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 16:7.</p>
                    </note>
                    for a season, and gives him favour with his bitterest persecutors. But setting
                    aside this exempt case, ‘the scandal of the cross is’ not yet ‘ceased’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            5:11.</p>
                    </note> but a man may say still, ‘If I please men, I am not the
                    servant of Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:10.</p>
                    </note> Let no man therefore
                    regard that pleasing suggestion (pleasing doubtless to flesh and blood), that
                    ‘Bad men only <hi rend="italic">pretend</hi> to hate and despise them that are
                    good, but do indeed love and esteem them in their hearts.’ Not so: they may
                    employ them sometimes, but it is for their own profit. They may put confidence
                    in them, for they know their ways are not like other men’s. But still they love
                    them not, unless so far as the Spirit of God may be striving with them. Our
                    Saviour’s words are express: ‘If ye were of the world, the world would love its
                    own: but because ye are not of the world, […] therefore the world hateth
                        you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            15:19.</p>
                    </note> Yea (setting aside what exceptions may be made by the
                    preventing grace<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An illuminating correlation of ‘preventing’
                            (prevenient) grace and providence. But note that here, ‘preventing’ has
                            its more nearly common meaning of ‘hindering’ as well as
                            ‘anticipating’.</p>
                    </note> or the peculiar providence of God) it hateth
                    them as cordially and sincerely as ever it did their Master.</p>
                <p n="9">9. It remains only to inquire, ‘How are the children of God to behave with
                    regard to persecution?’ And first, they ought not knowingly or designedly to
                    bring it upon themselves. This is <pb n="527"/>&gt;contrary both to the example and
                    advice of our Lord and all his apostles, who teach us not only not to seek, but
                    to avoid it as far as we can without injuring our conscience, without giving up
                    any part of that righteousness which we are to prefer before life itself. So our
                    Lord expressly saith, ‘When they persecute you in this city, flee ye into
                        another’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:23.</p>
                    </note>—which is indeed, when it can be taken, the most
                    unexceptionable way of avoiding persecution.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Yet think not that you can always avoid it, either by this or any
                    other means. If ever that idle imagination steals into your heart, put it to
                    flight by that earnest caution: ‘Remember the word that I said unto you, The
                    servant is not greater than his Lord. If they have persecuted me, they will also
                    persecute you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 15:20.</p>
                    </note> ‘Be ye wise as serpents, and
                    harmless as doves.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:16.</p>
                    </note> But will this screen you
                    from persecution? Not unless you have more wisdom than your Master, or more
                    innocence than the Lamb of God.</p>
                <p>Neither desire to avoid it, to escape it wholly; for if you do, you are none of
                    his. If you escape the persecution you escape the blessing, the blessing of
                    those who are persecuted for righteousness’ sake.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:10.</p>
                    </note> If
                    you are not persecuted for righteousness’ sake you cannot enter into the kingdom
                    of heaven. ‘If we suffer with him we shall also reign with him. But if we deny
                    him he will also deny us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. Nay, rather, ‘rejoice and be exceeding glad’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:12.</p>
                    </note> when
                    men persecute you for his sake, when ‘they persecute you by reviling’ you, and
                    by ‘saying all manner of evil against you falsely’ (which they will not fail to
                    mix with every kind of persecution; they must blacken you to excuse themselves):
                    ‘for so persecuted they the prophets which were before you,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> those who were most eminently holy in heart and
                    life; yea, and all the righteous which ever have been from the beginning of the
                    world. Rejoice, because by his mark also ye know unto whom ye belong. And
                    because ‘great is your reward in heaven,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> the
                    reward purchased by the blood of the covenant, and freely bestowed in proportion
                    to your sufferings, as well as to your holiness of heart and life. ‘Be exceeding
                        glad,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> knowing that ‘these light
                    afflictions, which are but for a moment, work out for you a far more exceeding
                    and eternal weight of glory.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">
                    <pb n="528"/>12. Meantime, let no persecution turn you out of the way of
                    lowliness and meekness, of love and beneficence. ‘Ye have heard’ indeed ‘that it
                    hath been said, An eye for an eye and a tooth for a tooth.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Matt. 5,]
                                ver. 38, etc.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And your miserable teachers have hence
                    allowed you to avenge yourselves, to return evil for evil.</p>
                <p>‘But I say unto you, that ye resist not evil’—not thus: not by returning it in
                    kind. ‘But’ (rather than do this) ‘whosoever smiteth thee on thy right cheek,
                    turn to him the other also. And if any man will sue thee at the law, and take
                    away thy coat, let him have thy cloak also. And whosoever shall compel thee to
                    go a mile, go with him twain.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:39-41.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>So invincible let thy meekness be.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, I.4 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> And be thy love suitable thereto. ‘Give to him that asketh
                    thee, and from him that would borrow of thee turn not thou away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:42.</p>
                    </note> Only give not away that which is another man’s, that which
                    is not thine own. Therefore, (1). Take care to owe no man anything.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        13:8.</p>
                    </note> For what thou owest is not thy own, but another man’s. (2).
                    Provide for those of thine own household.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Tim. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> This also God
                    hath required of thee: and what is necessary to sustain them in life and
                    godliness is also not thine own. Then, (3), give or lend all that remains from
                    day to day, or from year to year: only first, seeing thou canst not give or lend
                    to all, remember the household of faith.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:10. This paragraph is an anticipation
                            of ‘give all you can…’; cf. No. 50, ‘The Use of Money’.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. The meekness and love we are to feel, the kindness we are to show to
                    them which persecute us for righteousness’ sake, our blessed Lord describes
                    farther in the following verses. O that they were graven upon our hearts!</p>
                <p>‘Ye have heard that it hath been said, Thou shalt love thy neighbour, and hate
                    thy enemy.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 43, etc.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> (God indeed had said only the former
                    part, ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Lev. 19:18, etc.</p>
                    </note> the children of the
                        devil<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 3:10.</p>
                    </note> had added the latter, ‘and hate thy enemy.’) ‘But
                    I say unto you:’ (1). ‘Love your enemies.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:43-44.</p>
                    </note> See that you bear
                    a tender <pb n="529"/>goodwill to those who are most bitter of spirit against
                    you, who wish you all manner of evil. (2). ‘Bless them that curse you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:44.</p>
                    </note> Are there any whose bitterness of spirit breaks forth in
                    bitter words? Who are continually cursing and reproaching you when you are
                    present, and ‘saying all evil against you’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:11.</p>
                    </note> when absent? So
                    much the rather do you bless. In conversing with them use all mildness and
                    softness of language. Reprove them by repeating a better lesson before them, by
                    showing them how they ought to have spoken. And in speaking of them say all the
                    good you can without violating the rules of truth and justice. (3). ‘Do good to
                    them that hate you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:44.</p>
                    </note> Let your actions show that
                    you are as real in love as they in hatred. Return good for evil. ‘Be not
                    overcome of evil, but overcome evil with good.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 12:21.</p>
                    </note> (4).
                    If you can do nothing more, at least ‘pray for them that despitefully use you
                    and persecute you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:44.</p>
                    </note> You can never be disabled
                    from doing this; nor can all their malice or violence hinder you. Pour out your
                    souls to God, not only for those who did this once but now repent. This is a
                    little thing. ‘If thy brother seven times a day turn and say unto thee, I
                    repent’—that is, if after ever so many relapses he give thee reason to believe
                    that he is really and throughly changed—then ‘thou shalt forgive him,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke
                                17:3-4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> so as to trust him, to put him in thy bosom,
                    as if he had never sinned against thee at all. But pray for, wrestle with God
                    for those that do not repent, that now despitefully use thee and persecute thee.
                    Thus far forgive them, ‘not until seven times only, but until seventy times
                        seven’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 18:22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Whether they repent or no, yea, though
                    they appear farther and farther from it, yet show them this instance of
                    kindness: ‘that ye may be the children’, that ye may approve yourselves the
                    genuine children, ‘of your Father which is in heaven’, who shows his goodness by
                    giving such blessings as they are capable of even to his stubbornest enemies;
                    who ‘maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on the good, and sendeth rain on the
                    just and on the unjust.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:45.</p>
                    </note> ‘For if ye love them which
                    love you, what reward have ye? Do not even the publicans the same?’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Matt. 5,]
                                ver. 46.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—who pretend to no religion, whom ye
                    yourselves <pb n="530"/>acknowledge to be without God in the world. ‘And if ye
                    salute’, show kindness in word or deed to ‘your brethren’, your friends or
                    kinsfolk, ‘only, what do ye more than others?’ Than those who have no religion
                    at all? ‘Do not even the publicans so?’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 47.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Nay, but
                    follow ye a better pattern than them. In patience, in longsuffering, in mercy,
                    in beneficence of every kind, to all, even to your bitterest persecutors: ‘Be
                    ye’ Christians ‘perfect’ (in kind though not in degree) even ‘as your Father
                    which is in heaven is perfect.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 48.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>IV. Behold Christianity in its native form, as delivered by its great Author!
                    This is the genuine religion of Jesus Christ. Such he presents it to him whose
                    eyes are opened. See a picture of God, so far as he is imitable by man! A
                    picture drawn by God’s own hand! ‘Behold, ye despisers, and wonder and
                        perish!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 13:41.</p>
                    </note> Or rather, wonder and adore! Rather cry out, ‘Is
                    this the religion of Jesus of Nazareth? The religion which I persecuted! Let me
                    no more be found even to fight against God. Lord, what wouldst thou have me to
                        do?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A
                            composite of echoes from Acts 22:4; 5:39; 23:9; 9:6.</p>
                    </note> What
                    beauty appears in the whole! How just a symmetry! What exact proportion in every
                    part! How desirable is the happiness here described! How venerable, how lovely
                    the holiness! This is the <hi rend="italic">spirit</hi> of religion; the
                    quintessence of it. These are indeed the <hi rend="italic">fundamentals</hi> of
                    Christianity. O that we may not be hearers of it only!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:22.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘Like a man beholding his own face in a glass, who goeth his way, and
                    straightway forgetteth what manner of man he was.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:23-24.</p>
                    </note>
                    Nay, but let us steadily ‘look into this perfect law of liberty, and continue
                        therein’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:25.</p>
                    </note> Let us not rest until every line thereof is
                    transcribed into our own hearts. Let us watch and pray and believe and love, and
                    ‘strive for the mastery’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 9:25.</p>
                    </note> till every part of it
                    shall appear in our soul, graven there by the finger of God; till we are ‘holy
                    as he which hath called us is holy’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:15.</p>
                    </note> ‘perfect as our
                    Father which is in heaven is perfect’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:48. Notice the positive reference
                            to ‘religion’ here by contrast with No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’,
                            II.4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>