<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 10: The Witness of the Spirit, Discourse I</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon010</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 10: The Witness of the Spirit, Discourse
                                I</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="267" to="284"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="267"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 10-11]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The following two essays were written and published more than twenty years apart
                    (1746, 1767), but that they belong together was recognized by Wesley in the
                    collection of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I, where they appear as Sermons
                    10 and 11. While there is no record that either of them was ever preached, the
                    evidence is abundant that their shared and central concern—the ground and
                    character of Christian assurance—was paramount in Wesley’s mind. It was also a
                    bone of contention with his critics. Already, in <hi rend="italic">A Farther
                        Appeal</hi> (1745), Pt. I, III-V, Wesley had entered the lists against men
                    like Edmund Gibson, Bishop of London, Thomas Herring, Archbishop of York, and
                    Richard Smalbroke, Bishop of Lichfield and Coventry—all of whom had understood
                    Wesley’s doctrines of assurance and of religious intuition as ‘enthusiasm’
                    (11:117-76 of this edn.). Presently, he would be denounced by George Lovington,
                    Bishop of Exeter, in <hi rend="italic">The Enthusiasm of Methodists and Papists
                        Compared</hi> (1749). It was, therefore, important in 1746 for him to
                    summarize the issues and to clarify his own position as simply and directly as
                    possible.</p>
                <p>It was clear enough that Wesley’s theory of religious knowledge was frankly
                    intuitionist, but this had been all too easily misconstrued as a one-sided
                    subjectivism. Thus, he had to clarify his distinction between the ways in which
                    assurance might be <hi rend="italic">felt</hi> (‘the witness of our own spirit’)
                    and the objective ground of any such experience (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>,
                    the prior and direct ‘witness of the Holy Spirit’). The question at issue
                    between ‘enthusiasts ’ and ‘rationalists ’ was whether a believer’s
                    consciousness of justification and reconciliation was an inference from his
                    religious and moral feeling or whether those feelings, if valid, were first
                    prompted by a free and direct testimony of the Spirit to one’s divine sonship,
                    prompting to which faith had, responded and in which hope and love could
                    participate. Characteristically, Wesley opts for a both/and solution, stressing
                    the believer’s own consciousness of God’s favour but even more strongly the
                    priority of the Spirit’s prevenient and direct witness as the <pb n="268"/>necessary precondition of any <hi rend="italic">feelings</hi> of assurance.
                    That this is the crucial point for Wesley would appear from the fact that he
                    repeats the same basic argument for it in Discourse II.</p>
                <p>The controversy was as old as second-century Montanism at least, and Wesley’s
                    balanced stress on an objective witness and a subjective one was not new. He had
                    already found a survey of it in an essay on Romans 8 by Alexander Hamilton, <hi rend="italic">A Cordial for Christians Travelling Heaven-Ward</hi> (1696).
                    Hamilton’s conclusion foreshadows Wesley’s: ‘The witness of the Spirit is a
                    twofold testimony for our sonship: by the Spirit himself and from our
                    conscience’ (p. 105). Moreover, according to Hamilton, the Spirit’s testimony is
                    conveyed conjointly, through Scripture by divine illumination, and also by the
                    Spirit’s gracious, sanctifying presence. Wesley seeks to safeguard this notion
                    from subjectivity by insisting that the gifts of the Spirit, including the gift
                    of assurance, are always to be judged by reference to the <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi> of the Spirit (Gal. 5:22-23).</p>
                <p>But why two discourses of this sort, on the same text, with most of the same
                    arguments? An answer to this must be circumstantial; it will illustrate Wesley’s
                    understanding of the sermon genre as a way of repeating himself with fresh and
                    refined nuances. Discourse I is the basic statement; it seeks a middle course
                    between ‘enthusiasm’ and ‘rationalism’ by recourse to the idea of <hi rend="italic">testimonium internum Spiritus Sancti</hi> (the inner witness
                    of the Holy Spirit), in Lutheran and Reformed traditions, linked as they had
                    been to the notion of the inspiration of the Scriptures. But what Wesley had
                    intended as a moderating formulation had drawn a storm of criticism, repeating
                    the charge of ‘enthusiasm’ and ignoring Wesley’s stress on objectivity (cf.
                    Green, <hi rend="italic">Anti-Methodist Publications</hi>, where more than
                    twenty attacks are listed on this point alone, including major essays by John
                    Parkhurst, Theophilus Evans, and William Warburton; see also Umphrey Lee, <hi rend="italic">Early Methodist Enthusiasm</hi>, and R. A. Knox, <hi rend="italic">Enthusiasm</hi>). Moreover, as the Revival was moving on into
                    its second generation, there were cases of real enthusiasm that lent credence to
                    these other criticisms (e.g., William Cudworth and James Relly). By the
                    mid-sixties, then, the time was ripe for a restatement of the doctrine of the
                    ‘twofold testimony’ and also for a rehearsal and refutation of the main
                    objections that had been raised against it over the controversy’s course.
                    Discourse II is, therefore, more than a mere sequel; it is a significant
                    revision of Discourse I. Thus, the two essays are designed to be read together
                    with one eye on the arguments themselves and the other on their theological
                    context in the ongoing Revival.</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="269"/>The edited text of Discourse II is based on that of the first
                    edition of 1767. For a stemma illustrating the transmission of that text through
                    its six extant editions issued during Wesley’s lifetime, together with the
                    substantive variant readings from those editions, see the Appendix, Vol. IV. For
                    further details see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 303.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Witness of the Spirit, I</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 8:16</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The Spirit itself beareth witness with our spirit, that we are
                        the children of God.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. How many vain men, not understanding what they speak, neither whereof
                    they affirmed, have wrested this Scripture to the great loss if not the
                    destruction of their souls! How many have mistaken the voice of their own
                    imagination for this ‘witness of the Spirit’ of God, and thence idly presumed
                    they were the children of God while they were doing the works of the devil!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        3:8.</p>
                    </note> These are truly and properly <hi rend="italic">enthusiasts</hi>; and, indeed, in the worst sense of the word.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley would have
                            had in mind here the long tradition of this idea in Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>, and its history from the Messalians
                            (fourth century) through the Joachimites (thirteenth century), the
                            German ‘Schwärmer’ (sixteenth century), the ‘French prophets’
                            (eighteenth century), <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>; cf. Umphrey Lee,
                                <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> But since Wesley himself lay under
                            the constant charge of ‘enthusiast’ himself, he was careful to formulate
                            a positive alternative; cf. No. 37, ‘The Nature of Enthusiasm’. Cf. also
                            the claim in Bishop Smalbroke’s <hi rend="italic">Charge…to…the
                                Clergy</hi> (1744) that ‘the witness of the Spirit…cannot possibly
                            be applied to the private testimony of the Spirit given to our
                            consciences, as is pretended by modern enthusiasts’ (i.e., Methodists),
                            and Wesley’s reply in <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt I,
                            V.4-29 (11:141-73 of this edn.). Cf. also No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, II.13 and n.</p>
                    </note> But with what difficulty are they
                    convinced thereof, especially if they have drank deep into that spirit of
                        error!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            4:6.</p>
                    </note> All endeavours to bring them to the knowledge of
                    themselves they will then account ‘fighting against God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 5:39.</p>
                    </note> And that
                    vehemence and impetuosity of spirit which they call ‘contending earnestly for
                    the faith’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jude 3.</p>
                    </note> sets them so far above all the <pb n="270"/>usual
                    methods of conviction that we may well say, ‘With men it is impossible.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 10:27; cf.
                            Matt. 19:26.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Who can then be surprised if many reasonable men, seeing the dreadful
                    effects of this delusion, and labouring to keep at the utmost distance from it,
                    should sometimes lean toward another extreme? If they are not forward to believe
                    any who speak of having this witness concerning which others have so grievously
                    erred; if they are almost ready to set all down for ‘enthusiasts’ who use the
                    expressions which have been so terribly abused? Yea, if they should question
                    whether the witness or testimony here spoken of be the privilege of <hi rend="italic">ordinary</hi> Christians, and not rather one of those <hi rend="italic">extraordinary</hi> gifts which they suppose belonged only to
                    the apostolic age?</p>
                <p n="3">3. But is there any necessity laid upon us of running either into one
                    extreme or the other? May we not steer a middle course? Keep a sufficient
                    distance from that spirit of error and enthusiasm without denying the gift of
                    God and giving up the great privilege of his children? Surely we may. In order
                    thereto, let us consider, in the presence and fear of God,</p>
                <p><!--Decide if and how to number subsequent paragraphs unnumbered by Wesley.-->First:
                    What is this ‘witness (or testimony) of our spirit’? What is the ‘testimony of
                    God’s Spirit’? And how does he ‘bear witness with our spirit that we are the
                    children of God’?</p>
                <p>Secondly: How is this joint testimony of God’s Spirit and our own clearly and
                    solidly distinguished from the presumption of a natural mind, and from the
                    delusion of the devil?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. Let us first consider, what is the ‘witness’ or ‘testimony of our
                    spirit’? But here I cannot but desire all those who are for swallowing up the
                    testimony of the Spirit of God in the rational testimony of our own spirit to
                    observe that in this text the Apostle is so far from speaking of the testimony
                    of our own spirit <hi rend="italic">only</hi>, that it may be questioned whether
                    he speaks of it <hi rend="italic">at all</hi>—whether he does not speak <hi rend="italic">only</hi> of the testimony of God’s Spirit. It does not appear
                    but the original text may fairly be understood thus. The Apostle had just said,
                    in the preceding verse, ‘Ye have received the Spirit of adoption, whereby we
                    cry, Abba, Father,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> and immediately subjoins,
                    Αὐτὸ τὸ πνεῦμα (some copies read τὸ αὐτὸ πνεῦμα) συμμαρτυρεῖ τῷ πνεύματι ἡμῶν,
                    ὅτι <pb n="271"/>ἐσμὲν τέκνα
                        θεοῦ;<!--Identify this Greek with an xml:lang later.-->
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A more complicated point than
                            first appears; there are no early Greek texts that read τὸ αὐτὸ πνεῦμα,
                            and it does not appear in the <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>. However, four
                            sixteenth-century English translations read ‘the same Spirit’ instead of
                            ‘the Spirit himself’: (Tyndale [1525, 1535], Coverdale [1535], the Great
                            Bible [1539], the Geneva Bible [1560]). Moreover, Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Römerbriefvorlesung</hi> and his <hi rend="italic">Deutsche Bibel</hi> read ‘<hi rend="italic">derselbige Geist</hi>’
                            (‘the same Spirit’). Only the Douai-Rheims (1582), the Bishops’ Bible
                            (1568, 1602), and the King James (1611) read ‘the Spirit himself’. In
                            his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Wesley reads ‘the same spirit’ just as
                            John Heylyn did in his <hi rend="italic">Theological Lectures</hi>.
                            Bengel, however, had the <hi rend="italic">TR</hi> before him and still
                            read ‘the Spirit himself’.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">The key to these
                            variations would seem to lie in Erasmus’s Latin translation in his
                            Greek-Latin edn. of 1518-19, where we find <hi rend="italic">idem
                                spiritus</hi> in place of the Vulgate’s <hi rend="italic">ipse
                                spiritus</hi>. In his Greek edn. of 1589 Beza notices Erasmus’s <hi rend="italic">idem spiritus</hi> and back-translates τὸ αὐτὸ πνεῦμα;
                            this is the only Greek text with such a reading that I have found. Could
                            Wesley have seen this edn. or have heard this textual problem discussed
                            in a lecture or conversation?</p>
                    </note> which may be translated, ‘The
                    same Spirit beareth witness to our spirit that we are the children of God’ (the
                    preposition σύν only denoting that he witnesses this <hi rend="italic">at the
                        same time</hi> that he enables us to cry, ‘Abba, Father!’).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s
                            unwillingness to contend for this particular exegesis of σύν is
                            warranted; it is more curious than correct.</p>
                    </note> But I contend
                    not; seeing so many other texts, with the experience of all real Christians,
                    sufficiently evince that there is in every believer both the testimony of God’s
                    Spirit, and the testimony of his own, that he is a child of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. With regard to the latter, the foundation thereof is laid in those
                    numerous texts of Scripture which describe the marks of the children of God; and
                    that so plain that he which runneth may read them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Hab. 2:2.</p>
                    </note> These
                    are also collected together, and placed in the strongest light, by many both
                    ancient and modern writers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John Owen, <hi rend="italic">Of Communion With
                                God</hi> (1657), Pt. III. ii (espec. §4); see also Arthur Bedford’s
                            sermon on <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Assurance…</hi>, Appendix,
                            p. 35.</p>
                    </note> If any need farther light he may receive it by
                    attending on the ministry of God’s Word, by meditating thereon before God in
                    secret, and by conversing with those who have the knowledge of his ways. And by
                    the reason or understanding that God has given him—which religion was designed
                    not to extinguish, but to perfect, according to that [word] of the Apostle,
                    ‘Brethren, be not children in understanding; in malice (or wickedness) be ye
                    children; but in understanding be ye men.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 14:20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Every
                    man applying those scriptural marks to himself may know whether he is a child of
                    God. Thus if he know, first, ‘As many as are led by the Spirit of God’ into all
                        <pb n="272"/>holy tempers and actions, ‘they are the sons of God’ (for which
                    he has the infallible assurance of Holy Writ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:14.</p>
                    </note>); secondly, I am
                    thus ‘led by the Spirit of God’—he will easily conclude, ‘Therefore I am a “son
                    of God”.’</p>
                <p n="3">3. Agreeable to this are all those plain declarations of St. John in his
                    First Epistle, ‘Hereby we know that we do know him, if we keep his
                        commandments.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[1 John] 2:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Whoso keepeth his
                    word, in him verily is the love of God perfected; hereby know we that we are in
                        him’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—that we are indeed the children of God. ‘If
                    ye know that he is righteous, ye know that everyone that doth righteousness is
                    born of him.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 29.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘We know that we have
                    passed from death unto life, because we love the brethren.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Chap. 3,
                                ver. 14.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Hereby we know that we are of the truth,
                    and shall assure our hearts before him;’ namely, because we ‘love’ one another
                    not ‘in word, neither in tongue; but in deed and in truth’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                18.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Hereby know we that we dwell in him, …because
                    he hath given us of his (loving) Spirit.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Chap. 4, ver. 13.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    And, ‘Hereby we know that he abideth in us, by the (obedient) spirit which he
                    hath given us.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Chap. 3, ver. 24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. It is highly probable there never were any children of God, from the
                    beginning of the world unto this day, who were farther advanced in the grace of
                    God and the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ than the Apostle John at the time
                    when he wrote these words, and the ‘fathers in Christ’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:13,
                        14.</p>
                    </note> to whom he wrote. Notwithstanding which, it is evident both
                    the Apostle himself and all those pillars in God’s temple<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> were
                    very far from despising these marks of their being the children of God; and that
                    they applied them to their own souls for the confirmation of their faith Yet all
                    this is no other than rational evidence: the ‘witness of our spirit’, our reason
                    or understanding. It all resolves into this: those who have these marks, they
                    are the children of God. But we have these marks: therefore we are children of
                    God.</p>
                <p n="5">5. But how does it appear that we have these marks?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For this usage of ‘how does it
                            appear’ as equivalent to ‘how is it made evident’, cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, ‘appear’, 9.</p>
                    </note> This is a question which still
                    remains. How does it appear that we do love <pb n="273"/>God and our neighbour?
                    And that we keep his commandments? Observe that the meaning of the question is,
                    How does it appear to <hi rend="italic">ourselves</hi>—not to <hi rend="italic">others</hi>. I would ask him then that proposes this question, How does it
                    appear to you that you are alive?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Another instance of Wesley’s direct intuitionism in
                            spiritual knowledge; it presupposes self-awareness as self-evident. But
                            subjective consciousness must always be correlated with outward
                                marks—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, good works: love in action to God
                            and to neighbour.</p>
                    </note> And that you are now in ease and not in
                    pain? Are you not immediately conscious of it? By the same immediate
                    consciousness you will know if your soul is alive to God; if you are saved from
                    the pain of proud wrath, and have the ease of a meek and quiet spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        3:4.</p>
                    </note> By the same means you cannot but perceive if you love,
                    rejoice, and delight in God. By the same you must be directly assured if you
                    love your neighbour as yourself;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 19:19, etc.</p>
                    </note> if you are kindly
                    affectioned to all mankind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:10.</p>
                    </note> and full of gentleness
                    and longsuffering. And with regard to the outward mark of the children of God,
                    which is (according to St. John) the keeping his commandments, you undoubtedly
                    know in your own breast if, by the grace of God, it belongs to you. Your
                    conscience informs you from day to day if you do not take the name of God within
                    your lips unless with seriousness and devotion, with reverence and godly fear;
                    if you remember the sabbath day to keep it holy;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:8.</p>
                    </note> if you
                    honour your father and mother;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 20:12.</p>
                    </note> if you do to all as you
                    would they should do unto you;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:12; Luke 6:31.</p>
                    </note> if you
                    possess your body in sanctification and honour;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess. 4:4.</p>
                    </note> and if, whether
                    you eat or drink, you are temperate therein, and do all to the glory of
                        God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Cor. 10:31.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Now this is properly the ‘testimony of our own spirit’, even the
                    testimony of our conscience,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The Puritans had been much concerned with both ‘the
                            testimony of conscience’ and the careful ‘examination of conscience’.
                            Cf. William Perkins, <hi rend="italic">A Case of Conscience, the
                                greatest that ever was: How a man may know whether he be the child
                                of God, or no…</hi> (1595). See also his <hi rend="italic">Discourse
                                of Conscience…</hi> (1597), along with William Ames, <hi rend="italic">Conscience, with the power and cases thereof…</hi>
                            (1643), Richard Alleine, <hi rend="italic">Vindiciae Pietatis</hi>
                            (1676), and Samuel Annesley’s sermon on ‘How We May Be Universally and
                            Exactly Conscientious’, in <hi rend="italic">The Morning Exercise at
                                Cripplegate</hi> (1661). Richard Baxter had distinguished the <hi rend="italic">forum conscientiae</hi> from the <hi rend="italic">forum Dei</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Confession</hi> (1655), p.
                            189; Robert South had used the phrase, <hi rend="italic">forum
                                conscientiae</hi>, in ‘The Remorse Occasioned by the Rejection of
                            Christ’ (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.403). See also Wesley’s
                            fourth letter to ‘John Smith’ (Mar. 25, 1747), espec. §§6-7, and his
                            sermon No. 105, ‘On Conscience’.</p>
                    </note> that God hath given us to be
                    holy of heart, and holy in outward conversation. It is a <pb n="274"/>consciousness of our having received, in and by the Spirit of adoption, the
                    tempers mentioned in the Word of God as belonging to his adopted children; even
                    a loving heart toward God and toward all mankind, hanging with childlike
                    confidence on God our Father, desiring nothing but him, casting all our care
                    upon him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Pet. 5:7.</p>
                    </note> and embracing every child of man with earnest,
                    tender affection, so as to be ready to lay down our life for our brother, as
                    Christ laid down his life for us<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 3:16.</p>
                    </note>—a consciousness that we
                    are inwardly conformed by the Spirit of God to the image of his Son, and that we
                    walk before him in justice, mercy, and truth; doing the things which are
                    pleasing in his sight.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 3:22.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. But what is that testimony of God’s Spirit which is superadded to and
                    conjoined with this? How does he ‘bear witness with our spirit that we are the
                    children of God’? It is hard to find words in the language of men to explain
                    ‘the deep things of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> Indeed there are none that
                    will adequately express what the children of God experience. But perhaps one
                    might say (desiring any who are taught of God to correct, to soften or
                    strengthen the expression), the testimony of the Spirit is an inward impression
                    on the soul, whereby the Spirit of God directly ‘witnesses to my spirit that I
                    am a child of God’; that Jesus Christ hath loved me, and given himself for
                        me;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal.
                            2:20.</p>
                    </note> that all my sins are blotted out,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 3:19.</p>
                    </note> and
                    I, even I, am reconciled to God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:20. Cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’,
                            IV.2 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. That this ‘testimony of the Spirit of God’ must needs, in the very
                    nature of things, be antecedent to the ‘testimony of our own spirit’ may appear
                    from this single consideration: we must be holy of heart and holy in life before
                    we can be conscious that we are so, before we can have ‘the testimony of our
                    spirit’ that we are inwardly and outwardly holy. But we must love God before we
                    can be holy at all; this being the root of all holiness. Now we cannot love God
                    till we know he loves us: ‘We love him, because he first loved us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        4:19.</p>
                    </note> And we cannot know his pardoning love to us till his Spirit
                    witnesses it to our spirit. Since therefore this ‘testimony of his Spirit’ must
                    precede the love of God and all holiness, of consequence it must precede our
                    inward <pb n="275"/>consciousness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This reflects a shift (in 1738 and thereafter) from
                            Wesley’s earlier notion that holiness, in some degree and as intention,
                            normally precedes justification in the <hi rend="italic">ordo
                                salutis</hi>. Here assurance (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, of
                            pardon) ‘must precede [our awareness] of the love of God and all
                            holiness’. Note the stress on the <hi rend="italic">objective</hi>
                            aspects of the Spirit’s prevenient action as the precondition of
                            subjective experience. Cf. No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi>, II.6 and n.</p>
                    </note> thereof, or the ‘testimony of
                    our spirit’ concerning them.</p>
                <p n="9">9. Then, and not till then—when the Spirit of God beareth that witness to
                    our spirit, ‘God hath loved thee and given his own Son to be the propitiation
                    for thy sins;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:10.</p>
                    </note> ‘the Son of God hath loved thee, and hath
                    washed thee from thy sins in his blood’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 1:5.</p>
                    </note>—‘we love God, because
                    he first loved us,’ and for his sake we ‘love our brother also’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:19,
                            21.</p>
                    </note> And of this we cannot but be conscious to ourselves: we
                    ‘know the things that are freely given to us of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> we
                    know that we love God and keep his commandments; and hereby also ‘we know that
                    we are of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:19.</p>
                    </note> This is that testimony of our own spirit which,
                    so long as we continue to love God and keep his commandments, continues joined
                    with the testimony of God’s Spirit, ‘that we are the children of God’.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Not that I would by any means be understood by anything which has been
                    spoken concerning it to exclude the operation of the Spirit of God, even from
                    the ‘testimony of our own spirit’. In no wise. It is he that not only worketh in
                    us every manner of thing that is good, but also shines upon his own work, and
                    clearly shows what he has wrought. Accordingly this is spoken of by St. Paul as
                    one great end of our receiving the Spirit, ‘that we may know the things which
                    are freely given to us of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> that he may strengthen the
                    testimony of our conscience touching our ‘simplicity and godly sincerity’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        1:12.</p>
                    </note> and give us to discern in a fuller and stronger light that
                    we now do the things which please him.</p>
                <p n="11">11. Should it still be inquired, ‘How does the Spirit of God “bear witness
                    with our spirit that we are the children of God” so as to exclude all doubt, and
                    evince the reality of our sonship?’—the answer is clear from what has been
                    observed above. And, first, as to the witness of our spirit: the soul as
                    intimately and evidently perceives when it loves, delights, and rejoices in God,
                    as when it loves and delights in anything on earth; and it can no more doubt
                    whether it loves, delights, and rejoices, <pb n="276"/>or no, than whether it
                    exists, or no. If therefore this be just reasoning:</p>
                <p><!--Decide if and how to number subsequent paragraphs unnumbered by Wesley.-->He
                    that now loves God—that delights and rejoices in him with an humble joy, an holy
                    delight, and an obedient love—is a child of God;</p>
                <p>But I thus love, delight, and rejoice in God;</p>
                <p>Therefore I am a child of God;</p>
                <p>then a Christian can in no wise doubt of his being a child of God. Of the former
                    proposition he has as full an assurance as he has that the Scriptures are of
                    God. And of his thus loving God he has an inward proof, which is nothing short
                    of self-evidence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Another instance of an either/or notion of
                            assurance which Wesley will later soften to allow for <hi rend="italic">degrees</hi> of assurance; see above, No. 3, ‘<hi rend="italic">Awake, Thou That Sleepest</hi>’, III.6 and n.</p>
                    </note> Thus the
                    ‘testimony of our own spirit’ is with the most intimate conviction manifested to
                    our hearts; in such a manner as beyond all reasonable doubt to evince the
                    reality of our sonship.</p>
                <p n="12">12. The <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> how the divine testimony is
                    manifested to the heart I do not take upon me to explain. ‘Such knowledge is too
                    wonderful and excellent for me; I cannot attain unto it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 139:5 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘The wind bloweth; and I hear the sound thereof’; but I cannot ‘tell how it
                    cometh, or whither it goeth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:8.</p>
                    </note> As no one knoweth the
                    things of a man save the spirit of a man that is in him, so the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of the things of God knoweth no one save the
                    Spirit of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 2:11.</p>
                    </note> But the fact we know: namely, that the
                    Spirit of God does give a believer such a testimony of his adoption that while
                    it is present to the soul he can no more doubt the reality of his sonship than
                    he can doubt of the shining of the sun while he stands in the full blaze of his
                        beams.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">What
                            is here presupposed is Wesley’s whole theory of religious knowledge with
                            its notion of a ‘spiritual sensorium’ analogous to our physical senses
                            and responsive to prior initiatives of the Holy Spirt. Typically, it is
                            passive until acted upon by spiritual stimuli—e.g., divine light arouses
                            our latent capacities for ‘sight’ and insight; revelation prompts us to
                            insight and knowledge—always, however, as ‘re-actions’ to initiatives
                            beyond ourselves. Thus, no matter how intensely subjective our feelings
                            may be in religious experiences, their source is prevenient, and in that
                            sense, objective.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">This, then, is Wesley’s
                            version of the intuitionist views of Christian Platonism as he had known
                            that tradition from the Alexandrines, Bonaventura, the Cambridge
                            Platonists, Malebranche, and, especially John Norris of Bemerton. It
                            allowed him, without internal contradiction, to follow St. Thomas and
                            John Locke in his theories of empirical knowledge (cf. No. 117, ‘On the
                            Discoveries of Faith’, §1 and n.) and yet also to distinguish all such
                            knowledge from our spiritual knowledge of God and ‘of the deep things of
                            God’ (cf. 1 Cor. 2:10). This distinction, and its epistemological
                            import, are pervasive throughout the Wesley corpus: cf. Nos. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Steepest’</hi>, I.11; 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, III.5; 9, ‘The Spirit of
                            Bondage and of Adoption’, I.1; also, below, §II.9; 12, ‘The Witness of
                            Our Own Spirit’, §§8,18; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born
                            of God’, I.4; 23, ‘Sermon on the Mount, III’, I.6ff.; 34, ‘The Original,
                            Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law’, I.5; 36, ‘The Law Established
                            through Faith, II’, II.4; 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of
                                Salvation</hi>, II.1; 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, II.2;
                            45, ‘The New Birth’, II.4; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, I.3, III.1;
                            69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, §§ 3-4; 71, ‘Of Good Angels’,
                            I.2; 96, ‘On Obedience to Parents’, §1; 117, ‘On the Discoveries of
                            Faith’, §§1-2; 118, ‘On the Omnipresence of God’, II.8; 119, ‘Walking by
                            Sight and Walking by Faith’, §§1-2, 8, 11-12; 120, ‘The Unity of the
                            Divine Being’, §2; 125, ‘On a Single Eye’, I.2; 130, ‘On Living without
                            God’, §9; 132, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §18; 140, ‘The Promise of
                            Understanding’, III. 2.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also his letter
                            to Dr. Robertson, Sept. 24, 1753 (which seems contrary to his general
                            theory); his letter to Richard Tompson, Mar. 16, 1756; and to Miss
                            March, July 1, 1772; to Elizabeth Ritchie, Aug. 12, 1776; and to Joseph
                            Benson, May 21, 1781. Cf. his <hi rend="italic">Earnest Appeal</hi>,
                            §§34-37 (11: 57-58 of this edn.); his <hi rend="italic">Farther
                                Appeal</hi>, Pt. I, I.4, V.28 (11:106-7, 171-72). Also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 13:14; <hi rend="italic">A Short
                                Address to the Inhabitants of Ireland</hi>, §6 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 167, Vol. 9 of this edn.; ‘Of the Gradual
                            Improvement of Natural Philosophy’, §24 (<hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>,
                            I.21). Cf. also Jonathan Edwards, <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on
                                Religious Affections</hi>, Pt. II (see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 334, Vol. 16 of this edn.); Lucas, <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi>, III.79, 198; and Lee,
                                <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, pp. 140-41.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">
                    <pb n="277"/>II. 1. How this joint testimony of God’s Spirit and our spirit
                    may be clearly and solidly distinguished from the presumption of a natural mind,
                    and from the delusion of the devil, is the next thing to be considered. And it
                    highly imports all who desire the salvation of God to consider it with the
                    deepest attention, as they would not deceive their own souls. An error in this
                    is generally observed to have the most fatal consequences; the rather, because
                    he that errs seldom discovers his mistake till it is too late to remedy it.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And, first, How is this testimony to be distinguished from the
                    presumption of a natural mind? It is certain, one who was never convinced of sin
                    is always ready to flatter himself, and to think of himself, especially in
                    spiritual things, more highly than he ought to think.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:3.</p>
                    </note> And
                    hence it is in no wise strange if one who is vainly puffed up by his fleshly
                    mind, when he hears of this privilege of true Christians, among whom he
                    undoubtedly ranks himself, should soon work himself up into a persuasion that he
                    is already possessed thereof. Such instances now abound in the world, and have
                    abounded in all ages. How then may the real testimony of the Spirit with our
                    spirit be distinguished from this damning presumption?</p>
                <p n="3">3. I answer, the Holy Scriptures abound with marks whereby <pb n="278"/>the
                    one may be distinguished from the other. They describe in the plainest manner
                    the circumstances which go before, which accompany, and which follow, the true,
                    genuine testimony of the Spirit of God with the spirit of a believer. Whoever
                    carefully weighs and attends to these will not need to put darkness for
                        light.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                            5:20.</p>
                    </note> He will perceive so wide a difference with respect to
                    all these, between the real and the pretended witness of the Spirit, that there
                    will be no danger—I might say, no possibility—of confounding the one with the
                    other.</p>
                <p n="4">4. By these, one who vainly presumes on the gift of God might surely know,
                    if he really desired it, that he hath been hitherto ‘given up to a strong
                    delusion’ and suffered to ‘believe a lie’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 2:11.</p>
                    </note> For the
                    Scriptures lay down those clear, obvious marks as preceding, accompanying, and
                    following that gift, which a little reflection would convince him, beyond all
                    doubt, were never found in his soul. For instance, the Scripture describes
                    repentance, or conviction of sin, as constantly going before this witness of
                    pardon. So, ‘Repent; for the kingdom of heaven is at hand.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt.
                                3:2.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Repent ye, and believe the Gospel.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Mark
                                1:15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Repent, and be baptized every one of you…for
                    the remission of sins.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 2:38.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Repent ye therefore,
                    and be converted, that your sins may be blotted out.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Acts]
                                3:19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> In conformity whereto our Church also
                    continually places repentance before pardon or the witness of it: ‘He pardoneth
                    and absolveth all them that truly repent and unfeignedly believe his holy
                        gospel.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Morning Prayer, Absolution (4).</p>
                    </note> ‘Almighty God…hath
                    promised forgiveness of sins to all them who with hearty repentance and true
                    faith turn unto him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>, Communion, Absolution
                            (349). Pardon precedes assurance, but repentance precedes pardon. Here,
                            repentance (as self-knowledge of one’s sinful state, plus a hope for
                            pardon and amendment of life) is a fruit of the Spirit’s prevenient
                            stimulus; this gives the discussion of the antecedent conditions of
                            justification by faith a distinctive Anglican nuance.</p>
                    </note> But he
                    is a stranger even to this repentance. He hath never known ‘a broken and a
                    contrite heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 51:17.</p>
                    </note> The remembrance of his sins’ was never ‘grievous
                    unto’ him, nor ‘the burden of them intolerable’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Communion, Confession
                            (348).</p>
                    </note> In repeating those words he never meant what he <pb n="279"/>said; he merely paid a compliment to God. And were it only from the
                    want of this previous work of God he hath too great reason to believe that he
                    hath grasped a mere shadow, and never yet known the real privilege of the sons
                    of God.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Again, the Scriptures describe the being born of God, which must precede
                    the witness that we are his children, as a vast and mighty change, a change
                    ‘from darkness to light’, as well as ‘from the power of Satan unto God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        26:18.</p>
                    </note> as a ‘passing from death unto life’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 5:24; 1 John
                            3:14.</p>
                    </note> a resurrection from the dead. Thus the Apostle to the
                    Ephesians: ‘You hath he quickened, who were dead in trespasses and sins.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Eph.
                                2:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And again, ‘When we were dead in sins, he hath
                    quickened us together with Christ; …and hath raised us up together, and made us
                    sit together in heavenly places in Christ Jesus.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 5, 6.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> But
                    what knoweth he concerning whom we now speak of any such change as this? He is
                    altogether unacquainted with this whole matter. This is a language which he does
                    not understand. He tells you he always was a Christian. He knows no time when he
                    had need of such a change. By this also, if he give himself leave to think, may
                    he know that he is not born of the Spirit;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:6, 8.</p>
                    </note> that he has never yet
                    known God, but has mistaken the voice of nature for the voice of God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. But waiving the consideration of whatever he has or has not experienced
                    in time past, by the present marks may we easily distinguish a child of God from
                    a presumptuous self-deceiver. The Scriptures describe that joy in the Lord which
                    accompanies the witness of his Spirit as an humble joy, a joy that abases to the
                    dust; that makes a pardoned sinner cry out, ‘I am vile!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 40:4.</p>
                    </note> What am I
                    or my father’s house?—Now mine eye seeth thee I abhor myself in dust and
                        ashes!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Job 42:5-6.</p>
                    </note> And wherever lowliness is, there is meekness,
                    patience, gentleness, long-suffering.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 5:22-23.</p>
                    </note> There is a soft,
                    yielding spirit, a mildness and sweetness, a tenderness of soul which words
                    cannot express.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 97, ‘On Obedience to Pastors’, III.3; 100, ‘On Pleasing All
                            Men’, II.3; 108, ‘On Riches’, I.6-7; 120, ‘The Unity of the Divine
                            Being’, §22. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, especially for Phil.
                            4:5 and Jas. 3:17.</p>
                    </note> But do these fruits attend that <hi rend="italic">supposed</hi> testimony of the Spirit in a presumptuous man?
                    Just the <pb n="280"/>reverse. The more confident he is of the favour of God,
                    the more is he lifted up. The more does he exalt himself, the more haughty and
                    assuming is his whole behaviour. The stronger witness he imagines himself to
                    have, the more overbearing is he to all around him, the more incapable of
                    receiving any reproof, the more impatient of contradiction. Instead of being
                    more meek, and gentle, and teachable, more ‘swift to hear, and slow to
                        speak’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                            1:19.</p>
                    </note> he is more slow to hear and swift to speak, more
                    unready to learn of anyone, more fiery and vehement in his temper, and eager in
                    his conversation. Yea, perhaps, there will sometimes appear a kind of fierceness
                    in his air, his manner of speaking, his whole deportment, as if he were just
                    going to take the matter out of God’s hands, and himself to ‘devour the
                        adversaries’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:27.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Once more: the Scriptures teach, ‘This is the love of God’ (the sure
                    mark thereof) ‘that we keep his commandments.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 5:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And our
                    Lord himself saith, ‘He that keepeth my commandments, he it is that loveth
                        me.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John 14:21.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Love rejoices to obey, to do in every
                    point whatever is acceptable to the Beloved.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> A true lover of God
                    hastens to do his will on earth as it is done in heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 6:10; Luke
                        11:2.</p>
                    </note> But is this the character of the presumptuous pretender to
                    the love of God? Nay, but his love gives him a liberty to disobey, to break, not
                    keep, the commandments of God. Perhaps when he was in fear of the wrath of God
                    he did labour to do his will. But now, looking on himself as ‘not under the
                        law’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            6:14, 15.</p>
                    </note> he thinks he is no longer obliged to observe it He
                    is therefore less zealous of good works,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p>
                    </note> less careful to abstain
                    from evil, less watchful over his own heart, less jealous over his tongue. He is
                    less earnest to deny himself, and to take up his cross daily.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 9:23.</p>
                    </note> In a
                    word, the whole form of his life is changed since he has fancied himself to be
                    ‘at liberty’. He is no longer ‘exercising himself unto godliness’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim.
                            4:7.</p>
                    </note> ‘wrestling not only with flesh and blood, but with
                    principalities and powers’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:12.</p>
                    </note> ‘enduring
                        hardships’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 2:3.</p>
                    </note> ‘agonizing to enter in at the strait
                        gate’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            13:24; cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p>
                    </note> No; he has found an
                    easier way to heaven: a broad, smooth, flowery path, in which he can say to his
                    soul, ‘Soul, take thy ease; <pb n="281"/>eat, drink, and be merry.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            12:19.</p>
                    </note> It follows with undeniable evidence that he has not
                    the true testimony of his own spirit. He cannot be conscious of having those
                    marks which he hath not, that lowliness, meekness, and obedience. Nor yet can
                    the Spirit of the God of truth bear witness to a lie; or testify that he is a
                    child of God when he is manifestly a child of the devil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts 13:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. Discover thyself, thou poor self-deceiver! Thou who art confident of
                    being a child of God; thou who sayest, ‘I have the witness in myself,’ and
                    therefore defiest all thy enemies. Thou art weighed in the balance and found
                        wanting,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Dan. 5:27.</p>
                    </note> even in the balance of the sanctuary.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A familiar
                            metaphor at that time signifying an earnest reflection upon a problem in
                            the light of Holy Scripture and in the conscious presence of God (<hi rend="italic">coram Deo</hi>). Wesley would have known it from such
                            sources as William Perkins, <hi rend="italic">A Golden Chaine</hi>,
                            where in his preface to the 2nd edn. of 1597 Perkins had written: ‘This
                            treatise being thus finished, I commit it to the weight of the ballance
                            of the Sanctuarie…’. But see also Norris, <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies</hi>, p. 184; Boston, State IV, Head VI; South, <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi> (1823), 7:319. The phrase turns up in
                            Wesley’s ‘Preface’, §7, ‘Extracts from the Works of the Puritans’
                            (beginning with Bishop Joseph Hall’s <hi rend="italic">Meditations and
                                Vows</hi>), in the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, VII;
                            Nathaniel Culverwell, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, XVII.104; and Samuel
                            Clarke, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, XXVI.171. The Quakers seem to have
                            used it to denote the ‘inner light’, as in John Perrot, <hi rend="italic">An Epistle for the Most Pure Amity and Unity in the
                                Spirit and Life of God to All Sincere-hearted Souls</hi> (1662):
                            ‘Hear…the sound of the Spirit’s voice…and let it enter into the balance
                            of the sanctuary within you.’ Littré, <hi rend="italic">Dictionnaire de
                                la Langue Francaise</hi>, III. 1683, refers the phrase to ‘a
                            conventional Jewish usage meaning the standard weights and scales kept
                            in the Temple and supervised by the Temple priests’, and cites
                            Bourdaloue, Saci, and Fénelon as having borrowed it from thence; cf.
                            William G. Braude, ed. and tr., ‘Moses’s Journey Through Heaven’, Piska
                            20, in <hi rend="italic">Pesikta Rabbati: Discourses for Feasts, Fasts
                                and Special Sabbaths</hi> (New Haven, Yale University Press, 1968),
                            p. 401.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">It was a favourite figure of Wesley’s
                            and may first be found in his sermon ‘Wiser than the Children of Light’,
                            §III (No. 147, below); see also JWJ, June 4, 1742; Nos. 32, ‘Sermon on
                            the Mount XII’, III.9; 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’, III.2; see also <hi rend="italic">Predestination Calmly Considered</hi>, §7; and his
                            letter to Jasper Robinson, Nov. 17, 1790.</p>
                    </note> The Word of the
                    Lord hath tried thy soul, and proved thee to be reprobate silver.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., worthless,
                            inferior, or impure (<hi rend="italic">OED</hi>). Cf. Jer.
                        6:30.</p>
                    </note> Thou art not lowly of heart; therefore thou hast not
                    received the Spirit of Jesus unto this day. Thou art not gentle and meek;
                    therefore thy joy is nothing worth: it is not joy in the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Philem. 20.</p>
                    </note>
                    Thou dost not keep his commandments; therefore thou lovest him not, neither art
                    thou partaker of the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 6:4.</p>
                    </note> It is consequently as
                    certain and as evident as the oracles of God can make it, his Spirit doth not
                    bear witness with thy spirit that thou art a child of God. O cry unto him, that
                    the scales may fall off thine eyes;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 9:18.</p>
                    </note> that thou mayst know
                    thyself as <pb n="282"/>thou art known;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 13:12.</p>
                    </note> that thou mayst
                    receive the sentence of death in thyself, till thou hear the voice that raises
                    the dead, saying, ‘Be of good cheer; thy sins are forgiven; thy faith hath made
                    thee whole.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 9:2, 22, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘But how may one who has the real witness in himself distinguish it from
                    presumption?’ How, I pray, do you distinguish day from night? How do you
                    distinguish light from darkness? Or the light of a star, or glimmering taper,
                    from the light of the noonday sun? Is there not an inherent, obvious, essential
                    difference between the one and the other? And do you not immediately and
                    directly perceive that difference, provided your senses are rightly disposed? In
                    like manner, there is an inherent, essential difference between spiritual light
                    and spiritual darkness; and between the light wherewith the sun of
                        righteousness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mal. 4:2.</p>
                    </note> shines upon our heart, and
                    that glimmering light which arises only from ‘sparks of our own kindling’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            50:11.</p>
                    </note> And this difference also is immediately and directly
                    perceived, if our spiritual senses are rightly disposed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.12 and n.; also
                            No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and
                    n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. To require a more minute and philosophical account of the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> whereby we distinguish these, and of the <hi rend="italic">criteria</hi> or intrinsic marks whereby we know the voice of
                    God, is to make a demand which can never be answered; no, not by one who has the
                    deepest knowledge of God. Suppose, when Paul answered before Agrippa,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        26.</p>
                    </note> the wise Roman had said: ‘Thou talkest of hearing the voice
                    of the Son of God. How dost thou know it was his voice? By what <hi rend="italic">criteria</hi>, what intrinsic marks, dost thou know the voice
                    of God? Explain to me the <hi rend="italic">manner</hi> of distinguishing this
                    from a human or angelic voice.’ Can you believe the Apostle himself would have
                    once attempted to answer so idle a demand? And yet doubtless the moment he heard
                    that voice he knew it was the voice of God. But <hi rend="italic">how</hi> he
                    knew this who is able to explain? Perhaps neither man nor angel.</p>
                <p n="11">11. To come yet closer: suppose God were now to speak to any soul, ‘Thy
                    sins are forgiven thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 9:2, 5, etc.</p>
                    </note> He must be willing
                    that soul should know his voice; otherwise he would speak in vain. And he is
                    able to effect this, for whenever he wills, to do is present with <pb n="283"/>him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            echo of Rom. 7:18-19; a conscious contrast between the human bondage
                            depicted there and God’s radical freedom.</p>
                    </note> And he does effect
                    it. That soul is absolutely assured, ‘This voice is the voice of God.’ But yet
                    he who hath that witness in himself cannot explain it to one who hath not. Nor
                    indeed is it to be expected that he should. Were there any natural medium to
                    prove, or natural method to explain the things of God to unexperienced men, then
                    the natural man might discern and know the things of the Spirit of God. But this
                    is utterly contrary to the assertion of the Apostle that ‘he cannot know them,
                    because they are spiritually discerned;’ even by spiritual senses which the
                    natural man hath not.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 2:14.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. ‘But how shall I know that my spiritual senses are rightly disposed?’
                    This also is a question of vast importance; for if a man mistake in this he may
                    run on in endless error and delusion. ‘And how am I assured that this is not my
                    case; and that I do not mistake the voice of the Spirit?’ Even by the ‘testimony
                    of your own spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note> by ‘the answer of a good
                    conscience toward God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 3:21.</p>
                    </note> By the fruits which he hath
                    wrought in your spirit you shall know the ‘testimony of the Spirit of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:16.</p>
                    </note> Hereby you shall know that you are in no delusion; that
                    you have not deceived your own soul. The immediate fruits of the Spirit ruling
                    in the heart are ‘love, joy, peace’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22. Wesley here ignores the fact that
                            καρπόν, in the text, is singular (the ‘fruit’ of the Spirit). Elsewhere,
                            as in the following sermon (Discourse II, §§II.1, 6-7) and in No. 76, On
                            Perfection’, I.6, III.3, he holds to the singular form. But cf. No. 4,
                                <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, §4 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘bowels of mercies, humbleness of mind, meekness, gentleness,
                        long-suffering’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> And the outward fruits
                    are the doing good to all men, the doing no evil to any, and the walking in the
                    light—a zealous, uniform obedience to all the commandments of God.</p>
                <p n="13">13. By the same fruits shall you distinguish this voice of God from any
                    delusion of the devil. That proud spirit cannot humble thee before God. He
                    neither can nor would soften thy heart and melt it first into earnest mourning
                    after God and then into filial love. It is not the adversary of God and man that
                    enables thee to love thy neighbour; or to put on meekness, gentleness, patience,
                    temperance, and the whole armour of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:11, 13.</p>
                    </note> He is not divided <pb n="284"/>against himself,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:26, etc.</p>
                    </note> or a destroyer of sin,
                    his own work. No; it is none but the Son of God who cometh to ‘destroy the works
                    of the devil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 3:8.</p>
                    </note> As surely therefore as holiness is of God, and as
                    sin is the work of the devil, so surely the witness thou hast in thyself is not
                    of Satan, but of God.</p>
                <p n="14">14. Well then mayst thou say, ‘Thanks be unto God for his unspeakable
                        gift!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 9:15.</p>
                    </note> Thanks be unto God who giveth me to ‘know in whom
                    I have believed’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> who ‘hath sent forth
                    the Spirit of his Son into my heart, crying Abba, Father’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:6.</p>
                    </note> and
                    even now ‘bearing witness with my spirit that I am a child of God’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:16.</p>
                    </note> And see that not only thy lips, but thy life show forth
                    his praise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 51:15. See also BCP, Morning Prayer, General
                        Thanksgiving.</p>
                    </note> He hath sealed thee for his own; ‘glorify him then
                    in thy body and thy spirit which are’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 6:20.</p>
                    </note> his. Beloved, if
                    thou ‘hast this hope in thyself, purify thyself as he is pure’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John
                            3:3.</p>
                    </note> While thou ‘beholdest what manner of love the Father
                    hath given thee, that thou shouldst be called a child of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:1.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘cleanse thyself from all filthiness of flesh and Spirit, perfecting holiness in
                    the fear of God;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                    </note> and let all thy
                    thoughts, words, and works be a spiritual sacrifice, holy, acceptable to God
                    through Christ Jesus!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:1; 1 Pet. 2:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>