<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 39: Catholic Spirit</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-27</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon039</idno>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 39: Catholic Spirit</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="79" to="95"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:079"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>There was a nondogmatic strain in Anglicanism that had discouraged the
                    formulation of creeds, confessions, and systematic treatises. Wesley had
                    inherited this tradition from his mother. He was opinionated and partisan, like
                    his father, with a stubborn loyalty to what he understood to be the essential
                    core of Christian truth. But he never supposed that this core ever had been or
                    ever could be captured in a single form of words. This mistrust of rigid
                    statements may have had some connection with his ingrained impulse to revise
                    almost any sentence that might be set before him, including his own—and also his
                    careless way with quotations. He agreed with the Cambridge Platonists before him
                    that most of the cruel controversies in religion that had spilled so much blood
                    and ink were quarrels about ‘opinions’—i.e., subsidiary doctrines affecting the
                    fullness and variety of religious language, not its primary object. He also
                    agreed with William of St. Thierry that love is the surest way to truth and the
                    highest goal of thought. He had a clear enough view for himself of the Christian
                    essentials (cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6 and n.) but never ever
                    tried to formulate them in an unrevisable statement. He had ventured his most
                    elaborate summary of them in an open <hi rend="italic">Letter to a Roman
                        Catholic</hi> (1749); his least elaborate (‘love of God and love of
                    neighbour’) is repeated endlessly throughout the sermons; e.g., No. 120, ‘The
                    Unity of the Divine Being’, §16: ‘True religion is right tempers towards God and
                    man. It is, in two words, gratitude and benevolence: gratitude to our Creator
                    and supreme Benefactor, and benevolence to our fellow creatures. In other words,
                    it is the loving God with all our heart, and our neighbour as ourselves.’ In
                    every case, his concern is to narrow the field of irreducible disagreement
                    between professing, practising Christians and to transfer their concerns from
                    argument about faith in Christ to faith itself and to its consequences.</p>
                <p>‘Catholic Spirit’ is the most formal articulation of this nondogmatic method in
                    theology. In it we find yet another statement of ‘essentials’—and it goes with
                    his method that Wesley believes he could presuppose a consensus here. Then we
                    come to Wesley’s effort to redeem <pb n="02:080"/>controversy in general by the
                    spirit of Christian love and forbearance. Given clarity as to the essentials and
                    liberty as to ‘opinions’, he is glad for Methodists ‘to think and let think’.
                    Here, then, is a charter for a distinctive sort of doctrinal pluralism—one that
                    stands at an equal distance from dogmatism on the one extreme and indifferentism
                    on the other.</p>
                <p>The mood and method of ‘Catholic Spirit’ run widely through the entire Wesleyan
                    corpus and must have been heard in his oral preaching as well. But as for the
                    use of this particular text, 2 Kgs. 10:15, there are only three other recorded
                    instances (November 23, 1740; September 8, 1749; and November 3, 1749). This
                    sermon was republished separately in 1755 (and again in 1770), with an appended
                    hymn by Charles Wesley (seven six-line stanzas) on ‘Catholic Love’:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Weary of all this wordy strife,</l>
                    <l>These notions, forms, and modes, and names,</l>
                    <l>To Thee, the Way, the Truth, the Life,</l>
                    <l>Whose love my simple heart inflames,</l>
                    <l>Divinely taught, at last I fly,</l>
                    <l>With thee and thine to live and die.</l>
                </lg>
                <p>In some ears such language, and the attitude behind it, would inevitably sound
                    soft-headed. Its deeper concern, however, may represent Wesley’s most important
                    contribution to the cause of Christian unity and to the requisite spirit in
                    which that cause may best be served.</p>
                <p>For a stemma illustrating this sermon’s publishing history and a list of variant
                    readings, see Appendix, Vol. 4; see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                    211.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:081"/>
            <head>Catholic Spirit</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>2 Kings 10:15</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">And when he was departed thence, he lighted on Jehonadab the
                        son of Rechab coming to meet him. And he saluted him and said, Is thine
                        heart right, as my heart is with thy heart? And Jehonadab answered, It is.
                        If it be, give me thine hand.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. It is allowed even by those who do not pay this great debt that love is
                    due to all mankind, the royal law, ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as
                        thyself,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                            2:8; cf. Lev. 19:18; Matt. 19:19, etc.</p></note> carrying its own
                    evidence to all that hear it. And that, not according to the miserable
                    construction put upon it by the zealots of old times, ‘Thou shalt love thy
                    neighbour’, thy relation, acquaintance, friend, ‘and hate thine enemy.’ Not so.
                    ‘I say unto you’, said our Lord, ‘Love your enemies, bless them that curse you,
                    do good to them that hate you, and pray for them that despitefully use you and
                    persecute you; that ye may be the children’—may appear so to all mankind—‘of
                    your Father which is in heaven, who maketh his sun to rise on the evil and on
                    the good, and sendeth rain on the just and on the unjust.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                    5:43-45.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. But it is sure, there is a peculiar love which we owe to those that love
                    God. So David: ‘All my delight is upon the saints that are in the earth, and
                    upon such as excel in virtue.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 16:3 (BCP).</p></note> And so a greater than
                    he: ‘A new commandment I give unto you, that ye love one another: as I have
                    loved you, that ye also love one another. By this shall all men know that ye are
                    my disciples, if ye have love one to another.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">John 13:34-35.</p></note></hi> This
                    is that love on which the Apostle John so frequently and strongly insists.
                    ‘This’, said he, ‘is the message that ye heard from the beginning, that we
                    should love one another.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">1 John 3:11.</p></note></hi> ‘Hereby perceive we
                    the love of God, because he laid down his life for us. And we ought’, if love
                    should call us thereto, ‘to lay down our lives for the brethren.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                16.</p></note></hi> And again, ‘Beloved, let <pb n="02:082"/>us love
                    one another; for love is of God. He that loveth not, knoweth not God; for God is
                        love.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                >Chap. 4, ver. 7-8.</p></note></hi> ‘Not that we loved God, but that
                    he loved us, and sent his Son to be the propitiation for our sins. Beloved, if
                    God so loved us, we ought also to love one another.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                    10-11.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="3">3. All men approve of this. But do all men practise it? Daily experience
                    shows the contrary. Where are even the Christians who ‘love one another, as he
                    hath given us commandment’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:23.</p></note> How many hindrances lie
                    in the way! The two grand, general hindrances are, first, that they can’t all
                    think alike; and in consequence of this, secondly, they can’t all walk alike;
                    but in several smaller points their practice must differ in proportion to the
                    difference of their sentiments.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But although a difference in opinions or modes of worship may prevent an
                    entire external union, yet need it prevent our union in affection? Though we
                    can’t think alike, may we not love alike? May we not be of one heart, though we
                    are not of one opinion? Without all doubt we may. Herein all the children of God
                    may unite, notwithstanding these smaller differences. These remaining as they
                    are, they may forward one another in love and in good works.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Surely in this respect the example of Jehu himself, as mixed a character
                    as he was of, is well worthy both the attention and imitation of every serious
                    Christian. ‘And when he was departed thence, he lighted on Jehonadab the son of
                    Rechab coming to meet him. And he saluted him and said, Is thine heart right, as
                    my heart is with thy heart? And Jehonadab answered, It is. If it be, give me
                    thine hand.’</p>
                <p>The text naturally divides itself into two parts. First a question proposed by
                    Jehu to Jehonadab, ‘Is thine heart right, as my heart is with thy heart?’
                    Secondly, an offer made on Jehonadab’s answering, ‘It is.’—‘If it be, give me
                    thine hand.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, let us consider the question proposed by Jehu to
                    Jehonadab, ‘Is thine heart right, as my heart is with thy heart?’ The very first
                    thing we may observe in these words is that here is no inquiry concerning
                    Jehonadab’s opinions. And yet ’tis certain he held some which were very
                    uncommon, indeed quite <pb n="02:083"/> peculiar to himself; and some which had
                    a close influence upon practice, on which likewise he laid so great a stress as
                    to entail them upon his children’s children, to their latest posterity. This is
                    evident from the account given by Jeremiah, many years after his death. ‘I took
                    Jaazaniah and his brethren, and all his sons, and the whole house of the
                    Rechabites; …and set before them pots full of wine, and cups, and said unto
                    them, Drink ye wine. But they said, We will drink no wine; for Jonadab (or
                    Jehonadab) the son of Rechab our father’ (it would be less ambiguous if the
                    words were placed thus: Jehonadab ‘our father the son of Rechab’, out of love
                    and reverence to whom he probably desired his descendants might be called by his
                    name) ‘commanded us, saying, Ye shall drink no wine, neither ye nor your sons
                    for ever. Neither shall ye build house, nor sow seed, nor plant vineyard, nor
                    have any; but all your days ye shall dwell in tents…. And we have obeyed, and
                    done according to all that Jonadab our father commanded us.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Jer.
                                35:3-10 [Note the similarity between Wesley’s suggested word order
                                and that adopted for the NEB].</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="2">2. And yet Jehu (although it seems to have been his manner, both in things
                    secular and religious, to ‘drive furiously’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5"
                        n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Kgs. 9:20.</p></note> does not concern
                    himself at all with any of these things, but lets Jehonadab abound in his own
                        sense.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">A
                            proverbial expression derived from the late Latin <hi rend="italic"
                                >abundare in suo sensu</hi>: ‘to follow one’s own opinion’. (See <hi
                                rend="italic">OED </hi>for a citation from Taverner’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Proverbs</hi>, 1552, along with later examples,
                            including Edmund Burke, 1775.)</p></note> And neither of them appears to
                    have given the other the least disturbance touching the opinions which he
                    maintained.</p>
                <p n="3">3. ’Tis very possible that many good men now also may entertain peculiar
                    opinions; and some of them may be as singular herein as even Jehonadab was. And
                    ’tis certain, so long as ‘we know’ but ‘in part’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:12.</p></note> that
                    all men will not see all things alike. It is an unavoidable consequence of the
                    present weakness and shortness of human understanding that several men will be
                    of several minds, in religion as well as in common life. So it has been from the
                    beginning of the world, and so it will be ‘till the restitution of all
                        things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Acts 3:21.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. Nay farther: although every man necessarily believes that every
                    particular opinion which he holds is true (for to believe any <pb n="02:084"
                    />opinion is not true is the same thing as not to hold it) yet can no man be
                    assured that all his own opinions taken together are true. Nay, every thinking
                    man is assured they are not, seeing <hi rend="italic">humanum est errare et
                        nescire</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >The first part of this sentence is a familiar classical proverb; cf.
                            Sophocles, <hi rend="italic">Antigone </hi>(‘To err from the right path
                            is common to mankind’); Cicero, <hi rend="italic">Philippics</hi>,
                            XXI.ii.5; Seneca, <hi rend="italic">Naturales Quaestiones </hi>(<hi
                                rend="italic">Natural Questions</hi>), iv.2; Plutarch, <hi
                                rend="italic">Against Colotes </hi>(‘To err in opinion, though it be
                            not part of wisdom, is at least human’); Augustine, Sermon 164:14. Cf.
                            also, Jerome, <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, 57:12 (Migne, <hi
                                rend="italic">PL</hi>, XXII.579): ‘<hi rend="italic">Scio quod
                                nescio…</hi>’); and George Buchanan, <hi rend="italic">Geflugelte
                                Wörte </hi>(Berlin, 1961), 567-68.</p><p rend="footnote text">Pope’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Essay on Criticism</hi>, l. 525, popularized this
                            in the first half of ‘To err is human, to forgive divine.’ Wesley seems
                            to have regarded ‘<hi rend="italic">et nescire</hi>’, ‘to be ignorant’,
                            as also an integral part of ‘the maxim received in all ages’, quoting
                            his amplified version no fewer than four times in the <hi rend="italic"
                                >Sermons</hi>: cf. Nos. 51, <hi rend="italic">The Good Steward</hi>,
                            II.9; 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.2; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’,
                            III.3. See also his <hi rend="italic">Short Address to the Inhabitants
                                of Ireland</hi>, §15.</p></note>—to be ignorant of many things, and
                    to mistake in some, is the necessary condition of humanity. This therefore, he
                    is sensible, is his own case. He knows in the general that he himself is
                    mistaken; although in what particulars he mistakes he does not, perhaps cannot,
                    know.</p>
                <p n="5">5. I say, perhaps he cannot know. For who can tell how far invincible
                        ignorance<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">
                            ‘Invincible’ because rooted in one’s social influences and prejudices;
                            cf. Francis Bacon’s so-called ‘idols’ of one’s ‘tribe’, ‘cave’,
                            ‘market-place’, or ‘theatre’ as in No. 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’,
                            II.5 and n. Cf. St. Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologica </hi>I-II
                            (‘Human Acts’), Q. 76, 2nd art. (‘Whether Ignorance is a Sin?’):
                            ‘[Ignorance] is not imputed as a sin to man if he fails to know what he
                            is unable to know. Consequently, such ignorance is called <hi
                                rend="italic">invincible </hi>because it cannot be overcome by
                            study…; wherefore it is evident that no invincible ignorance is a sin….’
                            But ‘even inculpable ignorance’ ‘excludes from salvation’ those who do
                            not ‘know’ ‘that there is a God who will reward those who seek him’; cf.
                            Canon George D. Smith, ed., <hi rend="italic">The Teaching of the
                                Catholic Church</hi>, I.17. What might have surprised Wesley,
                            though, is that ‘the Church teaches no less clearly that actual
                            membership of the [Roman] Catholic Church is not necessary for the
                            salvation of those in invincible ignorance of her true nature’ (<hi
                                rend="italic">ibid</hi>., II.709). Cf. No. 55, <hi rend="italic">On
                                the Trinity</hi>, §18.</p></note> may extend? Or (what comes to the
                    same thing) invincible prejudice; which is often so fixed in tender minds that
                    it is afterwards impossible to tear up what has taken so deep a root. And who
                    can say, unless he knew every circumstance attending it, how far any mistake is
                    culpable? Seeing all guilt must suppose some concurrence of the will—of which he
                    only can judge who searcheth the heart.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Every wise man therefore will allow others the same liberty of thinking
                    which he desires they should allow him; and will no more insist on their
                    embracing his opinions than he would have them to insist on his embracing
                    theirs. He bears with those who differ from him, and only asks him with whom he
                    desires to unite <pb n="02:085"/> in love that single question. ‘Is thine heart
                    right, as my heart is with thy heart?’</p>
                <p n="7">7. We may, secondly, observe that here is no inquiry made concerning
                    Jehonadab’s mode of worship, although ’tis highly probable there was in this
                    respect also a very wide difference between them. For we may well believe
                    Jehonadab, as well as all his posterity, worshipped God at Jerusalem, whereas
                    Jehu did not; he had more regard to state policy than religion. And therefore
                    although he slew the worshippers of Baal, and ‘destroyed Baal out of Israel’,
                    yet ‘from the’ convenient ‘sin of Jeroboam’, the worship of ‘the golden calves,
                    he departed not’.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">2 Kgs. 10:28-29.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="8">8. But even among men of an upright heart, men who desire ‘to have a
                    conscience void of offence’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Acts 24:16.</p></note> it must needs be that as
                    long as there are various opinions there will be various ways of worshipping
                    God; seeing a variety of opinion necessarily implies a variety of practice. And
                    as in all ages men have differed in nothing more than in their opinions
                    concerning the Supreme Being, so in nothing have they more differed from each
                    other than in the manner of worshipping him. Had this been only in the heathen
                    world it would not have been at all surprising, for we know these ‘by their
                    wisdom knew not God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 1:21.</p></note> nor therefore could
                    they know how to worship him. But is it not strange that even in the Christian
                    world, although they all agree in the general, ‘God is a Spirit, and they that
                    worship him must worship him in spirit and in truth,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">John 4:24.</p></note> yet the
                    particular modes of worshipping God are almost as various as among the
                    heathens?</p>
                <p n="9">9. And how shall we choose among so much variety? No man can choose for or
                    prescribe to another. But everyone must follow the dictates of his own
                    conscience in simplicity and godly sincerity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14"
                        n="14"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 1:12.</p></note> He must be fully
                    persuaded in his own mind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Rom. 14:5.</p></note> and then act according to
                    the best light he has. Nor has any creature power to constrain another to walk
                    by his own rule. God has given no right to any of the children of men thus to
                    lord it over the conscience of his brethren. But every man must judge for
                    himself, as every man must give an account of himself to God.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 14:12.</p></note></p>
                <p n="10"><pb n="02:086"/>10. Although therefore every follower of Christ is obliged
                    by the very nature of the Christian institution to be a member of some
                    particular congregation or other, some church, as it is usually termed (which
                    implies a particular manner of worship­ping God; for ‘two cannot walk together
                    unless they be agreed’);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Amos 3:3.</p></note> yet none can be obliged by
                    any power on earth but that of his own conscience to prefer this or that
                    congregation to another, this or that particular manner of worship. I know it is
                    commonly supposed that the place of our birth fixes the church to which we ought
                    to belong; that one, for instance, who is born in England ought to be a member
                    of that which is styled ‘the Church of England’, and consequently to worship God
                    in the particular manner which is prescribed by that church. I was once a
                    zealous maintainer of this, but I find many reasons to abate of this zeal. I
                    fear it is attended with such difficulties as no reasonable man can get over.
                    Not the least of which is that if this rule had took place, there could have
                    been no Reformation from popery, seeing it entirely destroys the right of
                    private judgment on which that whole Reformation stands.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 105, ‘On Conscience’;
                            12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §6; 18, ‘The Marks of the New
                            Birth’, II.2; and 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, I.1. Cf.
                            also Benjamin Ibbot, <hi rend="italic">A Course of Sermons, preached for
                                the lecture founded by the Honourable Robert Boyle, Esq., at the
                                Church of St. Mary-le-Bow, in the Years 1713 and 1714, Wherein The
                                True Notion of the Exercise of Private Judgment…in Matters of
                                Religion is Stated and the Objections Against it Answered</hi>;
                            Vicesimus Knox, <hi rend="italic">Essays Moral and Literary
                            </hi>(Dublin, 1786), V.21; and <hi rend="italic">The Old Whig</hi>, No.
                            4, I.32-33: ‘The reformation owes its being to men, who had the honesty
                            and courage to oppose their own private judgments to the established
                            opinions of the whole Christian world; to think for themselves, though
                            threatened with all the terrors of civil punishment in the present life,
                            and damnation in a future state, for such dreadful impiety and
                            insolence; and to protest against those errors in opinion and
                            superstitions in practice, which the church had sanctified and the state
                            established.’</p><p rend="footnote text">Compare this with Kant’s later
                            definition of ‘enlightenment’: ‘Man’s release from…his inability to make
                            use of his own understanding [‘private judgment’] without direction from
                            another’, in <hi rend="italic">What is Enlightenment? </hi>(1784), §1.
                            See also Wesley’s refutation (JWJ, Mar. 25, 1743) of Richard Challoner’s
                            denial of the right of ‘private judgment’, in <hi rend="italic">The
                                Grounds of the Old Religion </hi>(1742), and his repeated insistence
                            ‘on the right of private judgment’ in JWJ, May 30, 1746, and in <hi
                                rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §§61-62 (11:70-71, in this
                            edn.).</p></note></p>
                <p n="11">11. I dare not therefore presume to impose my mode of worship on any
                    other. I believe it is truly primitive and apostolical. But my belief is no rule
                    for another. I ask not therefore of him with whom I would unite in love, ‘Are
                    you of my Church? Of my congregation? Do you receive the same form of church
                    government and allow the same church officers with me? Do you <pb n="02:087"
                    />join in the same form of prayer wherein I worship God?’ I inquire not, ‘Do you
                    receive the Supper of the Lord in the same posture and manner that I do?’ Nor
                    whether, in the administration of baptism, you agree with me in admitting
                    sureties for the baptized, in the manner of administering it, or the age of
                    those to whom it should be administered. Nay, I ask not of you (as clear as I am
                    in my own mind) whether you allow baptism and the Lord’s Supper at all. Let all
                    these things stand by: we will talk of them, if need be, at a more convenient
                        season.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 24:25.</p></note> My only question at present is this, ‘Is thine
                    heart right, as my heart is with thy heart?’</p>
                <p n="12">12. But what is properly implied in the question? I do not mean what did
                    Jehu imply therein, but what should a follower of Christ understand thereby when
                    he proposes it to any of his brethren?</p>
                <p>The first thing implied is this: Is thy heart right with God? Dost thou believe
                    his being, and his perfections? His eternity, immensity, wisdom, power; his
                    justice, mercy, and truth? Dost thou believe that he now ‘upholdeth all things
                    by the word of his power’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 1:3.</p></note> And that he governs even
                    the most minute, even the most noxious, to his own glory, and the good of them
                    that love him? Hast thou a divine evidence, a supernatural conviction, of the
                    things of God? Dost thou ‘walk by faith, not by sight’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:7.</p></note>
                    ‘Looking not at temporal things, but things eternal’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                    4:18.</p></note></p>
                <p n="13">13. Dost thou believe in the Lord Jesus Christ, ‘God over all, blessed for
                        ever’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 9:5.</p></note> Is he ‘revealed in’ thy soul?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:16.</p></note> Dost
                    thou ‘know Jesus Christ and him crucified’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 2:2.</p></note> Does he ‘dwell in
                    thee, and thou in him’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 6:56; 1 John 4:13, 15.</p></note> Is he
                    ‘formed in thy heart by faith’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:19; Eph. 3:17.</p></note> Having
                    absolutely disclaimed all thy own works, thy own righteousness, hast thou
                    ‘submitted thyself unto the righteousness of God’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:3.</p></note>
                    ‘which is by faith in Christ Jesus’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 3:22.</p></note> Art thou ‘found in him, not
                    having thy own righteousness, but the righteousness which is by faith’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            3:9.</p></note> And art thou, through him, ‘fighting the good fight of
                    faith, and laying hold of eternal life’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:12.</p></note></p>
                <p n="14"><pb n="02:088"/>14. Is thy faith ἐνεργουμένη δἰ ἀγάπης—filled with
                    the energy of love?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal 5:6, orig., πίστις δἰ ἀγάπης
                            ἐνεργουμένη (‘faith active in love’); Wesley’s reversal has the effect
                            of a different nuance (‘the energy <hi rend="italic">of </hi>love’). See
                            above, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.6 and
                            n.</p></note> Dost thou love God? I do not say ‘above all things’, for
                    it is both an unscriptural and an ambiguous expression, but ‘with all thy heart,
                    and with all thy mind, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 12:30;
                            Luke 10:27.</p></note> Dost thou seek all thy happiness in him alone?
                    And dost thou find what thou seekest? Does thy soul continually ‘magnify the
                    Lord, and thy spirit rejoice in God thy Saviour’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:46-47.</p></note>
                    Having learned ‘in everything to give thanks’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35"
                        n="35"><p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:18.</p></note> dost thou find it
                    is ‘a joyful and a pleasant thing to be thankfu1’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 147:1
                        (BCP).</p></note> Is God the centre of thy soul? The sum of all thy desires?
                    Art thou accordingly ‘laying up’ thy ‘treasure in heaven’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 6:20.</p></note> and
                    ‘counting all things else dung and dross’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                        n="38"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:8.</p></note> Hath the love of
                    God cast the love of the world out of thy soul? Then thou art ‘crucified to the
                        world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 6:14.</p></note> ‘Thou art dead’ to all below, ‘and thy life is hid
                    with Christ in God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:3.</p></note></p>
                <p n="15">15. Art thou employed in doing ‘not thy own will, but the will of him that
                    sent thee’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 6:38.</p></note> Of him that sent thee down to sojourn here a
                    while, to spend a few days in a strange land, till having finished the work he
                    hath given thee to do thou return to thy Father’s house? Is it thy meat and
                    drink ‘to do the will of thy Father which is in heaven’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:21,
                        etc.</p></note> Is ‘thine eye single’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43"
                        n="43"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:22.</p></note> in all things? Always
                    fixed on him? Always ‘looking unto Jesus’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44"
                        n="44"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:2.</p></note> Dost thou point at him
                    in whatsoever thou dost? In all thy labour, thy business, thy conversation?
                    Aiming only at the glory of God in all? ‘Whatsoever’ thou dost, either ‘in word
                    or deed, doing it all in the name of the Lord Jesus, giving thanks unto God,
                    even the Father, through him’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:17.</p></note></p>
                <p n="16">16. Does the love of God constrain thee to ‘serve’ him ‘with fear’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                        2:11.</p></note> To ‘rejoice unto him with reverence’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.
                            </hi>(BCP).</p></note> Art thou more afraid of displeasing God than
                    either of death or hell? Is nothing so terrible to thee as the thought of
                    ‘offending the eyes of his glory’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 3:8.</p></note> Upon this ground dost thou
                    ‘hate all evil ways’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:104 (BCP).</p></note> every transgression
                    of his holy and perfect law? And herein ‘exercise’ <pb n="02:089"/>thyself ‘to
                    have a conscience void of offence toward God and toward man’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 24:16.</p></note></p>
                <p n="17">17. Is thy heart right toward thy neighbour? Dost thou ‘love as
                        thyself’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Lev. 19:18, etc.</p></note> all mankind without exception? ‘If you love
                    those only that love you, what thank have you?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52"
                        n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 6:32.</p></note> Do you ‘love your
                        enemies’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 5:44.</p></note> Is your soul full of goodwill, of tender
                    affection toward them? Do you love even the enemies of God? The unthankful and
                    unholy? Do your bowels yearn over them? Could you ‘wish yourself (temporally)
                        accursed’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Rom. 9:3.</p></note> for their sake? And do you show this by
                    ‘blessing them that curse you, and praying for those that despitefully use you
                    and persecute you’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:44.</p></note></p>
                <p n="18">18. Do you show your love by your works? While you have time, as you have
                    opportunity, do you in fact ‘do good to all men’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                    6:10.</p></note>—neighbours or strangers, friends or enemies, good or bad? Do
                    you do them all the good you can? Endeavouring to supply all their wants,
                    assisting them both in body and soul to the uttermost of your power? If thou art
                    thus minded, may every Christian say—yea, if thou art but sincerely desirous of
                    it, and following on till thou attain—then ‘thy heart is right, as my heart is
                    with thy heart.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. ‘If it be, give me thine hand.’ I do not mean, ‘Be of my opinion.’
                    You need not. I do not expect nor desire it. Neither do I mean, ‘I will be of
                    your opinion.’ I cannot. It does not depend on my choice. I can no more think
                    than I can see or hear as I will. Keep you your opinion, I mine; and that as
                    steadily as ever. You need not even endeavour to come over to me, or bring me
                    over to you. I do not desire you to dispute those points, or to hear or speak
                    one word concerning them. Let all opinions alone on one side and the other. Only
                    ‘give me thine hand.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. I do not mean, ‘Embrace my modes of worship,’ or, ‘I will embrace
                    yours.’ This also is a thing which does not depend either on your choice or
                    mine. We must both act as each is fully persuaded in his own mind.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            14:5.</p></note> Hold you fast that which you believe <pb n="02:090"/>is
                    most acceptable to God, and I will do the same. I believe the episcopal form of
                    church government to be scriptural and apostolical. If you think the
                    presbyterian or independent is better, think so still, and act accordingly. I
                    believe infants ought to be baptized, and that this may be done either by
                    dipping or sprinkling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Note Wesley’s casual self-identification as
                            Anglican, here as elsewhere.</p></note> If you are otherwise persuaded,
                    be so still, and follow your own persuasion. It appears to me that forms of
                    prayer are of excellent use, particularly in the great congregation.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">As distinguished
                            from the religious society or informal worship group.</p></note> If you
                    judge extemporary prayer to be of more use, act suitably to your own judgment.
                    My sentiment is that I ought not to forbid water wherein persons may be
                    baptized, and that I ought to eat bread and drink wine as a memorial of my dying
                    Master. However, if you are not convinced of this, act according to the light
                    you have. I have no desire to dispute with you one moment upon any of the
                    preceding heads. Let all these smaller points stand aside. Let them never come
                    into sight. ‘If thine heart is as my heart’, if thou lovest God and all mankind,
                    I ask no more: ‘Give me thine hand.’</p>
                <p n="3">3. I mean, first, love me. And that not only as thou lovest all mankind;
                    not only as thou lovest thine enemies or the enemies of God, those that hate
                    thee, that ‘despitefully use thee and persecute thee’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:44.</p></note> not
                    only as a stranger, as one of whom thou knowest neither good nor evil. I am not
                    satisfied with this. No; ‘If thine heart be right, as mine with thy heart’, then
                    love me with a very tender affection, as a friend that is closer than a brother;
                    as a brother in Christ, a fellow-citizen of the new Jerusalem, a fellow-soldier
                    engaged in the same warfare, under the same Captain of our salvation.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb.
                            2:10.</p></note> Love me as a companion in the kingdom and patience of
                        Jesus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rev. 1:9.</p></note> and a joint-heir of his glory.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:17.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. Love me (but in an higher degree than thou dost the bulk of mankind)
                    with the love that is ‘long-suffering and kind’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:4.</p></note>
                    that is patient if I am ignorant or out of the way, bearing and not increasing
                    my burden; and is tender, soft, and compassionate still; that ‘envieth not’ if
                    at any time it please God to prosper me in his work even more than thee. Love me
                    with the love that ‘is not provoked’ either at my follies or infirmities, or
                    even at my acting <pb n="02:091"/>(if it should sometimes so appear to thee) not
                    according to the will of God. Love me so as to ‘think no evil’ of me, to put
                    away all jealousy and evil surmising. Love me with the love that ‘covereth all
                    things’, that never reveals either my faults or infirmities; that ‘believeth all
                    things’, is always willing to think the best, to put the fairest construction on
                    all my words and actions; that ‘hopeth all things’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:4-7.</p></note>
                    either that the thing related was never done, or not done with such
                    circumstances as are related, or, at least, that it was done with a good
                    intention, or in sudden stress of temptation. And hope to the end that whatever
                    is amiss will, by the grace of God, be corrected, and whatever is wanting
                    supplied, through the riches of his mercy in Christ Jesus.</p>
                <p n="5">5. I mean, secondly, commend me to God in all thy prayers; wrestle with him
                    in my behalf, that he would speedily correct what he sees amiss and supply what
                    is wanting in me. In thy nearest access to the throne of grace beg of him who is
                    then very present with thee that my heart may be more as thy heart, more right
                    both toward God and toward man; that I may have a fuller conviction of things
                    not seen,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Heb. 11:1.</p></note> and a stronger view of the love of God in Christ
                    Jesus; may more steadily walk by faith, not by sight,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:7.</p></note> and
                    more earnestly grasp eternal life. Pray that the love of God and of all mankind
                    may be more largely poured into my heart; that I may be more fervent and active
                    in doing the will of my Father which is in heaven,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 12:50.</p></note> more
                    zealous of good works,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p></note> and more careful to abstain
                    from all appearance of evil.</p>
                <p n="6">6. I mean, thirdly, provoke me to love and to good works.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 10:24.</p></note>
                    Second thy prayer as thou hast opportunity by speaking to me in love whatsoever
                    thou believest to be for my soul’s health. Quicken me in the work which God has
                    given me to do, and instruct me how to do it more perfectly. Yea, ‘smite me
                    friendly and reprove me’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 141:5 (BCP).</p></note> whereinsoever I appear
                    to thee to be doing rather my own will than the will of him that sent me.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">See John
                            6:38.</p></note> O speak and spare not, whatever thou believest may
                    conduce either to the amending my faults, the strengthening my weakness, the
                    building me up in love, or the making me more fit in any kind for the Master’s
                    use.</p>
                <p n="7">7. I mean, lastly, love me not in word only, but in deed and in <pb
                        n="02:092"/>truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 1 John 3:18.</p></note> So far as in conscience
                    thou canst (retaining still thy own opinions and thy own manner of worshipping
                    God), join with me in the work of God, and let us go on hand in hand. And thus
                    far, it is certain, thou mayst go. Speak honourably, wherever thou art, of the
                    work of God, by whomsoever he works, and kindly of his messengers. And if it be
                    in thy power, not only sympathize with them when they are in any difficulty or
                    distress, but give them a cheerful and effectual assistance, that they may
                    glorify God on thy behalf.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Two things should be observed with regard to what has been spoken under
                    this last head. The one, that whatsoever love, whatsoever offices of love,
                    whatsoever spiritual or temporal assistance, I claim from him whose heart is
                    right, as my heart is with his, the same I am ready, by the grace of God,
                    according to my measure, to give him. The other, that I have not made this claim
                    in behalf of myself only, but of all whose heart is right toward God and man,
                    that we may all love one another as Christ hath loved us.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">See John 13:34.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. One inference we may make from what has been said. We may learn
                    from hence what is a ‘catholic spirit’.</p>
                <p>There is scarce any expression which has been more grossly misunderstood and more
                    dangerously misapplied than this. But it will be easy for any who calmly
                    consider the preceding observations to correct any such misapprehensions of it,
                    and to prevent any such misapplication.</p>
                <p>For from hence we may learn, first, that a catholic spirit is not <hi
                        rend="italic">speculative latitudinarianism</hi>.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">A tradition of toleration of
                            theoretical differences that had arisen as an alternative to a tragic
                            century of divisive controversy and conflict. Its theory had been laid
                            down by the Cambridge Platonists (Whichcote, More, Cudworth); its
                            ecclesiological implications had been set out, in different ways, by
                            Hoadly and Tillotson; some of its unintended practical effects had been
                            made evident in the Bangorian controversy; cf. Sykes, <hi rend="italic"
                                >From Sheldon to Secker: Aspects of English Church History,
                                1660-1768 </hi>(Cambridge, England, Univ. Press, 1959), pp. 146-52,
                            for a brief review of this movement. What is significant is that Wesley
                            could have rejected latitudinarianism with such vehemence in the course
                            of espousing yet another form of ‘comprehension’. It means that he felt
                            closer to Richard Baxter, <hi rend="italic">The True Catholick and
                                Catholick Church Described </hi>(1660), in <hi rend="italic">Works
                            </hi>(1854), IV.729-58.</p></note> It is not an indifference to all
                    opinions. This is the spawn of hell, not the offspring of heaven. This
                    unsettledness of thought, this being ‘driven to and fro, and <pb n="02:093"
                    />tossed about with very wind of doctrine’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76"
                        n="76"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:14: an ironic reference to
                            Elijah’s challenge to the Israelites but not in the ‘catholic spirit’
                            here advocated.</p></note> is a great curse, not a blessing; an
                    irreconcilable enemy, not a friend, to true catholicism. A man of a truly
                    catholic spirit has not now his religion to seek. He is fixed as the sun in his
                    judgment concerning the main branches of Christian doctrine. ’Tis true he is
                    always ready to hear and weigh whatsoever can be offered against his principles.
                    But as this does not show any wavering in his own mind, so neither does it
                    occasion any. He does not halt between two opinions,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Kgs. 18:21.</p></note>
                    nor vainly endeavour to blend them into one. Observe this, you who know not what
                    spirit ye are of, who call yourselves men of a catholic spirit only because you
                    are of a muddy understanding; because your mind is all in a mist; because you
                    have no settled, consistent principles, but are for jumbling all opinions
                    together. Be convinced that you have quite missed your way: you know not where
                    you are. You think you are got into the very spirit of Christ, when in truth you
                    are nearer the spirit of antichrist. Go first and learn the first elements of
                    the gospel of Christ, and then shall you learn to be of a truly catholic
                    spirit.</p>
                <p n="2">2. From what has been said we may learn, secondly, that a catholic spirit
                    is not any kind of <hi rend="italic">practical latitudinarianism</hi>. It is not
                    indifference as to public worship or as to the outward manner of performing it.
                    This likewise would not be a blessing but a curse. Far from being an help
                    thereto it would, so long as it remained, be an unspeakable hindrance to the
                    worshipping of God in spirit and in truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78"
                        n="78"><p rend="footnote text">See John 4:23-24.</p></note> But the man of a
                    truly catholic spirit, having weighed all things in the balance of the
                        sanctuary,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, II.8 and n.</p></note> has
                    no doubt, no scruple at all concerning that particular mode of worship wherein
                    he joins. He is clearly convinced that <hi rend="italic">this </hi>manner of
                    worshipping God is both scriptural and rational. He knows none in the world
                    which is more scriptural, none which is more rational. Therefore without
                    rambling hither and thither he cleaves close thereto, and praises God for the
                    opportunity of so doing.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Hence we may, thirdly, learn that a catholic spirit is not indifference
                    to all congregations. This is another sort of latitudinarianism, no less absurd
                    and unscriptural than the former. But it is far from a man of a truly catholic
                    spirit. He is <pb n="02:094"/>fixed in his congregation as well as his
                    principles. He is united to one, not only in spirit, but by all the outward ties
                    of Christian fellowship. There he partakes of all the ordinances of God. There
                    he receives the Supper of the Lord. There he pours out his soul in public
                    prayer, and joins in public praise and thanksgiving. There he rejoices to hear
                    the word of reconciliation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:19.</p></note> the gospel of the grace of
                    God. With these his nearest, his best beloved brethren, on solemn occasions he
                    seeks God by fasting. These particularly he watches over in love, as they do
                    over his soul, admonishing, exhorting, comforting, reproving, and every way
                    building up each other in the faith. These he regards as his own household, and
                    therefore according to the ability God has given him naturally cares for them,
                    and provides that they may have all the things that are needful for life and
                    godliness.</p>
                <p n="4">4. But while he is steadily fixed in his religious principles, in what he
                    believes to be the truth as it is in Jesus; while he firmly adheres to that
                    worship of God which he judges to be most acceptable in his sight; and while he
                    is united by the tenderest and closest ties to one particular congregation; his
                    heart is enlarged toward all mankind, those he knows and those he does not; he
                    embraces with strong and cordial affection neighbours and strangers, friends and
                    enemies. This is catholic or universal love. And he that has this is of a
                    catholic spirit. For love alone gives the title to this character—catholic love
                    is a catholic spirit.</p>
                <p n="5">5. If then we take this word in the strictest sense, a man of a catholic
                    spirit is one who in the manner above mentioned ‘gives his hand’ to all whose
                    ‘hearts are right with his heart’. One who knows how to value and praise God for
                    all the advantages he enjoys: with regard to the knowledge of the things of God,
                    the true, scriptural manner of worshipping him; and above all his union with a
                    congregation fearing God and working righteousness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">See Acts 10:35.</p></note> One
                    who, retaining these blessings with the strictest care, keeping them as the
                    apple of his eye, at the same time loves as friends, as brethren in the Lord, as
                    members of Christ and children of God, as joint partakers now of the present
                    kingdom of God, and fellow-heirs of his eternal Kingdom, all of whatever opinion
                    or worship or congregation who believe in the Lord Jesus Christ; who love God
                    and man; who, rejoicing to please and fearing <pb n="02:095"/>to offend God, are
                    careful to abstain from evil and zealous of good works.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p></note> He is
                    the man of a truly catholic spirit who bears all these continually upon his
                    heart, who having an unspeakable tenderness for their persons, and longing for
                    their welfare, does not cease to commend them to God in prayer, as well as to
                    plead their cause before men; who speaks comfortably to them,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Chron. 32:6.</p></note>
                    and labours by all his words to strengthen their hands in God. He assists them
                    to the uttermost of his power in all things, spiritual and temporal. He is ready
                    ‘to spend and be spent for them’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 12:15.</p></note> yea, ‘to lay down his
                    life for’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 13:37.</p></note> their sake.</p>
                <p n="6">6. Thou, O man of God, think on these things. If thou art already in this
                    way, go on. If thou hast heretofore mistook the path, bless God who hath brought
                    thee back. And now run the race which is set before thee,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:1.</p></note> in
                    the royal way of universal love. Take heed lest thou be either wavering in thy
                    judgment or straitened in thy bowels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 6:12.</p></note> But keep an even pace,
                    rooted in the faith once delivered to the saints<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">Jude 3.</p></note> and
                    grounded in love,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Eph. 3:17.</p></note> in true, catholic love,
                    till thou art swallowed up in love for ever and ever.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text">The three edns. of ‘Catholic
                            Spirit’ as a separate sermon append the poem ‘Catholic Love’, by Charles
                            Wesley (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, VI.71-72).</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
