<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 28: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse VIII</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon028</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 28: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse VIII</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="612" to="631"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:612"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Eighth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 6:19-23</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and
                        rust doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal·</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">But lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither
                        moth nor rust doth corrupt, and where thieves do not break through nor
                        steal;</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">For where your treasure is, there will your heart be
                        also.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The light of the body is the eye: if therefore thine eye be
                        single, thy whole body shall be full of light.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of
                        darkness. If therefore the light that is in thee be darkness, how great is
                        that darkness!</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <p n="1">1. From those which are commonly termed ‘religious actions’, and which are real
                branches of true religion where they spring from a pure and holy intention and are
                performed in a manner suitable thereto, our Lord proceeds to the actions of ‘common
                life’, and shows that the same purity of intention is as indispensably required in
                our ordinary business as in giving alms, or fasting, or prayer.</p>
            <p>And without question the same purity of intention ‘which makes our alms and devotions
                acceptable must also make our labour or employment a proper offering to God. If a
                man […] pursues his business that he may raise himself to a state of honour and
                riches in the world, he is no longer serving God in his employment, […] and has no
                more title to a reward from God than he who gives alms that he may be <hi
                    rend="italic">seen</hi>, or prays that he may be <hi rend="italic">heard</hi> of
                men. For vain and earthly designs are no more allowable in our employments than in
                our alms and devotions. […] They are not only evil when they mix with our good
                works’, with our religious actions, ‘but they have the same evil nature […] when
                they enter into the common business of our employments. If it were allowable to
                pursue them in our worldly <pb n="01:613"/>employments, it would be allowable to
                pursue them in our devotions. But as our alms and devotions are not an acceptable
                service but when they proceed from a pure intention, so our common employment cannot
                be reckoned a service to him but when it is performed with the same piety of
                    heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">A
                        quotation from Law’s <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, (<hi rend="italic"
                            >Works</hi>, IV.33); but note Wesley’s alterations (e.g., ‘earthly
                        designs’ in place of ‘earthly desires’). Wesley had already published an
                        abridged edn. of <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi> in 1744 (cf. <hi
                            rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 86); here he abridges that abridgement
                        still further.</p></note></p>
            <p n="2">2. This our blessed Lord declares in the liveliest manner in those strong and
                comprehensive words which he explains, enforces, and enlarges upon throughout this
                whole chapter. ‘The light of the body is the eye. If therefore thine eye be single,
                thy whole body shall be full of light: but if thine eye be evil, thy whole body
                shall be full of darkness.’ The eye is the intention: what the eye is to the body,
                the intention is to the soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 12, ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’, §11 and
                        n.</p></note> As the one guides all the motions of the body, so does the
                other those of the soul. This eye of the soul is then said to be ‘single’ when it
                looks at one thing only; when we have no other design but to ‘know God, and Jesus
                Christ whom he hath sent’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                        rend="footnote text">John 17:3.</p></note> to know him with suitable
                affections, loving him as he hath loved us; to please God in all things; to serve
                God (as we love him) with all our heart and mind and soul and strength;<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">See Mark
                    12:30.</p></note> and to enjoy God in all and above all things, in time and in
                eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. ‘If thine eye be’ thus ‘single’, thus fixed on God, ‘thy whole body shall be
                full of light.’ ‘Thy whole body’—all that is guided by the intention, as the body is
                by the eye. All thou art, all thou dost: thy desires, tempers, affections; thy
                thoughts and words and actions. The whole of these ‘shall be full of light’; full of
                true, divine knowledge. This is the first thing we may here understand by light. ‘In
                his light thou shalt see light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 36:9.</p></note> ‘He which’ of old ‘commanded
                light to shine out of darkness, shall shine in thy heart.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:6.</p></note> He shall
                enlighten the eyes of thy understanding<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:18.</p></note> with the knowledge of the
                glory of God. His Spirit shall reveal unto thee the deep things of God.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                    2:10.</p></note> The inspiration of the Holy One shall <hi rend="Page"
                    >[01:614]</hi>give thee understanding, and cause thee to know wisdom secretly.
                Yea, the anointing which thou receivest of him ‘shall abide in thee and teach thee
                of all things’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                        John 2:27.</p></note></p>
            <p>How does experience confirm this? Even after God hath opened the eyes of our
                understanding, if we seek or desire anything else than God, how soon is our foolish
                heart darkened! Then clouds again rest upon our souls. Doubts and fears again
                overwhelm us. We are tossed to and fro, and know not what to do, or which is the
                path wherein we should go. But when we desire and seek nothing but God, clouds and
                doubts vanish away. We ‘who were sometime darkness are now light in the Lord’.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                    5:8.</p></note> The night now shineth as the day;<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 139:12.</p></note> and we
                find ‘the path of the upright is light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 4:18.</p></note> God showeth us the path
                wherein we should go, and ‘maketh plain the way before our face’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 5:8 (BCP).</p></note></p>
            <p n="4">4. The second thing which we may here understand by ‘light’ is holiness. While
                thou seekest God in all things thou shalt find him in all, the fountain of all
                holiness, continually filling thee with his own likeness, with justice, mercy, and
                truth. While thou lookest unto Jesus and him alone thou shalt be filled with the
                mind that was in him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p></note> Thy soul shall be renewed day
                by day after the image of him that created it. If the eye of thy mind be not removed
                from him, if thou endurest ‘as seeing him that is invisible’,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:27.</p></note> and
                seeking nothing else in heaven or earth, then as thou beholdest the glory of the
                Lord thou shalt be ‘transformed into the same image, from glory to glory, by the
                Spirit of the Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >2 Cor. 3:18.</p></note></p>
            <p>And it is also matter of daily experience that ‘by grace we are thus saved through
                    faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                        2:8.</p></note> It is by faith that the eye of the mind is opened to see the
                light of the glorious love of God. And as long as it is steadily fixed thereon, on
                God in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18"
                    n="18"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 5:19.</p></note> we are more and more
                filled with the love of God and man, with meekness, gentleness, long-suffering; with
                all the fruits of holiness, which are, through Christ Jesus, to the glory of God the
                Father.</p>
            <p n="5"><pb n="01:615"/>5. This light which fills him who has a single eye implies,
                thirdly, happiness as well as holiness. Surely ‘light is sweet, and a pleasant thing
                it is to see the sun.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 11:7. Cf. No. 91, ‘On Charity’, III.10,
                        where Wesley relates an anecdote of a victim of the Inquisition brought out
                        of prison to execution. Having not seen the sun in many years, looking up,
                        he cried out in surprise, ‘O how can anyone who sees that glorious luminary
                        worship any but the God that made it!’</p></note> But how much more to see
                the sun of righteousness continually shining upon the soul! And if there be any
                consolation in Christ, if any comfort of love,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                    n="20"><p rend="footnote text">Phil. 2:1.</p></note> if any peace that passeth
                all understanding,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Phil. 4:7.</p></note> if any rejoicing in hope of the glory of
                    God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                        5:2.</p></note> they all belong to him whose eye is single. Thus is his
                ‘whole body full of light’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:22.</p></note> He walketh in the light as God
                is in the light,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        1 John 1:7.</p></note> rejoicing evermore, praying without ceasing, and in
                everything giving thanks, <hi rend="italic">enjoying</hi> whatever is the will of
                God concerning him in Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess. 5:16-18.</p></note></p>
            <p n="6">6. ‘But if thine eye be evil, thy whole body shall be full of darkness.’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                    6:23.</p></note> ‘If thine eye be evil’: we see there is no medium between a
                single and an evil eye. If the eye be not single, then it is evil. If the intention
                in whatever we do be not singly to God, if we seek anything else, then our ‘mind and
                conscience are defiled’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 1:15. Cf. No. 125, ‘On a Single
                    Eye’.</p></note></p>
            <p n="">Our eye therefore is evil if in anything we do we aim at any other end than God;
                if we have any view but to know and to love God, to please and serve him in all
                things; if we have any other design than to enjoy God, to be happy in him both now
                and for ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Note
                        the echo here of the answer to <hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> 1 in the
                        Westminster <hi rend="italic">Shorter Catechism</hi> of 1647.</p></note></p>
            <p n="7">7. If thine eye be not singly fixed on God, ‘thy whole body shall be full of
                darkness.’ The veil shall still remain on thy heart. Thy mind shall be more and more
                blinded by ‘the God of this world, lest the light of the glorious gospel of Christ
                should shine upon thee’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:4.</p></note> Thou wilt be full of
                ignorance and error touching the things of God, not being able to receive or discern
                them. And even when thou hast some desire to serve God, thou wilt be full of
                uncertainty as to the manner of serving him; finding doubts and difficulties on
                every side, and not seeing any way to escape.</p>
            <p><pb n="01:616"/>Yea, if thine eye be not single, if thou seek any of the things of
                earth, thou shalt be full of ungodliness and unrighteousness, thy desires, tempers,
                affections, being all out of course, being all dark, and vile, and vain. And thy
                conversation will be evil as well as thy heart, not ‘seasoned with salt’,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Col. 4:6.</p></note>
                or ‘meet to minister grace unto the hearers’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31"
                    n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:29.</p></note> but idle, unprofitable,
                corrupt, grievous to the Holy Spirit of God.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Both ‘destruction and unhappiness are in thy ways;’ for ‘the way of peace
                hast thou not known.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:16-17.</p></note> There is no peace, no
                settled, solid peace, for them that know not God. There is no true nor lasting
                content for any who do not seek him with their whole heart. While thou aimest at any
                of the things that perish, ‘all that cometh is vanity.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Eccles. 11:8.</p></note> Yea, not
                only vanity, but ‘vexation of spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Eccles. 1:14, etc.</p></note> and that both in the
                pursuit and the enjoyment also. Thou walkest indeed in a vain shadow, and
                disquietest thyself in vain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Ps. 39:6.</p></note> Thou walkest in darkness that
                may be felt.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Exod. 10:21.</p></note> ‘Sleep on;’ but thou canst not ‘take thy rest.’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt.
                    26:45.</p></note> The dreams of life can give pain, and that thou knowest; but
                ease they cannot give. There is no rest in this world or the world to come, but only
                in God, the centre of spirits.</p>
            <p>‘If the light which is in thee be darkness, how great is that darkness!’ If the
                intention which ought to enlighten the whole soul, to fill it with knowledge, and
                love, and peace, and which in fact does so as long as it is single, as long as it
                aims at God alone—if this be darkness; if it aim at anything beside God, and
                consequently cover the soul with darkness instead of light, with ignorance and
                error, with sin and misery—O how great is that darkness! It is the very smoke which
                ascends out of the bottomless pit!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Rev. 11:7; 17:8.</p></note> It is the essential
                night which reigns in the lowest deep, in the land of the shadow of death.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 9:1-2; Matt.
                        4:16.</p></note></p>
            <p n="9">9. Therefore ‘lay not up for yourselves treasures upon earth, where moth and
                rust doth corrupt, and where thieves break through and steal.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:19.</p></note> If you do,
                it is plain your eye is evil; it is not singly fixed on God.</p>
            <p>With regard to most of the commandments of God, whether <pb n="01:617"/>relating to
                the heart or life, the heathens of Africa<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Most of what Wesley knew of Africa came from the
                        published accounts of travellers and was confined largely to the ‘dark
                        continent’s’ southern tip. Cf. Peter Kolben, <hi rend="italic">The Present
                            State of the Cape of Good Hope</hi> (1731) and Thomas Salmon, <hi
                            rend="italic">Modern History</hi>. The general label at that time for
                        the natives of the Cape Colony and its hinterlands was ‘Hottentots’, and
                        they are described in quite various lights (as ‘noble savages’ by some and
                        as uncivilized by others). Wesley’s concern here, however, is to use ‘the
                        heathens of Africa or America’ as foils in his scornful comparisons between
                        nominal Christians and so-called heathens. Cf. JWJ, Dec. 2, 1737 (§§21-28);
                        and Nos. 69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, II.5; 105, ‘On
                        Conscience’, §5. See also <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Original
                            Sin</hi>, Pt. II, II.1-10; <hi rend="italic">Thoughts upon Slavery</hi>,
                        II.1-2 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 350, Vol. 15); <hi rend="italic"
                            >Survey</hi>, IV.109; and <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>, 1789, 377-83.
                        Wesley seems never to have used the name ‘Africa’, but always, as here,
                        ‘Africk’ (1748) or ‘Afric’ (1771, 1787).</p></note> or America stand much on
                a level with those that are called Christians. The Christians observe them (a few
                only being excepted) very near as much as the heathens. For instance: the generality
                of the natives of England, commonly called Christians, are as sober and as temperate
                as the generality of the heathens near the Cape of Good Hope. And so the Dutch or
                French Christians are as humble and as chaste as the Choctaw or Cherokee Indians. It
                is not easy to say, when we compare the bulk of the nations in Europe with those in
                America, whether the superiority lies on the one side or the other. At least the
                American has not much the advantage. But we cannot affirm this with regard to the
                command now before us. Here the heathen has far the pre-eminence.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s lifelong rejection of
                        surplus accumulation as an economic moral principle would intensify in the
                        last decade of his life; see below, No. 87, ‘The Danger of Riches’ (1781).
                        Here, before Adam Smith’s <hi rend="italic">Wealth of Nations</hi> (1776)
                        and in sharp contrast, he is suggesting that, in terms of freedom from the
                        greed that expresses itself in ‘laying up treasures…’, the heathens are
                        morally superior to European Christians who, long since, had lost their
                        ‘natural’ scruples against hoarding and amassing wealth without stint. Cf.
                        No. 50, ‘The Use of Money’, espec. I.8-9, III.1.</p></note> He desires and
                seeks nothing more than plain food to eat and plain raiment to put on. And he seeks
                this only from day to day. He reserves, he lays up nothing; unless it be as much
                corn at one season of the year as he will need before that season returns. This
                command, therefore, the heathens, though they know it not, do constantly and
                punctually observe. They ‘lay up for themselves no treasures upon earth’; no stores
                of purple or fine linen, of gold or silver, which either ‘moth or rust may corrupt’,
                or ‘thieves break through and steal’. But how do the Christians observe what they
                profess to receive as a command of the most high God? Not at all; not in any degree;
                no more than if no such command had ever been given to man. Even the <hi
                    rend="italic">good</hi> Christians, as they are accounted by others as well as
                themselves, pay no manner of <pb n="01:618"/>regard thereto. It might as well be
                still hid in its original Greek for any notice they take of it. In what Christian
                city do you find one man of five hundred who makes the least scruple of laying up
                just as much treasure as he can? Of increasing his goods just as far as he is able?
                There are indeed those who would not do this unjustly; there are many who will
                neither rob nor steal; and some who will not defraud their neighbour; nay, who will
                not gain either by his ignorance or necessity. But this is quite another point. Even
                these do not scruple the thing, but the manner of it. They do not scruple the
                ‘laying up treasures upon earth’, but the laying them up by dishonesty.</p>
            <p>They do not start at disobeying Christ, but at a breach of heathen morality. So that
                even these honest men do no more obey this command than a highwayman or a
                housebreaker. Nay, they never designed to obey it. From their youth up it never
                entered into their thoughts. They were bred up by their Christian parents, masters,
                and friends, without any instruction at all concerning it; unless it were this, to
                break it as soon and as much as they could, and to continue breaking it to their
                life’s end.</p>
            <p n="10">10. There is no one instance of spiritual infatuation in the world which is
                more amazing than this. Most of these very men read or hear the Bible read, many of
                them every Lord’s day. They have read or heard these words an hundred times, and yet
                never suspect that they are themselves condemned thereby, any more than by those
                which forbid parents to offer up their sons or daughters unto Moloch.</p>
            <p>O that God would speak to these miserable self-deceivers with his own voice, his
                mighty voice! That they may at last awake out of the snare of the devil,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim.
                    2:26.</p></note> and the scales may fall from their eyes!<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See Acts 9:18.</p></note></p>
            <p n="11">11. Do you ask what it is to ‘lay up treasures on earth’? It will be needful
                to examine this thoroughly. And let us, first, observe what is not forbidden in this
                command, that we may then clearly discern what is.</p>
            <p>We are not forbidden in this command, first, to ‘provide things honest in the sight
                of all men,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                        Cor. 8:21.</p></note> to provide wherewith we may ‘render unto all their
                    due,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        13:7.</p></note> whatsoever they can justly demand of us. So far from it
                that we are taught of God to ‘owe no man anything’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                    n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:8.</p></note> We ought therefore to use
                all diligence in our calling, <pb n="01:619"/>in order to owe no man anything: this
                being no other than a plain law of common justice which our Lord came ‘not to
                destroy but to fulfil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:17.</p></note></p>
            <p>Neither, secondly, does he here forbid the providing for ourselves such things as are
                needful for the body; a sufficiency of plain, wholesome food to eat, and clean
                raiment to put on. Yea, it is our duty, so far as God puts it into our power, to
                provide these things also; to the end we may ‘eat our own bread’,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 3:12.</p></note> and
                be ‘burdensome to no man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 11:9.</p></note></p>
            <p>Nor yet are we forbidden, thirdly, to provide for our children and for those of our
                own household. This also it is our duty to do, even upon principles of heathen
                morality. Every man ought to provide the plain necessaries<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                        X’, §26 and n.</p></note> of life both for his own wife and children, and to
                put them into a capacity of providing these for themselves when he is gone hence and
                is no more seen. I say, of providing <hi rend="italic">these</hi>, the plain
                necessaries of life—not delicacies, not superfluities—and that by their <hi
                    rend="italic">diligent labour</hi>; for it is no man’s duty to furnish them any
                more than himself with the means either of luxury or idleness. But if any man
                provides not thus far for his own children (as well as for ‘the widows of his own
                    house’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                        Tim. 5:3, 8.</p></note> of whom primarily St. Paul is speaking in those
                well-known words to Timothy), ‘he hath’ practically ‘denied the faith, and is worse
                than an infidel,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        Tim. 5:8.</p></note> or heathen.</p>
            <p>Lastly, we are not forbidden in these words to lay up from time to time what is
                needful for the carrying on our worldly business in such a measure and degree as is
                sufficient to answer the foregoing purposes: in such a measure as, first, to ‘owe no
                man anything’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        13:8.</p></note> secondly, to procure for ourselves the necessaries of life;
                and, thirdly, to furnish those of our own house with them while we live, and with
                the means of procuring them when we are gone to God.</p>
            <p n="12">12. We may now clearly discern (unless we are unwilling to discern it) what
                that is which is forbidden here. It is the designedly procuring more of this world’s
                goods than will answer the foregoing purposes; the labouring after a larger measure
                of worldly substance, a larger increase of gold and silver; the laying up any more
                than these ends require is what is here expressly and absolutely forbidden. If the
                words have any meaning at all, it must <pb n="01:620"/>be this, for they are capable
                of no other. Consequently whoever he is that, owing no man anything, and having food
                and raiment for himself and his household, together with a sufficiency to carry on
                his worldly business so far as answers these reasonable purposes—whosoever, I say,
                being already in these circumstances, seeks a still larger portion on earth—he lives
                in an open habitual denial of the Lord that bought him. He hath practically ‘denied
                the faith, and is worse than an’ African or American ‘infidel’.</p>
            <p n="13">13. Hear ye this, all ye that dwell in the world, and love the world wherein
                ye dwell. Ye may be ‘highly esteemed of men’; but ye are an ‘abomination in the
                sight of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Luke 16:15.</p></note> How long shall your souls cleave to the dust?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                    119:25.</p></note> How long will ye load yourselves with thick clay?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">See Hab.
                    2:6.</p></note> When will ye awake and see that the open, speculative heathens
                are nearer the kingdom of heaven than you?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">Nicomachean
                            Ethics</hi>, had been Wesley’s undergraduate textbook in ethics, along
                        with the ethical writings of Seneca and Cicero; with one voice they had
                        condemned greed and covetousness.</p></note> When will ye be persuaded to
                choose the better part; that which cannot be taken away from you?<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 10:42.</p></note> When
                will ye seek only to ‘lay up treasures in heaven’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                    n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:20.</p></note> renouncing, dreading,
                abhorring all other? If you aim at ‘laying up treasures on earth’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt 6:19.</p></note> you are
                not <hi rend="italic">barely</hi> losing your time and spending your strength for
                that which is not bread:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Isa. 55:2.</p></note> for what is the fruit if you
                succeed? You have murdered your own soul. You have extinguished the last spark of
                spiritual life therein. Now indeed, in the midst of life you are in death.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">BCP, Burial
                        (477).</p></note> You are a living man, but a dead Christian. ‘For where
                your treasure is, there will your heart be also.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64"
                    n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:21.</p></note> Your heart is sunk into
                the dust; your soul cleaveth to the ground.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 119:25.</p></note> Your affections are set,
                not on things above, but on things of the earth;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66"
                    n="66"><p rend="footnote text">See Col. 3:2.</p></note> on poor husks that may
                poison, but cannot satisfy an everlasting spirit made for God. Your love, your joy,
                your desire are all placed on the things which perish in the using. You have thrown
                away the treasure in heaven: God and Christ are lost. You have gained riches, and
                hell-fire.</p>
            <p n="14">14. O ‘how hardly shall they that have riches enter into the kingdom of
                    God!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">Mark
                        10:23.</p></note> When our Lord’s disciples were astonished at <hi
                    rend="Page">[01:621]</hi>his speaking thus he was so far from retracting it that
                he repeated the same important truth in stronger terms than before. ‘It is easier
                for a camel to go through the eye of a needle, than for a rich man to enter into the
                kingdom of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Mark 10:25.</p></note> How hard is it for them whose very word is applauded
                not to be wise in their own eyes! How hard for them not to think themselves better
                than the poor, base, uneducated herd of men! How hard not to seek happiness in their
                riches, or in things dependent upon them; in gratifying the desire of the flesh, the
                desire of the eye, or the pride of life!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See 1 John 2:16. Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’,
                        II.2 and n.</p></note> O ye rich, how can ye escape the damnation of
                    hell?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        23:33.</p></note> Only, with God all things are possible.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 19:26.</p></note></p>
            <p n="15">15. And even if you do not succeed, what is the fruit of your <hi
                    rend="italic">endeavouring</hi> to lay up treasures on earth? ‘They that will be
                rich’ (οἱ βουλόμενοι πλουτεῖν, they that desire, that endeavour after it, whether
                they succeed or no) ‘fall into a temptation and a snare’, a gin, a trap of the
                devil, ‘and into many foolish and hurtful lusts’—ἐπιθυμίας [πολλὰς] ἀνοήτους,
                desires with which reason hath nothing to do, such as properly belong, not to
                rational and immortal beings, but only to the brute beasts which have no
                understanding; ‘which drown men in destruction and perdition’,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:9.</p></note> in
                present and eternal misery. Let us but open our eyes, and we may daily see the
                melancholy proofs of this: men who desiring, resolving to be rich, ‘coveting after
                money, the root of all evil, have already pierced themselves through with many
                    sorrows’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                        Tim. 6:10.</p></note> and anticipated the hell to which they are going.</p>
            <p>The cautiousness with which the Apostle here speaks is highly observable. He does not
                affirm this absolutely of <hi rend="italic">the rich</hi>; for a man may possibly be
                rich without any fault of his, by an overruling providence, preventing his own
                choice. But he affirms it of οἱ βουλόμενοι πλουτεῖν, ‘those who desire’ or seek ‘to
                be rich’. Riches, dangerous as they are, do not always ‘drown men in destruction and
                perdition’. But the <hi rend="italic">desire of riches</hi> does: those who calmly
                desire and deliberately seek to attain them, whether they do, in fact, gain the
                world or no, do infallibly lose their own souls. These are they that sell him who
                bought them with his blood, for a few pieces of gold or silver.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 26:14-15.</p></note>
                These enter into a covenant with <pb n="01:622"/>death and hell: and their covenant
                shall stand. For they are daily making themselves meet to partake of their
                inheritance with the devil and his angels.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:41.</p></note></p>
            <p n="16">16. O who shall warn this generation of vipers to flee from the wrath to
                    come!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                        3:7.</p></note> Not those who lie at their gate, or cringe at their feet,
                desiring to be fed with the crumbs that fall from their tables.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 16:20-21.</p></note> Not
                those who court their favour or fear their frown: none of those who mind earthly
                things. But if there be a Christian upon earth, if there be a man who hath overcome
                the world, who desires nothing but God, and fears none but him that is able to
                destroy both body and soul in hell<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Matt 10:28.</p></note>—thou, O man of God, speak
                and spare not; lift up thy voice like a trumpet.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79"
                    n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Isa. 58:1.</p></note> Cry aloud, and show these
                honourable sinners the desperate condition wherein they stand. It may be one in a
                thousand may have ears to hear, may arise and shake himself from the dust; may break
                loose from these chains that bind him to the earth, and at length lay up treasures
                in heaven.</p>
            <p n="17">17. And if it should be that one of these, by the mighty power of God, awoke
                and asked, What must I do to be saved?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Acts 16:30.</p></note> the answer, according to the
                oracles of God, is clear, full, and express. God doth not say to thee, ‘Sell all
                that thou hast.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Luke 18:22.</p></note> Indeed he who seeth the hearts of men saw it needful
                to enjoin this in one peculiar case, that of the <hi rend="italic">young, rich
                    ruler</hi>. But he never laid it down for a general rule to all rich men, in all
                succeeding generations. His general direction is, first, ‘Be not highminded.’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                    11:20.</p></note> ‘God seeth not as man seeth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83"
                    n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Sam. 16:7.</p></note> He esteems thee not
                for thy riches, for thy grandeur or equipage, for any qualification or
                accomplishment which is directly or indirectly owing to thy wealth, which can be
                bought or procured thereby. All these are with him as dung and dross: let them be so
                with thee also. Beware thou think not thyself to be one jot wiser or better for all
                these things. Weigh thyself in another balance:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84"
                    n="84"><p rend="footnote text">I.e., ‘in the balance of the sanctuary’; cf. No.
                        10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, II.8 and n.</p></note> estimate thyself
                only by the measure of faith and love which God hath given thee. If thou hast more
                of the <pb n="01:623"/>knowledge and love of God than he, thou art on this account,
                and no other, wiser and better, more valuable and honourable than him who is with
                the dogs of thy flock.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Job 30:1.</p></note> But if thou hast not this treasure
                those art more foolish, more vile, more truly contemptible—I will not say, than the
                lowest servant under thy roof but—than the beggar laid at thy gate, full of
                    sores.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                        16:20.</p></note></p>
            <p n="18">18. Secondly, ‘Trust not in uncertain riches.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:17.</p></note> Trust
                not in them for help; and trust not in them for happiness.</p>
            <p>First, trust not in them for help. Thou art miserably mistaken if thou lookest for
                this in gold or silver. These are no more able to set thee <hi rend="italic">above
                    the world</hi> than to set thee above the devil. Know that both the world and
                the prince of this world<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p
                        rend="footnote text">John 14:30; 16:11.</p></note> laugh at all such
                preparations against them. These will little avail in the day of trouble—even if
                they remain in the trying hour. But it is not certain that they will; for how oft do
                they ‘make themselves wings and fly away’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 23:5.</p></note> But if not, what support
                will they afford, even in the ordinary troubles of life? The desire of thy
                    eyes,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p rend="footnote text">See Ezek.
                        24:16, 21.</p></note> the wife of thy youth,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Prov. 5:18; Mal. 2:14.</p></note>
                thy son, thine only son, or the friend which was as thy own soul,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Deut. 13:6; see also 1 Sam.
                        18:3.</p></note> is taken away at a stroke.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93"
                    n="93"><p rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 24:16.</p></note> Will thy riches
                reanimate the breathless clay, or call back its late inhabitant? Will they secure
                thee from sickness, diseases, pain? Do these visit the poor only? Nay; he that feeds
                thy flocks or tills thy ground has less sickness and pain than thou. He is more
                rarely visited by these unwelcome guests: and if they come there at all they are
                more easily driven away from the little cot than from ‘the cloud-topped
                    palaces’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">The Tempest</hi>, IV. i. 152—a conflation
                        from memory of ‘The cloud-capp’d towers, the gorgeous palaces’.</p></note>
                And during the time that thy body is chastened with pain, or consumes away with
                pining sickness, how do thy treasures help thee? Let the poor heathen answer:</p>
            <lg>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ut lippum pictae tabulae, fomenta podagrum,</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Auriculas citharae collecta sorde dolentes.</hi>
                </l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Wesley seems to have held Horace in an especial
                        contempt; cf., e.g., No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>,
                        III.9, where Wesley refers to him with two unflattering epithets (‘a heathen
                        Epicurean poet’ and ‘this poor wretch’). The quotation here is from the <hi
                            rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, I. ii. 52-53, and speaks of ‘such pleasures
                        as pictures can afford to weak eyes or bounty-laden tables to a man with
                        gout’. Despite this disdain, however, Wesley quotes Horace at least
                        twenty-nine times in the <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>.</p>
                </note>
            </lg>
            <p n="19"><pb n="01:624"/>19. But there is at hand a greater trouble than all these. <hi
                    rend="italic">Thou</hi> art to die. <hi rend="italic">Thou</hi> art to sink into
                dust; to return to the ground from which thou wast taken, to mix with common clay.
                    <hi rend="italic">Thy</hi> body is to go to the earth as it was, while thy
                spirit returns to God that gave it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Eccles. 12:7.</p></note> And the time draws on: the
                years slide away with a swift though silent pace. Perhaps your day is far spent: the
                noon of life is past, and the evening shadows begin to rest upon you. You feel in
                yourself sure approaching decay. The springs of life wear away apace.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John’s later
                        comment on his brother Charles’s death (<hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi> of
                        Conference, 1788): ‘He had no disease, but after a gradual decay of some
                        months, “The weary wheels of life stood still at last”;’ the line of poetry
                        is from John Dryden and Nathaniel Lee, <hi rend="italic">Oedipus</hi>, Act
                        IV, sc. 1.</p></note> Now what help is there in your riches? Do they sweeten
                death? Do they endear that solemn hour? Quite the reverse. ‘O death, how bitter art
                thou to a man that liveth at rest in his possessions!’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus. 41:1.</p></note> How
                unacceptable to him is that awful sentence. ‘This night shall thy soul be required
                of thee!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                        12:20.</p></note> Or will they prevent the unwelcome stroke, or protract the
                dreadful hour? Can they deliver your soul that it should not see death?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 33:19
                        (AV).</p></note> Can they restore the years that are past? Can they add to
                your appointed time a month, a day, an hour, a moment? Or will the good things you
                have chosen for your portion here follow you over the great gulf? Not so: naked came
                you into this world; naked must you return.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101"
                    n="101"><p rend="footnote text">See Job 1:21.</p></note></p>
            <lg>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Linquenda tellus, et domus et placens</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Uxor: nec harum quas seris arborum</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Te, praeter invisam cupressum,</hi>
                </l>
                <l>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ulla brevem dominum sequetur.</hi>
                </l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Horace, again; this time from the <hi rend="italic"
                            >Odes</hi>, II. xiv. 21-24. The orig. reads <hi rend="italic">colis</hi>
                        (‘culture’) instead of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">seris</hi> (‘planting’)
                        and, in l. 23, it reads <hi rend="italic">invisas cupressos</hi> (i.e., the
                        plural): ‘You must take leave of lands, home, winsome wife; and no tree
                        whose culture had pleased shall survive your brief reign except those
                        mournful cypresses.’ Cf. also, JWJ, July 4, 1756, and Oct. 13, 1779.</p>
                </note>
            </lg>
            <p>Surely, were not these truths too plain to be <hi rend="italic">observed</hi>,
                because they are too plain to be <hi rend="italic">denied</hi>, no man that is to
                die could possibly ‘trust’ for help ‘in uncertain riches’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:17.</p></note></p>
            <p n="20">20. And trust not in them for happiness. For here also they will be found
                ‘deceitful upon the weights’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Ps. 62:9 (BCP).</p></note> Indeed this every <pb
                    n="625"/>reasonable man may infer from what has been observed already. For if
                neither thousands of gold and silver, nor any of the advantages or pleasures
                purchased thereby, can prevent our being miserable, it evidently follows they cannot
                make us happy. What happiness can they afford to him who in the midst of all is
                constrained to cry out,</p>
            <lg>
                <l>To my new courts sad thought does still repair,</l>
                <l>And round my gilded roofs hangs hovering care.</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Matthew Prior, <hi rend="italic">Solomon</hi>, ii. 53-54
                        (the orig. uses the past tense). Cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection of
                            Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>, II.129. Cf. Wesley’s ‘Thoughts on the
                        Character and Writings of Mr. Prior’, where he asserts that Prior’s best
                        passages ‘do not yield to anything that has been wrote by Pope, or Dryden,
                        or any English poet, except Milton’ (<hi rend="italic">AM</hi> 1782,
                        665).</p>
                </note>
            </lg>
            <p>Indeed experience is here so full, strong, and undeniable, that it makes all other
                arguments needless. Appeal we therefore to fact. Are the rich and great the only
                happy men? And is each of them more or less happy in proportion to his measure of
                riches? Are they happy at all? I had wellnigh said, they are of all men most
                    miserable!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        Cor. 15:19.</p></note> Rich man, for once, speak the truth from thy heart.
                Speak, both for thyself, and for thy brethren:</p>
            <lg>
                <l>Amidst our plenty something still…</l>
                <l>To me, to thee, to him is wanting!</l>
                <l>That cruel something unpossessed</l>
                <l>Corrodes and leavens all the rest.</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Matthew Prior, ‘The Ladle’, ll. 162, 164-66, with l. 163
                        omitted. See also No. 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, III.1.</p>
                </note>
            </lg>
            <p>Yea, and so it will, till thy wearisome days of vanity are shut up in the night of
                death.</p>
            <p>Surely then, to trust in riches for happiness is the greatest folly of all that are
                under the sun! Are you not convinced of this? Is it possible you should still expect
                to find happiness in money or all it can procure? What! Can silver and gold, and
                eating and drinking, and horses and servants, and glittering apparel, and diversions
                and pleasures (as they are called) make thee happy? They can as soon make thee
                immortal.</p>
            <p n="21">21. These are all dead show. Regard them not. ‘Trust’ thou ‘in the living
                    God;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                        4:10.</p></note> so shalt thou be safe under the shadow of the
                    Almighty;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Ps. 91:1.</p></note> his faithfulness and truth shall be thy shield and <pb
                    n="626"/>buckler.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Ps. 91:4 (BCP).</p></note> He is a very present help in
                time of trouble;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Ps. 46:1.</p></note> such an help as can never fail. Then shalt thou
                say, if all thy other friends die, ‘The Lord liveth, and blessed be my strong
                    helper!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                        18:47 (BCP).</p></note> He shall remember thee when thou liest sick upon thy
                    bed;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                        41:3 (BCP).</p></note> when vain is the help of man;<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 60:11; 108:12.</p></note>
                when all the things of earth can give no support, he will ‘make all thy bed in thy
                    sickness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Ps. 41:3.</p></note> He will sweeten thy pain; the consolations of God shall
                cause thee to clap thy hands in the flames. And even when this house of earth<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="footnote text">See below, §26.
                        Wesley’s thoroughgoing dualism is reflected in his oft-repeated metaphors
                        about the earthly body as temporary lodgement far the soul. His biblical
                        sources would include Job 4:19 (‘houses of clay’) and 2 Cor. 5:1 (‘the
                        earthly house of this tabernacle’); and he uses one or another variant of
                        the idea in other sermons (thirteen of them) and at least three letters, not
                        to mention his early imitation of Horace (<hi rend="italic">Odes</hi> I.
                        xxiv), ver. 6, l. 4: ‘[The body’s] ancient tenement of clay’. The metaphor
                        had come to be a cliché in English poetry, from Thomas Carew (‘On the Lady
                        Mary Villiers’: ‘The purest soul that e’er was sent/Into a clayey tenement’)
                        to John Dryden (‘Absalom and Achitophel’, I.144: ‘And o’er informed the
                        tenement of clay’) to James Thomson (‘Upon Happiness’, l. 125: ‘cage of
                        clay’), and many others.</p></note> is wellnigh shaken down, when it is just
                ready to drop into the dust, he will teach thee to say, ‘O death, where is thy
                sting? O grave, where is thy victory? […] Thanks be unto God, who giveth me the
                victory, through my Lord Jesus Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p
                        rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 15:55-57.</p></note></p>
            <p>O trust in him for happiness as well as for help. All the springs of happiness are in
                him. Trust in him ‘who giveth us all things richly to enjoy’, παρέχοντι [ἡμῖν]
                πλουσίως πάντα εἰς ἀπόλαυσιν;<!--Mark this with an xml:lang tag later.--><note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118"><p rend="footnote text">A paraphrase of the
                        meaning of 1 Tim. 6:17 in the <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>; cf. the AV: ‘who
                        giveth us richly all things to enjoy’.</p></note> who of his own rich and
                free mercy holds them out to us as in his own hand, that receiving them as his gift,
                and as pledges of his love, we may ‘enjoy all’ that we possess. It is his love gives
                a relish to all we taste, puts life and sweetness into all, while every creature
                leads us up to the great Creator, and all earth is a scale to heaven.<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 56, ‘God’s
                        Approbation of His Works’, I.14 and n.</p></note> He transfuses the joys
                that are at his own right hand into all he bestows on his thankful children; who,
                having fellowship with the Father and his Son Jesus Christ,<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 1:3.</p></note> enjoy
                him in all and above all.</p>
            <p n="22">22. Thirdly, seek not to <hi rend="italic">increase in goods</hi>. ‘Lay not up
                for thyself treasures upon earth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:19.</p></note> This is a flat, positive
                command, full as clear as ‘Thou shalt not commit adultery.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:14.</p></note> How then
                is it <pb n="01:627"/>possible for a rich man to grow richer without denying the
                Lord that bought him? Yea, how can any man who has already the necessaries of life
                gain or aim at more, and be guiltless? ‘Lay not up’, saith our Lord, ‘treasures upon
                earth.’ If in spite of this you do and will lay up money or goods, what ‘moth or
                rust’ may ‘corrupt, or thieves break through and steal’;<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt 6:19.</p></note> if you
                will add house to house, or field to field,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124"
                    n="124"><p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 5:8.</p></note> why do you call
                yourself a Christian? You do not obey Jesus Christ. You do not design it. Why do you
                name yourself by his name? ‘Why call ye me, Lord, Lord’, saith he himself, ‘and do
                not the things which I say?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Luke 6:46.</p></note></p>
            <p n="23">23. If you ask, ‘But what must we do with our goods, seeing we have more than
                we have occasion to use, if we must not lay them up? Must we throw them away?’ I
                answer: if you threw them into the sea, if you were to cast them into the fire and
                consume them, they would be better bestowed than they are now.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p rend="footnote text">But see No. 50, ‘The Use of
                        Money’, §§2-3, where certain positive uses of money are
                    acknowledged.</p></note> You cannot find so mischievous a manner of throwing
                them away as either the laying them up for your posterity or the laying them out
                upon yourselves in folly and superfluity. Of all possible methods of ‘throwing them
                away’ these two are the very worst—the most opposite to the gospel of Christ, and
                the most pernicious to your own soul.</p>
            <p>How pernicious to your own soul the latter of these is has been excellently shown by
                a late writer:</p>
            <quote>If we waste our money we are not only guilty of wasting a talent which God has
                given us, […] but we do ourselves this farther harm: we turn this useful talent into
                a powerful means of corrupting ourselves; because so far as it is spent wrong, so
                far it is spent in the support of some wrong temper, in gratifying some vain and
                unreasonable desires, which as Christians we are obliged to renounce.</quote>
            <quote>As wit and fine parts cannot be only trifled away, but will expose those that
                have them to greater follies, so money cannot be only trifled away, but if it is not
                used according to reason and religion, will make people live a more silly and
                extravagant life than they would have done without it. If therefore you don’t spend
                your money in doing good to others, you must spend it to the hurt of yourself. You
                act like one that refuses the cordial to his sick friend which he cannot drink
                himself without inflaming his blood. For this is the case of superfluous money; if
                you give it to those who want it it is a cordial; if you spend it upon yourself in
                something that you do not want it only inflames and disorders your mind. […]</quote>
            <quote><pb n="01:628"/>In using riches where they have no real use, nor we any real
                want, we only use them to our great hurt, in creating unreasonable desires, in
                nourishing ill tempers, in indulging in foolish passions, and supporting a vain turn
                of mind. For high eating and drinking, fine clothes and fine houses, state and
                equipage, gay pleasures and diversions, do all of them naturally hurt and disorder
                our heart. They are the food and nourishment of all the folly and weakness of our
                nature. […] They are all of them the support of something that ought not to be
                supported. They are contrary to that sobriety and piety of heart which relishes
                divine things. They are so many weights upon our mind, that makes us less able and
                less inclined to raise our thoughts and affections to things above.</quote>
            <quote>So that money thus spent is not merely wasted or lost, but it is spent to bad
                purposes and miserable effects; to the corruption and disorder of our hearts; to the
                making us unable to follow the sublime doctrines of the gospel. It is but like
                keeping money from the poor to buy poison for ourselves.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn127" n="127"><p rend="footnote text">Law, <hi rend="italic">Serious
                            Call</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.50-51); cf. above, §1 and n.
                        See also No. 108, ‘On Riches’, II.3.</p></note></quote>
            <p n="24">24. Equally inexcusable are those who <hi rend="italic">lay up</hi> what they
                do not need for any reasonable purposes:</p>
            <quote>If a man had hands and eyes and feet that he could give to those that wanted
                them; if he should lock them up in a chest […] instead of giving them to his
                brethren that were blind and lame, should we not justly reckon him an inhuman
                wretch? If he should rather choose to amuse himself with hoarding them up than
                entitle himself to an eternal reward by giving them to those that wanted eyes and
                hands, might we not justly reckon him mad?</quote>
            <quote>Now money has very much the nature of eyes and feet. If therefore we lock it up
                in chests […] while the poor and distressed want it for their necessary uses […] we
                are not far from the cruelty of him that chooses rather to hoard up the hands and
                eyes than to give them to those that want them. If we choose to lay it up rather
                than to entitle ourselves to an eternal reward by disposing of our money well, we
                are guilty of his madness that rather chooses to lock up eyes and hands than to make
                himself for ever blessed by giving them to those that want them.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p rend="footnote text">More from Law; but note that
                        Wesley reverses Law’s ordering of the ‘heads’ of his argument; cf. <hi
                            rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, ch. vi; cf. §1, above, and
                n.</p></note></quote>
            <p n="25">25. May not this be another reason why rich men shall so hardly enter into the
                kingdom of heaven?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Matt. 19:23.</p></note> A vast majority of them are under a curse,
                under the peculiar curse of God; inasmuch as in the general tenor of their lives
                they are not only robbing God continually, embezzling and wasting their Lord’s
                goods, and by that very means corrupting their own souls; but also robbing the poor,
                the hungry, the naked, wronging the widow and the fatherless, and making themselves
                accountable for all the <pb n="01:629"/>want, affliction, and distress which they
                may but do not remove. Yea, doth not the blood of all those who perish for want of
                what they either lay up or lay out needlessly, cry against them from the earth?<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p rend="footnote text">See Gen.
                    4:10.</p></note> O what account will they give to him who is ready to judge both
                the quick and the dead!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 4:5.</p></note></p>
            <p n="26">26. The true way of employing what you do not want yourselves you may,
                fourthly, learn from those words of our Lord which are the counterpart of what went
                before: ‘Lay up for yourselves treasures in heaven, where neither moth nor rust doth
                corrupt, and where thieves do not break through and steal.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn132" n="132"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:20.</p></note> Put out
                whatever thou canst spare upon better security than this world can afford. Lay up
                thy treasures in the bank of heaven; and God shall restore them in that day. ‘He
                that hath pity upon the poor lendeth unto the Lord,’ and look, ‘what he layeth out,
                it shall be paid him again.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 19:17.</p></note> Place that, saith he, unto
                my account. Howbeit, ‘thou owest me thine own self also!’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Philem. 19.</p></note></p>
            <p>Give to the poor with a single eye, with an upright heart, and write, ‘So much given
                to God.’ For ‘Inasmuch as ye did it unto one of the least of these my brethren, ye
                have done it unto me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:40.</p></note></p>
            <p>This is the part of a ‘faithful and wise steward’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136"
                    n="136"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 12:42.</p></note> not to sell either his
                houses or lands, or principal stock, be it more or less, unless some peculiar
                circumstance should require it; and not to desire or endeavour to increase it, any
                more than to squander it away in vanity; but to employ it wholly to those wise and
                reasonable purposes for which his Lord has lodged it in his hands. The wise steward,
                after having provided his own household with what is needful for life and
                    godliness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        2 Pet. 1:3.</p></note> ‘makes’ himself ‘friends with’ all that remains from
                time to time of the ‘mammon of unrighteousness; that when he fails they may receive
                him into everlasting habitations;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:9.</p></note> that whensoever his earthly
                    tabernacle<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        above, §21 and n.</p></note> is dissolved, they who were before carried into
                Abraham’s bosom,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >See Luke 16:22.</p></note> after having eaten his bread, and worn the
                fleece of his flock, and praised God for the consolation, may welcome him into
                paradise, and to ‘the house of God, eternal in the heavens’.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn141" n="141"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:1.</p></note></p>
            <p><pb n="01:630"/>27. We ‘charge you’, therefore, ‘who are rich in this world’,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim.
                        6:17.</p></note> as having authority from our great Lord and Master,
                    ἀγαθοεργεῖν<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        Tim. 6:18.</p></note>—‘to be habitually doing good’, to live in a course of
                good works. ‘Be ye merciful as your Father which is in heaven is merciful,’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                    6:36.</p></note> who doth good and ceaseth not. ‘Be ye merciful’—‘How far?’ <hi
                    rend="italic">After your power</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. the <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi>, §5:
                        ‘doing good, by being in every kind merciful <hi rend="italic">after their
                            power</hi>’.</p></note> with all the ability which God giveth. Make this
                your only measure of doing good, not any beggarly maxims or customs of the world. We
                charge you to ‘be rich in good works’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:17-18.</p></note> as you have much, to <hi
                    rend="italic">give plenteously</hi>. Freely ye have received; freely give;<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                    10:8.</p></note> so as to lay up no treasure but in heaven. Be ye ‘ready to
                    distribute’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148"><p rend="footnote text">1
                        Tim. 6:18.</p></note> to everyone according to his necessity. Disperse
                abroad, give to the poor: deal your bread to the hungry.<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn149" n="149"><p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 58:7.</p></note> Cover
                the naked with a garment,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150"><p
                        rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 18:7.</p></note> entertain the stranger,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb.
                    13:2.</p></note> carry or send relief to them that are in prison. Heal the sick;
                not by miracle, but through the blessing of God upon your seasonable support. Let
                the blessing of him that was ready to perish through pining want come upon
                    thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152"><p rend="footnote text">See Job
                        29:13.</p></note> Defend the oppressed, plead the cause of the fatherless,
                and make the widow’s heart sing for joy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153"
                        ><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note></p>
            <p n="28">28. We exhort <hi rend="italic">you</hi> in the name of the Lord Jesus Christ
                to be ‘willing to communicate’, κοινωνικοὺς εἴναι;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154"
                    n="154"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:18, … εὐμετάδοτους εἴναι,
                        κοινωνικούς, ….</p></note> to be of the same spirit (though not in the same
                outward state) with those believers of ancient times, who ‘remained steadfast’ ἐν τῇ
                    κοινωνίᾳ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                        2:42. Note Wesley’s ἐν for καὶ.</p></note> in that blessed and holy
                ‘fellowship’ wherein ‘none said that anything was his own, but they had all things
                    common.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Acts 4:32.</p></note> Be a steward, a faithful and wise steward,<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                    12:42.</p></note> of God and of the poor; differing from them in these two
                circumstances only, that your wants are first supplied out of the portion of your
                Lord’s goods which remains in your hands, and that you have the blessedness of
                giving. Thus ‘lay up for yourselves a good foundation’, not in the world which now
                is, but rather ‘for the time to come, that ye may lay hold on eternal life.’<note
                    place="foot" xml:id="ftn158" n="158"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim.
                        6:19.</p></note> The great <pb n="01:631"/>foundation indeed of all the
                blessings of God, whether temporal or eternal, is the Lord Jesus Christ, his
                righteousness and blood, what he hath done, and what he hath suffered for us. And
                ‘other foundation’, in this sense, ‘can no man lay;’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn159" n="159"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:11.</p></note> no, not
                an apostle, no, not an angel from heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn160" n="160"
                        ><p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 1:8.</p></note> But through his merits,
                whatever we do in his name is a foundation for a good reward in the day when ‘every
                man shall receive his own reward, according to his own labour.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn161" n="161"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:8.</p></note> Therefore
                ‘labour’ thou, ‘not for the meat that perisheth, but for that which endureth unto
                everlasting life.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn162" n="162"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >John 6:27.</p></note> Therefore ‘whatsoever thy hand’ now ‘findeth to do,
                do it with thy might’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn163" n="163"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Eccles. 9:10.</p></note> Therefore let</p>
            <lg>
                <l>No fair occasion pass unheeded by;</l>
                <l>Snatching the golden moments as they fly,</l>
                <l>Thou by few fleeting years ensure eternity!</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn164" n="164">
                    <p rend="footnote text">An adaptation from Samuel Wesley, Jun., ‘On the Death of
                        Mr. Morgan…’; ll. 19-21, in <hi rend="italic">Poems</hi> (1736), p. 108.
                        Later, John will quote the first line here (with his own variations) in a
                        letter to Ann Bolton, Nov. 28, 1772.</p>
                </note>
            </lg>
            <p>‘By patient continuance in well-doing, seek’ thou ‘for glory and honour and
                    immortality.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn165" n="165"><p rend="footnote text"
                        >Rom. 2:7.</p></note> In a constant, zealous performance of all good
                    works<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn166" n="166"><p rend="footnote text">See
                        Titus 2:14.</p></note> wait thou for that happy hour when ‘the King shall
                say, […] I was an hungered, and ye gave me meat; I was thirsty, and ye gave me
                drink. I was a stranger, and ye took me in, naked, and ye clothed me. I was sick,
                and ye visited me; I was in prison, and ye came unto me.’<note place="foot"
                    xml:id="ftn167" n="167"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:34-36.</p></note>
                ‘Come, ye blessed of my Father, receive the kingdom prepared for you from the
                foundation of the world!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn168" n="168"><p
                        rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt 25:34. Cf. No. 51, <hi rend="italic">The Good
                            Steward</hi>, III and IV.</p></note></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
