<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 33: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse XIII</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon033</idno>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 33: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse XIII</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="687" to="698"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:687"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Thirteenth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 7:21-27</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Not everyone that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into
                        the kingdom of heaven; but he that doeth the will of my Father which is in
                        heaven.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not
                        prophesied in thy name? And in thy name have cast out devils? And in thy
                        name done many wonderful works?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you: depart
                        from me, ye that work iniquity.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Therefore whosoever heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth
                        them, I will liken him unto a wise man, which built his house upon a
                        rock;</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds
                        blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell not; for it was founded upon a
                        rock.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And everyone that heareth these sayings of mine, and doeth
                        them not, shall be likened unto a foolish man, which built his house upon
                        the sand;</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">And the rain descended, and the floods came, and the winds
                        blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell: and great was the fall of
                        it.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Our divine Teacher, having declared the whole counsel of God with regard
                    to the way of salvation, and observed the chief hindrance of those who desire to
                    walk therein, now closes the whole with these weighty words; thereby, as it
                    were, setting his seal to his prophecy, and impressing his whole authority on
                    what he had delivered, that it might stand firm to all generations.</p>
                <p n="2">2. For thus saith the Lord, that none may ever conceive there is any other
                    way than this: ‘Not everyone that saith unto me, Lord, Lord, shall enter into
                    the kingdom of heaven, but he that doeth the will of my Father which is in
                    heaven. Many will say to me in that day, Lord, Lord, have we not prophesied in
                    thy name? And in thy name have cast out devils? And in thy name done many
                    wonderful works? And then will I profess unto them, I never knew you: depart
                    from me, ye that work iniquity. […] Therefore <pb n="01:688"/>everyone that
                    heareth these sayings of mine and doeth them not, shall be likened unto a
                    foolish man which built his house upon the sand. And the rain descended, and the
                    floods came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house; and it fell: and
                    great was the fall of it.’</p>
                <p n="3">3. I design in the following discourse, first, to consider the case of him
                    who thus builds his house upon the sand; secondly, to show the wisdom of him who
                    builds upon a rock; and thirdly, to conclude with a practical application.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, I am to consider the case of him who builds his house
                    upon the sand. It is concerning him our Lord saith, ‘Not everyone that saith
                    unto me, Lord, Lord! shall enter into the kingdom of heaven.’ And this is a
                    decree which cannot pass; which standeth fast for ever and ever.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps.
                        148:6.</p></note> It therefore imports us in the highest degree throughly to
                    understand the force of these words. Now what are we to understand by that
                    expression, ‘that saith unto me, Lord, Lord’? It undoubtedly means, ‘that thinks
                    of going to heaven by any other way than that which I have now described’. It
                    therefore implies (to begin at the lowest point) all good words, all verbal
                    religion. It includes whatever creeds we may rehearse; whatever professions of
                    faith we make; whatever number of prayers we may repeat, whatever thanksgivings
                    we read or say to God. We may speak good of his name;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">I.e., lead (or join in) the
                            responses of the daily offices, beginning with the ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >Jubilate Deo</hi>’, Ps. 100:4, etc., in BCP, Morning
                        Prayer.</p></note> and declare his loving-kindness to the children of
                        men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            another favourite Psalm in ‘Morning Prayer’: 107:8, 15, 21, 31
                            (BCP).</p></note> We may be talking of all his mighty acts, and telling
                    of his salvation from day to day. By comparing spiritual things with
                        spiritual,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Cor. 2:13.</p></note> we may show the meaning of the oracles of God.
                    We may explain the mysteries of his kingdom, which have been hid from the
                    beginning of the world.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Col. 1:26.</p></note> We may speak with the
                    tongue of angels rather than men concerning the deep things of God.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            13:1.</p></note> We may proclaim to sinners, ‘Behold the Lamb of God,
                    who taketh away the sin of the world.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 1:29.</p></note> Yea, we may do this with such
                    a measure of the power of God, and such demonstration of his Spirit, as to save
                    many souls from death,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Jas. 5:20.</p></note> and hide a multitude of
                        sins.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Pet.4:8.</p></note> And yet ’tis very possible all <pb n="01:689"/>this
                    may be no more than ‘saying, Lord, Lord!’ After I have thus successfully
                    preached to others, still I myself may be a castaway.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">A compounded echo here from 1
                            Cor. 9:27 and the shipboard memoranda back in January and February 1738;
                            cf. JWJ, Jan. 8, Jan. 24, and Feb. 1; see also Moore, I.342-44. Note
                            also the premonition here of John Wesley’s later outburst to Charles,
                            June 27, 1766: ‘Neither am I impelled to [my evangelical mission] by
                            fear of any kind. I have no more fear than love. Or if I have any fear,
                            it is not that of falling into hell but of falling into nothing.’ Cf.
                            No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.13 and
                        n.</p></note> I may in the hand of God snatch many souls from hell, and yet
                    drop into it when I have done. I may bring many others to the kingdom of heaven,
                    and yet myself never enter there. Reader, if God hath ever blessed my word to
                        <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> soul, pray that he may be merciful to <hi
                        rend="italic">me</hi> a sinner.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Luke 18:13; as we have seen, Wesley’s ‘assurance’
                            of 1738 had been confirmed to him in 1739 when <hi rend="italic"
                                >others</hi> received ‘assurance’ as a fruit of his preaching of
                            it.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. The ‘saying, Lord, Lord!’ may, secondly, imply the doing no harm.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. below,
                            III.2-4, and No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, II.4 and n.</p></note>
                    We may abstain from every presumptuous sin, from every kind of outward
                    wickedness. We may refrain from all those ways of acting or speaking which are
                    forbidden in Holy Writ. We may be able to say to all those among whom we live,
                    Which of you convinceth me of sin?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 8:46.</p></note> We may have a conscience void
                    of any external offence towards God and towards man.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">See Acts 24:16.</p></note> We
                    may be clear of all uncleanness, ungodliness, and unrighteousness as to the
                    outward act, or (as the Apostle testifies concerning himself) ‘touching the
                    righteousness of the law’, i.e. outward righteousness, ‘blameless’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            3:6.</p></note> but yet we are not hereby justified. Still this is no
                    more than ‘saying, Lord, Lord!’ And if we go no farther than this we shall never
                    ‘enter into the kingdom of heaven’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. The ‘saying, Lord, Lord!’ may imply, thirdly, many of what are usually
                    styled good works. A man may attend the Supper of the Lord, may hear abundance
                    of excellent sermons, and omit no opportunity of partaking all the other
                    ordinances of God. I may do good to my neighbour, deal my bread to the hungry,
                    and cover the naked with a garment. I may be so zealous of good works as even to
                    ‘give all my goods to feed the poor’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:3.</p></note> Yea, and I may do all
                    this with a desire to please God and a real belief that I do please him thereby
                    (which is undeniably the case of those our Lord introduces, ‘saying unto him,
                    Lord, Lord!’); and still I may have no part in the glory which shall be
                        revealed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 8:18; another description of ‘the almost
                    Christian’.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4"><pb n="01:690"/>4. If any man marvels at this, let him acknowledge he is a
                    stranger to the whole religion of Jesus Christ; and in particular to that
                    perfect portraiture thereof which he has set before us in this discourse. For
                    how far short is all this of that righteousness and true holiness<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        4:24.</p></note> which he has described therein! How widely distant from
                    that inward kingdom of heaven which is now opened in the believing soul! Which
                    is first sown in the heart as a grain of mustard seed, but afterwards putteth
                    forth great branches,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 13:31-32.</p></note> on which grow all
                    the fruits of righteousness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Phil. 1:11.</p></note> every good temper and word
                    and work.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Yet as clearly as he had declared this, as frequently as he had repeated
                    that none who have not this kingdom of God within them shall enter into the
                    kingdom of heaven, our Lord well knew that many would not receive this saying,
                    and therefore confirms it yet again. ‘Many’ (saith he; not one; not a few only;
                    it is not a rare or an uncommon case) ‘shall say unto me in that day’. Not only,
                    we have said many prayers; we have spoken thy praise; we have refrained from
                    evil; we have exercised ourselves in doing good; but what is abundantly more
                    than this—‘We have prophesied in thy name. In thy name have we cast out devils;
                    in thy name done many wonderful works.’ ‘We have prophesied’: we have declared
                    thy will to mankind; we have showed sinners the way to peace and glory. And we
                    have done this ‘in thy name’, according to the truth of thy gospel. Yea, and by
                    thy authority, who didst confirm the Word with the Holy Ghost sent down from
                    heaven. For ‘in’ (or <hi rend="italic">by</hi>) ‘thy name’, by the power of thy
                    Word and of thy Spirit, ‘have we cast out devils;’ out of the souls which they
                    had long claimed as their own, and whereof they had full and quiet possession.
                    ‘And in thy name’, by thy power, not our own, ‘have we done many wonderful
                    works;’ insomuch that even ‘the dead heard the voice of the Son of God’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                            5:25.</p></note> speaking by us, and lived. ‘And then will I profess’
                    even ‘unto them, I never knew you:’ no, not then, when you were ‘casting out
                    devils in my name’. Even then I did not know you as my own; for your heart was
                    not right toward God. Ye were not yourselves meek and lowly; ye were not lovers
                    of God and of all mankind; ye were not renewed in the image of God.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">See Col.
                            3:10.</p></note> Ye were not holy as I am holy.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 1:16.</p></note>
                    ‘Depart from me, ye’ who, <pb n="01:691"/>notwithstanding all this, are ‘workers
                    of iniquity’ (ἀνομία). Ye are transgressors of my law—my law of holy and perfect
                    love.</p>
                <p n="6">6. It is to put this beyond all possibility of contradiction that our Lord
                    confirms it by that apposite comparison. ‘Everyone’, saith he, ‘who heareth
                    these sayings of mine and doeth them not, shall be likened unto a foolish man
                    which built his house upon the sand. And the rain descended, and the floods
                    came, and the winds blew, and beat upon that house:’ as they will surely do,
                    sooner or later, upon every soul of man; even the floods of outward affliction,
                    or inward temptation; the storms of pride, anger, fear, or desire. ‘And it fell:
                    and great was the fall of it;’ so that it perished for ever and ever. Such must
                    be the portion of all who rest in anything short of that religion which is above
                    described. And the <hi rend="italic">greater</hi> will their fall be because
                    they ‘heard those sayings, and yet did them not’.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. I am, secondly, to show the wisdom of him that doth them, that
                    ‘buildeth his house upon a rock’. He indeed is wise who ‘doeth the will of my
                    Father which is in heaven’. He is truly wise whose ‘righteousness exceeds the
                    righteousness of the scribes and Pharisees’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                        n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:20.</p></note> He is poor in
                        spirit;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 5:3.</p></note> knowing himself even as also he is known.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            13:12.</p></note> He sees and feels all his sin, and all his guilt, till
                    it is washed away by the atoning blood. He is conscious of his lost estate, of
                    the wrath of God abiding on him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See John 3:36.</p></note> and of his utter
                    inability to help himself till he is filled with peace and joy in the Holy
                        Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            14:17.</p></note> He is meek and gentle, patient toward all men, never
                    ‘returning evil for evil, or railing for railing, but contrariwise
                        blessing’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 Pet. 3:9.</p></note> till he overcomes evil with good.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            12:21.</p></note> His soul is athirst for nothing on earth, but only for
                    God, the living God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Ps. 42:2.</p></note> He has bowels of love for
                    all mankind, and is ready to lay down his life for his enemies. He loves the
                    Lord his God with all his heart, and with all his mind and soul and
                        strength.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Mark 12:30.</p></note> He alone shall enter into the kingdom of
                    heaven who in this spirit doth good unto all men;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 6:10.</p></note> and
                    who, being for this cause despised and <pb n="01:692"/>rejected of men,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        53:3.</p></note> being hated, reproached, and persecuted, ‘rejoices and is
                    exceeding glad’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Matt. 5:12.</p></note> knowing in whom he hath believed;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim.
                            1:12.</p></note> and being assured these light, momentary afflictions
                    will ‘work out for him an eternal weight of glory’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                    4:17.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. How truly wise is this man! He knows himself: an everlasting spirit
                    which came forth from God, and was sent down into an house of clay,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">See Job 4:19. Cf.
                            No. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §28 and n.</p></note> not to do his
                    own will, but the will of him that sent him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39"
                        n="39"><p rend="footnote text">See John 6:38.</p></note> He knows the world:
                    the place in which he is to pass a few days or years, not as an inhabitant, but
                    as a stranger and sojourner in his way to the everlasting habitations;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                        16:9.</p></note> and accordingly he uses the world, as not abusing it, and
                    as knowing the fashion of it passes away.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41"
                        n="41"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 7:31. See also No. 20, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Lord Our Righteousness</hi>, II.20 and
                        n.</p></note> He knows God: his Father and his friend, the parent of all
                    good, the centre of the spirits of all flesh, the sole happiness of all
                    intelligent beings. He sees, clearer than the light of the noonday sun, that
                    this is the end of man: to glorify him who made him for himself, and to love and
                    enjoy him for ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                            rend="footnote text">An interesting conflation of two famous aphorisms:
                            Q.1 and A. in the Westminster <hi rend="italic">Shorter Catechism</hi>
                            and St. Augustine’s <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, I.i.; cf. No. 3,
                                <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, II.5 and
                        n.</p></note> And with equal clearness he sees the means to that end, to the
                    enjoyment of God in glory; even now to know, to love, to imitate God, and to
                    believe in Jesus Christ whom he hath sent.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43"
                        n="43"><p rend="footnote text">See John 6:29; 17:3.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. He is a wise man, even in God’s account; for ‘he buildeth his house upon
                    a rock;’ upon the Rock of Ages, the everlasting Rock, the Lord Jesus Christ.
                    Fitly is he so called; for he changeth not.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44"
                        n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See Mal. 3:6.</p></note> He is ‘the same
                    yesterday, today, and for ever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:8.</p></note> To him both the man of God of
                    old, and the Apostle citing his words, bear witness: ‘Thou, Lord, in the
                    beginning hast laid the foundation of the earth, and the heavens are the works
                    of thine hands. They shall perish, but thou remainest; they all shall wax old as
                    doth a garment: and as a vesture shalt thou fold them up, and they shall be
                    changed: but thou art the same, and thy years shall not fail.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Heb.
                                1:10-12 [quoting Ps. 102:25-27 (BCP)].</p></note></hi>
                    <pb n="01:693"/>Wise therefore is the man who buildeth on him; who layeth him
                    for his only foundation; who builds only upon his blood and righteousness, upon
                    what he hath done and suffered for us. On this corner-stone he fixes his faith,
                    and rests the whole weight of his soul upon it. He is taught of God to say, Lord
                    I have sinned; I deserve the nethermost hell. But I am ‘justified freely by thy
                    grace, through the redemption that is in Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24.</p></note> ‘And
                    the life I now live I live by faith in him who loved me and gave himself for
                        me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 2:20.</p></note> ‘The life I now live’: namely, a divine, heavenly
                    life, a life which is ‘hid with Christ in God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48"
                        n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:3.</p></note> I now live, even in the
                    flesh, a life of love, of pure love both to God and man; a life of holiness and
                    happiness, praising God and doing all things to his glory.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Yet let not such an one think that he shall not see war any more,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">See Mic.
                        4:3.</p></note> that he is now out of the reach of temptation. It still
                    remains for God to prove the grace he hath given: he shall be tried as gold in
                    the fire.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rev. 3:18.</p></note> He shall be tempted not less than they who know
                    not God; perhaps abundantly more. For Satan will not fail to try to the
                    uttermost those whom he is not able to destroy. Accordingly ‘the rain’ will
                    impetuously ‘descend’; only at such times and in such a manner as seems good,
                    not to the prince of the power of the air, but to him whose ‘kingdom ruleth over
                        all’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            103:19.</p></note> ‘The floods’, or torrents, ‘will come;’ they will
                    lift up their waves and rage horribly. But to them also the Lord that sitteth
                    above the water-floods, that remaineth a King for ever,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 29:9 (BCP).</p></note>
                    will say, ‘Hitherto shall ye come and no farther: here shall your proud waves be
                        stayed.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Job 38:11.</p></note> ‘The winds will blow, and beat upon that house,’
                    as though they would tear it up from the foundation. But they cannot prevail: it
                    falleth not; for it is founded upon a rock. He buildeth on Christ by faith and
                    love; therefore he shall not be cast down. ‘He shall not fear, though the earth
                    be moved, and though the hills be carried into the midst of the sea. Though the
                    waters thereof rage and swell, and the mountains shake at the tempest of the
                        same;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            46:2-3 (BCP).</p></note> still he ‘dwelleth under the defence of the
                    Most High, and is safe under the shadow of the Almighty’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 91:1 (BCP).</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1"><pb n="01:694"/>III. 1. How nearly then does it concern every child of man
                    practically to apply these things to himself! Diligently to examine on what
                    foundation he builds, whether on a rock or on the sand! How deeply are <hi
                        rend="italic">you</hi> concerned to inquire, What is the foundation of <hi
                        rend="italic">my</hi> hope? Whereon do I build my expectation of entering
                    into the kingdom of heaven? Is it not built on the sand? Upon my <hi
                        rend="italic">orthodoxy</hi> or right opinions (which by a gross abuse of
                    words I have called <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>);<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the
                            Kingdom’, I.6 and n.</p></note> upon my having a set of notions—suppose
                    more rational or scriptural than many others have? Alas! What madness is this?
                    Surely this is building on the sand; or rather, on the froth of the sea! Say I
                    am convinced of this. Am I not again building my hope on what is equally unable
                    to support it? Perhaps on my belonging to ‘so excellent a church; reformed after
                    the true Scripture model; blessed with the purest doctrine, the most primitive
                    liturgy, the most apostolical form of government’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">A sardonic reference here; but
                            cf. No. 13 ,<hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, I.3 and n., for
                            samples of Wesley’s own triumphalist sentiments on this very
                        point.</p></note> These are doubtless so many reasons for praising God, as
                    they may be so many helps to holiness. But they are not holiness itself. And if
                    they are separate from it they will profit me nothing. Nay, they will leave me
                    the more without excuse, and exposed to the greater damnation. Therefore, if I
                    build my hope upon this foundation I am still building upon the sand.</p>
                <p n="2">2. You cannot, you dare not, rest here. Upon what next will you build your
                    hope of salvation? Upon your innocence? Upon your doing no harm?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.2;
                            and No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, II.4 and n.</p></note> Your not
                    wronging or hurting anyone? Well; allow this plea to be true. You are just in
                    all your dealings; you are a downright honest man; you pay every man his own;
                    you neither cheat nor extort; you act fairly with all mankind. And you have a
                    conscience towards God; you do not live in any known sin. Thus far is well. But
                    still it is not the thing. You may go thus far and yet never come to heaven.
                    When all this harmlessness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 32, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XII’, II.2 and
                            n.</p></note> flows from a right principle it is the <hi rend="italic"
                        >least part</hi> of the religion of Christ. But in you it does not flow from
                    a right principle, and therefore is no part at all of religion. So that in
                    grounding your hope of salvation on this you are still building upon the
                    sand.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Do you go farther yet? Do you add to the doing no harm the attending all
                    the ordinances of God? Do you at all opportunities <pb n="01:695"/>partake of
                    the Lord’s Supper? Use public and private prayer? Fast often? Hear and search
                    the Scriptures, and meditate thereon? These things likewise ought you to have
                    done, from the time you first set your face towards heaven. Yet these things
                    also are nothing, being alone. They are nothing without the weightier matters of
                    the law.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 23:23.</p></note> And those you have forgotten. At least you
                    experience them not: faith, mercy, and love of God; holiness of heart; heaven
                    opened in the soul. Still therefore you build upon the sand.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Over and above all this, are you zealous of good works?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">Titus
                        2:14.</p></note> Do you, as you have time, do good to all men?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal.
                            6:10.</p></note> Do you feed the hungry and clothe the naked, and visit
                    the fatherless and widow in their affliction?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63"
                        n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:27.</p></note> Do you visit those that
                    are sick? Relieve them that are in prison? Is any a stranger and you take him
                    in? Friend, come up higher.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Luke 14:10.</p></note> Do you ‘prophesy in the
                    name’ of Christ?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Matt. 7:22.</p></note> Do you preach the truth as it is in
                        Jesus?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Eph. 4:21.</p></note> And does the influence of his Spirit attend your
                    word, and make it the power of God unto salvation?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 1:16.</p></note> Does he
                    enable you to bring sinners from darkness to light, from the power of Satan unto
                        God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            26:18.</p></note> Then go and learn what thou hast so often taught, ‘By
                    grace ye are saved, through faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:8.</p></note> ‘Not by works of
                    righteousness which we have done, but of his own mercy he saveth us.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus
                            3:5.</p></note> Learn to hang naked upon the cross of Christ, counting
                    all thou hast done but dung and dross.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:8.</p></note> Apply to him just in
                    the spirit of the dying thief,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Luke 23:42.</p></note> of the harlot with her
                    seven devils;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Mark 16:9.</p></note> else thou art still on the sand, and after
                    saving others thou wilt lose thy own soul.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Lord! Increase my faith, if I now believe! Else, give me faith, though
                    but as a grain of mustard seed!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 17:20.</p></note> But ‘what doth it
                    profit if a man say he hath faith, and have not works? Can’ <hi rend="italic"
                        >that</hi> ‘faith save him?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 2:14.</p></note> O no! That faith which
                    hath not works, which doth not produce both inward and outward holiness, which
                    does not stamp the whole image of God on the heart, and purify us as he is
                        pure;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            John 3:3.</p></note>
                    <pb n="01:696"/>that faith which does not produce the whole of the religion
                    described in the foregoing chapters, is not the faith of the gospel, not the
                    Christian faith, not the faith which leads to glory. O beware of this, above all
                    other snares of the devil, of resting on unholy, unsaving faith! If thou layest
                    stress on this thou art lost for ever: thou still buildest thy house upon the
                    sand. When ‘the rain descends and the floods come it’ will surely ‘fall; and
                    great’ will be ‘the fall of it.’</p>
                <p n="6">6. Now, therefore, build thou upon a rock. By the grace of God, know
                        thyself.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">The
                            prior human ‘re-action’ in all true repentance; see No. 7, ‘The Way to
                            the Kingdom’, II.1 and n.</p></note> Know and feel that thou wast shapen
                    in wickedness, and in sin did thy mother conceive thee;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 51:5 (BCP).</p></note>
                    and that thou thyself hast been heaping sin upon sin ever since thou couldst
                    discern good from evil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Heb. 5:14.</p></note> Own thyself guilty of
                    eternal death; and renounce all hope of ever being able to save thyself. Be it
                    all thy hope to be washed in his blood and purified by his Spirit ‘who himself
                    bore all thy sins in his own body upon the tree’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:24.</p></note> And if
                    thou knowest he hath taken away thy sins, so much the more abase thyself before
                    him in a continued sense of thy total dependence on him for every good thought
                    and word and work, and of thy utter inability to all good unless he ‘water thee
                    every moment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Isa. 27:3.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. Now weep for your sins, and mourn after God till he turns your heaviness
                    into joy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Jas. 4:9.</p></note> And even then weep with them that weep;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        12:15.</p></note> and for them that weep not for themselves. Mourn for the
                    sins and miseries of mankind. And see, but just before your eyes, the immense
                    ocean of eternity,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §4 and n.</p></note>
                    without a bottom or a shore;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, §18 and
                        n.</p></note> which has already swallowed up millions of millions of men,
                    and is gaping to devour them that yet remain. See here the house of God, eternal
                    in the heavens;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 2 Cor. 5:1.</p></note> there, hell and destruction without a
                        covering.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Job 26:6.</p></note> And thence learn the importance of every
                    moment, which just appears, and is gone for ever!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 29, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, IX’, §28 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8">8. Now add to your seriousness, meekness of wisdom. Hold an even scale as
                    to all your passions, but in particular as to anger, sorrow, and fear. Calmly
                    acquiesce in whatsoever is the will of God. Learn in every state wherein you
                    are, therewith to be <pb n="01:697"/>content.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89"
                        n="89"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 4:11.</p></note> Be mild to the
                    good; be gentle toward all men,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 2:24.</p></note> but especially toward the
                    evil and the unthankful. Beware not only of outward expressions of anger, such
                    as calling thy brother ‘Raca’, or ‘Thou fool’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91"
                        n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:22.</p></note> but of every inward
                    emotion contrary to love, though it go no farther than the heart. Be angry at
                    sin, as an affront offered to the majesty of heaven; but love the sinner
                        still,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount, II’, I.8 and n.</p></note> like our Lord
                    who ‘looked round about upon’ the Pharisees ‘with anger, being grieved for the
                    hardness of their hearts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 3:5.</p></note> He was grieved at the
                    sinners, angry at the sin. Thus ‘be thou angry and sin not.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:26.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. Now do thou hunger and thirst, not for ‘the meat that perisheth, but for
                    that which endureth unto everlasting life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95"
                        n="95"><p rend="footnote text">John 6:27.</p></note> Trample under foot the
                    world and the things of the world—all these riches, honours, pleasures. What is
                    the world to thee? Let the dead bury their dead: but follow thou after the image
                    of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 8:22; an interesting Christological note identifying Jesus Christ
                            as the representative ‘image of God’.</p></note> And beware of quenching
                    that blessed thirst, if it is already excited in thy soul, by what is vulgarly
                    called religion—a poor, dull farce, a religion of form, of outside show<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matthew
                            Prior, ‘An English Padlock’, l. 60: ‘’Tis a dull farce, an empty show;’
                            see No. 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, III.5 and n.</p></note>—which leaves
                    the heart still cleaving to the dust, as earthly and sensual as ever.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text">See Jas.
                            3:15.</p></note> Let nothing satisfy thee but the power of godliness,
                    but a religion that is spirit and life; the dwelling in God and God in thee; the
                    being an inhabitant of eternity; the entering in by the blood of sprinkling<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        12:24.</p></note> ‘within the veil’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100"
                        n="100"><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 6:19.</p></note> and ‘sitting in
                    heavenly places with Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:6.</p></note></p>
                <p n="10">10. Now, seeing thou canst do all things through Christ strengthening
                        thee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 4:13.</p></note> be merciful as thy Father in heaven is
                        merciful.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Luke 6:36.</p></note> Love thy neighbour as thyself.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="footnote text">Lev. 19:18,
                            etc.</p></note> Love friends and enemies as thy own soul. And let thy
                    love be <hi rend="italic">long-suffering</hi>, and patient towards all men.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">1 Thess.
                            5:14.</p></note> Let it be <hi rend="italic">kind</hi>, soft, benign:
                    inspiring thee with the most amiable sweetness, and the most fervent and tender
                    affection. Let it ‘rejoice in the truth’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106"
                        n="106"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:6.</p></note> wheresoever it
                    is found, the truth that is after godliness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107"
                        n="107"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Tim. 6:3.</p></note> Enjoy whatsoever
                    brings <pb n="01:698"/>glory to God, and promotes peace and goodwill among men.
                    In love ‘cover all things’, of the dead and the absent speaking nothing but
                        good;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.11 and
                            n.</p></note> ‘believe all things’ which may any way tend to clear your
                    neighbour’s character; ‘hope all things’ in his favour; and ‘endure all things’,
                    triumphing over all opposition. For true ‘love never faileth’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                        13:7-8.</p></note> in time or in eternity.</p>
                <p n="11">11. Now be thou ‘pure in heart’; purified through faith from every unholy
                    affection, ‘cleansing thyself from all filthiness of flesh and spirit, and
                    perfecting holiness in the fear of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110"
                        n="110"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p></note> Being through the
                    power of his grace purified from pride by deep poverty of spirit; from anger,
                    from every unkind or turbulent passion by meekness and mercifulness; from every
                    desire but to please and enjoy God by hunger and thirst after
                        righteousness;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:6.</p></note> now love the Lord thy God
                    with all thy heart and with all thy strength.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112"
                        n="112"><p rend="footnote text">See Mark 12:30.</p></note></p>
                <p n="12">12. In a word: let thy religion be the religion of the heart.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 25,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.13 and n.</p></note> Let it lie deep in thy
                    inmost soul. Be thou little and base, and mean and vile (beyond what words can
                    express) in thy own eyes; amazed and humbled to the dust by the love of God
                    which is in Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:39.</p></note> Be serious. Let the whole
                    stream of thy thoughts, words, and actions flow from the deepest conviction that
                    thou standest on the edge of the great gulf, thou and all the children of men,
                    just ready to drop in, either into everlasting glory or everlasting
                        burnings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Isa. 33:14. Cf. No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, III.6, IV.13 and
                            n.</p></note> Let thy soul be filled with mildness, gentleness,
                    patience, long-suffering towards all men, at the same time that all which is in
                    thee is athirst for God, the living God;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116"
                        n="116"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 42:2.</p></note> longing to awake up
                    after his likeness, and to be satisfied with it. Be thou a lover of God and of
                    all mankind. In this spirit do and suffer all things. Thus show thy faith by thy
                    works: thus ‘do the will of thy Father which is in heaven.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:21;
                        12:50.</p></note> And as sure as thou now walkest with God on earth, thou
                    shalt also reign with him in glory.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
