<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 31: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse XI</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 31: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse XI</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="664" to="674"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:664"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Eleventh</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 7:13-14</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Enter ye in at the strait gate: for wide is the gate, and
                        broad is the way, which leadeth to destruction, and many there be which go
                        in thereat:</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which
                        leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Our Lord, having warned us of the dangers which easily beset us at our
                    first entrance upon real religion, the hindrances which naturally arise from
                    within, from the wickedness of our own hearts, now proceeds to apprise us of the
                    hindrances from without, particularly ill example and ill advice. By one or the
                    other of these, thousands who once ran well have drawn back unto perdition; yea,
                    many of those who were not novices in religion, who had made some progress in
                    righteousness. His caution therefore against these he presses upon us with all
                    possible earnestness, and repeats again and again, in variety of expressions,
                    lest by any means we should let it slip. Thus, effectually to guard us against
                    the former, ‘Enter ye in’, saith he, ‘at the strait gate; for wide is the gate,
                    and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there be which go in
                    thereat: because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which leadeth unto
                    life, and few there be that find it.’ To secure us from the latter, ‘Beware’,
                    saith he, ‘of false prophets.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 7:15.</p></note> We shall at present consider
                    the former only.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘Enter ye in’, saith our blessed Lord, ‘at the strait gate; for wide is
                    the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many there be
                    which go in thereat: because strait is the gate, and narrow is the way, which
                    leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it.’</p>
                <p n="3">3. In these words we may observe, first, the inseparable <pb n="01:665"
                    />properties of the way to hell: ‘Wide is the gate, broad the way, that leadeth
                    to destruction, and many there be that go in thereat;’ secondly, the inseparable
                    properties of the way to heaven: ‘Strait is that gate, and narrow is the way,
                    which leadeth unto life, and few there be that find it;’ thirdly, a serious
                    exhortation grounded thereon: ‘Enter ye in at the strait gate.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. We may observe, first, the inseparable properties of the way to hell:
                    ‘Wide is the gate, and broad is the way, that leadeth to destruction, and many
                    there be that go in thereat.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. Wide indeed is the gate, and broad the way, that leadeth to destruction.
                    For sin is the gate of hell, and wickedness the way to destruction. And how wide
                    a gate is that of sin! How broad is the way of wickedness! The ‘commandment’ of
                    God ‘is exceeding broad’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:96.</p></note> as extending not only to all
                    our actions, but to every word which goeth out of our lips, yea, every thought
                    that rises in our heart. And sin is equally broad with the commandment, seeing
                    any breach of the commandment is sin. Yea, rather, it is a thousand times
                    broader, since there is only one way of keeping the commandment; for we do not
                    properly keep it unless both the thing done, the manner of doing it, and all the
                    other circumstances, are right. But there are a thousand ways of breaking every
                    commandment; so that this gate is wide indeed.</p>
                <p n="3">3. To consider this a little more particularly. How wide do those parent
                        sins<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No.
                            25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, III.2 and n.</p></note> extend, from which
                    all the rest derive their being: ‘that carnal mind which is enmity against
                        God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:7.</p></note> pride of heart, self-will, and love of the world! Can we
                    fix any bounds to them? Do they not diffuse themselves through all our thoughts,
                    and mingle with all our tempers? Are they not the leaven which leavens, more or
                    less, the whole mass of our affections? May we not, on a close and faithful
                    examination of ourselves, perceive these roots of bitterness continually
                    springing up,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Heb. 12:15.</p></note> infecting all our words, and tainting all our
                    actions? And how innumerable an offspring do they bring forth, in every age and
                    nation! Even enough to cover the whole earth with ‘darkness and cruel
                        habitations’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Ps. 74:21 (BCP).</p></note></p>
                <p n="4"><pb n="01:666"/>4. O who is able to reckon up their accursed fruits! To
                    count all the sins, whether against God or our neighbour, not which imagination
                    might paint, but which may be matter of daily, melancholy experience! Nor need
                    we range over all the earth to find them. Survey any one kingdom, any single
                    country, or city, or town, and how plenteous is this harvest! And let it not be
                    one of those which are still overspread with Mahometan or pagan darkness, but of
                    those which name the name of Christ, which profess to see the light of his
                    glorious gospel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 2 Cor. 4:4. For Wesley’s scorn of nominal Christianity in so-called
                            Christian countries or Christian churches, cf. Nos. 49, ‘The Cure of
                            Evil-speaking’, III.4; 61, ‘The Mystery of Iniquity’, §25; 63, ‘The
                            General Spread of the Gospel’, §§1-2; 64, ‘The New Creation’, §§1-2; 69,
                            ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, II.8-9; 122, ‘Causes of the
                            Inefficacy of Christianity’, §6. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">A Plain
                                Account of Christian Perfection</hi>, III.8, and <hi rend="italic">A
                                Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. II, II.28 (11:239-40 of this
                        edn.).</p></note> Go no farther than the kingdom to which we belong, the
                    city wherein we are now.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The ‘kingdom’, of course, is England; ‘the city’,
                            London.</p></note> We call ourselves Christians; yea, and that of the
                    purest sort; we are Protestants, reformed Christians! But alas! who shall carry
                    on the reformation of our opinions into our hearts and lives? Is there not a
                    cause? For how innumerable are our sins! And those of the deepest dye! Do not
                    the grossest abominations of every kind abound among us from day to day? Do not
                    sins of every sort cover the land, as the waters cover the sea?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Isa. 11:9; Hab.
                            2:14.</p></note> Who can count them? Rather go and count the drops of
                    rain, or the sands on the sea-shore. So ‘wide is the gate’, so ‘broad is the way
                    that leadeth to destruction’.</p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘And many there be who go in at’ that gate, many who walk in that
                    way—almost as many as go in at the gate of death, as sink into the chambers of
                    the grave.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Prov. 7:27.</p></note> For it cannot be denied (though neither can we
                    acknowledge it but with shame and sorrow of heart) that even in this which is
                    called a Christian country the generality of every age and sex, of every
                    profession and employment, of every rank and degree, high and low, rich and
                    poor, are walking in the way of destruction. The far greater part of the
                    inhabitants of this city to this day live in sin;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rudé, in <hi rend="italic"
                                >Hanoverian London</hi>, ch. 5 (‘The “Other” London’) and ch. 10
                            (‘Social Protest “From Below”’). Wesley makes no mention of having seen
                            William Hogarth’s famous engravings on ‘modern moral subjects’ (from ‘A
                            Harlot’s Progress’ [1732], to ‘Gin Lane’ [1751]); but they were famous,
                            and Wesley was interested in such things. More importantly, he himself
                            had seen what Hogarth saw and reacts to it here with words instead of
                            pictures.</p></note> in some <pb n="01:667"/>palpable, habitual, known
                    transgression of the law they profess to observe;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic"
                                >On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9, and n.</p></note> yea,
                    in some outward transgression, some gross, visible kind of ungodliness or
                    unrighteousness; some open violation of their duty, either to God or man. These
                    then, none can deny, are all in the way that leadeth to destruction. Add to
                    these those who ‘have a name, indeed, that they live’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 3:1.</p></note> but
                    were never yet alive to God;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Rom. 6:11.</p></note> those that outwardly
                    appear fair to men, but are inwardly full of all uncleanness;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 23:27.</p></note>
                    full of pride or vanity, of anger or revenge, of ambition or covetousness;
                    lovers of themselves, lovers of the world, lovers of pleasure more than lovers
                    of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Tim. 3:2-4.</p></note> These indeed may be highly esteemed of men, but
                    they are an abomination to the Lord. And how greatly will these saints of the
                        world<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.5 and
                        n.</p></note> swell the number of the children of hell! Yea, add
                    all—whatever they be in other respects, whether they have more or less of the
                    form of godliness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 3:5.</p></note>—who, ‘being ignorant of
                    God’s righteousness, and seeking to establish their own righteousness’ as the
                    ground of their reconciliation to God and acceptance with him, of consequence
                    have ‘not submitted themselves unto the righteousness which is of God by
                        faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 10:3.</p></note> Now all these things joined together in one, how
                    terribly true is our Lord’s assertion, ‘Wide is the gate and broad is the way
                    that leadeth to destruction, and many there be who go in thereat.’</p>
                <p n="6">6. Nor does this only concern the vulgar herd, the poor, base, stupid part
                    of mankind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Horace, <hi rend="italic">Odes</hi>, III.1 (<hi rend="italic">odi
                                profanum vulgus</hi>), and Abraham Cowley’s ‘imitation’ in <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi> (11th edn., 1710), II.751. These epithets
                            were commonplace in eighteenth-century English middle- and upper-class
                            language; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Tatler</hi>, No. 81 (Oct. 13-15,
                            1709), and <hi rend="italic">The Spectator</hi>, No. 114 (July 11,
                            1711), and No. 472 (Sept. 1, 1712), three samples from hundreds. It is
                            interesting that Wesley slips into them from time to time, despite his
                            self-conscious identification with ‘Christ’s poor’ (cf. No. 47,
                            ‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’, III.3; JWJ, Sept. 28, 1765,
                            and Apr. 5, 1782; his letter to Dorothy Furly, Sept. 25, 1757, to Brian
                            Bury Collins, June 14, 1780, and to Freeborn Garrettson, Sept. 30,
                            1786).</p><p rend="footnote text">Cf. II.6, 10; III.5, below; also Nos.
                            85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, §3; 108, ‘On Riches’, II.1; and
                            125, ‘On a Single Eye’, II.5. Cf. also his Pref. to the <hi
                                rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi>, §5. For Wesley’s use of ‘beasts
                            of the people’ see No. 52, <hi rend="italic">The Reformation of
                                Manners</hi>, I.5 and n.</p></note> Nay; men of eminence in the
                    world, men who have many fields and yoke of oxen, do not desire to be excused
                    from this. On the contrary, ‘many wise men after the <pb n="01:668"/>flesh’,
                    according to the human methods of judging, ‘many mighty’ in power, in courage,
                    in riches, many ‘noble are called’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 1:26.</p></note> called into the broad way,
                    by the world, the flesh, and the devil;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">BCP, Litany.</p></note> and they are not
                    disobedient to that calling. Yea, the higher they are raised in fortune and
                    power, the deeper do they sink into wickedness. The more blessings they have
                    received from God, the more sins do they commit; using their honour or riches,
                    their learning or wisdom, not as means of working out their salvation, but
                    rather of excelling in vice, and so ensuring their own destruction.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">For later and
                            more distanced views of England in the 1740s, see Williams, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Whig Supremacy</hi>, chs. ii, v, and Robertson,
                                <hi rend="italic">England Under the Hanoverians</hi>, chs. ii, iv.
                            For vivid contemporary accounts to the same effect, cf. Henry Fielding,
                                <hi rend="italic">The History of Tom Jones, A Foundling</hi> (1749);
                            Daniel Defoe, <hi rend="italic">The Fortune and Misfortune of the Famous
                                Moll Flanders</hi> (1722); and Samuel Richardson, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Clarissa, or. The History of a Young Lady</hi>
                        (1747-48).</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. And the very reason why many of these go on so securely in the
                    ‘broad way’ is because it is broad; not considering that this is the inseparable
                    property of the way to destruction. ‘Many there be’, saith our Lord, ‘who go in
                    thereat’—for the very reason why they should flee from it, even ‘because strait
                    is the gate and narrow the way that leadeth unto life, and few there be that
                    find it.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. This is an inseparable property of the way to heaven. So narrow is the
                    way that leadeth unto life, unto life everlasting, so strait the gate, that
                    nothing unclean, nothing unholy, can enter. No sinner can pass through that gate
                    until he is saved from all his sins. Not only from his outward sins, from his
                    evil ‘conversation, received by tradition from his fathers’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:18.</p></note> It
                    will not suffice that he hath ‘ceased to do evil’ and ‘learned to do well’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 1:16,
                            17.</p></note> He must not only be saved from all sinful actions and
                    from all evil and useless discourse; but inwardly changed, throughly renewed in
                    the spirit of his mind.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:23.</p></note> Otherwise he cannot pass
                    through the gate of life, he cannot enter into glory.</p>
                <p n="3">3. For ‘narrow is the way that leadeth unto life’—the way of universal
                    holiness. Narrow indeed is the way of poverty of spirit, the way of holy
                    mourning, the way of meekness, and that of hungering and thirsting after
                        righteousness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:3-6.</p></note> Narrow is the way of
                    mercifulness, of love unfeigned; the way of purity of heart; of <pb n="01:669"
                    />doing good unto all men, and of gladly suffering evil, all manner of evil, for
                    righteousness’ sake.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:7-8, 10.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. ‘And few there be that find it.’ Alas, how few find even the way of
                    heathen honesty!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >For other uses of this phrase as synonymous with natural morality, cf.
                            Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, I.1, 2, 4; 2, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I. (ii.)4; 50, ‘The Use of
                            Money’, II.2; 55, <hi rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>, §11. Cf. also
                            the letter to a clergyman, June 18, 1787; and JWJ, Feb. 8, 1753. See
                            also Lucas, <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi>,
                        I.101.</p></note> How few are there that do nothing to another which they
                    would not another should do unto them!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:12.</p></note> How few that are
                    clear before God from acts either of injustice or unkindness! How few that do
                    not ‘offend with their tongue’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus. 19:16.</p></note> that speak nothing
                    unkind, nothing untrue! What a small proportion of mankind are innocent even of
                    outward transgressions! And how much smaller a proportion have their hearts
                    right before God, clean and holy in his sight! Where are they whom his
                    all-searching eye discerns to be truly humble? To abhor themselves in dust and
                        ashes<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Job 42:6.</p></note> in the presence of God their Saviour? To be deeply
                    and steadily serious, feeling their wants, and ‘passing the time of their
                    sojourning with fear’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:17.</p></note> Truly meek and gentle,
                    never ‘overcome of evil, but overcoming evil with good’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 12:21.</p></note>
                    Throughly athirst for God, and continually panting<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 42:1-2
                        (AV).</p></note> after a renewal in his likeness? How thinly are they
                    scattered over the earth, whose souls are enlarged in love to all mankind; and
                    who love God with all their strength; who have given him their hearts, and
                    desire nothing else in earth or heaven!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 73:25.</p></note> How few are those
                    lovers of God and man that spend their whole strength in doing good unto all
                        men;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Gal. 6:10.</p></note> and are ready to suffer all things, yea, death
                    itself, to save one soul from eternal death!</p>
                <p n="5">5. But while so few are found in the way of life, and so many in the way of
                    destruction, there is great danger lest the torrent of example<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">An echo, here and elsewhere,
                            of Francis Bacon’s insight that human thought is more often warped by
                            ingrained prejudices than it is guided by reason or good example; e.g.,
                            Bacon’s famous ‘four idols’ of the ‘tribe’, the ‘cave’, the
                            ‘market-place’, and the ‘theatre’, as in <hi rend="italic">Novum
                                Organum</hi> (1620), I, Aphorisms 38-69. For other instances of the
                            phrase, ‘torrents of custom’, cf. No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.3
                            and n.</p></note> should bear us away with them. Even a single example,
                    if it be always in our sight, is apt to make much impression upon us; especially
                    when it has nature on its side, when it falls in with <pb n="01:670"/>our own
                    inclinations. How great then must be the force of so numerous examples,
                    continually before our eyes; and all conspiring together with our own hearts to
                    carry us down the stream of nature! How difficult must it be to stem the tide,
                    and to keep ourselves ‘unspotted in the world’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39"
                        n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:27.</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. What heightens the difficulty still more is that they are not the rude
                    and senseless part of mankind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.6 and n.</p></note> at least not these
                    alone, who set us the example, who throng the downward way; but the polite, the
                    well-bred, the genteel, the wise, the men who understand the world; the men of
                    knowledge, of deep and various learning, the rational, the eloquent! These are
                    all, or nearly all, against us. And how shall we stand against these? Do not
                    their tongues drop manna?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                            ii.112-13: ‘His tongue dropt manna, and could make the worse appear the
                            better reason.’</p></note> And have they not learned all the arts of
                    soft persuasion? And of reasoning too; for these are versed in all controversies
                    and strife of words. It is therefore a small thing with them to prove that the
                    way is <hi rend="italic">right</hi> because it is <hi rend="italic">broad</hi>;
                    that he who follows a multitude cannot do evil,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="42"><p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 23:2.</p></note> but only he who
                    will not follow them; that your way must be <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi> because
                    it is <hi rend="italic">narrow</hi> and because there are so few that find it.
                    These will make it clear to a demonstration that evil is good, and good is evil;
                    that the way of holiness is the way of destruction, and the way of the world the
                    only way to heaven.</p>
                <p n="7">7. O how can unlearned and ignorant men maintain their cause against such
                    opponents! And yet these are not all with whom they must contend, however
                    unequal to the task; for there are many mighty and noble and powerful men, as
                    well as wise, in the road that leadeth to destruction. And these have a shorter
                    way of confuting than that of reason and argument. They usually apply, not to
                    the understanding, but to the fears of any that oppose them—a method that seldom
                    fails of success, even where argument profits nothing, as lying level to the
                    capacities of all men: for all can fear, whether they can reason or no. And all
                    who have not a firm trust in God, a sure reliance both on his power and love,
                    cannot but fear to give any disgust<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">I.e., an offence; a then contemporary usage which
                            may be seen in both Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> and the
                                <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</p></note> to those who have the power
                    of the world in their hands. What wonder, therefore, if the example of these is
                    a law to all who know not God!</p>
                <p n="8"><pb n="01:671"/>8. Many rich are likewise in the broad way. And these apply
                    to the hopes of men, and to all their foolish desires, as strongly and
                    effectually as the mighty and noble to their fears. So that hardly can you hold
                    on in the way of the kingdom unless you are dead to all below, unless you are
                    crucified to the world and the world crucified to you,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 6:14.</p></note>
                    unless you desire nothing more but God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. For how dark, how uncomfortable, how forbidding is the prospect on the
                    opposite side! A strait gate! A narrow way! And few finding that gate! Few
                    walking in the way. Besides, even those few are not wise men, not men of
                    learning or eloquence. They are not able to reason either strongly or clearly;
                    they cannot propose an argument to any advantage. They know not how to prove
                    what they profess to believe; or to explain even what they say they experience.
                    Surely such advocates as these will never recommend, but rather discredit the
                    cause they have espoused.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Add to this that they are not noble, not honourable men: if they were,
                    you might bear with their folly. They are men of no interest, no authority, of
                    no account in the world. They are mean and base, low in life;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.6 and
                        n.</p></note> and such as have no power, if they had the will, to hurt you.
                    Therefore there is nothing at all to be feared from them; and there is nothing
                    at all to hope: for the greater part of them may say, ‘Silver and gold have I
                        none’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            3:6.</p></note>—at least a very moderate share. Nay, some of them have
                    scarce food to eat or raiment to put on. For this reason, as well as because
                    their ways are not like those of other men, they are everywhere spoken against,
                    are despised, have their names cast out as evil, are variously persecuted, and
                    treated as the filth and offscouring of the world.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 4:13.</p></note> So
                    that both your fears, your hopes, and all your desires (except those which you
                    have immediately from God), yea, all your natural passions, continually incline
                    you to return into the broad way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. Therefore it is that our Lord so earnestly exhorts, ‘Enter ye in at
                    the strait gate.’ Or (as the same exhortation is elsewhere expressed) ‘Strive to
                    enter in’: ἀγωνίζεσθε εἰσελθεῖν, strive as in an agony. ‘For many’, saith our
                    Lord, ‘shall seek to enter in’—indolently strive—‘and shall not be able.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 13:24. Cf.
                                <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, III.5, and No. 17, ‘The Circumcision
                            of the Heart’, II.7 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2"><pb n="01:672"/>2. ’Tis true he intimates what may seem another reason for
                    this, for their ‘not being able to enter in’, in the words which immediately
                    follow these. For after he had said, ‘Many, I say unto you, will seek to enter
                    in, and shall not be able,’ he subjoins: ‘When once the master of the house is
                    risen up and hath shut to the door, and ye begin to stand without’ (ἄρξησθε ἔξω
                    ἑστάναι: rather, ‘ye stand without’, for ἄρξησθε seems to be only an elegant
                    expletive) ‘and to knock at the door, saying, Lord, Lord, open unto us; he shall
                    answer and say unto you, I know you not. Depart from me, all ye workers of
                        iniquity.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Luke 13:24-27.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="3">3. It may appear, upon a transient view of these words, that their delaying
                    to seek at all, rather than their manner of seeking, was the reason why they
                    were not able to enter in. But it comes in effect to the same thing. They were
                    therefore commanded to depart, because they had been ‘workers of iniquity’,
                    because they had walked in the broad road; in other words, because they had not
                    agonized to enter in at the strait gate. Probably they did <hi rend="italic"
                        >seek</hi>, before the door was shut; but that did not suffice. And they did
                        <hi rend="italic">strive</hi>, after the door was shut; but then it was too
                    late.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Therefore ‘strive’ ye now, in this your day, ‘to enter in at the strait
                    gate’. And in order hereto, settle it in your heart, and let it be ever
                    uppermost in your thoughts, that if you are in a broad way, you are in the way
                    that leadeth to destruction. If many go with you, as sure as God is true, both
                    they and you are going to hell. If you are walking as the generality of men
                    walk, you are walking to the bottomless pit. Are many wise, many rich, many
                    mighty or noble<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 1 Cor. 1:26.</p></note> travelling with you in the same way? By
                    this token, without going any farther, you know it does not lead to life. Here
                    is a short, a plain, an infallible rule, before you enter into particulars. In
                    whatever profession you are engaged, you must be singular or be damned.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">One of Wesley’s
                            aims was to raise up men and women in his societies who could stand in
                            their own dignity against the ‘torrents of example’ and ‘custom’ (cf.
                            No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.3 and n.); hence his ‘infallible
                            rule’ of singularity. Cf. Nos. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.7; 32, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XII’, I.3; 52, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Reformation of Manners</hi>, V.7; 66, ‘The Signs
                            of the Times’, II.5; 125, ‘On a Single Eye’ (on Matt. 6:22-23); and 148,
                            ‘A Single Intention’ (on the same text). Cf. also his letters to his
                            father, June 13, 1733, and Dec. 10, 1734; to ‘John Smith’, 1745; and to
                            Miss March, Sept 16, 1774. Cf. also William Tilly, Sermon XVI, <hi
                                rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, p. 463; and John Norris, Discourse III,
                            ‘Concerning Singularity’, <hi rend="italic">Practical Discourses</hi>,
                            II.45-70, and Discourse V, ‘Of Walking by Faith’, IV.125-71.</p><p
                            rend="footnote text">Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi> cites
                            Robert South for an illustration of ‘singularly’: ‘Solitude and
                            singularity can neither daunt nor disgrace him, unless we could suppose
                            it a disgrace to be singularly good.’ For an opposite viewpoint, cf. Ben
                            Franklin, <hi rend="italic">Poor Richard’s Almanac</hi> (1757):
                            ‘Singularity…hath ruined many; happy those who are convinced of the
                            general opinion.’</p></note> The way to hell has nothing singular in it;
                    but the way <pb n="01:673"/>to heaven is singularity all over. If you move but
                    one step towards God you are not as other men are.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 18:11.</p></note> But
                    regard not this. ’Tis far better to stand alone than to fall into the pit.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 32,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, XII’, I.7 and n.</p></note> Run then with patience
                    the race which is set before thee,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:1.</p></note> though thy companions
                    therein are but few. They will not always be so. Yet a little while and thou
                    wilt ‘come to an innumerable company of angels, to the general assembly and
                    church of the first-born, and to the spirits of just men made perfect’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            12:22-23.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. Now, then, ‘strive to enter in at the strait gate,’ being penetrated
                    with the deepest sense of the inexpressible danger your soul is in so long as
                    you are in a broad way, so long as you are void of poverty of spirit and all
                    that inward religion which the many, the rich, the wise, account madness.
                    ‘Strive to enter in,’ being pierced with sorrow and shame for having so long run
                    on with the unthinking crowd,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.6 and n.</p></note> utterly neglecting
                    if not despising that ‘holiness, without which no man can see the Lord’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        12:14.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">Strive</hi> as in an agony of holy fear, lest ‘a promise being
                    made you of entering into his rest’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 4:1. Cf. No. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the
                            Heart’, II.7 and n. See also III.1, above, and III.6, below.</p></note>
                    even that ‘rest which remaineth for the people of God’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 4:9.</p></note> you
                    should nevertheless ‘come short of it’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Heb. 4:1.</p></note> Strive in all the fervour
                    of desire, with ‘groanings which cannot be uttered’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:26.</p></note> Strive
                    by prayer without ceasing,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess. 5:17.</p></note> at all times, in all
                    places lifting up your heart to God, and giving him no rest till you ‘awake up
                    after his likeness’ and are ‘satisfied with it’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 17:16
                        (BCP).</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. To conclude: ‘Strive to enter in at the strait gate,’ not only by this
                    agony of soul, of conviction, of sorrow, of shame, of desire, of <pb n="01:674"
                    />fear, of unceasing prayer, but likewise by ‘ordering thy conversation
                        aright’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 50:23,</p></note> by walking with all thy strength in all the ways
                    of God, the way of innocence, of piety, and of mercy. Abstain from all
                    appearance of evil;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:22.</p></note> do all possible good to
                    all men;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Gal. 6:10.</p></note> deny thyself, thy own will, in all things, and
                    take up thy cross daily.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Luke 9:23.</p></note> Be ready to cut off thy
                    right hand, to pluck out thy right eye and cast it from thee;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 5:29;
                        18:9.</p></note> to suffer the loss of goods, friends, health, all things on
                    earth, so thou mayst enter into the kingdom of heaven.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
