<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 45: The New Birth</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon045</idno>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 45: The New Birth</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="186" to="201"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:186"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>In conventional Anglican soteriology the basic remedy for original sin had always
                    lain in the church and the sacrament of baptism (as it had been in the ancient
                    church, where ἄφεσιν ἁμαρτιών, ‘remission of sins’, is regularly included in the
                    third article of the creeds in connection with belief in the Holy Spirit and the
                    church). The young Wesley had grown up with this tradition and had reproduced it
                    in his publication of ‘A Treatise on Baptism’ (1758), without any
                    acknowledgement that he had abridged his father’s discourse, <hi rend="italic"
                        >The Pious Communicant Rightly Prepared; …to which is added, A Short
                        Discourse of Baptism</hi> (1700). Even the mature Wesley had remarked, as if
                    it were a general commonplace, ‘that these privileges [of being “born again”] by
                    the free mercy of God, are ordinarily annexed to baptism’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">See No. 18, ‘The Marks of the
                            New Birth’, §1.</p></note> But as tensions in the Revival mounted,
                    between the claims of nominal Christians to baptismal regeneration and the
                    claims of the evangelicals to ‘conversion’, the whole problem of regeneration in
                    relation both to justification and sanctification became more and more urgent.
                    And now that Wesley had restated his doctrine of original sin, there was an
                    obvious logic in following it with an updated version of his doctrine of ‘new
                    birth’, with a special reference, in the new situation, to some of his revisions
                    of the conventional notions of baptismal regeneration.</p>
                <p>This written sermon, then, is a sort of distillate of more than sixty oral
                    sermons on John 3:7, reaching back to the 1740s (once in 1740) and continued
                    with increasing frequency in the 1750s (five times in 1755; eleven in 1756; six
                    in 1757; fourteen in 1758; thirteen in 1759). We may see here a rough measure of
                    the importance of the point about ‘conversion’ as perceived by Wesley and his
                    people. ‘The New Birth’ is Wesley’s conscious effort to provide them with a
                    formal statement of the issue, even though, as an essay, it is clearly
                    incomplete in both its form and argument. Similar comments may be found in
                    Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 18:4 and John 3:7; see also Nos.
                    1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, II.7; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of
                    those that are Born of God’, §1-2; 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.9-10; and 83,
                    ‘On Patience’, §9.</p>
                <p><pb n="02:187"/>In addition to its first appearance in <hi rend="italic"
                        >SOSO</hi>, IV (1760), and again in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771), IV,
                    this sermon was printed separately at least five times during Wesley’s lifetime.
                    For its publishing history, together with a list of variant readings, see the
                    Appendix, Vol 4; see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 131.i.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The New Birth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>John 3:7</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ye must be born again.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="">1. If any doctrines within the whole compass of Christianity may be properly
                    termed fundamental they are doubtless these two—the doctrine of justification,
                    and that of the new birth: the former relating to that great work which God does
                        <hi rend="italic">for us</hi>, in forgiving our sins; the latter to the
                    great work which God does <hi rend="italic">in us</hi>, in renewing our fallen
                        nature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, II.1 and n.</p></note> In order of time
                    neither of these is before the other. In the moment we are justified by the
                    grace of God through the redemption that is in Jesus we are also ‘born of the
                        Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">John
                            3:6, 8.</p></note>; but in order of thinking, as it is termed,
                    justification precedes the new birth. We first conceive his wrath to be turned
                    away, and then his Spirit to work in our hearts.</p>
                <p n="">2. How great importance, then, must it be of to every child of man throughly
                    to understand these fundamental doctrines! From a full conviction of this, many
                    excellent men have wrote very largely concerning justification, explaining every
                    point relating thereto, and opening the Scriptures which treat upon it. Many
                    likewise have wrote on the new birth—and some of them largely enough—but yet not
                    so clearly as might have been desired, nor so deeply and accurately; having
                    either given a dark, abstruse account of it, or a slight and superficial one.
                    Therefore a full and at the same time a clear account of the new birth seems to
                    be wanting still. Such as may enable us to give a satisfactory answer to these
                    three questions: First, why must we be born again? What <pb n="02:188"/>is the
                    foundation of this doctrine of the new birth? Secondly, how must we be born
                    again? What is the nature of the new birth? And thirdly, wherefore must we be
                    born again? To what end is it necessary? These questions, by the assistance of
                    God, I shall briefly and plainly answer, and then subjoin a few inferences which
                    will naturally follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And, first, why must we be born again? What is the foundation of this
                    doctrine? The foundation of it lies near as deep as the creation of the world,
                    in the scriptural account whereof we read, ‘And God’, the three-one God,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 55, <hi
                                rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>, §17 and n.</p></note> ‘said, Let
                    us make man in our image, after our likeness. So God created man in his own
                    image, in the image of God created he him.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Gen. 1:26-27.</p></note></hi> Not
                    barely in his <hi rend="italic">natural image</hi>, a picture of his own
                    immortality, a spiritual being endued with understanding, freedom of will, and
                    various affections; nor merely in his <hi rend="italic">political image</hi>,
                    the governor of this lower world, having ‘dominion over the fishes of the sea,
                    and over the fowl of the air, and over the cattle, and over all the earth’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen.
                        1:26.</p></note> but chiefly in his <hi rend="italic">moral image</hi>,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">These phrases,
                            ‘political image’ (i.e., social) and ‘moral image’, are borrowings from
                            Isaac Watts, <hi rend="italic">Ruin and Recovery of Mankind</hi> (1740);
                            cf. Wesley’s long quotation from Watts in <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine
                                of Original Sin</hi> (1757), pp. 310-11. See also No. 1, <hi
                                rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p></note> which,
                    according to the Apostle, is ‘righteousness and true holiness’.<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Eph.
                                4:24.</p></note></hi> In this image of God was man made. ‘God is
                        love:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            4:8, 16.</p></note> accordingly man at his creation was full of love,
                    which was the sole principle of all his tempers, thoughts, words, and
                        actions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">This
                            passage reappears, in altered form, in J. Wakelin, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Christ and Nicodemus</hi> (1760), a rare instance of any attention
                            paid to Wesley’s sermons outside his own Methodist
                        constituency.</p></note> God is full of justice, mercy, and truth: so was
                    man as he came from the hands of his Creator. God is spotless purity: and so man
                    was in the beginning pure from every sinful blot. Otherwise God could not have
                    pronounced <hi rend="italic">him</hi> as well as all the other works of his
                    hands, ‘very good’.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Gen. 1:31. [Cf. No. 141, ‘The Image of
                                God’.]</p></note></hi> This he could not have been had he not been
                    pure from sin, and filled with righteousness and true holiness. For there is no
                    medium. If we suppose an intelligent creature not to love God, not to be <pb
                        n="02:189"/>righteous and holy, we necessarily suppose him not to be good at
                    all; much less to be ‘very good’.</p>
                <p n="2">2. But although man was made in the image of God, yet he was not made
                    immutable. This would have been inconsistent with that state of trial in which
                    God was pleased to place him. He was therefore created able to stand, and yet
                    liable to fall. And this God himself apprised him of, and gave him a solemn
                    warning against it. Nevertheless ‘man did not abide in honour.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 49:12
                            (BCP).</p></note> He fell from his high estate. He ‘ate of the tree
                    whereof the Lord had commanded him, Thou shalt not eat thereof.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen. 3:11,
                            17.</p></note> By this wilful act of disobedience to his Creator, this
                    flat rebellion against his sovereign, he openly declared that he would no longer
                    have God to rule over him; that he would be governed by his own will, and not
                    the will of him that created him, and that he would not seek his happiness in
                    God, but in the world, in the works of his hands. Now God had told him before,
                    ‘In the day that thou eatest’ of that fruit ‘thou shalt surely die.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                        2:17.</p></note> And the word of the Lord cannot be broken. Accordingly in
                    that day he did die: he died to God, the most dreadful of all deaths. He lost
                    the life of God: he was separated from him in union with whom his spiritual life
                    consisted. The body dies when it is separated from the soul, the soul when it is
                    separated from God. But this separation from God Adam sustained in the day, the
                    hour, he ate of the forbidden fruit. And of this he gave immediate proof;
                    presently showing by his behaviour that the love of God was extinguished in his
                    soul, which was now ‘alienated from the life of God’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:18.</p></note> Instead
                    of this he was now under the power of servile fear, so that he fled from the
                    presence of the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Jonah 1:10.</p></note> Yea, so little did he retain
                    even of the knowledge of him who filleth heaven and earth that he endeavoured to
                    ‘hide himself from the Lord God, among the trees of the garden’.<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Gen.
                                3:8.</p></note></hi> So had he lost both the knowledge and the love
                    of God, without which the image of God would not subsist. Of this therefore he
                    was deprived at the same time, and became unholy as well as unhappy.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. below, III.3;
                            also No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, I.4 and n.</p></note> In the room
                    of this he had sunk into <pb n="02:190"/>pride and self-will, the very image of
                    the devil, and into sensual appetites and desires, the image of the beasts that
                    perish.</p>
                <p n="3">3. If it be said, ‘Nay, but that threatening, “In the day that thou eatest
                    thereof thou shalt surely die,” refers to temporal death, and that alone, to the
                    death of the body only;’ the answer is plain: to affirm this is flatly and
                    palpably to make God a liar—to aver that the God of truth positively affirmed a
                    thing contrary to truth. For it is evident Adam did not <hi rend="italic"
                        >die</hi> in this sense ‘in the day that he ate thereof’. He lived, in the
                    sense opposite to this death, above nine hundred years after; so that this
                    cannot possibly be understood of the death of the body without impeaching the
                    veracity of God. It must therefore be understood of spiritual death, the loss of
                    the life and image of God.</p>
                <p n="4">4. And ‘in Adam all died,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 15:22.</p></note> all humankind, all the
                    children of men who were then in Adam’s loins. The natural consequence of this
                    is that everyone descended from him comes into the world spiritually dead, dead
                    to God, wholly ‘dead in sin’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:5; Col. 2:13.</p></note> entirely void
                    of the life of God, void of the image of God, of all that ‘righteousness and
                        holiness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Eph. 4:24.</p></note> wherein Adam was created. Instead of this every
                    man born into the world now bears the image of the devil, in pride and
                    self-will; the image of the beast, in sensual appetites and desires. This then
                    is the foundation of the new birth—the entire corruption of our nature.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">A recapitulation
                            of the effects of the Fall, as in No. 44, <hi rend="italic">Original
                                Sin</hi>, I.3, II.9; see also Nos. 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’; 60,
                            ‘The General Deliverance’, I.6-II.2; 69, ‘The Imperfection of Human
                            Knowledge’, §3; 76, ‘On Perfection’, I.1-2; 95, ‘On the Education of
                            Children’, §5; 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, §2; 130, ‘On
                            Living without God’, §15; and 141, ‘The Image of God’, II.</p></note>
                    Hence it is that being ‘born in sin’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 9:34.</p></note> we ‘must be born
                        again’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text">John
                            3:7.</p></note> Hence everyone that is born of a woman must be born of
                    the Spirit of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. But how must a man be born again? What is the nature of the new
                        birth?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            No. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’, I.1-2 and
                            n.</p></note> This is the second question. And a question it is of the
                    highest moment that can be conceived. We ought not, therefore, in so weighty a
                    concern, to be content with a slight inquiry, but to examine it with all
                    possible care, and to ponder it in our hearts, till we fully understand this
                    important point, and clearly see how we are to be born again.</p>
                <p n="2"><pb n="02:191"/>2. Not that we are to expect any minute, philosophical
                    account of the <hi rend="italic">manner how</hi> this is done. Our Lord
                    sufficiently guards us against any such expectation by the words immediately
                    following the text: wherein he reminds Nicodemus of as indisputable a fact as
                    any in the whole compass of nature—which, notwithstanding, the wisest man under
                    the sun is not able fully to explain. ‘The wind bloweth where it listeth’, not
                    by thy power or wisdom, ‘and thou hearest the sound thereof.’ Thou art
                    absolutely assured, beyond all doubt, that it doth blow. ‘But thou canst not
                    tell whence it cometh, neither whither it goeth.’ The precise manner how it
                    begins and ends, rises and falls, no man can tell. ‘So is everyone that is born
                    of the Spirit.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >John 3:8.</p></note> Thou mayst be as absolutely assured of the fact as
                    of the blowing of the wind; but the precise manner how it is done, how the Holy
                    Spirit works this in the soul, neither thou nor the wisest of the children of
                    men is able to explain.</p>
                <p n="3">3. However, it suffices for every rational and Christian purpose that
                    without descending into curious, critical inquiries, we can give a plain
                    scriptural account of the nature of the new birth. This will satisfy every
                    reasonable man who desires only the salvation of his soul. The expression,
                    ‘being born again’, was not first used by our Lord in his conversation with
                    Nicodemus. It was well known before that time, and was in common use among the
                    Jews when our Saviour appeared among them. When an adult heathen was convinced
                    that the Jewish religion was of God, and desired to join therein, it was the
                    custom to baptize him first, before he was admitted to circumcision. And when he
                    was baptized he was said to be ‘born again’: by which they meant that he who was
                    before a child of the devil was now adopted into the family of God, and
                    accounted one of his children.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See an extensive documentation of this in <hi
                                rend="italic">The Jewish Encyclopedia</hi> (‘Birth, New’ and
                            ‘Baptism’).</p></note> This expression therefore which Nicodemus, being
                    ‘a teacher in Israel’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 3:10 (Geneva Bible).</p></note> ought to have
                    understood well, our Lord uses in conversing with him; only in a stronger sense
                    than he was accustomed to. And this might be the reason of his asking, ‘How can
                    these things be?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 3:9.</p></note> They cannot be literally. ‘A
                    man’ cannot ‘enter a second time into his mother’s womb and be born’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                        3:4.</p></note> But they may, spiritually. A man may be <pb n="02:192"
                    />‘born from above’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 3:3. Cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou
                                That Steepest’</hi>, I.2 and n.</p></note> ‘born of God’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9,
                            etc.</p></note> ‘born of the Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29"
                        n="29"><p rend="footnote text">John 3:6, 8.</p></note>—in a manner which
                    bears a very near analogy to the natural birth.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Before a child is born into the world he has eyes, but sees not; he has
                    ears, but does not hear. He has a very imperfect use of any other sense. He has
                    no knowledge of any of the things of the world, nor any natural understanding.
                    To that manner of existence which he then has we do not even give the name of
                    life. It is then only when a man is born that we say, he begins to live. For as
                    soon as he is born he begins to see the light and the various objects with which
                    he is encompassed. His ears are then opened, and he hears the sounds which
                    successively strike upon them. At the same time all the other organs of sense
                    begin to be exercised upon their proper objects. He likewise breathes and lives
                    in a manner wholly different from what he did before. How exactly does the
                    parallel hold in all these instances!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text">This point, basic to Wesley’s intuitionist
                            epistemology, will be made again, with a remarkable anecdote, in No.
                            130, ‘On Living without God’; see also No. 10, ‘The Witness of the
                            Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p></note> While a man is in a mere natural
                    state, before he is born of God, he has, in a spiritual sense, eyes and sees
                    not; a thick impenetrable veil lies upon them. He has ears, but hears not; he is
                    utterly deaf to what he is most of all concerned to hear. His other spiritual
                    senses are all locked up; he is in the same condition as if he had them not.
                    Hence he has no knowledge of God, no intercourse with him; he is not at all
                    acquainted with him. He has no true knowledge of the things of God, either of
                    spiritual or eternal things. Therefore, though he is a living man, he is a dead
                    Christian. But as soon as he is born of God there is a total change in all these
                    particulars. The ‘eyes of his understanding are opened’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:18.</p></note> (such is
                    the language of the great Apostle). And he who of old ‘commanded light to shine
                    out of darkness shining on his heart’, he sees ‘the light of the glory of God’,
                    his glorious love, ‘in the face of Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:6.</p></note> His
                    ears being opened, he is now capable of hearing the inward voice of God, saying,
                    ‘Be of good cheer, thy sins are forgiven thee:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33"
                        n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 9:2.</p></note> ‘Go and sin no
                        more.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">John
                            8:11.</p></note> This is the purport of what God speaks to his heart;
                    although perhaps not in these very words. He is now ready to hear whatsoever ‘he
                    that teacheth man knowledge’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 94:10.</p></note> is pleased <pb n="02:193"
                    />from time to time to reveal to him. He ‘feels in his heart’ (to use the
                    language of our Church) ‘the mighty working of the Spirit of God’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">The echoes here
                            are from the Elizabethan Homily XVII for ‘Rogation Week’, III; and also
                            XVI, for ‘Whitsunday’, I. From the former, cf. <hi rend="italic"
                                >Homilies</hi>, p. 434: ‘God give us grace, good people, to know
                            these things and to feel them in our hearts…. Let us therefore meekly
                            call upon…the Holy Ghost…that he would assist us…that in him we may be
                            able to hear the goodness of God declared unto us for our salvation.’
                            From the latter, cf. <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, p. 409: ‘…the more it
                            is hid from our understanding, the more it ought to move all men to
                            wonder at the <hi rend="italic">secret and mighty working of God’s Holy
                                Spirit</hi> which is within us. For it is the Holy Ghost…that doth
                            quicken the minds of men, stirring up good and godly motions in their
                            hearts [i.e., prevenient grace].’ See also No. 130, ‘On Living without
                            God’, §8; and <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. I, V.24-26
                            (11:166-70 in this edn.).</p></note> Not in a gross, carnal sense, as
                    the men of the world stupidly and wilfully misunderstand the expression, though
                    they have been told again and again, we mean thereby neither more nor less than
                    this: he feels, is inwardly sensible of, the graces which the Spirit of God
                    works in his heart. He feels, he is conscious of, a ‘peace which passeth all
                        understanding’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:7.</p></note> He many times feels such a
                    joy in God as is ‘unspeakable and full of glory’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:8.</p></note> He
                    feels ‘the love of God shed abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghost which is given
                    unto him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 5:5.</p></note> And all his spiritual senses are then ‘exercised to
                    discern’ spiritual ‘good and evil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 5:14.</p></note> By the use of these he is
                    daily increasing in the knowledge of God, of Jesus Christ whom he hath sent, and
                    of all the things pertaining to his inward kingdom. And now he may properly be
                    said <hi rend="italic">to live</hi>: God having quickened him by his
                        Spirit,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Pet. 3:18.</p></note> he is alive to God through Jesus Christ.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        6:11.</p></note> He lives a life which the world knoweth not of, a ‘life’
                    which ‘is hid with Christ in God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Col. 3:3.</p></note> God is continually breathing,
                    as it were, upon his soul, and his soul is breathing unto God. Grace is
                    descending into his heart, and prayer and praise ascending to heaven. And by
                    this intercourse between God and man, this fellowship with the Father and the
                        Son,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            John 1:3.</p></note> as by a kind of spiritual respiration, the life of
                    God in the soul is sustained: and the child of God grows up, till he comes to
                    ‘the full measure of the stature of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45"
                        n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:13.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. From hence it manifestly appears what is the nature of the new birth. It
                    is that great change which God works in the soul when he brings it into
                        life:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’, I.1 and
                            n.</p></note> when he raises it from the death of sin <pb n="02:194"/>to
                    the life of righteousness. It is the change wrought in the whole soul by the
                    almighty Spirit of God when it is ‘created anew in Christ Jesus’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            2:10.</p></note> when it is ‘renewed after the image of God’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col.
                            3:10.</p></note> ‘in righteousness and true holiness’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:24.</p></note> when the
                    love of the world is changed into the love of God, pride into humility, passion
                    into meekness; hatred, envy, malice, into a sincere, tender, disinterested love
                    for all mankind. In a word, it is that change whereby the ‘earthly, sensual,
                    devilish’ mind<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Jas. 3:15.</p></note> is turned into ‘the mind which was in
                        Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Phil. 2:5.</p></note> This is the nature of the new birth. ‘So is
                    everyone that is born of the Spirit.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 3:8.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. It is not difficult for any who has considered these things to see
                    the necessity of the new birth, and to answer the third question: Wherefore, to
                    what ends, is it necessary that we should be born again? It is very easily
                    discerned that this is necessary, first, in order to holiness. For what is
                    holiness, according to the oracles of God? Not a bare external religion, a round
                    of outward duties, how many soever they be, and how exactly soever performed.
                    No; gospel holiness is no less than the image of God stamped upon the
                        heart.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Wesley’s letter to his father, Dec. 10, 1734, §§4, 6 (25:398-99 in this
                            edn.): ‘That course of life tends most to the glory of God wherein we
                            can most promote holiness in ourselves and others…. By holiness I mean,
                            not fasting, or bodily austerity, or any other external means of
                            improvement, but that inward temper to which all these are subservient,
                            a renewal of soul in the image of God.’</p></note> It is no other than
                    the whole mind which was in Christ Jesus. It consists of all heavenly affections
                    and tempers mingled together in one. It implies such a continual, thankful love
                    to him who hath not withheld from us his Son, his only Son,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">See Gen. 22:12, 16.</p></note>
                    as makes it natural, and in a manner necessary to us, to love every child of
                    man; as fills us with ‘bowels of mercies, kindness, gentleness,
                        long-suffering’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:12. For this concept of holiness as <hi
                                rend="italic">love</hi> (of God <hi rend="italic">and</hi> of ‘every
                            child of man’), cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.10 and
                        n.</p></note> It is such a love of God as teaches us to be blameless in all
                    manner of conversation; as enables us to present our souls and bodies, all we
                    are and all we have, all our thoughts, words, and actions, a continual sacrifice
                    to God, acceptable through Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 2:5.</p></note> Now this holiness
                    can have no existence till we are renewed in the image of our mind. It cannot
                    commence in the soul till that change be wrought, till by <pb n="02:195"/>the
                    power of the highest overshadowing us<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:35.</p></note> we are brought ‘from
                    darkness to light, from the power of Satan unto God’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 26:18.</p></note> that
                    is, till we are born again; which therefore is absolutely necessary in order to
                    holiness.</p>
                <p n="2">2. But ‘without holiness no man shall see the Lord,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:14.</p></note>
                    shall see the face of God in glory. Of consequence the new birth is absolutely
                    necessary in order to eternal salvation. Men may indeed flatter themselves (so
                    desperately wicked and so deceitful is the heart of man!)<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">See Jer. 17:9.</p></note> that
                    they may live in their sins till they come to the last gasp, and yet afterward
                    live with God. And thousands do really believe that they have found a ‘broad way
                    which leadeth’ not ‘to destruction’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 7:13.</p></note> What danger, say they,
                    can a woman be in, that is so <hi rend="italic">harmless</hi> and so<hi
                        rend="italic"> virtuous</hi>? What fear is there that so <hi rend="italic"
                        >honest</hi> a man, one of so strict <hi rend="italic">morality</hi>, should
                    miss of heaven? Especially if over and above all this they constantly attend on
                    church and sacrament. One of these will ask with all assurance, ‘What, shall not
                    I do as well as my neighbours?’ Yes, as well as your unholy neighbours; as well
                    as your neighbours that die in their sins. For you will all drop into the pit
                    together, into the nethermost hell. You will all lie together in the lake of
                    fire, ‘the lake of fire burning with brimstone’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Rev. 19:20.</p></note> Then at
                    length you will see (but God grant you may see it before!) the necessity of
                    holiness in order to glory—and consequently of the new birth, since none can be
                    holy except he be born again.</p>
                <p n="3">3. For the same reason, except he be born again none can be happy even in
                    this world. For it is not possible in the nature of things that a man should be
                    happy who is not holy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See above, I.2 and n.</p></note> Even the poor
                    ungodly poet could tell us,</p>
                <lg><l><hi rend="italic">Nemo malus felix</hi></l>—<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64"
                        n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Juvenal, <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi>, iv.
                            8-9: <hi rend="italic">Nemo malus felix, minime corruptor et idem
                                incestus</hi> (‘no bad man can be happy: least of all an incestuous
                            seducer’). This dictum of Juvenal’s (here levied against Crispinus) is
                            repeated in No. 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>,
                            III.7.</p></note></lg>
                <p>no wicked man is happy. The reason is plain: all unholy tempers are uneasy
                    tempers. Not only malice, hatred, envy, jealousy, revenge, create a present hell
                    in the breast, but even the softer passions, if not kept within due bounds, give
                    a thousand times more pain than pleasure. Even ‘hope’, when ‘deferred’ (and how
                        <pb n="02:196"/>often must this be the case!) ‘maketh the heart sick.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">Prov.
                        13:12.</p></note> And every desire which is not according to the will of God
                    is liable to ‘pierce us through with many sorrows’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:10.</p></note>
                    And all those general sources of sin, pride, self-will, and idolatry, are, in
                    the same proportion as they prevail, general sources of misery. Therefore as
                    long as these reign in any soul happiness has no place there. But they must
                    reign till the bent of our nature is changed, that is, till we are born again.
                    Consequently the new birth is absolutely necessary in order to happiness in this
                    world, as well as in the world to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>IV. I proposed in the last place to subjoin a few inferences which naturally
                    follow from the preceding observations.</p>
                <p n="1">1. And, first, it follows that baptism is not the new birth: they are not
                    one and the same thing. Many indeed seem to imagine they are just the same; at
                    least, they speak as if they thought so. But I do not know that this opinion is
                    publicly avowed by any denomination of Christians whatever. Certainly it is not
                    by any within these kingdoms, whether of the Established Church, or dissenting
                    from it. The judgment of the latter is clearly declared in their <hi
                        rend="italic">Larger Catechism</hi>: ‘<hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. What are the
                    parts of a sacrament? <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. The parts of a sacrament are
                    two: the one, an outward and sensible sign […]; the other, an inward and
                    spiritual grace thereby signified: […] <hi rend="italic">Q</hi>. What is
                    baptism? <hi rend="italic">A</hi>. Baptism is a sacrament […] wherein Christ
                    hath ordained the washing with water […] to be a sign and seal of […]
                    regeneration by his Spirit.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text"><hi rend="italic">Qq</hi>. 163, 165. [Published
                                by the Westminster Assembly in 1647; the ellipses are here added to
                                indicate Wesley’s abridgements of the original. Cf. his earlier
                                abridgement of the Westminster <hi rend="italic">Shorter
                                    Catechism</hi> (also in 1647) in the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                                    Lib.</hi>, Vol. XXXI; see also the passage on ‘The Sacraments’
                                in the BCP Catechism.]</p></note></hi> Here it is manifest [that]
                    baptism, the sign, is spoken of as distinct from regeneration, the thing
                    signified.</p>
                <p>In the Church Catechism likewise the judgment of our Church is declared with the
                    utmost clearness. ‘What meanest thou by this word, “sacrament”? I mean an
                    outward and visible sign of an inward and spiritual grace. […] What is the
                    outward part or form in baptism? Water, wherein the person is baptized, “In the
                    name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghost”. What is the inward part or thing
                    signified? A death unto sin, and a new birth unto <pb n="02:197"
                        />righteousness.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="footnote text">An abridgement of the section on Baptism in the BCP
                            Catechism. Henry Hammond, <hi rend="italic">Practical Catechism</hi>,
                            VI.ii.348-57, had made no sharp distinction between the external and
                            internal ‘works’ in baptism, nor had any of the other representative
                            spokesmen of the Church of England; see, for examples, More and Cross,
                                <hi rend="italic">Anglicanism</hi>, pp. 423-29, and espec. Jeremy
                            Taylor, <hi rend="italic">The Great Exemplar; …the History of the Life
                                and Death of the Ever-Blessed Jesus Christ</hi> (1649), I.ix, in <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi> (1844), I.129: ‘In baptism we are born
                            again…. The second birth spoken of in Scripture is baptism.’ See also
                            Wesley’s own ‘Treatise on Baptism’: ‘This regeneration which our Church
                            in so many places ascribes to baptism is more than barely being admitted
                            into the Church…. By…the water of baptism we are regenerated or born
                            again; whence it is also called by the Apostle, “the washing of
                            regeneration” [Titus 3:5]….’ The fact is that Wesley had changed his
                            views on this point; his evangelical concern was to separate ‘the new
                            birth’ from all ‘external acts’ in order to support his newer emphasis
                            on ‘conversion’. See also <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771),
                            XIX.275-97.</p></note> Nothing therefore is plainer than that, according
                    to the Church of England, baptism is not the new birth.</p>
                <p>But indeed the reason of the thing is so clear and evident as not to need any
                    other authority. For what can be more plain than that the one is an external,
                    the other an internal work? That the one is a visible, the other an invisible
                    thing, and therefore wholly different from each other: the one being an act of
                    man, purifying the body, the other a change wrought by God in the soul. So that
                    the former is just as distinguishable from the latter as the soul from the body,
                    or water from the Holy Ghost.</p>
                <p n="2">2. From the preceding reflections we may, secondly, observe that as the new
                    birth is not the same thing with baptism, so it does not always accompany
                    baptism; they do not constantly go together. A man may possibly be ‘born of
                        water’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">John
                            3:5.</p></note> and yet not be ‘born of the Spirit’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">John 3:6, 8.</p></note> There
                    may sometimes be the outward sign where there is not the inward grace. I do not
                    now speak with regard to infants: it is certain, our Church supposes that all
                    who are baptized in their infancy are at the same time born again. And it is
                    allowed that the whole office for the baptism of infants proceeds upon this
                    supposition. Nor is it an objection of any weight against this that we cannot
                    comprehend how this work can be wrought in infants: for neither can we
                    comprehend <hi rend="italic">how</hi> it is wrought in a person of riper years.
                    But whatever be the case with infants, it is sure all of riper years who are
                    baptized are not at the same time born again. ‘The tree is known by its
                        fruits.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 12:33.</p></note> And hereby it appears too plain to be denied
                    that divers of those who were children of the devil before they were baptized
                    continue the same after baptism: ‘For the works of’ their ‘father they do’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 8:41,
                            44.</p></note> they <pb n="02:198"/>continue servants of sin, without
                    any pretence either to inward or outward holiness.</p>
                <p n="3">3. A third inference which we may draw from what has been observed is that
                    the new birth is not the same with sanctification. This is indeed taken for
                    granted by many; particularly by an eminent writer in his late treatise on ‘the
                    nature and grounds of Christian regeneration’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72"
                        n="72"><p rend="footnote text">Law, <hi rend="italic">The Grounds and
                                Reasons of Christian Regeneration or the New Birth</hi> (1739), <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi> (1762), V.155-66. Wesley had reacted
                            sharply against this little book shortly after its publication, as in
                            JWJ, Oct 23, 1739: ‘I read over Mr. Law’s book on the new birth:
                            philosophical, speculative, precarious; Behmenish, void, and vain! “O
                            what a fall is there!”’ See also CWJ, Oct 19, 1739. There are, however,
                            echoes of Law’s treatise in Wesley’s sermon. For instance, Law is much
                            concerned with ‘the nature, manner, and necessity of our redemption
                            through Christ’s blood, and a life received from him…’ (§16), and holds
                            it ‘proper to inquire when and how this great work is done in the soul’
                            (§29). More, regeneration is defined as consisting ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >solely</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">restoration</hi> of the birth
                            of the Son of God in the human soul’ (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>). The
                            crucial disagreement came over Law’s conflation of regeneration and
                            sanctification, where he speaks of ‘regeneration…as a certain <hi
                                rend="italic">process</hi>, a <hi rend="italic">gradual release</hi>
                            from our captivity and disorder, consisting of several <hi rend="italic"
                                >stages</hi> and <hi rend="italic">degrees</hi>, both of life and
                            death, which the soul must go through before it can have thoroughly put
                            off the old Man’ (§49). Even here, Wesley argued for <hi rend="italic"
                                >sanctification</hi> as process, ‘a gradual release from our
                            captivity and disorder’. What he denied was that it <hi rend="italic"
                                >had</hi> to go through life <hi rend="italic">and death</hi> before
                            ‘perfection in love’ might be attained.</p></note> To waive several
                    other weighty objections which might be made to that tract, this is a palpable
                    one: it all along speaks of regeneration as a progressive work carried on in the
                    soul by slow degrees from the time of our first turning to God.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">See No. 107, ‘On
                            God’s Vineyard’, I.7.</p></note> This is undeniably true of
                    sanctification; but of regeneration, the new birth, it is not true. This is a
                    part of sanctification, not the whole; it is the gate of it, the entrance into
                    it. When we are born again, then our sanctification, our inward and outward
                    holiness, begins. And thenceforward we are gradually to ‘grow up in him who is
                    our head’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 4:15.</p></note> This expression of the Apostle admirably
                    illustrates the difference between one and the other, and farther points out the
                    exact analogy there is between natural and spiritual things. A child is born of
                    a woman in a moment, or at least in a very short time. Afterward he gradually
                    and slowly grows till he attains the stature of a man. In like manner a child is
                    born of God in a short time, if not in a moment. But it is by slow degrees that
                    he afterward grows up to the measure of the full stature of Christ.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                            4:13.</p></note> The same relation therefore which there is between our
                    natural birth and our growth there is also between our new birth and our
                    sanctification.</p>
                <p n="4"><pb n="02:199"/>4. One point more we may learn from the preceding
                    observations. But it is a point of so great importance as may excuse the
                    considering it the more carefully, and prosecuting it at some length. What must
                    one who loves the souls of men, and is grieved that any of them should perish,
                    say to one whom he sees living in sabbath-breaking, drunkenness, or any other
                    wilful sin? What can he say, if the foregoing observations are true, but ‘you
                    must be born again.’ ‘No’, says a zealous man, ‘that cannot be. How can you talk
                    so uncharitably to the man? Has he not been baptized already? He cannot be born
                    again now.’ Can he not be born again? Do you affirm this? Then he cannot be
                    saved. Though he be as old as Nicodemus was, yet, ‘except he be born again, he
                    cannot see the kingdom of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:3.</p></note> Therefore in saying, ‘he
                    cannot be born again,’ you in effect deliver him over to damnation. And where
                    lies the uncharitableness now? On my side, or on yours? I say, ‘He may be born
                    again, and so become an heir of salvation.’ You say, ‘He cannot be born again.’
                    And if so, he must inevitably perish. So you utterly block up his way to
                    salvation, and send him to hell out of mere charity!</p>
                <p>But perhaps the sinner himself, to whom in real charity we say, ‘You must be born
                    again,’ has been taught to say, ‘I defy your new doctrine; I need not be born
                    again. I was born again when I was baptized. What! Would you have me deny my
                    baptism?’ I answer, first, there is nothing under heaven which can excuse a lie.
                    Otherwise I should say to an open sinner, ‘If you have been baptized, do not own
                    it.’ For how highly does this aggravate your guilt! How will it increase your
                    damnation! Was you devoted to God at eight days old, and have you been all these
                    years devoting yourself to the devil? Was you, even before you had the use of
                    reason, consecrated to God the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost? And have
                    you, ever since you had the use of it, been flying in the face of God, and
                    consecrating yourself to Satan? Does the abomination of desolation,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        24:15.</p></note> the love of the world, pride, anger, lust, foolish desire,
                    and a whole train of vile affections, stand where it ought not? Have you set up
                    all these accursed things in that soul which was once a ‘temple of the Holy
                        Ghost’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 6:19.</p></note> Set apart for ‘an habitation of God through the
                        Spirit’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Eph. 2:22.</p></note> Yea, solemnly <pb n="02:200"/>given up to him?
                    And do you glory in this, that you once belonged to God? O, be ashamed! Blush!
                    Hide yourself in the earth! Never boast more of what ought to fill you with
                    confusion, to make you ashamed before God and man! I answer, secondly, you have
                    already denied your baptism; and that in the most effectual manner. You have
                    denied it a thousand and a thousand times; and you do so still day by day. For
                    in your baptism you renounced the devil and all his works.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. in the BCP rite ‘For the
                            Ministration of Holy Baptism’, the question addressed to ‘Godfathers and
                            Godmothers’ (in the case of infants) or to an adult baptized directly:
                            ‘Dost thou, therefore, in the name of this child, renounce the devil and
                            all his works, the vain pomp and glory of the world…?’</p></note>
                    Whenever therefore you give place to him again, whenever you do any of the works
                    of the devil, then you deny your baptism. Therefore you deny it by every wilful
                    sin; by every act of uncleanness, drunkenness, or revenge; by every obscene or
                    profane word; by every oath that comes out of your mouth. Every time you profane
                    the day of the Lord you thereby deny your baptism; yea, every time you do
                    anything to another which you would not he should do to you.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:12.</p></note> I
                    answer, thirdly, be you baptized or unbaptized, you must be born again.
                    Otherwise it is not possible you should be inwardly holy: and without inward as
                    well as outward holiness you cannot be happy even in this world; much less in
                    the world to come. Do you say, ‘Nay, but I do no harm to any man; I am honest
                    and just in all my dealings; I do not curse, or take the Lord’s name in vain; I
                    do not profane the Lord’s day; I am no drunkard, I do not slander my neighbour,
                    nor live in any wilful sin’? If this be so, it were much to be wished that all
                    men went as far as you do. But you must go farther yet, or you cannot be saved.
                    Still you must be born again. Do you add, ‘I do go farther yet; for I not only
                    do no harm, but do all the good I can.’ I doubt that fact; I fear you have had a
                    thousand opportunities of doing good which you have suffered to pass by
                    unimproved, and for which therefore you are accountable to God. But if you had
                    improved them all, if you really had done all the good you possibly could to all
                    men, yet this does not at all alter the case. Still you must be born again.
                    Without this nothing will do any good to your poor, sinful, polluted soul. ‘Nay,
                    but I constantly attend all the ordinances of God: I keep to my church and
                    sacrament.’ It is well you do. But all this will not keep you from hell, except
                    you be born again. Go to church twice a day, go to the Lord’s table every week,
                        <pb n="02:201"/>say ever so many prayers in private; hear ever so many
                    sermons, good sermons, excellent sermons, the best that ever were preached; read
                    ever so many good books—still you must be born again. None of these things will
                    stand in the place of the new birth. No, nor anything under heaven. Let this,
                    therefore, if you have not already experienced this inward work of God, be your
                    continual prayer, ‘Lord, add this to all thy blessings: let me be “born again”.
                    Deny whatever thou pleasest, but deny not this: let me be “born from above”.
                    Take away whatsoever seemeth thee good, reputation, fortune, friends, health.
                    Only give me this: to be “born of the Spirit”! To be received among the children
                    of God. Let me be born, “not of corruptible seed, but incorruptible, by the Word
                    of God, which liveth and abideth for ever”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82"
                        n="82"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:23.</p></note> And then let me daily
                    “grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus
                        Christ”!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">2
                            Pet. 3:18.</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
