<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 8: The First-Fruits of the Spirit</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon008</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 8: The First-Fruits of the Spirit</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="233" to="247"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <pb n="233"/>
            </p>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Wesley’s accent on salvation by faith as salvation from sin had already raised
                    the question of ‘sin in believers’ and had involved him in the tortured debates
                    about the residues of sin in the believer (<hi rend="italic">fomes peccati</hi>)
                    after justification and reconciliation. The classical Protestant doctrine of
                    invincible concupiscence had supported Luther’s characterization of the
                    Christian as <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi> (see No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>). But this collided with Wesley’s
                    holy living tradition, and it deferred entire sanctification until <hi rend="italic">in statu gloriae</hi> (‘in the state of glory only’). It also
                    fed the flames of scrupulosity, so that one of the marks of Puritan examinations
                    of conscience had come to be self-accusation and self-reproach.</p>
                <p>In this sermon (one of only five recorded uses of Rom. 8:1; another in 1741, two
                    in 1745, and one in 1760) Wesley is wrestling with the problem of Christian
                    self-accusation. It is a problem for those who already profess faith in Christ
                    but who retain their guilty memories and are still aware of continued
                    shortfallings.</p>
                <p>Here, then, is an early statement of Wesley’s ‘third alternative’ to two
                    extremes: of Christians, on the one hand, who might continue in sin and still
                    plead Christ’s atoning mercies, and Christians, on the other, who sag toward
                    despair under the weight of their guilt-ridden consciences. The crucial
                    distinction is between <hi rend="italic">wilful</hi> sins—lapses for which guilt
                    and repentance are the sinner’s only hope—and the <hi rend="italic">residue</hi>
                    of sin in believers for which ‘there is therefore now no condemnation in Christ
                    Jesus’. It is this sort of surcease from guilt and anxiety that Wesley here
                    identifies as ‘the first-fruits of the Spirit’. This, then, is a preparatory
                    essay on the paradox of a Christian’s sensitivity (in repentance) and serenity
                    (in grace). Thus it belongs with <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi> and
                    its qualifiers (<hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, <hi rend="italic">On
                        Sin in Believers</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                        Believers</hi>) as part of Wesley’s composite doctrine of salvation as
                    pardon and of its fruits as a deliverance of the Christian conscience from
                    anxiety and guilt.</p>
                <p>Yet another angle of the same, ancient controversy may be seen in Wesley’s
                    rejection of the Calvinist contention for ‘the perseverance of the <pb n="234"/>saints’. For Wesley, the way from the threshold to the plerophory of faith is
                    a risky one, chiefly because the residues of sin are forever capable of
                    thrusting themselves up to the level of direct temptation or even something like
                    unconscious control. Christians walk in the certainties of grace with the
                    assurance that sins repented are always forgivable, but they must always be
                    alert lest the ‘remains of sin’ turn into wilful sins (which, unrepented, lead
                    to backsliding). Here then, is an early sample of Wesley’s lifelong endeavour to
                    hold both ‘faith alone’ and ‘holy living’ in the same integrated vision of
                    Christian existence.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The First-fruits of the Spirit</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 8:1</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">There is therefore now no condemnation to them which are in
                        Christ Jesus, who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. By ‘them which are in Christ Jesus’ St. Paul evidently means those who
                    truly believe in him; those who ‘being justified by faith, have peace with God,
                    through our Lord Jesus Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:1.</p>
                    </note> They who thus believe do no
                    longer ‘walk after the flesh’, no longer follow the motions of corrupt nature,
                    but ‘after the Spirit’. Both their thoughts, words, and works are under the
                    direction of the blessed Spirit of God.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘There is therefore now no condemnation to’ these. There is no
                    condemnation to them from God, for he hath ‘justified them freely by his grace,
                    through the redemption that is in Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note> He hath forgiven all
                    their iniquities, and blotted out all their sins. And there is no condemnation
                    to them from within, for they ‘have received, not the spirit of the world, but
                    the Spirit which is of God, that they might know the things which are freely
                    given to them of God’:<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 2:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘which Spirit
                    beareth witness with their spirits that they are the children of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        8:16.</p>
                    </note> And to this is added ‘the testimony <pb n="235"/>of their
                    conscience, that in simplicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but
                    by the grace of God, they have had their conversation in the world’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor.
                                1:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. But because this Scripture has been so frequently misunderstood, and
                    that in so dangerous a manner; because such multitudes of ‘unlearned and
                    unstable men’ (οἱ ἀμαθεῖς καὶ ἀστήρικτοι,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:16.</p>
                    </note> men untaught of
                    God, and consequently unestablished in ‘the truth which is after
                        godliness’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus 1:1.</p>
                    </note> have ‘wrested it to their own destruction’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet.
                            3:16.</p>
                    </note> I propose to show as clearly as I can, first, who those
                    are ‘which are in Christ Jesus, and walk not after the flesh, but after the
                    Spirit’; and secondly, how ‘there is no condemnation to’ these.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        8:1.</p>
                    </note> I shall conclude with some practical inferences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. First, I am to show who those are that ‘are in Christ Jesus’. And are
                    they not those who believe in his name? Those who are ‘found in him, not having
                    their own righteousness, but the righteousness which is of God by faith’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                        3:9.</p>
                    </note> These, who ‘have redemption through his blood’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:7; Col.
                            1:14.</p>
                    </note> are properly said to be ‘in him’, for <hi rend="italic">they</hi> ‘dwell in Christ and Christ in them’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.1 John 4:13.</p>
                    </note>
                    They are ‘joined unto the Lord in one Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 6:17.</p>
                    </note> They are engrafted
                    into him as branches into the vine.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 15:4-5.</p>
                    </note> They are united, as
                    members to their head, in a manner which words cannot express, nor could it
                    before enter into their hearts to conceive.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 12:12-27; John
                    15:1-8.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Now ‘whosoever abideth in him sinneth not,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:6.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘walketh not after the flesh’. The flesh, in the usual language of St. Paul,
                    signifies corrupt nature. In this sense he uses the word, writing to the
                    Galatians, ‘The works of the flesh are manifest;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 5:19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and
                    a little before, ‘Walk in the Spirit, and ye shall not fulfil the lust (or
                    desire) of the flesh.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> To prove which, namely,
                    that those who ‘walk by the Spirit do not fulfil the lust of the flesh’, he
                    immediately adds, ‘For the flesh lusteth against the spirit; but the spirit
                    lusteth against the flesh (for these are contrary to each other), that ye may
                    not do the things which ye would.’ So the <pb n="236"/>words are literally
                    translated (ἵνα μὴ ἅ ἅν θέλετε, ταῦτα
                        ποιῆτε);<!--Mark this Hebrew with an xml:lang later, as well as any
                            other instances of foreign language.-->
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:17, as
                            in <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>: Wesley’s printers introduced a medley of
                            variant breathings and accents (e.g., Pine [1771] ἴνα μὴ ἅ ἁν θέλητε).
                            Modern critical edns. read ἐὰν instead of the contraction, ἄν, and most
                            modern translators take the whole phrase as a negative subjunctive,
                            meaning ‘so that what you will to do you cannot do’ (NEB); cf.
                            Goodspeed, Knox, etc. Wesley will not have it so: our moral disabilities
                            are not part of God’s original design for mankind; always, a remnant of
                            freedom (and, therefore, of responsibility) remains. Cf. Nos. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, I.3, IV.7; and 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, III.6.</p>
                    </note>
                    not, ‘So that ye cannot do the things that ye would,’ as if the flesh overcame
                    the spirit—a translation which hath not only nothing to do with the original
                    text of the Apostle, but likewise makes his whole argument nothing worth, yea,
                    asserts just the reverse of what he is proving.</p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘They who are of Christ’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:24.</p>
                    </note> who ‘abide in him’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:27,
                            28.</p>
                    </note> ‘have crucified the flesh with its affections and
                        lusts.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 5:24.</p>
                    </note> They abstain from all those works of the flesh:
                    from ‘adultery and fornication’; from ‘uncleanness and lasciviousness’; from
                    ‘idolatry, witchcraft, hatred, variance’; from ‘emulations, wrath, strife,
                    sedition, heresies, envyings, murders, drunkenness, revellings’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                        5:19-21.</p>
                    </note>—from every design, and word, and work to which the
                    corruption of nature leads. Although they feel the root of bitterness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        12:15.</p>
                    </note> in themselves, yet are they endued with power from on high
                    to trample it continually under foot, so that it cannot ‘spring up to trouble
                        them’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                                <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> insomuch that every fresh
                    assault which they undergo only gives them fresh occasion of praise, of crying
                    out, ‘Thanks be unto God, who giveth us the victory, through Jesus Christ our
                        Lord.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            Cor. 15:57.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. They now ‘walk after the Spirit’ both in their hearts and lives. They
                    are taught of him to love God and their neighbour with a love which is as ‘a
                    well of water, springing up into everlasting life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 4:14.</p>
                    </note> And by
                    him they are led into every holy desire, into every divine and heavenly temper,
                    till every thought which arises in their heart is holiness unto the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Zech.
                            14:20-21; Jer. 2:3.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. They who ‘walk after the Spirit’ are also led by him into all holiness
                    of conversation. Their speech is ‘always in grace, seasoned with salt’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col.
                        4:6.</p>
                    </note> with the love and fear of God. ‘No corrupt communication
                    comes out of their mouth, but (only) that which is good;’ that which is ‘to the
                    use of edifying’, which is ‘meet to <pb n="237"/>minister grace to the
                        hearers’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:29.</p>
                    </note> And herein likewise do they exercise
                    themselves day and night to do only the things which please God; in all their
                    outward behaviour to follow him who ‘left us an example that we might tread in
                    his steps’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Pet. 2:21.</p>
                    </note> in all their intercourse with their neighbour to
                    walk in justice, mercy, and truth; and ‘whatsoever they do’, in every
                    circumstance of life, to ‘do all to the glory of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                    10:31.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. These are they who indeed ‘walk after the Spirit’. Being filled with
                    faith and with the Holy Ghost, they possess in their hearts, and show forth in
                    their lives, in the whole course of their words and actions, the genuine fruits
                    of the Spirit of God, namely, ‘love, joy, peace, long-suffering, gentleness,
                    goodness, fidelity, meekness, temperance’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22-23.</p>
                    </note> and whatsoever else
                    is lovely or praiseworthy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 4:8.</p>
                    </note> They ‘adorn in all things
                    the gospel of God our Saviour’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 2:10.</p>
                    </note> and give full proof to
                    all mankind that they are indeed actuated by the same Spirit ‘which raised up
                    Jesus from the dead’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. I proposed to show, in the second place, how ‘there is no
                    condemnation to them which are’ thus ‘in Christ Jesus’, and thus ‘walk, not
                    after the flesh, but after the Spirit.’</p>
                <p>And, first, to believers in Christ walking thus ‘there is no condemnation’ on
                    account of their past sins. God condemneth them not for any of these; they are
                    as though they had never been; they are ‘cast as a stone into the depth of the
                        sea’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Mic. 7:19.</p>
                    </note> and he remembereth them no more. God having ‘set
                    forth his Son to be a propitiation for them, through faith in his blood, hath
                    declared unto them his righteousness, for the remission of the sins that are
                        past’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 3:25.</p>
                    </note> He layeth therefore none of these to their
                        charge;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 7:60; Rom. 8:33.</p>
                    </note> their memorial is perished with
                        them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            9:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. And there is no condemnation in their own breast, no sense of guilt, or
                    dread of the wrath of God. They ‘have the witness in themselves’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John
                            5:10.</p>
                    </note> they are conscious of their interest in the blood of
                        sprinkling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:24.</p>
                    </note> They ‘have not received again the spirit of
                    bondage unto fear’, unto doubt and racking uncertainty; but they ‘have <pb n="238"/>received the Spirit of adoption, crying in their hearts, Abba,
                        Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> Thus ‘being justified by faith, they have the
                        peace’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 5:1.</p>
                    </note> of God ruling in their hearts, flowing from a
                    continual sense of his pardoning mercy, and ‘the answer of a good conscience
                    toward God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 3:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. If it be said, ‘But sometimes a believer in Christ may lose his sight of
                    the mercy of God; sometimes such darkness may fall upon him that he no longer
                    sees him that is invisible,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 11:27.</p>
                    </note> no longer feels that
                    witness in himself of his part in the atoning blood; and then he is inwardly
                    condemned, he hath again “the sentence of death in himself”.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 1:9.</p>
                    </note> I
                    answer, supposing it so to be, supposing him not to see the mercy of God, then
                    he is not a believer; for faith implies light, the light of God shining upon the
                    soul. So far therefore as anyone loses this light, he for the time loses his
                    faith. And no doubt a true believer in Christ may lose the light of faith. And
                    so far as this is lost he may for a time fall again into condemnation. But this
                    is not the case of them who now ‘are in Christ Jesus’, who now believe in his
                    name. For so long as they believe and walk after the Spirit neither God condemns
                    them nor their own heart.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note the ‘third alternative’ here to the polarities
                            of over-anxious consciences, on the one hand, and to the ‘perseverance
                            of the saints’, on the other. Assurance (‘the light of faith’) is a
                            gift; it may be lost and yet also recovered. It is interesting to see
                            how tenaciously Wesley argued against ‘final perseverance’, as in <hi rend="italic">Predestination Calmly Considered</hi>, 72-86, and Nos.
                            13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>; 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>; 46, ‘The Wilderness State’; and 47,
                            ‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’. See also how skilfully he
                            edits his Puritan authors in <hi rend="italic">A Christian Library</hi>,
                            quietly omitting their arguments for it, as in Manton (1620-77), <hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Subjects</hi>, in Vol.
                        12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. They are not condemned, secondly, for any present sins, for now
                    transgressing the commandments of God. For they do not transgress them; they do
                    not ‘walk after the flesh, but after the Spirit’. This is the continual proof of
                    their ‘love of God, that they keep his commandments’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:3 and <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>.</p>
                    </note> even as St. John bears witness,
                    ‘Whosoever is born of God doth not commit sin. For his seed remaineth in him,
                    and he cannot sin, because he is born of God;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9.</p>
                    </note> he cannot so long as
                    that seed of God, that loving, holy faith, remaineth in him. So long as ‘he
                    keepeth himself’ herein ‘that wicked one toucheth him not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:18.</p>
                    </note> Now it
                    is evident he is not condemned for the sins which he doth not commit at all.
                    They <pb n="239"/>therefore who are thus ‘led by the Spirit are not under the
                        law’:<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 5:18.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> not under the curse or condemnation of
                    it, for it condemns none but those who break it. Thus that law of God, ‘Thou
                    shalt not steal,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:15.</p>
                    </note> condemns none but those who
                    do steal. Thus, ‘Remember the sabbath day to keep it holy’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:8.</p>
                    </note>
                    condemns those only who do not keep it holy. But ‘against’ the fruits of the
                    Spirit ‘there is no law.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> As the Apostle more
                    largely declares in those memorable words of his former Epistle to Timothy, ‘We
                    know that the law is good if a man use it lawfully; knowing this’ (if while he
                    uses the law of God, in order either to convince or direct, he know and remember
                    this), ὅτι δικαίῳ νόμος οὐ κεῖται (not ‘that the law is not made for a righteous
                    man’, but) ‘that the law does not lie against a righteous man’ (it has no force
                    against him, no power to condemn him), ‘but against the lawless and disobedient,
                    against the ungodly and sinners, against the unholy and profane; …according to
                    the glorious gospel of the blessed God.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Tim. 1:8-9, 11. [κεῖται, from
                                κεῖμαι, means ‘to lie’ or ‘to lean’, as Wesley has it here (<hi rend="italic">pace</hi> Sugden, I.169 and n.). Its figurative
                                meaning is ‘to be valid’ or ‘relevant’. The clause may thus be
                                translated, ‘The Law has no valid bearing on behaviour at this
                                level…’ (which is Wesley’s point). Cf. Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>, p. 428; see also
                                Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on this
                    ver.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. They are not condemned, thirdly, for inward sin, even though it does now
                    remain. That the corruption of nature does still remain, even in those who are
                    the children of God by faith; that they have in them the seeds of pride and
                    vanity, of anger, lust and evil desire, yea, sin of every kind, is too plain to
                    be denied, being matter of daily experience. And on this account it is that St.
                    Paul, speaking to those whom he had just before witnessed to be ‘in Christ
                        Jesus’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 1:2.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> to have been ‘called of God into the
                    fellowship (or participation) of his Son Jesus Christ’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> yet declares, ‘Brethren, I could not speak unto
                    you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal; even as unto babes in Christ.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor.
                                3:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘Babes in Christ’—so we see they were ‘in
                    Christ’; they were believers in a low degree. And yet how much of sin remained
                    in them! Of that ‘carnal mind’ which ‘is not subject to the law of God’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">
                    <pb n="240"/>6. And yet for all this they are not condemned. Although they
                    feel the flesh, the evil nature in them; although they are more sensible day by
                    day that their ‘heart <hi rend="italic">is</hi> deceitful, and desperately
                        wicked’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 17:9.</p>
                    </note> yet so long as they do not yield thereto, so long
                    as they give no place to the devil, so long as they maintain a continual war
                    with all sin, with pride, anger, desire, so that the flesh hath not dominion
                    over them, but they still ‘walk after the Spirit’: there is ‘no condemnation to
                    them which are in Christ Jesus’. God is well-pleased with their sincere though
                    imperfect obedience;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A reference to Wesley’s crucial distinction between
                            wilful or deliberate sin (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ‘a voluntary
                            transgression of a known law of God’ as in Nos. 19, ‘The Great Privilege
                            of those that are Born of God’, II.2-3; and 76, ‘On Perfection’, III.9)
                            and a faithful Christian’s ‘sincere but imperfect obedience’. See below,
                            No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> and they ‘have confidence toward God’, knowing they are
                    his ‘by the Spirit which he hath given them’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John 3:[21],
                    24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. Nay, fourthly, although they are continually convinced of sin cleaving
                    to all they do; although they are conscious of not fulfilling the perfect law,
                    either in their thoughts, or words, or works; although they know they do not
                    love the Lord their God with all their heart, and mind, and soul, and strength;
                    although they feel more or less of pride or self-will stealing in and mixing
                    with their best duties; although even in their more immediate intercourse with
                    God, when they assemble themselves with the great congregation, and when they
                    pour out their souls in secret to him who seeth all the thoughts and intents of
                    the heart, they are continually ashamed of their wandering thoughts,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>.</p>
                    </note> or of the deadness
                    and dullness of their affections—yet there is no condemnation to them still,
                    either from God or from their own heart. The consideration of these manifold
                    defects only gives them a deeper sense that they have always need of that blood
                    of sprinkling<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:24.</p>
                    </note> which speaks for them in the ears of God, and
                    that advocate with the Father<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:1.</p>
                    </note> who ‘ever liveth to make
                    intercession for them.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 7:25.</p>
                    </note> So far are these from driving
                    them away from him in whom they have believed, that they rather drive them the
                    closer to him, whom they feel the want of every moment. And at the same time,
                    the deeper sense they have of this want the more earnest <pb n="241"/>desire do
                    they feel, and the more diligent they are, as they ‘have received the Lord
                    Jesus, so to walk in him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 2:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. They are not condemned, fifthly, for ‘sins of infirmity’, as they are
                    usually called.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Thomas Westfield, ‘Sermon at St. Bartholomew the Great, on 2 Sam.
                            5:3’ (1628); Richard Kidder (Bishop of Bath and Wells), ‘A Discourse
                            Concerning Sins of Infirmity and Wilful Sins’ (1704), pp. 3-33; and
                            Lucas, <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi>, II.178; III.23 ,
                            296. Reformed theologians, generally, rejected the Catholic distinction
                            between ‘mortal’ (wilful) sins and ‘venial’ (involuntary) sins. But see
                            the list of sins in Johannes Heidegger, <hi rend="italic">Corpus
                                Theologiae</hi> (1700), V.61-71 (§§26-27), where No. 8 pertains to
                            ‘sins of weakness’ (i.e., ‘ignorance’, etc. ). See also J. A.
                            Quendstedt, <hi rend="italic">Theologia Didactico-Polemica</hi> (1685),
                            II.70: ‘Sins of infirmity, which overtake the regenerate without any
                            certain purpose of sinning. Such are sinful emotions of the mind, which
                            have suddenly arisen without their will, and whatever unlawful words or
                            deeds are the result of inadvertence or precipitancy, and contrary to
                            the purposes of one’s will.’</p>
                    </note> (Perhaps it were advisable
                    rather to call them <hi rend="italic">infirmities</hi>, that we may not seem to
                    give any countenance to sin, or to extenuate it in any degree by thus coupling
                    it with infirmity.) But if we must retain so ambiguous and dangerous an
                    expression, by ‘sins of infirmity’ I would mean such involuntary failings as the
                    saying a thing we believe true, though in fact it prove to be false; or the
                    hurting our neighbour without knowing or designing it, perhaps when we designed
                    to do him good. Though these are deviations from the holy and acceptable and
                    perfect will of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:1, 2.</p>
                    </note> yet they are not
                    properly sins, nor do they bring any guilt on the conscience of ‘them which are
                    in Christ Jesus’. They separate not between God and them, neither intercept the
                    light of his countenance, as being no ways inconsistent with their general
                    character of ‘walking not after the flesh, but after the Spirit’.</p>
                <p n="9">9. Lastly, ‘there is no condemnation’ to them for anything whatever which
                    it is not in their power to help; whether it be of an inward or outward nature,
                    and whether it be doing something or leaving something undone. For instance, the
                    Lord’s Supper is to be administered, but you do not partake thereof. Why do you
                    not? You are confined by sickness; therefore you cannot help omitting it—and for
                    the same reason you are not condemned. There is no guilt, because there is no
                    choice. As there is ‘a willing mind, it is accepted, according to that a man
                    hath, not according to that he hath not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 8:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">
                    <pb n="242"/>10. A believer indeed may sometimes be <hi rend="italic">grieved</hi> because he cannot do what his soul longs for. He may cry out,
                    when he is detained from worshipping God in the great congregation, ‘Like as the
                    hart panteth after the water brooks, so panteth my soul after thee, O God. My
                    soul is athirst for God, yea even for the living God. When shall I come to
                    appear in the presence of God?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 42:1-2 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> He may earnestly
                    desire (only still saying in his heart, ‘Not as I will, but as thou wilt’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:39,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note>) to ‘go again with the multitude, and bring them forth
                    into the house of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 42:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> But still, if he cannot
                    go, he feels no condemnation, no guilt, no sense of God’s displeasure; but can
                    cheerfully yield up those desires with, ‘O my soul, put thy trust in God: for I
                    will yet give him thanks, who is the help of my countenance and my God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 42:6-7
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. It is more difficult to determine concerning those which are usually
                    styled ‘sins of surprise’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Law, <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, (p.
                            21), where Law is sure that God ‘will be merciful to our unavoidable
                            weaknesses and infirmities’, including those surprising discoveries of
                            residual sins of which we have not yet repented. His aim is ‘to excite
                            [Christians] to an earnest examination of their lives…, etc.’. Wesley
                            stresses, more stringently than Law, the dangers of such ‘sudden
                            assaults’ (see below, II.13) and, consequently, the importance of
                            constant alertness to their disclosures. But here, again, the crucial
                            issue is the vexed question of the borderline between involuntary
                            shortfallings and wilful sins.</p>
                    </note> as when one who commonly in
                    patience possesses his soul on a sudden and violent temptation speaks or acts in
                    a manner not consistent with the royal law, ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as
                        thyself.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Lev. 19:18, etc.</p>
                    </note> Perhaps it is not easy to fix a general
                    rule concerning transgressions of this nature. We cannot say either that men
                    are, or that they are not, condemned for sins of surprise in general. But it
                    seems whenever a believer is by surprise overtaken in a fault there is more or
                    less condemnation as there is more or less concurrence of his will. In
                    proportion as a sinful desire or word or action is more or less voluntary, so we
                    may conceive God is more or less displeased, and there is more or less guilt
                    upon the soul.</p>
                <p n="12">12. But if so, then there may be some sins of surprise which bring much
                    guilt and condemnation. For in some instances our being surprised is owing to
                    some wilful and culpable neglect; or to a sleepiness of soul which might have
                    been prevented, or shaken off before the temptation came. A man may be
                    previously warned, either of God or man, that trials and danger are at hand, and
                    yet may say in his heart, ‘A little more slumber, a little more <pb n="243"/>folding of the hands to rest.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 6:10; 24:33.</p>
                    </note> Now if such an
                    one afterwards fall, though unawares, into the snare which he might have
                    avoided, that he fell unawares is no excuse—he might have foreseen and have
                    shunned the danger. The falling even by surprise, in such an instance as this,
                    is in effect a wilful sin; and as such must expose the sinner to condemnation
                    both from God and his own conscience.</p>
                <p n="13">13. On the other hand, there may be sudden assaults either from the world,
                    or the god of this world, and frequently from our own evil hearts, which we did
                    not, and hardly could foresee. And by these even a believer, while weak in
                    faith, may possibly be borne down, suppose into a degree of anger, or thinking
                    evil of another, with scarce any concurrence of his will. Now in such a case the
                    jealous God would undoubtedly show him that he had done foolishly. He would be
                    convinced of having swerved from the perfect law, from the mind which was in
                        Christ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> and consequently <hi rend="italic">grieved</hi>
                    with a godly sorrow, and lovingly <hi rend="italic">ashamed</hi> before God. Yet
                    need he not come into condemnation. God layeth not folly to his charge, but hath
                    compassion upon him, even ‘as a father pitieth his own children’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 103:13
                            (BCP).</p>
                    </note> And his heart condemneth him not; in the midst of that
                    sorrow and shame he can still say, ‘I will trust and not be afraid. For the Lord
                    Jehovah is my strength and my song; he is also become my salvation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                        12:2.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. It remains only to draw some practical inferences from the
                    preceding considerations.</p>
                <p>And, first, if there be ‘no condemnation to them which are in Christ Jesus’, and
                    ‘walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit’, on account of their past sins;
                    then ‘Why art thou fearful, O thou of little faith?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 8:26.</p>
                    </note>
                    Though thy sins were once more in number than the sand,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 139:18.</p>
                    </note> what is
                    that to thee now thou art in Christ Jesus? ‘Who shall lay anything to the charge
                    of God’s elect? It is God that justifieth: who is he that condemneth?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:33-34.</p>
                    </note> All the sins thou hast committed from thy youth up until
                    the hour when thou wast ‘accepted in the Beloved’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:6.</p>
                    </note> are
                    driven away as chaff,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Hos. 13:3.</p>
                    </note> are gone, are lost,
                    swallowed up, remembered no more. Thou art now ‘born <pb n="244"/>of the
                        Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:6, 8.</p>
                    </note> wilt thou be troubled or afraid for what was
                    done before thou wert born? Away with thy fears! Thou art not called to fear,
                    but to the ‘spirit of love and of a sound mind’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 1:7.</p>
                    </note> Know
                    thy calling. Rejoice in God thy Saviour, and give thanks to God thy Father
                    through him.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Wilt thou say, ‘But I have again committed sin, since I had redemption
                    through his blood;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:7; Col.1:14.</p>
                    </note> and therefore it is
                    that “I abhor myself, and repent in dust and ashes”’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 42:6.</p>
                    </note> It is
                    meet thou shouldst abhor thyself; and it is God who hath wrought thee to this
                    selfsame thing. But dost thou now believe? Hath he again enabled thee to say, ‘I
                    know that my Redeemer liveth;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job 19:25.</p>
                    </note> ‘and the life which I now
                    live, I live by faith in the Son of God’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note> Then that faith
                    again cancels all that is past, and there is no condemnation to thee. At
                    whatsoever time thou truly believest in the name of the Son of God, all thy sins
                    antecedent to that hour vanish away as the morning dew. Now, then, ‘Stand thou
                    fast in the liberty wherewith Christ hath made thee free.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:1.</p>
                    </note> He
                    hath once more made thee free from the power of sin, as well as from the guilt
                    and punishment of it. O ‘be not entangled again with the yoke of bondage’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> Neither the vile, devilish bondage of sin, of
                    evil desires, evil tempers, or words, or works, the most grievous yoke on this
                    side hell; nor the bondage of slavish tormenting fear, of guilt and
                    self-condemnation.</p>
                <p n="3">3. But, secondly, do all they which abide ‘in Christ Jesus walk not after
                    the flesh, but after the Spirit’? Then we cannot but infer that whosoever now
                    committeth sin hath no part or lot in this matter. He is even now condemned by
                    his own heart. But ‘if our heart condemn us’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:20.</p>
                    </note> if our own conscience
                    beareth witness that we are guilty, undoubtedly God doth; for he ‘is greater
                    than our heart, and knoweth all things’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> so that
                    we cannot deceive him, if we can ourselves. And think not to say, ‘I was
                    justified once; my sins were once forgiven me.’ I know not that; neither will I
                    dispute whether they were or no. Perhaps, at this distance of time, ‘tis next to
                    impossible to know with any tolerable degree of certainty whether that was a
                    true, genuine work of God, or whether thou didst only deceive thy own soul. But
                    this I know with the utmost <pb n="245"/>degree of certainty, ‘He that
                    committeth sin is of the devil.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3 :8. A sharp denial of the notion popularly
                            associated with Calvinism: ‘once in grace, always in grace.’ Here,
                            again, is Wesley’s insistence that only <hi rend="italic">wilful
                                sin</hi> forfeits grace. But even wilful sins may be repented and
                            forgiven.</p>
                    </note> Therefore thou art of thy father the devil. It
                    cannot be denied; for the works of thy father thou dost. O flatter not thyself
                    with vain hopes. Say not to thy soul, ‘Peace, peace!’ For there is no
                        peace.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Jer. 6:14; 8:11.</p>
                    </note> Cry aloud! Cry unto God out of the
                        deep,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ps. 130:1 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> if haply he may hear thy voice. Come unto
                    him as at first, as wretched and poor, as sinful, miserable, blind, and naked.
                    And beware thou suffer thy soul to take no rest till his pardoning love be again
                    revealed, till he ‘heal thy backslidings’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer. 3:22.</p>
                    </note> and fill thee again
                    with the ‘faith that worketh by love’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:6; cf. also, No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.6 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Thirdly, is there no condemnation to them which ‘walk after the Spirit’
                    by reason of <hi rend="italic">inward sin</hi> still remaining, so long as they
                    do not give way thereto; nor by reason of <hi rend="italic">sin cleaving</hi> to
                    all they do? Then fret not thyself because of ungodliness, though it still
                    remain in thy heart.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Notice Wesley’s version here of Luther’s <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi> and his different
                            nuancing of it. See above, II.6; and No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9 and n.</p>
                    </note> Repine not because
                    thou still comest short of the glorious image of God; nor yet because pride,
                    self-will, or unbelief, cleave to all thy words and works. And be not afraid to
                    know all the evil of thy heart, to know thyself as also thou art known.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            13:12.</p>
                    </note> Yea, desire of God that thou mayst not think of
                    thyself more highly than thou oughtest to think.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 12:3.</p>
                    </note> Let
                    thy continual prayer be:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Show me, as my soul can bear,</l>
                    <l>The depth of inbred sin:</l>
                    <l>All the unbelief declare,</l>
                    <l>The pride that lurks within!</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘Waiting for Christ the Prophet’,
                            st. 5, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 209
                                (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, II.263).</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p>But when he heareth thy prayer, and unveils thy heart, when he shows thee
                    throughly what spirit thou art of; then beware that thy faith fail thee not,
                    that thou suffer not thy shield to be torn from thee. Be abased. Be humbled in
                    the dust. See thyself <pb n="246"/>nothing, less than nothing, and vanity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            40:17.</p>
                    </note> But still, ‘let not thy heart be troubled, neither let
                    it be afraid.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 14:27.</p>
                    </note> Still hold fast, ‘I’, even I, ‘have an
                    advocate with the Father, Jesus Christ the righteous.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:1.</p>
                    </note> And ‘as
                    the heavens are higher than the earth, so is his love higher than even my
                        sins.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 103:11.</p>
                    </note> Therefore God is merciful to thee a sinner!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke
                            18:13.</p>
                    </note> Such a sinner as thou art! God is love; and Christ
                    hath died. Therefore the Father himself loveth thee. Thou art his child.
                    Therefore he will withhold from thee no manner of thing that is good.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        7:11.</p>
                    </note> Is it good that the whole body of sin which is now
                    crucified in thee should be destroyed? It shall be done. Thou shalt be ‘cleansed
                    from all filthiness both of flesh and spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                    </note> Is it good that
                    nothing should remain in thy heart but the pure love of God alone? Be of good
                    cheer! ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart and mind and soul
                    and strength.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 12:30; Luke 10:27.</p>
                    </note> ‘Faithful is he that hath promised,
                    who also will do it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:23.</p>
                    </note> It is thy part patiently
                    to continue in the work of faith, and in the labour of love; and in cheerful
                    peace, in humble confidence, with calm, and resigned, and yet earnest
                    expectation to wait till ‘the zeal of the Lord of Hosts shall perform
                        this’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 9:7; note this whole paragraph as a comment on the meaning of a
                            believer’s assurance, despite the remains of sin in believers (for
                            which, see No. 13). It is equally an exhortation to the <hi rend="italic">constant</hi> repentance of believers (for which, see
                            No. 14).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Fourthly, if they that ‘are in Christ and walk after the Spirit’ are not
                    condemned for <hi rend="italic">sins of infirmity</hi>, as neither for <hi rend="italic">involuntary failings</hi>, nor for anything whatever which
                    they are not able to help; then beware, O thou that hast faith in his blood,
                    that Satan herein ‘gain no advantage over thee’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 2:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    Thou art still foolish and weak, blind and ignorant; more weak than any words
                    can express, more foolish than it can yet enter into thy heart to conceive,
                    knowing nothing yet as thou oughtest to know. Yet let not all thy weakness and
                    folly, or any fruit thereof which thou art not yet able to avoid, shake thy
                    faith, thy filial trust in God, or disturb thy peace or joy in the Lord. The
                    rule which some give as to wilful sins, and which in that case may perhaps be
                    dangerous, is undoubtedly wise and safe if it be applied only to the case of
                    weakness and infirmities.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of Law’s stress on God’s <hi rend="italic">mercifulness</hi> toward all Christians who hold to their trust in
                            Christ’s sufficient merit and grace: ‘Weak and imperfect men shall,
                            notwithstanding their frailties and defects, be received as having
                            pleased God, if they have done their <hi rend="italic">utmost</hi> to
                            please him…. We cannot offer to God the service of angels [or of] man in
                            a state of perfection; but fallen men can do their <hi rend="italic">best</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">this</hi> is the perfection that
                            is required of us’ (<hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.23-24).</p>
                    </note> Art <pb n="247"/>thou fallen, O man of God?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 14:12.</p>
                    </note> Yet do not lie there,
                    fretting thyself and bemoaning thy weakness; but meekly say, ‘Lord, I shall fall
                    thus every moment unless thou uphold me with thy hand.’ And then, arise! Leap
                    and walk. Go on thy way. ‘Run with patience the race set before thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            12:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Lastly, since a believer need not come into condemnation, even though he
                    be <hi rend="italic">surprised</hi> into what his soul abhors (suppose his being
                    surprised is not owing to any carelessness or wilful neglect of his own); if
                    thou who believest art thus overtaken in a fault, then grieve unto the Lord: it
                    shall be a precious balm. Pour out thy heart before him,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 62:8.</p>
                    </note> and
                    show him of thy trouble. And pray with all thy might to him who is ‘touched with
                    the feeling of thy infirmities’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.4:15.</p>
                    </note> that he would stablish and
                    strengthen and settle<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet. 5:10.</p>
                    </note> thy soul, and suffer
                    thee to fall no more. But still he condemneth thee not. Wherefore shouldst thou
                    fear? Thou hast no need of any ‘fear that hath torment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:18.</p>
                    </note>
                    Thou shalt love him that loveth thee, and it sufficeth: more love will bring
                    more strength. And as soon as thou lovest him with all thy heart thou shall be
                    ‘perfect and entire, lacking nothing’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:4.</p>
                    </note> Wait in peace for that
                    hour when ‘the God of peace shall sanctify thee wholly, so that thy whole spirit
                    and soul and body may be preserved blameless unto the coming of our Lord Jesus
                        Christ’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Thess. 5:23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>