<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 51: The Good Steward</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 51: The Good Steward</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="263" to="280"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:281"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>In its substance and theme this sermon follows as a sequel to ‘The Use of Money’,
                    but its form is different and so also is its style. It is one of the very few of
                    Wesley’s sermons to the nobility, the fruit of a brief period of closer
                    cooperation between Wesley and the Countess of Huntingdon and her circle of
                    high-born friends in the closing years of the 1760s—an alliance shortly to be
                    disrupted by the controversies stirred up by that provocative Minute of 1770.
                    ‘The Use of Money’ is clearly to ‘plain people’ (<hi rend="italic">ad
                        populum</hi>). <hi rend="italic">The Good Steward</hi> is an ‘inaugural
                    sermon’ marking Wesley’s somewhat unlikely appointment as ‘Chaplain to the
                    Countess Dowager of Buchan’. The Countess had been born Lady Agnes Stewart of
                    Goodtrees (near Edinburgh), and now was the widow of David Erskine, tenth Earl
                    of Buchan. After the latter’s triumphant death, December 1, 1767, his son and
                    heir (also a convert to Methodism) ‘appointed Mr. Venn, Mr. Fletcher, and Mr.
                    Berridge as his (personal chaplains]’; see the vivid account in Seymour, <hi
                        rend="italic">Countess of Huntingdon</hi>, II.14-19. His mother (the
                    Dowager), ‘a woman of strong natural understanding and of a highly cultivated
                    mind’, seems to have been persuaded by Lady Huntingdon to appoint Mr. Wesley as
                    her own chaplain (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, I.427; see also WHS, X.91-92).
                    This was promptly acknowledged in a mildly stilted letter of Wesley’s to Lady
                    Huntingdon on January 4, 1768: ‘I am obliged to your Ladyship, and to Lady
                    Buchan, for such a mark of your regard as I did not at all expect. I purpose to
                    return her Ladyship thanks by this post.’ On the following May 15, in Edinburgh,
                    he preached to a ‘sufficiently crowded house, even with the rich and
                    honourable’, and one may suppose that his topic for that occasion had been <hi
                        rend="italic">The Good Steward</hi> (a <hi rend="italic">concio ad
                        aulam</hi>, dated for publication as of May 14). He had already spoken on
                    this same theme in No. 28, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §§26-27. He and the
                    well-read in his audience would have recognized the echoes here from William
                    Law’s classic description of <hi rend="italic">the stewardship of life
                        itself</hi> in his <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>. The special
                    obligations of Christian stewardship amongst ‘the rich and honourable’ had
                    already been analyzed in quite genteel fashion by John Chappelow, <hi
                        rend="italic">The Right Way to be Rich</hi>. What <pb n="02:282"/>Wesley
                    adds is a vivid description of ‘The Last Judgment’, echoing his earlier sermon,
                    No. 15, <hi rend="italic">The Great Assize</hi>.</p>
                <p>Wesley’s style here is noticeably more formal than in the generality of his
                    sermons, his learning slightly more in evidence. Even more notable, however, are
                    his brief excursions into speculation (e.g., the controverted question about
                    ‘the sleep of death’, etc.). The basic message is, of course, familiar from
                    Wesley’s earliest interest in holy living: all of life is from God, and our use
                    of <hi rend="italic">all</hi> its gifts and bounties are to be received
                    gratefully and administered faithfully as ‘‘good <hi rend="italic"
                    >stewards</hi>’, and always <hi rend="italic">ad interim</hi>.</p>
                <p>What Wesley’s chaplaincy to the Dowager Countess amounted to is not altogether
                    dear. He adverts to it in the title of his open <hi rend="italic">Letter to the
                        Rev. Dr. Rutherforth</hi> (March 24, 1768) and, again, on the titlepage of
                    his memorial sermon on the death of George Whitefield, November 18, 1770 (see
                    No. 53).</p>
                <p>Does his subsequent silence suggest that the appointment lapsed after the
                    ‘Calvinist-Arminian’ disputes of the 1770s heated up? We do not know. What is
                    certain is that, while it lasted, the patronage of the Erskine family would have
                    aided Wesley’s work in Scotland. The sermon itself was first published in
                    Newcastle in 1768 and then inserted into Vol. IV of Wesley’s <hi rend="italic"
                        >Works</hi> (1771). For the publishing history of its nine extant editions
                    during Wesley’s lifetime, and a list of its variant readings, see Appendix, Vol.
                    4, and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 311.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Good Steward</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Luke 16:2</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Give an account of thy stewardship; for thou canst be no longer
                        steward.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div>
                <p>1. The relation which man bears to God, the creature to his Creator, is exhibited
                    to us in the oracles of God under various representations. Considered as a
                    sinner, a fallen creature, he is there represented as a <hi rend="italic"
                        >debtor</hi> to his Creator. He is also frequently represented as a <hi
                        rend="italic">servant</hi>, which indeed is essential to him as a creature,
                    insomuch that this appellation is given to the Son of <pb n="02:283"/>God when
                    in his state of humiliation: he ‘took upon him the form of a servant, being made
                    in the likeness of men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:7.</p></note></p>
                <p>2. But no character more exactly agrees with the present state of man than that
                    of a <hi rend="italic">steward</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (Luke
                            16:1); and also Poole, <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>: ‘We are but
                            stewards of the good things God lends us, and must give an account to
                            our Master of them.’ Henry, <hi rend="italic">Exposition</hi>, on the
                            same passage, quotes from Rabbi Kimchi: ‘This world is a house; heaven
                            the roof; the stars the lights; the earth…a table spread…; man is the
                                <hi rend="italic">steward</hi>…; if he behave himself well, he shall
                            find favour in the eyes of the Lord; if not, he shall be turned out of
                            his stewardship.’</p></note> Our blessed Lord frequently represents him
                    as such; and there is a peculiar propriety in the representation. It is only in
                    one particular respect, namely, as he is a sinner, that he is styled a ‘debtor’;
                    and when he is styled a ‘servant’ the appellation is general and indeterminate.
                    But a ‘steward’ is a servant of a particular kind; such a one as man is in all
                    respects. This appellation is exactly expressive of his situation in the present
                    world, specifying what kind of servant he is to God, and what kind of service
                    his divine master expects from him.</p>
                <p>It may be of use, then, to consider this point throughly, and to make our full
                    improvement of it. In order to this let us, first, inquire in what respects we
                    are now God’s ‘stewards’. Let us, secondly, observe that when he requires our
                    souls of us we ‘can be no longer stewards’. It will then only remain, as we may
                    in the third place observe, to ‘give an account of our stewardship’.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>I. 1. And, first, we are to inquire in what respects we are now God’s stewards.
                    We are now indebted to him for all we have; but although a debtor is obliged to
                    return what he has received, yet until the time of payment comes he is at
                    liberty to use it as he pleases. It is not so with a steward: he is not at
                    liberty to use what is lodged in his hands as <hi rend="italic">he</hi> pleases,
                    but as his master pleases. He has no right to dispose of anything which is in
                    his hands but according to the will of his lord. For he is not the proprietor of
                    any of these things, but barely entrusted with them by another: and entrusted on
                    this express condition, that he shall dispose of all as his master orders. Now
                    this is exactly the case of every man with relation to God. We are not at
                    liberty to use what he has lodged in our hands as <hi rend="italic">we</hi>
                    please, but as he pleases, who alone is the Possessor of heaven and earth,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Gen. 14:19,
                        22.</p></note> and the Lord of every creature. We have no right to dispose
                    of anything we have but according to <pb n="02:284"/>his will, seeing we are not
                    proprietors of any of these things. They are all, as our Lord speaks,
                        ἀλλότρια<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            16:12.</p></note>, ‘belonging to another person’; nor is anything
                    properly ‘our own’ in the land of our pilgrimage.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">See Exod. 6:4.</p></note> We
                    shall not receive τὰ ἴδια,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 4:32; but see also Bauer in Arndt and
                            Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>.</p></note> ‘our
                    own things’, till we come to our own country. Eternal things only are our own:
                    with all these temporal things we are barely entrusted by another—the Disposer
                    and Lord of all. And he entrusts us with them on this express condition, that we
                    use them only as our Master’s goods, and according to the particular directions
                    which he has given us in his Word.</p>
                <p>2. On this condition he hath entrusted us with our souls, our bodies, our goods,
                    and whatever other talents we have received: but in order to impress this
                    weighty truth on our hearts it will be needful to come to particulars.</p>
                <p>And first, God has entrusted us with our <hi rend="italic">soul</hi>, an immortal
                    spirit made in the image of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Gen. 1:27; 9:6, etc.</p></note> together with all
                    the powers and faculties thereof—understanding, imagination, memory; will, and a
                    train of affections either included in it or closely dependent upon it; love and
                    hatred, joy and sorrow, respecting present good and evil; desire and aversion,
                    hope and fear, respecting that which is to come. All these St. Paul seems to
                    include in two words when he says, ‘The peace of God shall keep your <hi
                        rend="italic">hearts</hi> and <hi rend="italic">minds</hi>.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">Phil.
                        4:7.</p></note> Perhaps, indeed the latter word, νσήματα, might rather be
                    rendered ‘thoughts’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Bengel, <hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi>, <hi
                                rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>: ‘The heart is the seat of one’s
                            thoughts.’ But see Bauer in Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Greek-English Lexicon</hi> on νόημα.</p></note> provided we take
                    that word in its most extensive sense, for every perception of the mind, whether
                    active or passive.</p>
                <p>3. Now of all these it is certain we are only stewards. God has entrusted us with
                    these powers and faculties, not that we may employ them according to our own
                    will, but according to the express orders which he has given us; although it is
                    true that in doing his will we most effectually secure our own happiness, seeing
                    it is herein only that we can be happy either in time or in eternity. Thus we
                    are to use our understanding, our imagination, our memory, wholly to the glory
                    of him that gave them. Thus our will is to be wholly given up to him, and all
                    our affections to be <pb n="02:285"/>regulated as he directs. We are to love and
                    hate, to rejoice and grieve, to desire and shun, to hope and fear, according to
                    the rule which he prescribes whose we are, and whom we are to serve in all
                        things.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 27:23.</p></note> Even our thoughts are not our own in this sense:
                    they are not at our own disposal, but for every deliberate motion of our mind we
                    are accountable to our great Master.</p>
                <p>4. God has, secondly, entrusted us with our <hi rend="italic">bodies</hi> (those
                    exquisitely wrought machines, so ‘fearfully and wonderfully made’),<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 139:14. For
                            Wesley’s frequent descriptions of the body as a machine, cf. Nos. 56,
                            ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’, I.7; 57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.1,
                            5; 69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, I.13; 71, ‘Of Good
                            Angels’, I.7; 72, ‘Of Evil Angels’, II.8; 82, ‘On Temptation’, I.2; 116,
                            ‘What is Man? Ps. 8:4’, §§1-4; 141, ‘The Image of God’, II.1. See also
                            his <hi rend="italic">Thoughts Upon Necessity</hi>, III.9; and his <hi
                                rend="italic">Survey</hi>, I.27-29, 164; II.275-76; IV.89; V.254.
                            For another comment on his body/soul dualism, see No. 41, <hi
                                rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, III.5 and n.</p></note> with
                    all the powers and members thereof. He has entrusted us with the organs of <hi
                        rend="italic">sense</hi>, of sight, hearing, and the rest: but none of these
                    are given us as our own, to be employed according to our own will. None of these
                    are <hi rend="italic">lent</hi> us in such a sense as to leave us at liberty to
                    use them as we please for a season. No; we have received them on these very
                    terms, that as long as they abide with us we should employ them all in that very
                    manner, and no other, which he appoints.</p>
                <p>5. It is on the same terms that he has imparted to us that most excellent talent
                    of <hi rend="italic">speech</hi>. ‘Thou hast given me a tongue’, says the
                    ancient writer, ‘that I may praise thee therewith.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Augustine, Confessions, V.i:
                                ‘<hi rend="italic">Accipe sacrificium confessionum mearum de manu
                                linguae meae, quam formasti et excitasti, ut confiteatur nomini
                                tuo</hi>.’</p></note> For this purpose was it given to all the
                    children of men, to be employed in glorifying God. Nothing therefore is more
                    ungrateful, or more absurd, than to think or say, ‘our tongues are our own.’
                    That cannot be, unless we have created ourselves, and so are independent on the
                    Most High. Nay, but ‘it is he that hath made us, and not we ourselves.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps.
                            100:3.</p></note> The manifest consequence is that he is still <hi
                        rend="italic">Lord over us</hi>, in this as in all other respects. It
                    follows that there is not a word of our tongue for which we are not accountable
                    to him.</p>
                <p>6. To him we are equally accountable for the use of our <hi rend="italic"
                        >hands</hi> and <hi rend="italic">feet</hi>, and all the <hi rend="italic"
                        >members</hi> of our body. These are so many talents which are committed to
                    our trust,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Tim. 1:11.</p></note> until the time appointed by the Father.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal.
                        4:2.</p></note> Until then we have the use of all these; <pb n="02:286"/>but
                    as stewards, not as proprietors: to the end we should ‘render them, not as
                    instruments of unrighteousness unto sin, but as instruments of righteousness
                    unto God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 6:13.</p></note></p>
                <p>7. God has entrusted us, thirdly, with a portion of <hi rend="italic">worldly
                        goods</hi>, with food to eat, raiment to put on, and a place where to lay
                    our head, with not only the necessaries but the conveniences of life. Above all,
                    he has committed to our charge that precious talent which contains all the rest,
                        <hi rend="italic">money</hi>. Indeed, it is unspeakably precious if we are
                    ‘wise and faithful stewards’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 12:42.</p></note> of it; if we employ
                    every part of it for such purposes as our blessed Lord has commanded us to
                    do.</p>
                <p>8. God has entrusted us, fourthly, with several talents which do not properly
                    come under any of these heads: such is bodily <hi rend="italic">strength</hi>;
                    such are <hi rend="italic">health</hi>, a pleasing <hi rend="italic"
                    >person</hi>, an agreeable <hi rend="italic">address</hi>; such are <hi
                        rend="italic">learning</hi> and <hi rend="italic">knowledge</hi> in their
                    various degrees, with all the other advantages of <hi rend="italic"
                        >education</hi>. Such is the <hi rend="italic">influence</hi> which we have
                    over others, whether by their <hi rend="italic">love</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >esteem</hi> of us, or by <hi rend="italic">power</hi>—power to do them good
                    or hurt, to help or hinder them in the circumstances of life. Add to these that
                    invaluable talent of <hi rend="italic">time</hi>, with which God entrusts us
                    from moment to moment. Add, lastly, that on which all the rest depend, and
                    without which they would all be curses, not blessings: namely, the <hi
                        rend="italic">grace</hi> of God, the power of his Holy Spirit, which alone
                    worketh in us<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Eph. 3:20.</p></note> all that is acceptable in his sight.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 19:14; 1
                            Tim. 2:3.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div><p>II. 1. In so many respects are the children of men stewards of the Lord, ‘the
                    possessor of heaven and earth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Gen. 14:19, 22.</p></note> So large a portion of
                    his goods of various kinds hath he committed to their charge. But it is not for
                    ever, nor indeed for any considerable time. We have this trust reposed in us
                    only during the short, uncertain space that we sojourn here below; only so long
                    as we remain on earth, as this fleeting breath is in our nostrils. The hour is
                    swiftly approaching, it is just at hand, when we ‘can be no longer
                        stewards’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Luke 16:2.</p></note> The moment the body ‘returns to the dust as
                    it was, and the spirit to God that gave it’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22"
                        n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 12:7.</p></note> we bear that
                    character no more; the time of our stewardship is at an end. Part of those goods
                        <pb n="02:287"/>wherewith we were before entrusted are now come to an end;
                    at least they are so with regard to <hi rend="italic">us</hi>; nor are we longer
                    entrusted with them—and that part which remains can no longer be employed or
                    improved as it was before.</p>
                <p>2. Part of what we were entrusted with before is at an end, at least with regard
                    to us. What have we to do after this life with food, and raiment, and houses,
                    and earthly possessions? The food of the dead is the dust of the earth: they are
                    clothed only with worms and rottenness. They dwell in ‘the house prepared for
                    all flesh’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Job 30:23, ‘the house appointed for all living’.</p></note> their lands
                    know them no more. All their worldly goods are delivered into other hands, and
                    they have ‘no more portion under the sun’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24"
                        n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 9:6.</p></note></p>
                <p>3. The case is the same with regard to the <hi rend="italic">body</hi>. The
                    moment the spirit returns to God we are no longer stewards of this machine,
                    which is then sown in corruption and dishonour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25"
                        n="25"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 15:42-43. Cf. No. 129, ‘Heavenly
                            Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, I.1.</p></note> All the parts and members
                    of which it was composed lie mouldering in the clay. The hands have no longer
                    power to move; the feet have forgot their office; the flesh, the sinews, the
                    bones are all hasting to be dissolved into common dust.</p>
                <p>4. Here end also the talents of a <hi rend="italic">mixed</hi> nature: our <hi
                        rend="italic">strength</hi>, our <hi rend="italic">health</hi>, our <hi
                        rend="italic">beauty</hi>; our <hi rend="italic">eloquence</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">address</hi>; our faculty of pleasing, of persuading or
                    convincing others. Here end likewise all the <hi rend="italic">honours</hi> we
                    once enjoyed, all the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> which was lodged in our
                    hands, all the <hi rend="italic">influence</hi> which we once had over others,
                    either by the love or the esteem which they bore us. ‘Our love, our hatred, our
                    desire is perished:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles. 9:6.</p></note> none regard how we were
                    once affected toward them. They look upon the dead as neither able to help nor
                    hurt them; so that ‘a living dog is better than a dead lion.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Eccles. 9:4.</p></note></p>
                <p>5. Perhaps a doubt may remain concerning some of the other talents wherewith we
                    are now entrusted, whether they will cease to exist when the body returns to
                    dust, or only cease to be improvable. Indeed there is no doubt but the kind of
                        <hi rend="italic">speech</hi> which we now use, by means of these bodily
                    organs, will then be entirely at an end, when those organs are destroyed. It is
                    certain the tongue will no more occasion any vibrations in the air, neither will
                        <pb n="02:288"/>the ear convey these tremulous motions to the common
                        sensory.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>, ‘Sensory’: ‘<hi
                                rend="italic">Sensorium commune</hi>, the seat of the common sense;
                            or that part or place where the sensible soul is supposed more
                            immediately to preside [over the body/soul interconnections]…. Descartes
                            will have it in the conarion or pineal gland.’ But see also John Norris,
                                <hi rend="italic">Reason and Religion</hi> (1689), II.ii.188. The
                            classical source of the notion is in Aristotle, <hi rend="italic">De
                                Memoria</hi>, 450<hi rend="italic">a</hi>, which speaks of ‘the
                            primary faculty of perception’. Cf. also No. 124, ‘Human Life a Dream’,
                            §7.</p></note> Even the <hi rend="italic">sonus exilis</hi>,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Sugden’s
                            note, II.468-69; but none of his citations there comes close to the
                            phrase, <hi rend="italic">sonus exilis</hi>. Could it be Wesley’s own
                            Latin translation of Homer’s ὤχετο τετριγυῖα (<hi rend="italic"
                                >Iliad</hi>, xxiii.99-101)? <hi rend="italic">Vox exilis</hi> is
                            cited in Lewis and Short, <hi rend="italic">A Latin Dictionary</hi>, as
                            from Quintilian (XI.iii.15), but not <hi rend="italic">sonus
                            exilis</hi>; and Quintilian was not a ‘poet’.</p></note> the low, shrill
                    voice which the poet supposes to belong to a separate spirit, we cannot allow to
                    have a real being; it is a mere flight of imagination. Indeed it cannot be
                    questioned but separate spirits have some way to communicate their sentiments to
                    each other; but what inhabitant of flesh and blood can explain that way? What we
                    term ‘speech’ they cannot have. So that we can no longer be stewards of this
                    talent when we are numbered with the dead.</p>
                <p>6. It may likewise admit of a doubt whether our <hi rend="italic">senses</hi>
                    will exist when the organs of sense are destroyed. Is it not probable that those
                    of the lower kind will cease—the feeling, the smell, the taste—as they have a
                    more immediate reference to the body, and are chiefly, if not wholly, intended
                    for the preservation of it? But will not some kind of <hi rend="italic"
                        >sight</hi> remain, although the eye be closed in death? And will there not
                    be something in the soul equivalent to the present sense of <hi rend="italic"
                        >hearing</hi>? Nay, is it not probable that these will not only exist in the
                    separate state, but exist in a far greater degree, in a more eminent manner than
                    now. When the soul, disentangled from its clay, is no longer</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>A dying sparkle in a cloudy place;</l>
                    <l>when it no longer</l>
                    <l>Looks through the windows of the eye and ear,</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s
                            adaptation of Sir John Davies’s <hi rend="italic">Nosce Teipsum</hi>
                            (‘Of Human Knowledge’), Pt. I, st. 17:</p><l>How can we hope, that
                            through the eye and ear,</l><l>This dying sparkle, in this cloudy
                            place,</l><l>Can recollect these beams of knowledge clear</l><l>Which
                            were infused in the first minds by grace?</l><p rend="footnote text">St.
                            15 has the phrase ‘windows of the mind’ which Wesley conflated with l.
                            1, above. See also <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred
                                Poems</hi> (1744), I.17.</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p><pb n="02:289"/>but rather is all eye, all ear, all sense, in a manner we cannot
                    yet conceive. And have we not a clear proof of the possibility of this, of
                    seeing without the use of the eye, and hearing without the use of the ear? Yea,
                    and an earnest of it continually? For does not the soul see, in the clearest
                    manner, when the eye is of no use, namely in dreams?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 124, ‘Human Life a
                            Dream’, §4 and n.</p></note> Does she not then enjoy the faculty of
                    hearing without any help from the ear? But however this be, certain it is that
                    neither will our <hi rend="italic">senses</hi>, any more than our <hi
                        rend="italic">speech</hi>, be entrusted to us in the manner they are now,
                    when the body lies in the silent grave.</p>
                <p>7. How far the <hi rend="italic">knowledge</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                        >learning</hi> which we have gained by <hi rend="italic">education</hi> will
                    then remain, we cannot tell. Solomon indeed says, ‘There is no work, nor device,
                    nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in the grave whither thou goest.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Eccles. 9:10.</p></note> But
                    it is evident, these words cannot be understood in an absolute sense; for it is
                    so far from being true that there is <hi rend="italic">no knowledge</hi> after
                    we have quitted the body that the doubt lies on the other side, whether there be
                    any such thing as real knowledge till then? Whether it be not a plain, sober
                    truth, not a mere poetical fiction, that </p>
                <lg>
                    <l>…all these shadows which for things we take,</l>
                    <l>Are but the empty dreams which in death’s sleep we make<note place="foot"
                            xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Abraham Cowley, <hi
                                    rend="italic">Pindarique Odes</hi>, ‘Life’, II.22-23. See also,
                                    <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>
                                (1744), I.43.</p></note></l>
                </lg>— <p>only excepting those things which God himself has been pleased to reveal
                    to man? I will speak for one. After having sought for truth with some diligence
                    for half a century I am at this day hardly sure of anything but what I learn
                    from the Bible. Nay, I positively affirm I know nothing else so certainly that I
                    would dare to stake my salvation upon it.</p>
                <p>So much, however, we may learn from Solomon’s words, that ‘there is no’ <hi
                        rend="italic">such</hi> ‘knowledge or wisdom in the grave’ as will be of any
                    use to an unhappy spirit; there is ‘no device’ there whereby he can now improve
                    those talents with which he was once entrusted. For <hi rend="italic">time</hi>
                    is no more: the time of our trial for everlasting happiness or misery is past.
                        <hi rend="italic">Our day</hi>, the day of man, is over; ‘the day of
                        salvation’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 6:2; cf. Isa. 49:8.</p></note> is ended. Nothing now remains but
                    the day of the Lord, ushering in wide, unchangeable eternity.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 54, ‘On Eternity’,
                            §§1, 5-7.</p></note></p>
                <p>8. But still our souls, being incorruptible and immortal, of a <pb n="02:290"
                    />nature ‘little lower than the angels’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 8:5; Heb. 2:7, 9.</p></note> (even if we
                    are to understand that phrase of our original nature, which may well admit of a
                    doubt), when our bodies are mouldered into earth, will remain with all their
                    faculties. Our <hi rend="italic">memory</hi>, our <hi rend="italic"
                        >understanding</hi>, will be so far from being destroyed, yea, or impaired
                    by the dissolution of the body, that on the contrary we have reason to believe
                    they will be inconceivably strengthened. Have we not the clearest reason to
                    believe that they will then be wholly freed from those defects which now
                    naturally result from the union of the soul with the corruptible body? It is
                    highly probable that from the time these are disunited our memory will let
                    nothing slip; yea, that it will faithfully exhibit everything to our view which
                    was ever committed to it. It is true that the invisible world is in Scripture
                    termed ‘the land of forgetfulness’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 88:12 (AV).</p></note> or, as it is still more
                    strongly expressed in the old translation, ‘the land where all things are
                        forgotten’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text"
                                ><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> (BCP). Cf. No. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §20
                            and n.</p></note> They are forgotten; but by whom? Not by the
                    inhabitants of that land, but by the inhabitants of the earth. It is with regard
                    to them that the unseen world is ‘the land of forgetfulness’. All things therein
                    are too frequently forgotten by these; but not by disembodied spirits. From the
                    time they have put off the earthly tabernacle<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39"
                        n="39"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 5:1; 2 Pet. 1:13, 14.</p></note>
                    we can hardly think they forget anything.</p>
                <p>9. In like manner the <hi rend="italic">understanding</hi> will doubtless be
                    freed from the defects that are now inseparable from it. For many ages it has
                    been an unquestioned maxim, <hi rend="italic">humanum est errare et
                        nescire</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See above, No. 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’, I.4 and n.</p></note>—‘ignorance
                    and mistake are inseparable from human nature.’ But the whole of this assertion
                    is only true with regard to living men, and holds no longer than while ‘the
                    corruptible body presses down the soul’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 9:15. Cf. No. 41, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Wandering Thoughts</hi>, II.3 and n.</p></note> Ignorance indeed
                    belongs to every finite understanding (seeing there is none beside God that
                    knoweth all things), but not mistake. When the body is laid aside, this also is
                    laid aside for ever.</p>
                <p>10. What then can we say to an ingenious man who has lately made a discovery that
                    disembodied spirits have not only no senses (not even sight or hearing), but no
                    memory or understanding, no thought or perception, not so much as a
                    consciousness of their <pb n="02:291"/>own existence! That they are in a dead
                    sleep from death to the resurrection!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                            rend="footnote text">This theory runs back to the Anabaptists, at least;
                            cf. G. H. Williams, <hi rend="italic">The Radical Reformation</hi>, pp.
                            20-24, 104-6, 580-92. It had been denounced by Calvin in one of his
                            earliest essays, <hi rend="italic">Psychopannychia; Or, a Refutation of
                                the Error that the Soul Sleeps in the Interval Between Death and the
                                Judgment</hi> (written in 1534; published in 1542). Cf. ‘First Part
                            of the Sermon, against the Fear of Death’, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Homilies</hi>, pp. 81-85. The same idea is analysed rather
                            differently in John Donne’s famous sermon, ‘Death’s Duel’ (Sermon 15 in
                            his <hi rend="italic">XXVI Sermons</hi> [1660]).</p><p
                            rend="footnote text">The ‘ingenious man’ cited here, however, was Edmund
                            Law (archdeacon of Carlisle; later bishop), who had advocated
                            ‘mortalism’ in a D. D. exercise at Cambridge (1754), published as an
                            ‘Appendix’ to the 3rd edn. of <hi rend="italic">The Theory of
                                Religion</hi> (1755). This ‘Appendix’ had been roundly criticized
                            (e.g., by John Steffe [1758]) but had then been defended by Francis
                            Blackbume, <hi rend="italic">A Short Historical View Concerning An
                                Intermediate State…</hi> (1765), and by Joseph Priestley, <hi
                                rend="italic">Disquisitions Relating to Matter and Spirit…</hi>
                            (1777), Sec. XIII, p. 155, and Sec. XVII, espec. p. 232. It is
                            noteworthy that Wesley would have been so knowledgeable and yet also so
                            casual in his references here and elsewhere to such a controversy; see
                            No. 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’, I.3 and n.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">Consanguineus lethi sopor</hi><note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Virgil, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Aeneid</hi>, vi.278 (borrowed from Homer, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Iliad</hi>, xiv.231). See also, Wesley’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Survey</hi>, V.254, where the same phrase appears in a different
                            form, ‘<hi rend="italic">consanguineus somni</hi>’. The English
                            quotation which follows is, of course, Wesley’s translation of the
                            Latin.</p></note> indeed! Such a sleep we may well call ‘a near kinsman
                    of death’, if it be not the same thing. What can we say but that ingenious men
                    have strange dreams; and these they sometimes mistake for realities.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">Locke discusses
                            this in his <hi rend="italic">Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi>
                            (1690), II.i.17, and espec. II.xix.4. Cf. also No. 57, ‘On the Fall of
                            Man’, II.2, where Wesley says: ‘the soul cannot dispense with [the
                            body’s] service, imperfect as it is. For an embodied spirit cannot form
                            one thought but by the mediation of its bodily organs. For thinking is
                            not, as many suppose, an act of a pure spirit, but the act of a spirit
                            connected with a body, and playing upon a set of material keys.’ Cf.
                            also his letter to Mrs. Bennis, Oct 28, 1771; No. 132, ‘On Faith, Heb.
                            11:1’, §8; and his <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, I.178.</p></note></p>
                <p>11. But to return. As the soul will retain its understanding and memory,
                    notwithstanding the dissolution of the body, so undoubtedly the <hi
                        rend="italic">will</hi>, including all the <hi rend="italic"
                    >affections</hi>, will remain in its full vigour. If our love or anger, our hope
                    or desire, perish, it is only with regard to those whom we leave behind. To them
                    it matters not whether they were the objects of our love or hate, of our desire
                    or aversion. But in separate spirits themselves we have no reason to believe
                    that any of these are extinguished. It is more probable that they work with far
                    greater force than while the soul was clogged with flesh and blood.</p>
                <p>12. But although all these, although both our knowledge and senses, our memory
                    and understanding, together with our will, our love, hate, and all our
                    affections, remain after the body is dropped off, yet in this respect they are
                    as though they were not; we are no longer stewards of them. The things continue,
                    but our <hi n="02:292"/> stewardship does not; we no more act in that capacity.
                    Even the <hi rend="italic">grace</hi> which was formerly entrusted with us, in
                    order to enable us to be faithful and wise stewards, is now no longer entrusted
                    for that purpose. The days of our stewardship are ended.</p></div>
            <div>
                <p>III. 1. It now remains that, being ‘no longer stewards’, we ‘give an account of
                    our stewardship’. Some have imagined, this is to be done immediately after
                    death, as soon as we enter into the world of spirits. Nay, the Church of Rome
                    does absolutely assert this; yea, makes it an article of faith.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">This refers to
                            the so-called ‘Doctrine of Particular Judgment’, which is not, strictly
                            speaking, ‘an article of faith’ in the Roman Catholic Church. It
                            affirms, as Wesley says, ‘that there are two judgments, a particular and
                            a general’. The first divides the dead into three groups: (1) those free
                            from all sin who are received forthwith into heaven (<hi rend="italic"
                                >mox in coelum recipi</hi>); (2) those in a state of grace who need
                            further purification; (3) those dying in mortal sin and impenitent who
                            go forthwith to hell (<hi rend="italic">mox in infernum
                            descendere</hi>), to be punished in proportion to their sin (<hi
                                rend="italic">poenis tamen disparibus puniendas</hi>). See the
                            decree of the Second Council of Lyons (1274) and the ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >de sorte defunctorum</hi>’ in the ‘Union Decree’ of Eugenius IV,
                            1439 (Heinrich Denzinger, <hi rend="italic">Enchiridion Symbolorum</hi>
                            [24th edn.], 1304-6). Wesley and his Protestant colleagues had collapsed
                            groups (2) and (3) and supposed that ‘Purgatory’ held out the promise of
                            salvation to souls dying in mortal sin and unrepentant; see Wesley’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Roman Catechism</hi> (abridged from Bishop John
                            Williams), <hi rend="italic">Qq.</hi> 20-24, where Bellarmine and Trent
                            are misread as if they taught a purgatorial hope for souls dying in
                            mortal sin. But see George Bull, <hi rend="italic">Some Important Points
                                of Primitive Christianity</hi> (1713), Vol. I, Sermon II, pp. 25-49:
                            ‘The soul of every man presently after death hath its proper place and
                            state allotted by God, of happiness or misery, according as the man hath
                            been good or bad in his past life.’ Cf. Wesley’s teachings on the
                            intermediate state in No. 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’, I.3 and
                        n.</p></note> And thus much we may allow: the moment a soul drops the body,
                    and stands naked before God, it cannot but know what its portion will be to all
                    eternity. It will have full in its view either everlasting joy or everlasting
                    torment, as it is no longer possible to be deceived in the judgment which we
                    pass upon ourselves. But the Scripture gives us no reason to believe that God
                    will then sit in judgment upon us. There is no passage in all the oracles of God
                    which affirms any such thing. That which has been frequently alleged for this
                    purpose seems rather to prove the contrary; namely, ‘It is appointed for men
                    once to die, and after this, the judgment.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Heb. 9:27.</p></note></hi> For in all
                    reason, the word ‘once’ is here to be applied to judgment as well as death. So
                    that the fair inference to be drawn from this very text is, not that there are
                    two judgments, a particular and a general, but that we are to be judged, as well
                    as to die, once only; not once immediately after death, and again after the
                    general resurrection, but then only <pb n="02:293"/>‘when the Son of Man shall
                    come in his glory, and all his holy angels with him’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:31.</p></note>
                    The imagination therefore of one judgment at death, and another at the end of
                    the world, can have no place with those who make the written Word of God the
                    whole and sole standard of their faith.</p>
                <p>2. The time then when we are to give this account is when the ‘great white throne
                    comes down from heaven, and he that sitteth thereon, from whose face the heavens
                    and the earth flee away, and there is found no place for them’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                            20:11.</p></note> It is then ‘the dead, small, and great,’ will ‘stand
                    before God; and the books’ will be ‘opened’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48"
                        n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 20:12.</p></note>—the book of
                    Scripture, to them who were entrusted therewith, the book of conscience to all
                    mankind. The ‘book of remembrance’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Mal. 3:16.</p></note> likewise (to use another
                    scriptural expression), which had been writing from the foundation of the
                        world,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            13:35, etc. ‘writing’ is the erratum in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Works</hi> (1771) for ‘written’ (Mal. 3:16) present in all the
                            other printed edns.</p></note> will then be laid open to the view of all
                    the children of men. Before all these, even the whole human race, before the
                    devil and his angels,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:41.</p></note> before an innumerable
                    company of holy angels,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:22.</p></note> and before God the Judge of
                        all;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                            18:25; Heb. 12:23.</p></note> thou wilt appear without any shelter or
                    covering, without any possibility of disguise, to give a particular account of
                    the manner wherein thou hast employed all thy Lord’s goods.</p>
                <p>3. The Judge of all will then inquire: ‘How didst thou employ thy <hi
                        rend="italic">soul</hi>? I entrusted thee with an immortal spirit, endowed
                    with various powers and faculties, with understanding, imagination, memory,
                    will, affections. I gave thee withal full and express directions how all these
                    were to be employed. Didst thou employ thy <hi rend="italic">understanding</hi>,
                    as far as it was capable, according to those directions, namely, in the
                    knowledge of thyself and me? My nature, my attributes? My works, whether of
                    creation, of providence, or of grace? In acquainting thyself with my Word? In
                    using every means to increase thy knowledge thereof? In meditating thereon day
                    and night?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Josh. 1:8.</p></note> Didst thou employ thy <hi rend="italic"
                        >memory</hi> according to my will? In treasuring up whatever knowledge thou
                    hadst acquired which might conduce to my glory, to thy own salvation, or the
                    advantage of others? Didst thou store <pb n="02:294"/>up therein, not things of
                    no value, but whatever experience thou hadst learned from my Word; and whatever
                    experience thou hadst gained of my wisdom, truth, power, and mercy? Was thy <hi
                        rend="italic">imagination</hi> employed, not in painting vain images, much
                    less such as nourished foolish and hurtful desires,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:9.</p></note> but in
                    representing to thee whatever would profit thy soul, and awaken thy pursuit of
                    wisdom and holiness? Didst thou follow my directions with regard to thy <hi
                        rend="italic">will</hi>? Was it wholly given up to me? Was it swallowed up
                    in mine, so as never to oppose, but always run parallel with it? Were thy <hi
                        rend="italic">affections</hi> placed and regulated in such a manner as I
                    appointed in my Word? Didst thou give me thy heart? Didst thou not love the
                    world, neither the things of the world?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 2:15.</p></note> Was I the object of
                    thy love? Was all thy desire unto me, and unto the remembrance of my name? Was I
                    the joy of thy heart, the delight of thy soul, the chief among ten
                        thousand?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p rend="footnote text">S.
                            of S. 5:10.</p></note> Didst thou sorrow for nothing but what grieved my
                    spirit? Didst thou fear and hate nothing but sin? Did the whole stream of thy
                    affections flow back to the ocean from whence they came? Were thy <hi
                        rend="italic">thoughts</hi> employed according to my will? Not in ranging to
                    the ends of the earth, not on folly, or sin; but on “whatsoever things were
                    pure, whatsoever things were holy”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:8.</p></note> on whatsoever was
                    conducive to my “glory”, and to “peace and goodwill among men”?’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            2:14.</p></note></p>
                <p>4. Thy Lord will then inquire, ‘How didst thou employ the <hi rend="italic"
                        >body</hi> wherewith I entrusted thee? I gave thee a <hi rend="italic"
                        >tongue</hi> to praise me therewith. Didst thou use it to the end for which
                    it was given? Didst thou employ it, not in evil-speaking or idle-speaking, not
                    in uncharitable or unprofitable conversation; but in such as was good, as was
                    necessary or useful, either to thyself or others? Such as always tended,
                    directly or indirectly, to “minister grace to the hearers”?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:29.</p></note> I gave
                    thee, together with thy other senses, those grand avenues of knowledge, <hi
                        rend="italic">sight</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">hearing</hi>. Were these
                    employed to those excellent purposes for which they were bestowed upon thee? In
                    bringing thee in more and more instruction in righteousness<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 3:16.</p></note> and
                    true holiness? I gave thee hands and feet and various <hi rend="italic"
                        >members</hi> wherewith to perform the works which were prepared for thee.
                    Were they employed, not in doing “the will of the flesh”,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 1:13.</p></note> of
                    thy evil nature, or “the will of the <pb n="02:295"/>mind”,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic"
                                >ibid.</hi></p></note> the things to which thy reason or fancy led
                    thee, but “the will of him that sent”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 6:38.</p></note> thee into the world, merely
                    to work out thy own salvation?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:12.</p></note> Didst thou present all
                    thy members, not to sin, as instruments of unrighteousness, but to me alone,
                    through the Son of my love, “as instruments of righteousness”?’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        6:13.</p></note></p>
                <p>5. The Lord of all will next inquire, ‘How didst thou employ the <hi
                        rend="italic">worldly goods</hi> which I lodged in thy hands? Didst thou use
                    thy food, not so as to seek or place thy happiness therein, but so as to
                    preserve thy body in health, in strength and vigour, a fit instrument for the
                    soul? Didst thou use apparel, not to nourish pride or vanity, much less to tempt
                    others to sin, but conveniently and decently to defend thyself from the injuries
                    of the weather? Didst thou prepare and use thy house and all other conveniences
                    with a single eye to my glory? In every point seeking not thy own honour, but
                    mine; studying to please, not thyself, but me? Once more: in what manner didst
                    thou employ that comprehensive talent, <hi rend="italic">money</hi>? Not in
                    gratifying the desire of the flesh, the desire of the eye, or the pride of
                        life?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            2:16.</p></note> Not squandering it away in vain expenses, the same as
                    throwing it into the sea? Not hoarding it up to leave behind thee, the same as
                    burying it in the earth? But first supplying thy own reasonable wants, together
                    with those of thy family; then restoring the remainder to me, through the poor,
                    whom I had appointed to receive it; looking upon thyself as only one of that
                    number of poor whose wants were to be supplied out of that part of my substance
                    which I had placed in thy hands for this purpose; leaving thee the right of
                    being supplied first, and the blessedness of giving rather than receiving?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">See Acts 20:35. A
                            crucial clarification of the rule in No. 50, ‘The Use of Money’,
                            III.1-2: ‘<hi rend="italic">Give</hi> all you can.’ Our stewardship of
                            wealth is <hi rend="italic">to</hi> God, ‘<hi rend="italic">through the
                                poor</hi>, whom [God has] appointed to receive it’. Charity is an
                            expression of benevolence but, more, it is a specification of the
                            Christian’s accountability to God.</p></note> Wast thou accordingly a
                    general benefactor to mankind? Feeding the hungry, clothing the naked,
                    comforting the sick, assisting the stranger, relieving the afflicted according
                    to their various necessities?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 25:35-36.</p></note> Wast thou eyes to
                    the blind, and feet to the lame?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Job 29:15.</p></note> A father to the
                    fatherless, and an husband to the widow?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 68:5.</p></note> And didst thou labour
                    to improve all outward works of mercy, as means of saving souls from
                        death?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Jas. 5:20.</p></note></p>
                <p><pb n="02:296"/>6. Thy Lord will farther inquire: ‘Hast thou been a wise and
                    faithful steward with regard to the talents of a mixed nature which I lent thee?
                    Didst thou employ thy health and strength, not in folly or sin, not in the
                    pleasures which perished in the using, “not in making provision for the flesh,
                    to fulfil the desires thereof”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:14.</p></note> but in a vigorous pursuit of
                    that better part which none could take away from thee?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 10:42.</p></note>
                    Didst thou employ whatever was pleasing in thy person or address, whatever
                    advantages thou hadst by education, whatever share of learning, whatever
                    knowledge of things or men was committed thee, for the promoting of virtue in
                    the world, for the enlargement of my kingdom? Didst thou employ whatever share
                    of power thou hadst, whatever influence over others, by the love or esteem of
                    thee which they had conceived, for the increase of their wisdom and holiness?
                    Didst thou employ that inestimable talent of time with wariness and
                    circumspection, as duly weighing the value of every moment, and knowing that all
                    were numbered in eternity? Above all, wast thou a good steward of my grace,
                    preventing, accompanying, and following thee? Didst thou duty observe and
                    carefully improve all the influences of my Spirit? Every good desire? Every
                    measure of light? All his sharp or gentle reproofs? How didst thou profit by
                    “the spirit of bondage and fear” which was previous to “the Spirit of
                        adoption”?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 8:15.</p></note> And when thou wast made a partaker of this
                    Spirit, “crying in thy heart, Abba, Father”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76"
                        n="76"><p rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> didst
                    thou stand fast in the glorious liberty wherewith I made thee free? Didst thou
                    from thenceforth present thy soul and body, all thy thoughts, thy words, and
                    actions, in one flame of love, as an holy sacrifice, glorifying me with thy body
                    and thy spirit?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 1 Cor. 6:20.</p></note> Then “well done, good and faithful servant!
                    […] Enter thou into the joy of thy Lord!”’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78"
                        n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:21, 23.</p></note> And what will
                    remain, either to the faithful or unfaithful steward? Nothing but the execution
                    of that sentence which has been passed by the righteous Judge; fixing thee in a
                    state which admits of no change, through everlasting ages. It remains only that
                    thou be rewarded to all eternity according to thy works.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <p>IV. 1. From these plain considerations we may learn, first, how important is this
                    short, uncertain day of life! How precious, above all utterance, above all
                    conception, is every portion of it! </p>
                <pb n="02:297"/>
                <lg>
                    <l>The least of these a serious care demands;</l>
                    <l>For though they are little, they are golden sands!</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                            Gambold, ‘Upon Listening to the Vibrations of a Clock’, ll. 5-6, in his
                                <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1789), p. 266. Wesley had published
                            this in his <hi rend="italic">Moral and Sacred Poems</hi> (1744),
                            III.195. See also Wesley’s letter to Samuel Furly, Nov. 10, 1756. Though
                            Wesley and Gambold had long since parted company, Wesley is still
                            prepared to quote his quondam friend.</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p>How deeply does it concern every child of man to let none of these run to waste;
                    but to improve them all to the noblest purposes as long as the breath of God is
                    in his nostrils!</p>
                <p>2. We learn from hence, secondly, that there is no employment of our time, no
                    action or conversation, that is purely <hi rend="italic">indifferent</hi>. All
                    is good or bad, because all our time, as everything we have, is<hi rend="italic"
                        > not our own</hi>. All these are, as our Lord speaks, τὰ ἀλλότρια,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 16:12; cf.
                            above, I.1.</p></note> the property of another—of God, our Creator. Now
                    these either are or are not employed according to his will. If they are so
                    employed, all is good; if they are not, all is evil. Again: it is his will that
                    we should continually grow in grace and in the living knowledge of our Lord
                    Jesus Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See 2 Pet. 3:18.</p></note> Consequently every thought, word, and work
                    whereby this knowledge is increased, whereby we grow in grace, is good; and
                    every one whereby this knowledge is not increased is truly and properly
                    evil.</p>
                <p>3. We learn from hence, thirdly, that there are no works of supererogation,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Art. XIV,
                            which rejects all such ‘voluntary works besides, over and above, God’s
                            commandments’. These may not be claimed ‘without arrogance and impiety’.
                            In the Roman perspective, they are virtuous acts surpassing what is
                            required by moral <hi rend="italic">duty</hi> or <hi rend="italic"
                                >legal</hi> obligation. They are thus compared to other works, ‘not
                            as good works to evil ones but as better works to good ones’ (cf. <hi
                                rend="italic">The New Catholic Encyclopedia</hi>). And even Wesley
                            allows for this distinction in his doctrine of <hi rend="italic">facere
                                quod in se est</hi>.</p></note> that we can never do more than our
                    duty; seeing all we have is not our own, but God’s, all we can do is due to him.
                    We have not received this or that, or many things only, but everything from him:
                    therefore everything is his due. He that gives us all must needs have a right to
                    all. So that if we pay him anything less than all we cannot be ‘faithful
                    stewards’. And considering ‘every man shall receive his own reward, according to
                    his own labour,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Cor. 3:8.</p></note> we cannot be ‘wise stewards’ unless we labour to
                    the uttermost of our power; not leaving anything undone which we possibly can
                    do, but putting forth all our strength.</p>
                <p>4. Brethren, ‘Who is an understanding man and endued with knowledge among
                        you?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jas. 3:13.</p></note> Let him show the wisdom from above <pb n="02:298"
                    />by walking suitably to his character. If he so account of himself as a steward
                    of the manifold gifts of God, let him see that all his thoughts, and words, and
                    works be agreeable to the post God has assigned him. It is no small thing to lay
                    out for God all which you have received from God. It requires all your wisdom,
                    all your resolution, all your patience and constancy; far more than ever you had
                    by nature, but not more than you may have by grace. For his grace is sufficient
                    for you,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Cor. 12:9.</p></note> and ‘all things’, you know, ‘are possible to him
                    that believeth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Mark 9:23.</p></note> By faith, then, ‘put on the Lord Jesus
                        Christ;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 13:14.</p></note> ‘put on the whole armour of God,’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        6:11.</p></note> and you shall be enabled to glorify him in all your words
                    and works, yea, to bring every thought into captivity to the obedience of
                        Christ.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            2 Cor. 10:5.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <p>Edinburgh</p>
            <p>May 14, 1768</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
