<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 40: Christian Perfection</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-27</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon040</idno>                
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 40: Christian Perfection</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="97" to="122"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:097"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>If, for Wesley, salvation was the total restoration of the deformed image of God
                    in us, and if its fullness was the recovery of our negative power not to sin and
                    our positive power to love God supremely, this denotes that furthest reach of
                    grace and its triumphs in this life that Wesley chose to call ‘Christian
                    Perfection’. Just as justification and regeneration are thresholds for the
                    Christian life in earnest (‘what God does <hi rend="italic">for</hi> us’), so
                    also sanctification is ‘what God does <hi rend="italic">in</hi> us’, to mature
                    and fulfil the human potential according to his primal design. Few Christians
                    had ever denied some such prospect, <hi rend="italic">in statu gloriae</hi>;
                    few, in the West at least, had ever envisioned it as a realistic possibility <hi
                        rend="italic">in this life</hi>. Those few were obscure exceptions like
                    Robert Gell and Thomas Drayton—or William Law in a very different sense. Thus,
                    Wesley’s encouragement to his people to ‘go on to perfection’ and to ‘<hi
                        rend="italic">expect</hi> to be made perfect in love in this life’ aroused
                    lively fears that this would foster more of the self-righteous perfection<hi
                        rend="italic">ism</hi>, already made objectionable by earlier pietists.</p>
                <p>Obviously, this fear was in the background of an unofficial hearing granted
                    Wesley by Bishop Edmund Gibson at Whitehall in the latter end of the year 1740
                    (cf. Wesley’s version of the hearing in his <hi rend="italic">Plain Account of
                        Christian Perfection as believed and taught by the Rev. Mr. John Wesley,
                        from the year 1725 to the year 1765</hi>, §72; note its omission from the
                    Journal—and other discrepancies between the historical data in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Plain Account…</hi> and other sources). The bishop felt
                    entitled to a direct account of Wesley’s teaching since the Methodist movement
                    was headquartered in his diocese, even if not within his jurisdiction. Wesley’s
                    response was candid: ‘I told him, without any disguise or reserve [‘what I meant
                    by perfection’]. When I ceased speaking, he said, “Mr. Wesley, if this be all
                    you mean, publish it to all the world. If anyone then can confute what you say,
                    he may have free leave.” I answered, “My Lord, I will,” and accordingly wrote
                    and published the sermon on <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>.’ The
                    sermon’s title page indicates that it had been ‘preached by John Wesley, M.A.,
                    Fellow of Lincoln College, Oxford’ in 1741 (or earlier). There is, however, no
                        <pb n="02:098"/>other record of the place or occasion of its being preached
                    and no other record of Wesley’s use of Phil. 3:12, except as the motto of <hi
                        rend="italic">The Character of a Methodist</hi>, which Wesley dates (in <hi
                        rend="italic">A Plain Account…</hi>, §10) as in 1739; the extant first
                    edition is dated 1742. This 1741 sermon is the one that Wesley chooses to place
                    here, out of sequence but with a clear logic, as the crown of <hi rend="italic"
                        >SOSO</hi>, III (1750).</p>
                <p>Wesley’s doctrinal position on this point had, of course, been staked out long
                    before, in ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’ (1733), in which he had described the
                    goal of Christian living as ‘the being so “renewed in the image of our mind” as
                    to be “perfect as our Father in heaven is perfect”’. Thereafter, he stoutly
                    maintained that he had never wavered from that first baseline nor ever had
                    encountered serious difficulty in harmonizing ‘Christian perfection’ with his
                    later emphases on ‘faith alone’ and ‘assurance’. In <hi rend="italic">A Plain
                        Account…</hi> he recalls that ‘the first tract I ever wrote expressly on
                    [perfection]’ was <hi rend="italic">The Character of a Methodist</hi>; in it,
                    the label ‘Methodist’ is used provocatively as the idealized equivalent of
                    ‘perfect Christian’; the paradigm for both is taken from Clement of Alexandria’s
                    description of the perfect Christian in his <hi rend="italic">Stromateis</hi>,
                    VII.</p>
                <p>In 1741 (as Wesley continues, in <hi rend="italic">A Plain Account…</hi>, §13),
                    he and his brother published ‘a second volume of hymns’, in the preface of which
                    John came as close as he ever would to an unnuanced claim for sinless
                    perfection—‘freedom from <hi rend="italic">all</hi> self-will and even
                    “wandering thoughts”’. It was so close in fact that soon afterwards he felt
                    obliged to qualify such a claim. Even so, the critical reaction was less against
                    his particular formulations than the bare idea itself—<hi rend="italic">‘there
                        is no perfection on earth!’</hi> Wesley found this all the more
                    disconcerting since he was confident that he and his brother ‘were clear on
                    justification by faith, and careful to ascribe the <hi rend="italic">whole</hi>
                    of salvation to the mere grace of God’ (§11).</p>
                <p>Protestants, convinced of the <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi>—and
                    used to translating <hi rend="italic">perfectio</hi> as some sort of perfected
                    perfection—were bound to see in the Wesleyan doctrine, despite all its formal
                    disclaimers, a bald advertisement of spiritual pride and, implicitly,
                    works-righteousness. Even the Methodists, working from their own unexamined
                    Latin traditions of forensic righteousness, tended to interpret ‘perfection’ in
                    terms of a spiritual elitism—and so misunderstood Wesley and the early Eastern
                    traditions of τελειότης as a never ending aspiration for all of love’s fullness
                    (perfecting perfection). Thus, ‘Christian Perfection’ came to be the most
                    distinctive and also the most widely misunderstood of all Wesley’s doctrines. He
                    continued to teach it, however, in season and out, <pb n="02:099"/>as the
                    farthest horizon of his vision of Christian existence, an idea with radical
                    implications for personal ethics and for social transformation as well. First
                    and last, it is his doctrine of grace carried to its climax—‘grace abounding’.
                    It is, also, a doctrine of ‘double justification’ by God’s pardoning and
                    reconciling grace; the ‘relative change’ in No. 43, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, I.4, and also the ‘real change’ (<hi
                        rend="italic">ibid.</hi>) which involves the believer in an actual and
                    lively participation in God’s own loving business in creation.</p>
                <p>The text here is based on the first edition of 1741, collated against the six
                    other editions issued during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma illustrating its
                    publishing history and a list of variant reading, see Appendix, Vol. 4; see also
                        <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 53.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>Christian Perfection</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Philippians 3:12</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Not as though I had already attained, either were already
                        perfect.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. There is scarce any expression in Holy Writ which has given more offence
                    than this. The word ‘perfect’ is what many cannot bear. The very sound of it is
                    an abomination to them. And whosoever ‘preaches perfection’ (as the phrase
                        is),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text">E.g.,
                            Robert Gell in his <hi rend="italic">Essay Towards the Amendment of the
                                Last English Translation of the Bible</hi> (1659), where his Sermon
                            20 is entitled, ‘Some Saints Without Sin for a Season’. On p. 797, Gell
                            cites Dr. Thomas Drayton and Mr. William Parker as having ‘preached
                            perfection’ and as having defended it in <hi rend="italic">A
                                Revindication of the Possibility of a Total Mortification of Sin in
                                this Life; and of the Saints’ Perfect Obedience to the Law of God,
                                to be the Orthodox Protestant Doctrine</hi> (1658). On pp. 797-804
                            Gell sets out a catena of Scripture texts that ‘<hi rend="italic"
                                >prove</hi> a possibility of ἀναμαρτησία—the having of no
                            sin…according to the will of God’. This leads to his triumphant
                            conclusion, based on 2 Tim. 3:16-17, ‘That the man of God may be <hi
                                rend="italic">perfect</hi>, throughly furnished to every good
                            work…’.</p></note> i.e. asserts that it is attainable in this life, runs
                    great hazard of being accounted by them worse than a heathen man or a
                    publican.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And hence some have advised, wholly to lay aside the use of those
                    expressions, ‘because they have given so great offence’. But are they not found
                    in the oracles of God? If so, by what authority can any messenger of God lay
                    them aside, even though all men <pb n="02:100"/>should be offended?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            26:33.</p></note> We have not so learned Christ;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:20.</p></note>
                    neither may we thus give place to the devil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
                        n="4"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:27.</p></note> Whatsoever God hath
                    spoken, that will we speak, whether men will hear or whether they will
                        forbear:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Ezek. 2:5, 7; 3:11.</p></note> knowing that then alone can any minister
                    of Christ be ‘pure from the blood of all men’, when he hath ‘not shunned to
                    declare unto them all the counsel of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Acts 20:26-27.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. We may not therefore lay these expressions aside, seeing they are the
                    words of God, and not of man.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 1 Thess. 2:13.</p></note> But we may and ought
                    to explain the meaning of them, that those who are sincere of heart may not err
                    to the right hand or to the left from the mark of the prize of their high
                        calling.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 3:14.</p></note> And this is the more needful to be done because
                    in the verse already repeated the Apostle speaks of himself as not perfect:
                    ‘Not’, saith he, ‘as though I were already perfect.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Phil. 3:12.</p></note> And yet
                    immediately after, in the fifteenth verse, he speaks of himself, yea and many
                    others, as perfect. ‘Let us’, saith he, ‘as many as be perfect, be thus
                    minded.’</p>
                <p n="4">4. In order therefore to remove the difficulty arising from this seeming
                    contradiction, as well as to give light to them who are pressing forward to the
                    mark, and that those who are lame be not turned out of the way,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb.
                            12:13.</p></note> I shall endeavour to show,</p>
                <p>First, in what sense Christians are <hi rend="italic">not</hi>, and</p>
                <p>Secondly, in what sense they <hi rend="italic">are</hi>, perfect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. In the first place I shall endeavour to show in what sense Christians
                    are <hi rend="italic">not perfect</hi>. And both from experience and Scripture
                    it appears, first, that they are not perfect in knowledge: they are not <hi
                        rend="italic">so</hi> perfect in this life as to be free from ignorance.
                    They know, it may be, in common with other men, many things relating to the
                    present world; and they know, with regard to the world to come, the general
                    truths which God hath revealed. They know likewise (what ‘the natural man
                    receiveth not’, for these things ‘are spiritually discerned’)<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 2:14; cf. No. 10,
                            ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p></note> ‘what manner of
                    love it is wherewith the Father hath loved them, that they should be called the
                    sons of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 John 3:1.</p></note> They know ‘the mighty working of his
                        Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Eph. 1:19.</p></note> in their hearts, and the wisdom of his providence
                    directing all <pb n="02:101"/>their paths, and causing all things to work
                    together for their good.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:28.</p></note> Yea, they know in every
                    circumstance of life what the Lord requireth of them, and how ‘to keep a
                    conscience void of offence both toward God and toward man’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 24:16.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. But innumerable are the things which they know not. ‘Touching the
                    Almighty himself’, ‘they cannot search him out to perfection.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 37:23.</p></note> ‘Lo,
                    these are but a part of his ways; but the thunder of his power who can
                        understand?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Job 26:14.</p></note> They cannot understand, I will not say, how
                    ‘there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Son, and the Holy
                    Spirit, and these three are one;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:7; see below, No. 55, <hi
                                rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>.</p></note> or how the eternal Son
                    of God ‘took upon himself the form of a servant’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:7.</p></note> but
                    not any one attribute, not any one circumstance of the divine nature. Neither is
                    it for them ‘to know the times and seasons’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20"
                        n="20"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 1:7.</p></note> when God will work
                    his great works upon the earth; no, not even those which he hath in part
                    revealed, by his servants the prophets, since the world began. Much less do they
                    know when God, having ‘accomplished the number of his elect, will hasten his
                        kingdom’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Mark 13:20.</p></note> when ‘the heavens shall pass away with a
                    great noise, and the elements shall melt with fervent heat.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 3:10.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. They know not the reasons even of many of his present dispensations with
                    the sons of men; but are constrained to rest here, though ‘clouds and darkness
                    are round about him, righteousness and judgment are the habitation of his
                        seat.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            97:2 (BCP).</p></note> Yea, often with regard to his dealings with
                    themselves doth their Lord say unto them, ‘What I do, thou knowest not now; but
                    thou shalt know hereafter.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 13:7.</p></note> And how little do they know
                    of what is ever before them, of even the visible works of his hands! How ‘he
                    spreadeth the north over the empty place, and hangeth the earth upon
                        nothing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Job 26:7.</p></note> How he unites all the parts of this vast
                    machine by a secret chain which cannot be broken. So great is the ignorance, so
                    very little the knowledge of even the best of men.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">See below, No. 69, ‘The
                            Imperfection of Human Knowledge’.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. No one then is so perfect in this life as to be free from ignorance.
                    Nor, secondly, from mistake, which indeed is almost an unavoidable consequence
                    of it; seeing those who ‘know but in <pb n="02:102"/>part’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 13:9,
                        12.</p></note> are ever liable to err touching the things which they know
                    not. ’Tis true the children of God do not mistake as to the things essential to
                    salvation. They do not ‘put darkness for light, or light for darkness’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            5:20.</p></note> neither ‘seek death in the error of their life’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 1:12. Cf.
                            No. 6, ‘The Righteousness of Faith’, §2 and n.</p></note> For they are
                    ‘taught of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >John 6:45; 1 Thess. 4:9.</p></note> and the way which he teaches them,
                    the way of holiness, is so plain that ‘the wayfaring man, though a fool, need
                    not err therein.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 35:8.</p></note> But in things unessential
                    to salvation they do err, and that frequently. The best and wisest of men are
                    frequently mistaken even with regard to facts; believing those things not to
                    have been which really were, or those to have been done which were not. Or
                    suppose they are not mistaken as to the fact itself, they may be with regard to
                    its circumstances; believing them, or many of them, to have been quite different
                    from what in truth they were. And hence cannot but arise many farther mistakes.
                    Hence they may believe either past or present actions which were or are evil to
                    be good; and such as were or are good to be evil. Hence also they may judge not
                    according to truth with regard to the characters of men; and that not only by
                    supposing good men to be better, or wicked men to be worse, than they are, but
                    by believing them to have been or to be good men who were or are very wicked; or
                    perhaps those to have been or to be wicked men who were or are holy and
                    unreprovable.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Nay, with regard to the Holy Scriptures themselves, as careful as they
                    are to avoid it, the best of men are liable to mistake, and do mistake day by
                    day; especially with respect to those parts thereof which less immediately
                    relate to practice. Hence even the children of God are not agreed as to the
                    interpretation of many places in Holy Writ; nor is their difference of opinion
                    any proof that they are not the children of God on either side. But it is a
                    proof that we are no more to expect any living man to be <hi rend="italic"
                        >infallible</hi> than to be <hi rend="italic">omniscient</hi>.</p>
                <p n="6">6. If it be objected to what has been observed under this and the preceding
                    head that St. John speaking to his brethren in the faith says, ‘Ye have an
                    unction from the Holy One, and know all things,’<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">1 John 2:20.</p></note></hi>
                    the answer is plain—‘Ye know all things that are needful <pb n="02:103"/>for
                    your soul’s health.’ That the Apostle never designed to extend this farther,
                    that he could not speak it in an absolute sense, is clear first from hence: that
                    otherwise he would describe the disciple as ‘above his Master’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        10:24.</p></note> seeing Christ himself, as man, knew not all things. ‘Of
                    that hour’, saith he, ‘knoweth no man, no, not the Son, but the Father
                        only.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 24:36.</p></note> It is clear, secondly, from the Apostle’s own
                    words that follow: ‘These things have I written unto you concerning them that
                    deceive you,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 John 2:26.</p></note> as well as from his frequently repeated
                    caution, ‘Let no man deceive you,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:6; 1 John 3:7.</p></note> which had been
                    altogether needless had not those very persons who had that unction from the
                    Holy One<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            2:20.</p></note> been liable not to ignorance only but to mistake
                    also.</p>
                <p n="7">7. Even Christians therefore are not <hi rend="italic">so</hi> perfect as
                    to be free either from ignorance or error. We may, thirdly, add: nor from
                    infirmities. Only let us take care to understand this word aright. Let us not
                    give that soft title to known sins, as the manner of some is. So, one man tells
                    us, ‘Every man has his infirmity, and mine is drunkenness.’ Another has the
                    infirmity of uncleanness; another of taking God’s holy name in vain; and yet
                    another has the infirmity of calling his brother, ‘Thou fool ,’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        5:22.</p></note> or returning ‘railing for railing’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 3:9.</p></note> It is
                    plain that all you who thus speak, if ye repent not, shall with your infirmities
                    go quick into hell.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Ps. 55:15 (AV).</p></note> But I mean hereby
                    not only those which are properly termed ‘bodily infirmities’, but all those
                    inward or outward imperfections which are not of a moral nature. Such are
                    weakness or slowness of understanding, dullness or confusedness of apprehension,
                    incoherency of thought, irregular quickness or heaviness of imagination. Such
                    (to mention no more of this kind) is the want of a ready or of a retentive
                    memory. Such in another kind are those which are commonly in some measure
                    consequent upon these: namely slowness of speech, impropriety of language,
                    ungracefulness of pronunciation—to which one might add a thousand nameless
                    defects either in conversation or behaviour. These are the infirmities which are
                    found in the best of men in a larger or smaller proportion. And from these none
                    can hope to be perfectly freed till the spirit returns to God that gave it.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">See Eccles.
                            12:7.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8"><pb n="02:104"/>8. Nor can we expect till then to be wholly free from
                    temptation. Such perfection belongeth not to this life. It is true, there are
                    those who, being given up to work all uncleanness with greediness,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        4:19.</p></note> scarce perceive the temptations which they resist not, and
                    so seem to be without temptation. There are also many whom the wise enemy of
                    souls, seeing [them] to be fast asleep in the dead form of godliness, will not
                    tempt to gross sin, lest they should awake before they drop into everlasting
                        burnings.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Isa. 33:14.</p></note> I know there are also children of God who, being
                    now ‘justified freely’, having found ‘redemption in the blood of Christ’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            3:24.</p></note> for the present feel no temptation. God hath said to
                    their enemies, ‘Touch not mine anointed, and do my children no harm’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Chron.
                            16:22; Ps. 105:15.</p></note> And for this season, it may be for weeks
                    or months, he causeth them to ‘ride on high places’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Deut. 32:13.</p></note> he
                    beareth them as on eagles’ wings,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Exod. 19:4.</p></note> above all the fiery
                    darts of the wicked one.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 6:16.</p></note> But this state will not last
                    always, as we may learn from that single consideration that the Son of God
                    himself, in the days of his flesh, was tempted even to the end of his life.
                    Therefore so let his servant expect to be; for ‘it is enough that he be as his
                        Master.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 10:25.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. Christian perfection therefore does not imply (as some men seem to have
                    imagined) an exemption either from ignorance or mistake, or infirmities or
                    temptations. Indeed, it is only another term for holiness. They are two names
                    for the same thing. Thus everyone that is perfect is holy, and everyone that is
                    holy is, in the Scripture sense, perfect. Yet we may, lastly, observe that
                    neither in this respect is there any absolute perfection on earth. There is no
                    ‘perfection of degrees’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For the notion that in the ladder of perfections
                            there is an unsurpassable top rung, cf. Thomas Drayton, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Proviso, or Condition of the Promises</hi> (1657),
                            where he distinguishes between the ‘manifold perfection’ attributed by
                            the Papists to their ‘saints’, the perfection of <hi rend="italic"
                                >parts</hi> (some partial perfection in this respect or that) and
                            ‘the <hi rend="italic">perfection of degrees</hi>, when holiness in a
                            full degree is attained by us…’ (p. 37). ‘This is threefold: the first
                            is of love to God above all and to our neighbour as ourselves…. The
                            second is…when the saints are wholly dead with [Christ] to sin. The
                            third is <hi rend="italic">perfectio patriae</hi>…with Christ after his
                            ascension and glorification…’ (p. 38). Wesley opts for a perfection of
                            love, to God and neighbour, and quietly ignores the other two. But note
                            that, on p. 46, Drayton affirms that ‘the work which God hath given us
                            to do must be perfected and finished <hi rend="italic">in this
                            life</hi>’. Cf. also No. 83, ‘On Patience’, §10; and Wesley’s letter to
                            William Dodd, Mar. 12, 1756.</p></note> as it is termed; none which does
                    not admit of a continual increase. So that how much soever any man hath
                    attained, or in how high a degree soever he is perfect, he hath <pb n="02:105"
                    />still need to ‘grow in grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 3:18.</p></note> and daily to advance in the
                    knowledge and love of God his Saviour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. In what sense then are Christians perfect? This is what I shall
                    endeavour, in the second place, to show. But it should be premised that there
                    are several stages in Christian life as well as in natural: some of the children
                    of God being but new-born babes, others having attained to more maturity. And
                    accordingly St. John, in his first Epistle,<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Chap. 2, ver. 12,
                        etc.</p></note></hi> applies himself severally to those he terms little
                    children, those he styles young men, and those whom he entitles fathers.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 13, <hi
                                rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, III.2 and n.</p></note> ‘I
                    write unto you, little children’, saith the Apostle, ‘because your sins are
                    forgiven you;’ because thus far ye have attained, being ‘justified freely’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:24.</p></note> you ‘have peace with God, through Jesus Christ’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        5:1.</p></note> ‘I write unto you, young men, because ye have overcome the
                    wicked one;’ or (as he afterwards adds) ‘because ye are strong, and the word of
                    God abideth in you.’ Ye have quenched the fiery darts of the wicked one,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        6:16.</p></note> the doubts and fears wherewith he disturbed your first
                    peace, and the witness of God that your sins are forgiven now ‘abideth in your
                        heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 John 2:14, 27.</p></note> ‘I write unto you, fathers, because ye have
                    known him that is from the beginning.’ Ye have known both the Father and the Son
                    and the Spirit of Christ in your inmost soul. Ye are ‘perfect men, being grown
                    up to the measure of the stature of the fullness of Christ’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:13.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. It is of these chiefly I speak in the latter part of this discourse; for
                    these only are properly Christians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Taken literally, this would mean that none but the
                            perfect are ‘proper Christians’. In 1750 and thereafter, Wesley altered
                            this to read, ‘these only are perfect Christians.’</p></note> But even
                    babes in Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Cor. 3:1.</p></note> are in such a sense perfect, or ‘born of
                        God’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:9; 4:7.</p></note> (an expression taken also in divers senses) as,
                    first, not to commit sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See No. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are
                            Born of God’.</p></note> If any doubt of this privilege of the sons of
                    God, the question is not to be decided by abstract reasonings, which may be
                    drawn out into an endless length, and leave the point just as it was before.
                    Neither is it to be determined by the experience of this or that particular
                    person. Many may suppose they do not commit sin when they do, but this <pb
                        n="02:106"/>proves nothing either way. ‘To the law and to the
                        testimony’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Isa. 8:20.</p></note> we appeal. ‘Let God be true, and every man a
                        liar.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            3:4.</p></note> By his Word will we abide, and that alone. Hereby we
                    ought to be judged.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Now the Word of God plainly declares that even those who are justified,
                    who are born again in the lowest sense, do not ‘continue in sin’; that they
                    cannot ‘live any longer therein’;<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"
                                ><p rend="endnote text">Rom. 6:1, 2.</p></note></hi> that they are
                    ‘planted together in the likeness of the death of Christ’;<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                5.</p></note></hi> that their ‘old man is crucified with him, the
                    body of sin being destroyed, so that thenceforth they do not serve sin’; that
                    ‘being dead with Christ, they are freed from sin’;<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver. 6, 7.</p></note></hi>
                    that they are ‘dead unto sin’, and ‘alive unto God’;<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver. 11.</p></note></hi> that
                    ‘sin hath not<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Altered from 1750 onwards to ‘no more’.</p></note> dominion over them’,
                    who are ‘not under the law, but under grace’; but that these, ‘being made free
                    from sin, are become the servants of righteousness’.<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver. 14, [15,]
                        18.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="4">4. The very least which can be implied in these words is that the persons
                    spoken of therein, namely all real Christians or believers in Christ, are made
                    free from outward sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For this crucial distinction between <hi
                                rend="italic">outward</hi> sin and all other, cf. No. 13, <hi
                                rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., III.1-9, and
                        n.</p></note> And the same freedom which St. Paul here expresses in such
                    variety of phrases St. Peter expresses in that one: ‘He that hath suffered in
                    the flesh hath ceased from sin; that he no longer should live…to the desires of
                    men, but to the will of God.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">1 Pet. 4:1-2.</p></note></hi> For this ‘ceasing
                    from sin’, if it be interpreted in the lowest sense, as regarding only the
                    outward behaviour, must denote the ceasing from the outward act, from any
                    outward transgression of the law.</p>
                <p n="5">5. But most express are the well-known words of St. John in the third
                    chapter of his first Epistle (verse eight, etc.): ‘He that committeth sin is of
                    the devil; for the devil sinneth from the beginning. For this purpose the Son of
                    God was manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil. Whosoever is
                    born of God doth not commit sin; for his seed remaineth in him, and he cannot
                    sin, because he is born of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 3:8-9.</p></note> And those in the fifth,
                    verse eighteen: ‘We know that whosoever is born of God sinneth <pb n="02:107"
                    />not. But he that is begotten of God keepeth himself, and that wicked one
                    toucheth him not.’</p>
                <p n="6">6. Indeed it is said this means only, he sinneth not <hi rend="italic"
                        >wilfully</hi>; or he doth not commit sin <hi rend="italic">habitually</hi>;
                    or, <hi rend="italic">not as other men do</hi>; or, <hi rend="italic">not as he
                        did before</hi>. But by whom is this said? By St. John? No.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">A flat negative
                            to comments like those of James Hervey and William Cudworth (see No. 18,
                            ‘The Marks of the New Birth’, I.5 and n.). But notice Wesley’s
                            qualifications of the absolute in Nos. 14, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.20, II.3-4; 18, ‘The Marks of the
                            New Birth’, I.4-5; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of
                            God’, II.2; 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, IV.1-3. The
                            irony here is that Wesley is moved to denounce qualifications of the
                            doctrine when made by others and then come up with some of his own as if
                            oblivious to the discrepancies involved in any such argument.</p></note>
                    There is no such word in the text, nor in the whole chapter, nor in all this
                    Epistle, nor in any part of his writings whatsoever. Why, then, the best way to
                    answer a bold<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >I.e., ‘impudent’; note Johnson’s definition of ‘bold’ as
                            ‘impudent’.</p></note> assertion is simply to deny it. And if any man
                    can prove it from the Word of God, let him bring forth his strong reasons.</p>
                <p n="7">7. And a sort of reason there is which has been frequently brought to
                    support these strange assertions, drawn from the examples recorded in the Word
                    of God: ‘What!’, say they, ‘did not Abraham himself commit sin, prevaricating
                    and denying his wife? Did not Moses commit sin when he provoked God “at the
                    waters of strife”?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ps. 106:32.</p></note> Nay, to produce one for all,
                    did not even David, “the man after God’s own heart”,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">Acts 13:22.</p></note> commit
                    sin in the matter of Uriah the Hittite, even murder and adultery?’ It is most
                    sure he did. All this is true. But what is it you would infer from hence? It may
                    be granted, first, that David, in the general course of his life, was one of the
                    holiest men among the Jews. And, secondly, that the holiest men among the Jews
                        <hi rend="italic">did sometimes commit sin</hi>. But if you would hence
                    infer that <hi rend="italic">all Christians do, and must commit sin, as long as
                        they live</hi>, this consequence we utterly deny. It will never follow from
                    those premises.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Those who argue thus seem never to have considered that declaration of
                    our Lord: ‘Verily I say unto you, among them that are born of women there hath
                    not risen a greater than John the Baptist. Notwithstanding, he that is least in
                    the kingdom of heaven is greater than he.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Matt. 11:11.</p></note></hi> I fear
                    indeed there are some who have imagined ‘the kingdom of heaven’ here to mean the
                    kingdom of <hi n="02:108"/> glory. As if the Son of God had just discovered to
                    us that the least glorified saint in heaven is greater than any man upon earth!
                    To mention this is sufficiently to refute it. There can therefore no doubt be
                    made but ‘the kingdom of heaven’ here (as in the following verse, where it is
                    said to be ‘taken by force’)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 11:12.</p></note> or, ‘the kingdom of
                    God’, as St. Luke expresses it, is that kingdom of God on earth whereunto all
                    true believers in Christ, all real Christians, belong. In these words then our
                    Lord declares two things. First, that before his coming in the flesh among all
                    the children of men, there had not been one greater than John the Baptist;
                    whence it evidently follows that neither Abraham, David, nor any Jew was greater
                    than John. Our Lord, secondly, declares that he which is least in the kingdom of
                    God (in that kingdom which he came to set up on earth, and which ‘the violent’
                    now began ‘to take by force’) is greater than he. The plain consequence is, the
                    least of these who have now Christ for their King is greater than Abraham or
                    David or any Jew ever was. None of them was ever greater than John. But the
                    least of these is greater than he.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The previous three sentences are found only in the
                            first separate edition of 1741 (p. 20) and the second of 1743 (p. 11).
                            The passage was omitted from the first collected edition of 1750 (and
                            henceforth), apparently because of a simple error of the compositor’s
                            eye slipping from one occurrence of ‘is greater than he’ to another five
                            lines lower. It seems highly unlikely that Wesley himself deliberately
                            omitted this logical extension of his argument.</p></note> Not ‘a
                    greater prophet’ (as some have interpreted the word), for this is palpably false
                    in fact, but greater in the grace of God and the knowledge of our Lord Jesus
                    Christ. Therefore we cannot measure the privileges of real Christians by those
                    formerly given to the Jews. ‘Their ministration’ (or dispensation) we allow ‘was
                    glorious’; but ours ‘exceeds in glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 3:8-9.</p></note> So that whosoever
                    would bring down the Christian dispensation to the Jewish standard, whosoever
                    gleans up the examples of weakness recorded in the law and the prophets, and
                    thence infers that they who have ‘put on Christ’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 3:27.</p></note> are
                    endued with no greater strength, doth ‘greatly err, neither knowing the
                    Scriptures nor the power of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 22:29.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘But are there not assertions in Scripture which prove the same thing,
                    if it cannot be inferred from those examples? Does not the Scripture say
                    expressly, ‘Even a just man sinneth seven <pb n="02:109"/>times a day”?’ I
                    answer, No. The Scripture says no such thing. There is no such text in all the
                    Bible. That which seems to be intended is the sixteenth verse of the
                    twenty-fourth chapter of the Proverbs, the words of which are these: ‘A just man
                    falleth seven times, and riseth up again.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75"
                        n="75"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. the Elizabethan ‘Homily or an Information
                            for Them That Take Offence at Certain Places in the Holy Scriptures’,
                            Pt. II, <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p. 335. See also No. 9, ‘The
                            Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’, I.7 and n.</p></note> But this is
                    quite another thing. For, first, the words ‘a day’ are not in the text. So that
                    if a just man falls seven times in his life it is as much as is affirmed here.
                    Secondly, here is no mention of ‘falling into sin’ at all: what is here
                    mentioned is ‘falling into temporal affliction’. This plainly appears from the
                    verse before, the words of which are these: ‘Lay not wait, O wicked man, against
                    the dwelling of the righteous; spoil not his resting place.’ It follows, ‘For a
                    just man falleth seven times, and riseth up again: but the wicked shall fall
                    into mischief.’ As if he had said, ‘God will deliver him out of his trouble. But
                    when thou fallest, there shall be none to deliver thee.’</p>
                <p n="10">10. But, however, in other places, continue the objectors, Solomon does
                    assert plainly, ‘There is no man that sinneth not;’<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">1 Kgs. 8:46; 2 Chron.
                                6:36.</p></note></hi> yea, ‘there is not a just man upon earth that
                    doth good, and sinneth not.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Eccles. 7:20.</p></note></hi> I answer: Without
                    doubt, thus it was in the days of Solomon. Yea, thus it was from Adam to Moses,
                    from Moses to Solomon, and from Solomon to Christ. There was <hi rend="italic"
                        >then</hi> no man that sinned not. Even from the day that sin entered into
                    the world there was not a just man upon earth that did good and sinned not, <hi
                        rend="italic">until</hi> the Son of God was manifested ‘to take away our
                        sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 3:5. It was from this way of expressing the effect of Christ’s
                            atonement that Cudworth developed his notion of guiltless perfection
                            (i.e., ‘from the guilt of all our sins, past and future’); cf. his <hi
                                rend="italic">Dialogue</hi>, p. 11. See also James Relly’s <hi
                                rend="italic">Union: Or a Treatise of the Consanguinity and Affinity
                                Between Christ and His Church</hi> (1759), p. 112, where the thesis
                            is that those ‘in Christ’ are, on the ground of the ‘consanguinity’ with
                            him, rendered ‘sinless’. Wesley recoiled from this as antinomian; cf.
                            his two <hi rend="italic">Dialogues Between an Antinomian and His
                                Friend</hi>. Cf. also No. 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of
                                Salvation</hi>, III.11.</p></note> It is unquestionably true that
                    ‘the heir, as long as he is a child, differeth nothing from a servant.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                        4:1.</p></note> And that ‘even so’ they (all the holy men of old who were
                    under the Jewish dispensation) ‘were’, during that infant state of the church,
                    ‘in bondage under the elements of the world. But when the fullness of the time
                    was <pb n="02:110"/>come, God sent forth his Son, made under the law, to redeem
                    them that were under the law, that they might receive the adoption of
                        sons;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 4:3-5.</p></note> that they might receive that ‘grace which is now
                    made manifest by the appearing of our Saviour, Jesus Christ, who hath abolished
                    death, and brought life and immortality to light through the gospel.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">2 Tim.
                                1:10.</p></note></hi> Now therefore they ‘are no more servants, but
                        sons’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 4:7.</p></note> So that, whatsoever was the case of those under the
                    law, we may safely affirm with St. John that since the gospel was given, ‘He
                    that is born of God sinneth not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 5:18.</p></note></p>
                <p n="11">11. It is of great importance to observe, and that more carefully than is
                    commonly done, the wide difference there is between the Jewish and the Christian
                    dispensation, and that ground of it which the same Apostle assigns in the
                    seventh chapter of his Gospel, verse thirty-eight, etc. After he had there
                    related those words of our blessed Lord, ‘He that believeth on me, as the
                    Scripture hath said, out of his belly shall flow rivers of living water,’ he
                    immediately subjoins, ‘This spake he of the Spirit,’ οὗ ἔμελλον λαμβάνειν οἱ
                    πιστεύοντες εἰς αὐτόν,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Thus <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>; modern editors read
                            πιστεύσαντες.</p></note> ‘which they who should believe on him were
                    afterwards to receive. For the Holy Ghost was not yet given, because that Jesus
                    was not yet glorified.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 7:38-39.</p></note> Now the Apostle cannot
                    mean here (as some have taught) that the miracle-working power of the Holy Ghost
                    was not yet given. For this was given: our Lord had given it to all his apostles
                    when he first sent them forth to preach the gospel. He then gave them ‘power
                    over unclean spirits to cast them out’, power to ‘heal the sick’, yea, to ‘raise
                    the dead’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            10:1, 8.</p></note> But the Holy Ghost was not yet given in his
                    sanctifying graces, as he was after Jesus was glorified. It was then when ‘he
                    ascended up on high, and led captivity captive’, that he ‘received those gifts
                    for men, yea, even for the rebellious, that the Lord God might dwell among
                        them.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 68:18.</p></note> And ‘when the day of Pentecost was fully
                        come’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            2:1.</p></note> then first it was that they who ‘waited for the promise
                    of the Father’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Acts 1:4.</p></note> were made more than conquerors over sin by the
                    Holy Ghost given unto them.</p>
                <p n="12"><pb n="02:111"/>12. That this great salvation from sin was not given till
                    Jesus was glorified St. Peter also plainly testifies, where speaking of his
                    ‘brethren in the flesh’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 4:2, 6.</p></note> as now ‘receiving the
                    end of their faith, the salvation of their souls’, he adds: ‘Of which salvation
                    the prophets have inquired and searched diligently, who prophesied of the grace
                    (i.e. the gracious dispensation) that should come unto you; searching what, or
                    what manner of time, the Spirit of Christ which was in them did signify, when it
                    testified beforehand the sufferings of Christ and the glory (the glorious
                    salvation) that should follow. Unto whom it was revealed that not unto
                    themselves, but unto us they did minister the things which are now reported unto
                    you by them that have preached the gospel unto you with the Holy Ghost sent down
                    from heaven’ (viz., at the day of Pentecost, and so unto all generations, into
                    the hearts of all true believers). On this ground, even ‘the grace which was
                    brought unto them by the revelation of Jesus Christ’, the Apostle might well
                    build that strong exhortation, ‘Wherefore, girding up the loins of your mind,
                    …as he which hath called you is holy, so be ye holy in all manner of
                        conversation.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">1 Pet. 1:9, 10, etc.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="13">13. Those who have duly considered these things must allow that the
                    privileges of Christians are in no wise to be measured by what the Old Testament
                    records concerning those who were under the Jewish dispensation, seeing the
                    fullness of times is now come, the Holy Ghost is now given, the great salvation
                    of God is brought unto men by the revelation of Jesus Christ. The kingdom of
                    heaven is now set up on earth; concerning which the Spirit of God declared of
                    old (so far is David from being the pattern or standard of Christian
                    perfection), ‘He that is feeble among them at that day, shall be as David; and
                    the house of David shall be as God, as the angel of the Lord before them.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Zech.
                                12:8.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="14">14. If therefore you would prove that the Apostle’s words, ‘He that is
                    born of God sinneth not,’ are not to be understood according to their plain,
                    natural, obvious meaning, it is from the New Testament you are to bring your
                    proofs; else you will fight as one that beateth the air.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 9:26.</p></note>
                    And the first of these which is usually brought is taken from the examples
                    recorded in the New <pb n="02:112"/> Testament. ‘The Apostles themselves (it is
                    said) committed sin; nay the greatest of them, Peter and Paul: St. Paul by his
                    sharp contention with Barnabas,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Acts 15:39. See also No. 19, ‘The Great Privilege
                            of those that are Born of God’, II.3-8.</p></note> and St. Peter by his
                    dissimulation at Antioch.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:11-14.</p></note> Well; suppose both
                    Peter and Paul did then commit sin. What is it you would infer from hence? That
                        <hi rend="italic">all the other apostles</hi> committed sin sometimes? There
                    is no shadow of proof in this. Or would you thence infer that <hi rend="italic"
                        >all the other Christians</hi> of the apostolic age committed sin? Worse and
                    worse. This is such an inference as one would imagine a man in his senses could
                    never have thought of. Or will you argue thus?—‘If two of the apostles did once
                    commit sin, then <hi rend="italic">all other Christians, in all ages</hi>, do,
                    and will commit sin as long as they live.’ Alas, my brother! a child of common
                    understanding would be ashamed of such reasoning as this. Least of all can you
                    with any colour of argument infer that any man <hi rend="italic">must</hi>
                    commit sin at all. No; God forbid we should thus speak. No necessity of sinning
                    was laid upon <hi rend="italic">them</hi>. The grace of God was surely
                    sufficient for them. And it <hi rend="italic">is</hi> sufficient for <hi
                        rend="italic">us</hi> at this day. With the temptation which fell on <hi
                        rend="italic">them</hi> that <hi rend="italic">was</hi> a way to escape, as
                    there <hi rend="italic">is</hi> to every soul of man in every temptation; so
                    that whosoever is tempted to any sin <hi rend="italic">need</hi> not yield; for
                    no man is tempted above that he is able to bear.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                    10:13.</p></note></p>
                <p n="15">15. ‘But St. Paul besought the Lord thrice, and yet he could not escape
                    from his temptation.’ Let us consider his own words literally translated: ‘There
                    was given to me a thorn, to the flesh,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">All edns. except that of 1787 retain this
                            literal translation of the dative τῇ as it stands in the Greek of 2 Cor.
                            12:7; in 1787 this was changed to ‘in the flesh’.</p></note> an angel or
                    messenger of Satan, to buffet me. Touching this I besought the Lord thrice, that
                    it (or he)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text">This
                            parenthetical phrase—there are no parentheses here in Wesley’s text—is
                            added to the text of 1750 and subsequent edns., suggesting that Wesley
                            had thought of ‘Satan’ as a likely referent in the ‘thorn’
                        metaphor.</p></note> might depart from me. And he said unto me, My grace is
                    sufficient for thee: for my strength is made perfect in weakness. Most gladly
                    therefore will I rather glory in these my weaknesses, that the strength of
                    Christ may rest upon me. Therefore I take pleasure in weaknesses…; for when I am
                    weak, then am I strong.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on 2 Cor.
                            12:7-10.</p></note></p>
                <p n="16">16. As this Scripture is one of the strongholds of the patrons of sin, it
                    may be proper to weigh it thoroughly. Let it be observed <pb n="02:113"/>then,
                    first, it does by no means appear that this thorn, whatsoever it was, occasioned
                    St. Paul to commit sin, much less laid him under any necessity of doing so.
                    Therefore from hence it can never be proved that any Christian <hi rend="italic"
                        >must</hi> commit sin. Secondly, the ancient Fathers inform us it was bodily
                    pain: ‘a violent headache’, saith Tertullian,<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi rend="italic">De Pudic</hi> [<hi
                                    rend="italic">itia</hi>, §13 (‘Of Purity’); cf. <hi
                                    rend="italic">Ancient Christian Writers</hi> (ed, J. Quasten <hi
                                    rend="italic">et al.</hi>), 28:88. What Tertullian actually said
                                is ‘<hi rend="italic">…per dolorem, ut aiunt, auriculae vel
                                    capitis</hi>’ (‘as they say, an earache or a headache’). Notice
                                Tertullian’s distinction between Paul’s ‘thorn’ and the fate of
                                blasphemers and incestuous persons who are ‘deservedly delivered
                                over completely into the possession of Satan himself and not just an
                                angel of his’. Chrysostom understood ‘the thorn’ as a metaphor for
                                all of Paul’s various indignities suffered at the hands of ‘public
                                executions’ (cf. <hi rend="italic">Letters to Olympias</hi>, 2, in
                                    <hi rend="italic">NPNF</hi>, I, IX.295). For Cyprian, see <hi
                                    rend="italic">Treatise</hi> IX.9, in <hi rend="italic">A Library
                                    of Fathers</hi> (1839), III.222-23].</p></note></hi> to which
                    both Chrysostom and St. Jerome agree. St. Cyprian expresses it a little more
                    generally, in those terms, ‘many and grievous torments of the flesh and of the
                        body’.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                    >‘<hi rend="italic">Carnis et corporis multa ac gravia
                                    tormenta</hi>’, <hi rend="italic">De Mortalitate</hi> [<hi
                                    rend="italic">Of Mortality</hi>. Wesley was using Dean Fell’s
                                famous Oxford edn. of 1682; cf. 1690 edn., p. 161; see also, Migne,
                                    <hi rend="italic">PL</hi>, IV:613].</p></note></hi> Thirdly, to
                    this exactly agree the Apostle’s own words, ‘A thorn to the flesh to smite,
                    beat, or buffet me…. My strength is made perfect in weakness’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 12:7,
                    9.</p></note>—which same word occurs no less than four times in these two verses
                        only.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">I.e.,
                            ἀσθενεία, which, with its cognates, appears four times in ver.
                        9-10.</p></note> But, fourthly, whatsoever it was, it could not be either
                    inward or outward sin. It could no more be inward stirrings than outward
                    expressions of pride, anger, or lust. This is manifest beyond all possible
                    exception from the words that immediately follow: ‘Most gladly will I glory in
                    these my weaknesses, that the strength of Christ rested upon me.’ What! Did he
                    glory in pride, in anger, in lust? Was it through these ‘weaknesses’ that the
                    strength of Christ rested upon him? He goes on: ‘Therefore I take pleasure in
                    weaknesses; for when I am weak, then am I strong;’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 12:9-10.</p></note>
                    i.e. when I am weak <hi rend="italic">in body</hi>, then am I strong <hi
                        rend="italic">in spirit</hi>. But will any man dare to say, When I am weak
                    by pride or lust, then am I strong in spirit? I call you all to record this day,
                    who find the strength of Christ resting upon you, can <hi rend="italic">you</hi>
                    glory in anger, or pride, or lust? Can <hi rend="italic">you</hi> take pleasure
                    in <hi rend="italic">these</hi> infirmities? Do <hi rend="italic">these</hi>
                    weaknesses make you strong? Would you not leap into hell, were it possible, to
                    escape them? Even by yourselves, then, judge whether the Apostle could <pb
                        n="02:114"/>glory and take pleasure in them! Let it be, lastly, observed,
                    that this thorn was given to St. Paul ‘above fourteen years’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 12:2.</p></note> before
                    he wrote this Epistle, which itself was wrote several years before he finished
                    his course. So that he had after this a long course to run, many battles to
                    fight, many victories to gain, and great increase to receive in all the gifts of
                    God and the knowledge of Jesus Christ. Therefore from any spiritual weakness (if
                    such it had been) which he <hi rend="italic">at that time</hi> felt, we could by
                    no means infer that he was never made strong, that Paul the aged, the father in
                    Christ, still laboured under the same weaknesses; that he was in no higher state
                    till the day of his death. From all which it appears that this instance of St.
                    Paul is quite foreign to the question, and does in no wise clash with the
                    assertion of St. John, ‘He that is born of God sinneth not.’</p>
                <p n="17">17. ‘But does not St. James directly contradict this? His words are, “In
                    many things we offend all.”<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Chap. 3, ver. 2.</p></note></hi> And is not <hi
                        rend="italic">offending</hi> the same as <hi rend="italic">committing
                        sin</hi>?’ In this place I allow it is. I allow <hi rend="italic">the
                        persons here spoken of</hi> did commit sin; yea, that they <hi rend="italic"
                        >all</hi> committed <hi rend="italic">many</hi> sins. But who are ‘the
                    persons here spoken of’? Why, those ‘many masters’ or ‘teachers’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas.
                        3:1.</p></note> whom God had not sent (probably the same ‘vain men’ who
                    taught that ‘faith without works’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 2:20.</p></note> which is so sharply
                    reproved in the preceding chapter); not the Apostle himself, nor any real
                    Christian. That in the word ‘we’ (used by a figure of speech common in all other
                    as well as the inspired writings) the Apostle could not possibly include himself
                    or any other true believer appears evidently, first, from the use of the same
                    word in the ninth verse: ‘Therewith (saith he) bless <hi rend="italic">we</hi>
                    God and therewith curse <hi rend="italic">we</hi> men. Out of the same mouth
                    proceedeth blessing and cursing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:9-10.</p></note> True; but not out of the
                    mouth of the Apostle, nor of anyone who is in Christ a new creature.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor.
                            5:17.</p></note> Secondly, from the verse immediately preceding the
                    text, and manifestly connected with it: ‘My brethren, be not many masters (or
                    teachers), knowing that <hi rend="italic">we</hi> shall receive the greater
                    condemnation: for in many things <hi rend="italic">we</hi> offend all.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        3:1-2.</p></note> ‘We’! Who? <pb n="02:115"/>Not the apostles, not true
                    believers; but they who know they should ‘receive the greater condemnation’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        3:1.</p></note> because of those many offences. But this could not be spoke
                    of the Apostle himself, or of any who trod in his steps, seeing ‘there is no
                    condemnation for them who walk not after the flesh, but after the Spirit.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:1.</p></note> Nay, thirdly, the very verse itself proves that ‘we
                    offend all’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Jas. 3:1.</p></note> cannot be spoken either of all men, or of all
                    Christians; for in it there immediately follows the mention of a man who
                    ‘offends not’, as the ‘we’ first mentioned did; from whom therefore he is
                    professedly contradistinguished, and pronounced ‘a perfect man’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107"><p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        3:2.</p></note></p>
                <p n="18">18. So clearly does St. James explain himself and fix the meaning of his
                    own words. Yet, lest anyone should still remain in doubt, St. John, writing many
                    years after St. James, puts the matter entirely out of dispute by the express
                    declarations above recited. But here a fresh difficulty may arise. How shall we
                    reconcile St. John with himself? In one place he declares, ‘Whosoever is born of
                    God doth not commit sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9.</p></note> And again, ‘We know that he
                    which is born of God sinneth not.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:18.</p></note> And yet in another he
                    saith, ‘If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is
                    not in us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            John 1:8.</p></note> And again, ‘If we say that we have not sinned we
                    make him a liar, and his word is not in us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111"
                        n="111"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:10.</p></note></p>
                <p n="19">19. As great a difficulty as this may at first appear, it vanishes away if
                    we observe, first, that the tenth verse fixes the sense of the eighth: ‘If we
                    say we have no sin’ in the former being explained by, ‘If we say we have not
                    sinned’ in the latter verse.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 1:8, 10.</p></note> Secondly, that the point
                    under present consideration is not whether we <hi rend="italic">have or have not
                        sinned heretofore</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 13:2.</p></note> and neither of these
                    verses asserts that we <hi rend="italic">do sin, or commit sin now</hi>.
                    Thirdly, that the ninth verse explains both the eighth and tenth: ‘If we confess
                    our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from
                    all unrighteousness.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 1:9.</p></note> As if he had said, ‘I have
                    before affirmed, “The blood of Jesus Christ cleanseth us from all sin.” But let
                    no man say, I need it not; I have no sin to be cleansed from. If we say <pb
                        n="02:116"/>“that we have no sin”, “that we have not sinned”, we deceive
                    ourselves, and make God a liar. But if we confess our sins, he is faithful and
                    just, not only to forgive our sins, but also to cleanse us from all
                    unrighteousness, that we may go and sin no more.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn115" n="115"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John
                    5:14.</p></note></p>
                <p n="20">20. St. John therefore is well consistent with himself, as well as with
                    the other holy writers; as will yet more evidently appear if we place all his
                    assertions touching this matter in one view. He declares, first, ‘The blood of
                    Jesus Christ cleanseth us from all sin.’ Secondly, ‘No man can say I have not
                    sinned, I have no sin to be cleansed from.’ Thirdly, ‘But God is ready both to
                    forgive our past sins and to save us from them for the time to come.’ Fourthly,
                    ‘These things I write unto you’, saith the Apostle, ‘that ye may not sin: but if
                    any man should sin’, or ‘have sinned’ (as the word might be rendered)<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116"><p rend="footnote text">A softening, in
                            1750, of the arbitrary dictum in the first two edns. which read, ‘as the
                            word should rather be rendered’; cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Notes</hi> on 1 John 1:10: ‘Yet still we are to retain, even to our
                            lives’ end, a deep sense of our past sins…. “If we say we have not
                            sinned, we make [God] a liar,” who saith, “All have sinned.”’</p></note>
                    he need not continue in sin, seeing ‘we have an advocate with the Father, Jesus
                    Christ the righteous.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 2:1.</p></note> Thus far all is clear.
                    But lest any doubt should remain in a point of so vast importance the Apostle
                    resumes this subject in the third chapter, and largely explains his own meaning.
                    ‘Little children’, saith he, ‘let no man deceive you’ (as though I had given any
                    encouragement to those that continue in sin); ‘he that doth righteousness is
                    righteous, even as he is righteous. He that committeth sin is of the devil; for
                    the devil sinneth from the beginning. For this purpose the Son of God was
                    manifested, that he might destroy the works of the devil. Whosoever is born of
                    God doth not commit sin; for his seed remaineth in him, and he cannot sin,
                    because he is born of God. In this the children of God are manifest, and the
                    children of the devil.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">[1 John 3,] ver. 7-10.</p></note></hi> Here the
                    point, which till then might possibly have admitted of some doubt in weak minds,
                    is purposely settled by the last of the inspired writers, and decided in the
                    clearest manner. In conformity therefore both to the doctrine of St. John, and
                    to the whole tenor of the New Testament, we fix this conclusion: ‘A Christian is
                    so far perfect as not to commit sin.’</p>
                <p n="21"><pb n="02:117"/>21. This is the glorious privilege of every Christian;
                    yea, though he be but ‘a babe in Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118"
                        n="118"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 3:1.</p></note> But it is only of
                    those who ‘are strong in the Lord’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:10.</p></note> and ‘have overcome the
                    wicked one’, or rather of those who ‘have known him that is from the
                        beginning’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 John 2:13, 14.</p></note> that it can be affirmed
                    they are in such a sense perfect as, secondly, to be freed from evil thoughts
                    and evil tempers. First, from evil or sinful thoughts. But here let it be
                    observed that thoughts concerning evil are not always evil thoughts; that a
                    thought concerning sin and a sinful thought are widely different. A man, for
                    instance, may think of a murder which another has committed, and yet this is no
                    evil or sinful thought. So our blessed Lord himself doubtless thought of or
                    understood the thing spoken by the devil when he said, ‘All this will I give
                    thee if thou wilt fall down and worship me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121"
                        n="121"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 4:9.</p></note> Yet had he no evil
                    or sinful thought, nor indeed was capable of having any. And even hence it
                    follows that neither have real Christians; for ‘everyone that is perfect is as
                    his master.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Luke 6:40 [not τέλειος but κατηρτισμένος
                                (i.e., ‘expert’ or ‘fully equipped’); cf. below, II.24; see also
                                Wesley’s own translation in <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, ‘every
                                (disciple) that is perfected shall be as his
                        master’].</p></note></hi> Therefore, if he was free from evil or sinful
                    thoughts, so are they likewise.</p>
                <p n="22">22. And indeed, whence should evil thoughts proceed in the servant who is
                    ‘as his master’? Out of the heart of man (if at all) proceed evil thoughts.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Mark
                                7:21.</p></note></hi> If therefore his heart be no longer evil, then
                    evil thoughts can no longer proceed out of it. If the tree were corrupt, so
                    would be the fruit. But the tree is good. The fruit therefore is good also.<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Matt.
                                12:33.</p></note></hi> Our Lord himself bearing witness: ‘Every good
                    tree bringeth forth good fruit. A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit, as a
                    corrupt tree cannot bring forth good fruit.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Matt. 7:17-18.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="23">23. The same happy privilege of real Christians St. Paul asserts from his
                    own experience: ‘The weapons of our warfare’, saith he, ‘are not carnal, but
                    mighty through God to the pulling down of strongholds; casting down
                    imaginations’ (or ‘reasonings’ rather, for so the word λογισμούς signifies: all
                    the reasonings of pride and unbelief against the declarations, promises, or
                    gifts of God) ‘and every high thing that exalteth itself against the knowledge
                    of <pb n="02:118"/>God; and bringing into captivity every thought to the
                    obedience of Christ.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">2 Cor. 10:[4,] 5, etc.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="24">24. And as Christians indeed are freed from evil thoughts, so are they,
                    secondly, from evil tempers. This is evident from the above-mentioned
                    declaration of our Lord himself: ‘The disciple is not above his master; but
                    everyone that is perfect shall be as his master.’ He had been delivering just
                    before some of the sublimest doctrines of Christianity, and some of the most
                    grievous to flesh and blood: ‘I say unto you, love your enemies, do good to them
                    which hate you: and unto him that smiteth thee on the one cheek, offer also the
                        other.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Luke 6:27, 29.</p></note> Now these he well knew the world would not
                    receive, and therefore immediately adds, ‘Can the blind lead the blind? Will
                    they not both fall into the ditch?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Luke 6:39.</p></note> As if he had said, ‘Do not
                    confer with flesh and blood<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Gal. 1:16.</p></note> touching these things,
                    with men void of spiritual discernment, the eyes of whose understanding God hath
                    not opened,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Eph. 1:18; 4:18.</p></note> lest they and you perish
                        together.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Job 34:15.</p></note> In the next verse he removes the two grand
                    objections with which these wise fools<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 1:22.</p></note> meet us at every
                    turn: ‘these things are too grievous to be borne,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn128" n="128"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 23:4.</p></note>
                    or, ‘they are too high to be attained,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129"
                        n="129"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 139:6 (AV).</p></note> saying, ‘The
                    disciple is not above his master.’ Therefore if I have suffered be content to
                    tread in my steps. And doubt ye not then but I will fulfil my word: ‘For
                    everyone that is perfect shall be as his master.’ But his Master was free from
                    all sinful tempers. So therefore is his disciple, even every real Christian.</p>
                <p n="25">25. Every one of these can say with St. Paul, ‘I am crucified with Christ:
                    nevertheless I live; yet not I, but Christ liveth in me’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn130" n="130"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:20.</p></note>—words
                    that manifestly describe a deliverance from inward as well as from outward sin.
                    This is expressed both negatively, ‘I live not’—my evil nature, the body of sin,
                    is destroyed—and positively, ‘Christ liveth in me’—and therefore all that is
                    holy, and just, and good. Indeed both these, ‘Christ liveth in me,’ and ‘I live
                    not,’ are inseparably connected; for ‘what communion hath light with darkness’
                    or ‘Christ with Belial?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:14-15.</p></note></p>
                <p n="26"><pb n="02:119"/>26. He therefore who liveth in true believers hath
                    ‘purified their hearts by faith’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 15:9.</p></note>, insomuch that ‘everyone
                    that hath Christ in him, the hope of glory’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133"
                        n="133"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 1:27.</p></note>, ‘purifieth
                    himself even as he is pure’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">1 John 3:3.</p></note></hi>. He is purified from
                    pride; for Christ was lowly of heart. He is pure from self-will or desire; for
                    Christ desired only to do the will of his Father, and to finish his work. And he
                    is pure from anger, in the common sense of the word; for Christ was meek and
                    gentle, patient and long-suffering. I say, ‘in the common sense of the word’;
                    for all anger is not evil. We read of our Lord himself that he once ‘looked
                    round with anger’.<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Mark 3:5.</p></note></hi> But with what kind of
                    anger? The next word shows, συλλυπούμενος, being <hi rend="italic">at the same
                        time</hi> ‘grieved for the hardness of their hearts’. So then he was <hi
                        rend="italic">angry at the sin</hi>, and in the same moment <hi
                        rend="italic">grieved for the sinners</hi>; angry or displeased <hi
                        rend="italic">at the offence</hi>, but sorry <hi rend="italic">for the
                        offenders</hi>. With anger, yea, hatred, he looked upon <hi rend="italic"
                        >the thing</hi>; with grief and love upon the <hi rend="italic"
                    >persons</hi>. Go thou that art perfect, and do likewise.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn134" n="134"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 10:37.</p></note>
                    ‘Be thus angry, and <hi rend="italic">thou</hi> sinnest not:’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn135" n="135"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:26.</p></note>
                    feeling a displacency<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136"><p
                            rend="footnote text">‘Displacency’ was a familiar eighteenth-century
                            antonym to ‘complacency’ and is defined in Johnson’s <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi> as ‘disgust’. But Johnson derives it from ‘the
                            Latin, <hi rend="italic">displicentia</hi>’, which throws light on the
                            fact that the first four edns. of Wesley’s text read ‘displicency’ here.
                            This was altered in 1771 and 1787 to ‘displacency’, and is cited thus as
                            an example in <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>.</p></note> at every offence
                    against God, but only love and tender compassion to the offender.</p>
                <p n="27">27. Thus doth Jesus ‘save his people from their sins’:<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn137" n="137"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 1:21.</p></note>
                    and not only from outward sins, but also from the sins of their hearts; from
                    evil thoughts and from evil tempers. ‘True’, say some, ‘we shall thus be saved
                    from our sins, but not till death; not in this world.’ But how are we to
                    reconcile this with the express words of St. John? ‘Herein is our love made
                    perfect, that we may have boldness in the day of judgment: because as he is, so
                    are we <hi rend="italic">in this world</hi>.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text">1 John 4:17.</p></note></hi> The
                    Apostle here beyond all contradiction speaks of himself and other living
                    Christians, of whom (as though he had foreseen this very evasion, and set
                    himself to overturn it from the <hi n="02:120"/> foundation) he flatly affirms
                    that not only at or after death but ‘in this world’ they are as their
                    Master.</p>
                <p n="28">28. Exactly agreeable to this are his words in the first chapter of this
                    Epistle: ‘God is light, and in him is no darkness at all. If we walk in the
                    light, as he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood
                    of Jesus Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin.’ And again, ‘If we confess
                    our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins, and to cleanse us from
                    all unrighteousness.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. [5,] 6, etc.</p></note></hi> Now it is
                    evident the Apostle here also speaks of a deliverance wrought ‘in this world’.
                    For he saith not, ‘the blood of Christ will cleanse’ (at the hour of death, or
                    in the day of judgment) but it ‘cleanseth (at the time present) us (living
                    Christians) from all sin.’ And it is equally evident that if <hi rend="italic"
                        >any sin</hi> remain we are not cleansed from <hi rend="italic">all
                    sin</hi>: if <hi rend="italic">any</hi> unrighteousness remain in the soul it is
                    not cleansed from <hi rend="italic">all</hi> unrighteousness. Neither let any
                    sinner against his own soul say that this relates to justification only, or the
                    cleansing us from the guilt of sin. First, because this is confounding together
                    what the Apostle clearly distinguishes, who mentions first, ‘to forgive us our
                    sins’, and then ‘to cleanse us from all unrighteousness’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn138" n="138"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:9.</p></note>
                    Secondly, because this is asserting justification by works in the strongest
                    sense possible. It is making all inward as well as outward holiness necessarily
                    previous to justification. For if the cleansing here spoken of is no other than
                    the cleansing us from the guilt of sin, then we are not cleansed from guilt;
                    i.e. are not justified, unless on condition of ‘walking in the light, as he is
                    in the light’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 John 1:7.</p></note> It remains, then, that Christians are saved
                    in this world from all sin, from all unrighteousness; that they are now in such
                    a sense perfect as not to commit sin, and to be freed from evil thoughts and
                    evil tempers.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See below, No. 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>,
                        II.2.</p></note></p>
                <p n="29">29. Thus hath the Lord fulfilled the things he spake by his holy prophets,
                    which have been since the world began:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:70.</p></note> by Moses in
                    particular, saying, ‘I will circumcise thine heart, and the heart of thy seed,
                    to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy soul;’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Deut.
                                30:6.</p></note></hi> by David, crying out, ‘Create in me a clean
                        <pb n="02:121"/>heart, and renew a right spirit within me;’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 51:10
                            (AV).</p></note> and most remarkably by Ezekiel, in those words: ‘Then
                    will I sprinkle clean water upon you, and ye shall be clean; from all <hi
                        rend="italic">your</hi> filthiness, and from <hi rend="italic">all</hi> your
                    idols will I cleanse you. A new heart also will I give you, and a new spirit
                    will I put within you, and cause you to walk in my statutes, and ye shall keep
                    my judgments, and do them…. Ye shall be my people, and I will be your God. I
                    will also save you from all your uncleannesses…. Thus saith the Lord your God,
                    In the day that I shall have cleansed you from all your iniquities…the heathen
                    shall know that I the Lord build the ruined places; …I the Lord have spoken it,
                    …and I will do it.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ezek. 36:25, etc.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="30">30. ‘Having therefore these promises, dearly beloved’, both in the law and
                    in the prophets, and having the prophetic word confirmed unto us in the gospel
                    by our blessed Lord and his apostles, ‘let us cleanse ourselves from all
                    filthiness of flesh and spirit, perfecting holiness in the fear of God.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        7:1.</p></note> ‘Let us fear lest’ so many promises ‘being made us of
                    entering into his rest’ (which he that hath entered into ‘is ceased from his own
                    works’) ‘any of us should come short of it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144"
                        n="144"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 4:1, 10.</p></note> ‘This one thing
                    let us do: forgetting those things which are behind, and reaching forth unto
                    those things which are before, let us press toward the mark for the prize of the
                    high calling of God in Christ Jesus;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:13-14.</p></note> crying unto him
                    day and night till we also are ‘delivered from the bondage of corruption into
                    the glorious liberty of the sons of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146"
                        n="146"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:21. This last division was a
                            conscious rejection of the idea behind the slogan, <hi rend="italic"
                                >simul justus et peccator</hi>. Cf. No. 46, ‘The Wilderness State’,
                            II.6-8. Thus Wesley comes yet again, in II.21-28, to the verge of a
                            doctrine of sinless perfection. Cf. also No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On
                                Sin in Believers</hi>, V.2 and n.</p></note></p>
                <pb n="02:122"/>
                <p style="text-align: center;">THE<lb/>PROMISE<lb/>OF<lb/>SANCTIFICATION</p>
                <!--Not sure if these instructions to center will work, but it's work a shot.-->
                <p style="text-align: center;>">Ezekiel 36:25, etc.</p>
                <p rend="Verse" style="text-align: center;">By the Reverend Mr. Charles Wesley.</p>
                <lg n="1">
                    <l>1. God of all power, and truth, and grace,</l>
                    <l>Which shall from age to age endure;</l>
                    <l>Whose word, when heaven and earth shall pass,</l>
                    <l>Remains, and stands for ever sure.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="2">
                    <l>2. Calmly to thee my soul looks up,</l>
                    <l>And waits thy promises to prove;</l>
                    <l>The object of my stedfast hope,</l>
                    <l>The seal of thine eternal love.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="3">
                    <l>3. That I thy mercy may proclaim,</l>
                    <l>That all mankind thy truth may see,</l>
                    <l>Hallow thy great and glorious name,</l>
                    <l>And perfect holiness in me.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="4">
                    <l>4. Chose from the world if now I stand,</l>
                    <l>Adorned in righteousness divine,</l>
                    <l>If brought unto the promised land</l>
                    <l>I justly call the Saviour mine;</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="5">
                    <l>5. Perform the work thou hast begun,</l>
                    <l>My inmost soul to thee convert:</l>
                    <l>Love me, for ever love thine own,</l>
                    <l>And sprinkle with thy blood my heart.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="6">
                    <l>6. Thy sanctifying Spirit pour</l>
                    <l>To quench my thirst, and wash me clean;</l>
                    <l>Now, Father, let the gracious shower</l>
                    <l>Descend, and make me pure from sin.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="7">
                    <l>7. Purge me from every sinful blot;</l>
                    <l>My idols all be cast aside:</l>
                    <l>Cleanse me from every evil thought,</l>
                    <l>From all the filth of self and pride.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="8">
                    <l>8. Give me a new, a perfect heart,</l>
                    <l>From doubt, and fear, and sorrow free;</l>
                    <l>The mind which was in Christ impart,</l>
                    <l>And let my spirit cleave to thee.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="9">
                    <l>9. O take this heart of stone away,</l>
                    <l>(Thy rule it doth not, cannot own)</l>
                    <l>In me no longer let it stay:</l>
                    <l>O take away this heart of stone.</l>
                </lg>
                <pb n="02:123"/>
                <lg n="10">
                    <l>10. The hatred of my carnal mind</l>
                    <l>Out of my flesh at once remove;</l>
                    <l>Give me a tender heart, resigned,</l>
                    <l>And pure, and filled with faith and love.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="11">
                    <l>11. Within me thy good Spirit place,</l>
                    <l>Spirit of health, and love and power;</l>
                    <l>Plant in me thy victorious grace,</l>
                    <l>And sin shall never enter more.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="12">
                    <l>12. Cause me to walk in Christ my way,</l>
                    <l>And I thy statutes shall fulfil;</l>
                    <l>In every point thy law obey.</l>
                    <l>And perfectly perform thy will.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="13">
                    <l>13. Hast thou not said, who canst not lie,</l>
                    <l>That I thy law shall keep and do?</l>
                    <l>Lord, I believe, though men deny:</l>
                    <l>They all are false; but thou art true.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="14">
                    <l>14. O that I now, from sin released,</l>
                    <l>Thy word might to the utmost prove!</l>
                    <l>Enter into the promised rest,</l>
                    <l>The Canaan of thy perfect love!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="15">
                    <l>15. There let me ever, ever dwell;</l>
                    <l>By thou my God, and I will be</l>
                    <l>Thy servant: O set to thy seal;</l>
                    <l>Give me eternal life in thee.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="16">
                    <l>16. From all remaining filth within</l>
                    <l>Let me in Thee salvation have:</l>
                    <l>From actual, and from inbred sin</l>
                    <l>My ransomed soul persist to save.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="17">
                    <l>17. Wash out my old orig’nal stain:</l>
                    <l>Tell me no more, It cannot be,</l>
                    <l>Demons or men! The Lamb was slain,</l>
                    <l>His blood was all poured out for me.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="18">
                    <l>18. Sprinkle it, Jesus, on my heart!</l>
                    <l>One drop of thy all-cleansing blood</l>
                    <l>Shall make my sinfulness depart,</l>
                    <l>And fill me with the life of God.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="19">
                    <l>19. Father, supply my every need:</l>
                    <l>Sustain the life thyself hast given;</l>
                    <l>Call for the corn, the living bread,</l>
                    <l>The manna that comes down from heaven.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="20">
                    <l>20. The gracious fruits of righteousness,</l>
                    <l>Thy blessings’ unexhausted store,</l>
                    <l>In me abundantly increase;</l>
                    <l>Nor let me ever hunger more.</l>
                </lg>
                <pb n="02:124"/>
                <lg n="21">
                    <l>21. Let me no more in deep complaint</l>
                    <l>‘My leanness, O my leanness!’ cry,</l>
                    <l>Alone consumed with pining want</l>
                    <l>Of all my Father’s children I!</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="22">
                    <l>22. The painful thirst, the fond desire</l>
                    <l>Thy joyous presence shall remove,</l>
                    <l>While my full soul doth still require</l>
                    <l>Thy whole eternity of love.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="23">
                    <l>23. Holy, and true, and righteous Lord,</l>
                    <l>I wait to prove thy perfect will:</l>
                    <l>Be mindful of thy gracious word,</l>
                    <l>And stamp me with thy Spirit’s seal.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="24">
                    <l>24. Thy faithful mercies let me find</l>
                    <l>In which thou causest me to trust;</l>
                    <l>Give me the meek and lowly mind,</l>
                    <l>And lay my spirit in the dust.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="25">
                    <l>25. Show me how foul my heart hath been,</l>
                    <l>When all renewed by grace I am;</l>
                    <l>When thou hast emptied me of sin,</l>
                    <l>Show me the fullness of my shame.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="26">
                    <l>26. Open my faith’s interior eye,</l>
                    <l>Display thy glory from above;</l>
                    <l>And all I am shall sink and die,</l>
                    <l>Lost in astonishment and love.</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="27">
                    <l>27. Confound, o’erpower me with thy grace!</l>
                    <l>I would be by myself abhorred,</l>
                    <l>(All might, all majesty, all praise,</l>
                    <l>All glory be to Christ my Lord!)</l>
                </lg>
                <lg n="28">
                    <l>28. Now let me gain perfection’s height!</l>
                    <l>Now let me into nothing fall!</l>
                    <l>Be less than nothing in thy sight,</l>
                    <l>And feel that Christ is all in all!</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147"><p rend="footnote text">This poem was
                            incorporated in the 1st edn. of 1741, omitted from the 2nd edn. of 1743
                            (which was compressed into 24 pages) and from the first two edns. of the
                            collected <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, which may possibly have
                            derived from the 1743 edn. It was restored by Wesley his <hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771), and also to the last edn. of <hi
                                rend="italic">SOSO</hi> (1787). It had already been reprinted <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), pp.
                        261-64.</p></note>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
