<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 32: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount, Discourse XII</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon032</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 32: Upon Our Lord’s Sermon On The Mount,
                                Discourse XII</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="466" to="469"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="675" to="686"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="01:466"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 21-33]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The unifying theme of these next thirteen ‘discourses’ on the Sermon on the
                    Mount, with all their variations and nuancings, is the Christian life understood
                    as the fruit of justifying faith. But given such faith, what follows? Wesley’s
                    answer is given in this extended exposition of the Christian life based on the
                        <hi rend="italic">locus classicus</hi> of evangelical ethics, ‘The Sermon on
                    the Mount’ (i.e., Matthew 5-7). Since Tyndale, this ‘sermon’ had been understood
                    as ‘the epitome of God’s laws and promises’ for Christian believers; cf.
                    Clebsch, <hi rend="italic">England’s Earliest Protestants</hi>, p. 184; see also
                    William Burkitt, <hi rend="italic">Expository Notes…on the New Testament</hi>
                    (eleven editions between 1700 and 1739), Preface to chapter 5: ‘Christ’s famous
                    Sermon on the Mount comprehends the sum and substance of both the Old and New
                    Testaments.’</p>
                <p>Taken together, the following sermons are not a thirteen-part essay, tightly
                    organized and argued. Instead, they are separate sermons, drawn from materials
                    running back to 1725, arranged in a triadic pattern that seems to have been
                    original with Wesley. Each is a discourse in its own right; yet the series is
                    designed so that each appears as a part of a whole. This means that the sermons
                    may be read singly or together, but with an eye on their shared aim: ‘to assert
                    and prove every branch of <hi rend="italic">gospel obedience</hi> as
                    indispensably necessary to eternal salvation’; cf. Wesley’s open letter (Nov.
                    17, 1759) to John Downes in reply to the latter’s abusive <hi rend="italic"
                        >Methodism Examined and Exposed</hi> (1759).</p>
                <p>Many of the great and near-great commentators of the seventeenth and eighteenth
                    centuries had devoted their talents to the interpretation of Matthew 5-7 as the
                    principal summary of Christian ethics, or, in Henry Hammond’s phrase, as ‘an
                    abstract of Christian philosophy’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Catechism</hi> (1st edn., <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1644), II.1, in the <hi
                        rend="italic">Library of Anglo-Catholic Theology</hi> (1847), p. 83. Chief
                    among these earlier works, in the order of their influences upon Wesley’s
                    thought, were Bishop Offspring Blackall, ‘Eighty-Seven Practical Discourses Upon
                    Our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.1-561;
                    II.609-939; <pb n="01:467"/>John Norris, <hi rend="italic">Practical
                        Discourses</hi>; the American, James Blair, <hi rend="italic">Our Saviour’s
                        Divine Sermon on the Mount in IV Volumes</hi> (1722; 2nd edn., 1740, with a
                    preface by Daniel Waterland); John Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Guide to
                        Eternity…</hi> (six editions in English between 1672 and 1712); and Henry
                    Hammond, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> Echoes of all these are scattered along
                    the way, together with lesser borrowings from Bengel, Poole, and Henry. This
                    makes it all the more remarkable that Wesley came up with a model of his own,
                    both inform and substance. This series thus reminds us, yet again, of Wesley’s
                    ready appeal to tradition—even while he maintains his own originality and
                    independence.</p>
                <p>Benjamin Ingham records in his Journal that ‘during the voyage [to Georgia]
                    Wesley went over our Saviour’s Sermon on the Mount’ with the ship’s company
                    aboard the <hi rend="italic">Simmonds</hi>. There are also other records of his
                    preaching, very early on, from one or another text in Matthew 5-7. For example,
                    his second sermon was preached at Binsey (near Oxford), November 21, 1725, on
                    Matt. 6:33. A first draft of the sermon which appears here as ‘Discourse VIII’
                    seems to have been written out in 1736. Later, it was the example of the Sermon
                    on the Mount that encouraged Wesley to break out of his High Church prejudices
                    in Bristol, April 1, 1739: ‘In the evening (Mr. Whitefield being gone) I begun
                    expounding our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount (one pretty remarkable precedent of
                        <hi rend="italic">field preaching</hi>, though I suppose <hi rend="italic"
                        >there were churches</hi> at that time also) to a little society which was
                    accustomed to meet once or twice a week in Nicholas Street;’ cf. <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries for this whole story of the unplanned
                    outbreak of the Wesleyan Revival.</p>
                <p>The records show that, between 1739 and 1746, Wesley preached more than one
                    hundred sermons from separate texts in the Sermon on the Mount. There is,
                    however, no recorded instance of his having treated that Sermon as a whole
                    anywhere else. Evidently, he was prepared to allow this series, once published,
                    to stand as his sufficient comment on the subject.</p>
                <p>In his introduction to ‘Discourse X’, §§1-3, Wesley repeats his explanation (cf.
                    ‘Discourse I’, Proem, §10) of how he had conceived the design of Matthew 5-7,
                    according to its three unfolding themes: (1) ‘the sum of true religion’; (2)
                    ‘rules touching that right intention which we are to preserve in all our outward
                    actions’; and (3) ‘the main hindrances of this religion’. He then adds a
                    clarifying summary: ‘In the fifth chapter [of St. Matthew] our great Teacher…has
                    laid before us those <hi rend="italic">dispositions of the soul</hi> which
                    constitute real Christianity…. In the sixth [chapter] he has shown how all our
                        <hi rend="italic">actions</hi>…may be made holy, and good, and acceptable to
                    God, by a pure and holy intention…. In <pb n="01:468"/>the former part of [ch.
                    7] he points out the most common and fatal hindrances of this holiness; in the
                    latter [part] he exhorts us, by various motives, to break through all [such
                    hindrances] and secure that prize of our high calling [of God in Christ Jesus]’
                    (cf. Phil. 3:14).</p>
                <p>The thirteen discourses are divided almost equally over the three chapters of St.
                    Matthew: five for chapter five, four each for six and seven. Of the first five,
                    Discourse I is devoted to the first two Beatitudes; Discourse II to Beatitudes
                    three through five (with a hymn to love based on 1 Cor. 13); Discourse III to
                    the remainder of the Beatitudes; Discourse IV turns to Christianity as ‘a social
                    religion’ in which inward holiness (our love of God) prompts outward holiness
                    (love of neighbour); Discourse V is a balancing of law <hi rend="italic"
                        >and</hi> gospel. Discourses VI-IX are based on chapter six: VI to the
                    problems of purity and holiness of intention (to the ‘works of piety and of
                    mercy’); VII to fasting; VIII to a denunciation of greed and surplus
                    accumulation; IX to the mutually exclusive services of God and Mammon.
                    Discourses X-XIII turn to various hindrances to holy living and to their
                    avoidance: X to ‘judging’ (contrary to love), ‘intemperate zeal’, ‘neglect of
                    prayer’, ‘neglect of charity’; XI to the noxious influences of ill-example and
                    ill-advice with which the world deludes us; XII to false prophets and unedifying
                    preachers (and yet also our duties to attend church nonetheless and to avail
                    ourselves of all means of grace); XIII is an inevitable comment on the parable
                    of the houses built on sand and rock. Discourse XII was also published
                    separately in the same year that it appeared in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, III
                    (1750), under the title, ‘A Caution Against False Prophets. A Sermon on Matt.
                    vii. 15-20. Particularly recommended to the People Called Methodists’. This went
                    through seven editions during Wesley’s lifetime. For a stemma delineating the
                    publishing history of that sermon (‘collected’ and ‘separate’) and a list of
                    variant readings, see Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV, see also <hi
                        rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 130 and 13o.i.</p>
                <p>Obviously there is no interest, in any of these sermons, in critical textual
                    problems or in the historical context. Everywhere it is assumed that in St.
                    Matthew’s text we are dealing with divine <hi rend="italic">ipsissima
                    verba</hi>—i.e., with a direct address from ὁ ὤν, ‘the self-existent, the
                    Supreme, the God who is over all, blessed for ever’ (§9 below). The Sermon on
                    the Mount, in Wesley’s view, is the only Gospel passage where Christ designed
                    ‘to lay down at once the whole plan of his religion, to give us a full prospect
                    of Christianity’. What matters most in our reading, therefore, is an awareness
                    of Wesley’s sense of the wholeness of the message he is interpreting, of his
                    conviction of the honest integration of an evangel profoundly ethical with an
                    ethic that is also vividly <pb n="01:469"/>evangelical. Maybe more than anywhere
                    else in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> this particular bloc displays Wesley’s
                    distinctive concern for integration and balance—between the faith that justifies
                    and the faith that works by love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="01:675"/>
            <head>Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount,<lb/>Discourse the Twelfth</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Matthew 7:15-20</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Beware of false prophets, which come to you in sheep’s
                        clothing, but inwardly they are ravening wolves.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Ye shall know them by their fruits. Do men gather grapes of
                        thorns, or figs of thistles?</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Even so every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a
                        corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit; neither can a
                        corrupt tree bring forth good fruit.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down and
                        cast into the fire.</hi>
                </p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Wherefore by their fruits ye shall know them.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. It is scarce possible to express or conceive what multitudes of souls
                    run on to destruction because they would not be persuaded to walk in a <hi
                        rend="italic">narrow</hi> way, even though it were the way to everlasting
                    salvation. And the same thing we may still observe daily. Such is the folly and
                    madness of mankind that thousands of men still rush on in the way to hell only
                    because it is a broad way. They walk in it themselves because others do: because
                    so many perish they will add to the number. Such is the amazing influence of
                    example over the weak, miserable children of men! It continually peoples the
                    regions of death, and drowns numberless souls in everlasting perdition.</p>
                <p n="2">2. To warn mankind of this, to guard as many as possible against this
                    spreading contagion, God has commanded his watchmen to cry aloud, and show the
                    people the danger they are in.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Isa. 58:1.</p></note> For this end he has sent
                    his servants, the prophets, in their succeeding generations, to point out the
                    narrow path, and exhort all men not to be conformed to this world.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                        12:2.</p></note> But what if the <pb n="01:676"/>watchmen themselves fall
                    into the snare against which they should warn others? What if ‘the prophets
                    prophesy deceits’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Isa. 30:10.</p></note> If they ‘cause the people to err from the
                        way’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jer.
                            23:13, 32.</p></note> What shall be done if they point out, as the way
                    to eternal life, what is in truth the way to eternal death? And exhort others to
                    walk, as they do themselves, in the broad, not the narrow way?</p>
                <p n="3">3. Is this an unheard of, is it an uncommon thing? Nay, God knoweth it is
                    not. The instances of it are almost innumerable. We may find them in every age
                    and nation. But how terrible is this! When the ambassadors of God turn agents
                    for the devil! When they who are commissioned to teach men the way to heaven do
                    in fact teach them the way to hell! These are like the locusts of Egypt ‘which
                    eat up the residue that had escaped’, that had ‘remained after the hail’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Exod.
                        10:5.</p></note> They devour even the residue of men that had escaped, that
                    were not destroyed by ill example. It is not therefore without cause that our
                    wise and gracious master so solemnly cautions us against them: ‘Beware’, saith
                    he, ‘of false prophets, which come to you in sheep’s clothing, but inwardly they
                    are ravening wolves.’</p>
                <p n="4">4. A caution this of the utmost importance. That it may the more
                    effectually sink into our hearts, let us inquire, first, who these false
                    prophets are; secondly, what appearance they put on; and, thirdly, how we may
                    know what they really are, notwithstanding their fair appearance.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. We are, first, to inquire who these false prophets are. And this it
                    is needful to do the more diligently because these very men have so laboured to
                    ‘wrest this Scripture to their own (though not only their own)
                        destruction’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 2 Pet. 3:16.</p></note> In order therefore to cut off all dispute I
                    shall raise no dust<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A rare instance of slang in Wesley; this usage is
                            not noted in the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>. But cf. E. Partridge, <hi
                                rend="italic">A Dictionary of Slang and Unconventional English</hi>
                            (1937), and E. C. Brewer’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Phrase and
                                Fable</hi> (1870, <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi>).</p></note> (as
                    the manner of some is) neither use any loose, rhetorical exclamations to deceive
                    the hearts of the simple, but speak rough, plain truths, such as none can deny
                    who has either understanding or modesty left, and such truths as have the
                    closest connection with the whole tenor of the preceding <pb n="01:677"
                    />discourse; whereas too many have interpreted these words without any regard to
                    all that went before, as if they bore no manner of relation to the sermon in the
                    close of which they stand.</p>
                <p n="2">2. By ‘prophets’ here (as in many other passages of Scripture, particularly
                    in the New Testament) are meant, not those who foretell things to come, but
                    those who speak in the name of God; those men who profess to be sent of God to
                    teach others the way to heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The Puritans had identified prophecy as
                            preaching-teaching (‘forthtelling’ rather than ‘foretelling’) and Wesley
                            reflects that tradition here. Cf. William Perkins, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Art of Prophesying</hi>. See No. 121, ‘Prophets and Priests’, §6,
                            which corresponds to Perkins’s conception of prophecy and prophesying;
                            cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on 1 Thess.
                    5:20.</p></note></p>
                <p>Those are ‘false prophets’ who teach a false way to heaven, a way which does not
                    lead thither; or (which comes in the end to the same point) who do not teach the
                    true.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Every broad way is infallibly a false one. Therefore this is one plain,
                    sure rule, ‘They who teach men to walk in a broad way, a way that many walk in,
                    are false prophets.’</p>
                <p>Again, the true way to heaven is a narrow way. Therefore this is another plain,
                    sure rule, ‘They who do not teach men to walk in a narrow way, to be singular,
                    are false prophets.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, III.4 and
                            n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. To be more particular: the only true way to heaven is that pointed out
                    in the preceding sermon. Therefore they are false prophets who do not teach men
                    to walk in <hi rend="italic">this way</hi>.</p>
                <p>Now the way to heaven pointed out in the preceding sermon is the way of
                    lowliness, mourning, meekness, and holy desire, love of God and of our
                    neighbour, doing good, and suffering evil for Christ’s sake. They are therefore
                    false prophets who teach as the way to heaven any other way than <hi
                        rend="italic">this</hi>.</p>
                <p n="5">5. It matters not what they call that other way. They may call it ‘faith’,
                    or ‘good works’; or ‘faith and works’; or ‘repentance’; or ‘repentance, faith,
                    and new obedience’. All these are good words. But if under these, or any other
                    terms whatever, they teach men any way distinct from <hi rend="italic"
                    >this</hi>, they are properly false prophets.</p>
                <p n="6">6. How much more do they fall under that condemnation who speak evil of
                    this good way! But above all they who teach the directly opposite way—the way of
                    pride, of levity, of passion, of worldly desires, of loving pleasure more than
                    God, of unkindness to our neighbour, of unconcern for good works, and suffering
                    no evil, no persecution for righteousness’ sake!</p>
                <p n="7"><pb n="01:678"/>7. If it be asked, ‘Why, who ever did teach this?’ Or, ‘Who
                    does teach it as the way to heaven?’ I answer, Ten thousand wise and honourable
                    men; even all those, of whatever denomination,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10"
                        n="10"><p rend="footnote text">This usage, connoting an <hi rend="italic"
                                >ecclesial</hi> entity, was rather new; the first instance of it in
                            the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, in this sense, is dated 1716. Even in
                            1755, Dr. Johnson would use it of ‘sects’ of philosophers without any
                            ecclesial connotation at all. For other instances of Wesley’s use of the
                            term, see Nos. 104, ‘On Attending the Church Service’, §4, and 107, ‘On
                            God’s Vineyard’, II.8.</p></note> who encourage the proud, the trifler,
                    the passionate, the lover of the world, the man of pleasure, the unjust or
                    unkind, the easy, careless, harmless, useless creature, the man who suffers no
                    reproach for righteousness’ sake, to imagine he is in the way to heaven. These
                    are false prophets in the highest sense of the word. These are traitors both to
                    God and man. These are no other than the first-born of Satan, the eldest sons of
                    Apollyon, the destroyer.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Rev. 9:11: ‘the angel of the bottomless pit,
                            whose name in the Hebrew tongue is Abaddon, but in the Greek tongue hath
                            his name Apollyon’. In Enoch 20:2 the angel presiding over ‘Tarturus’
                            was named Uriel. Cf. John Bunyan, <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim’s
                                Progress</hi> (1st edn., 1678; Philadelphia, Porter and Coates,
                            n.d.), pp. 61-65. This metaphor of ‘the bottomless pit’ was one of
                            Wesley’s favourites; cf. e.g., III.4, below, and Nos. 25, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, V’, III.5; 66, ‘The Signs of the Times’, II.7; 90, ‘An Israelite
                            Indeed’, II.4; 96, ‘On Obedience to Parents’, II.4; 100, ‘On Pleasing
                            All Men’, II.2; 102, ‘Of Former Times’, §16; 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’,
                            I.7; and 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §18.</p><p
                            rend="footnote text">For ‘the first-born of Satan’, cf. ‘The Epistle of
                            Polycarp to the Philippians’, VII.1, in <hi rend="italic">The Apostolic
                                Fathers</hi>, Loeb, I:293 (quoting 1 John 4:2, 3, and 2 John 7):
                            ‘“For everyone who does not confess that Jesus Christ has come in the
                            flesh is an antichrist;” and whosoever does not confess the testimony of
                            the cross is of the devil; and whosoever perverts the oracles of the
                            Lord for his own lusts, and says that there is neither resurrection nor
                            judgment—this man is the first-born of Satan.’ A footnote here says
                            that, according to St. Irenaeus, <hi rend="italic">Against
                            Heresies</hi>, iii.3, 4, this phrase, ‘first-born of Satan’, was later
                            applied by Polycarp specifically to Marcion. Cf. also Nos. 128, ‘The
                            Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, I.1; and 150, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’,
                            I.3, where Wesley uses the Greek phrase, πρωτότοκοι τοῦ
                        Σατανᾶ.</p></note> These are far above the rank of ordinary cut-throats; for
                    they murder the souls of men. They are continually peopling the realms of night;
                    and whenever they follow the poor souls whom they have destroyed, ‘hell’ shall
                    be ‘moved from beneath to meet them at their coming’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 14:9.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. But do they come now in their own shape? By no means. If it were so
                    they could not destroy. You would take the alarm and flee for your life.
                    Therefore they put on a quite contrary appearance, which was the second thing to
                    be considered: ‘they come to you in sheep’s clothing,’ although ‘inwardly they
                    are ravening wolves.’</p>
                <p n="2"><pb n="01:679"/>2. ‘They come to you in sheep’s clothing;’ that is, with an
                    appearance of harmlessness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Wesley speaks frequently of ‘harmlessness’, often
                            sarcastically, as here. Cf. Nos. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.2;
                            52, <hi rend="italic">The Reformation of Manners</hi>, III.3; 81, ‘In
                            What Sense we are to Leave the World’, §23; 119, ‘Walking by Sight and
                            Walking by Faith’, §18; and 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’,
                        §16.</p></note> They come in the most mild, inoffensive manner, without any
                    mark or token of enmity. Who can imagine that these quiet creatures would do any
                    hurt to anyone? Perhaps they may not be so zealous and active in doing good as
                    one would wish they were. However, you see no reason to suspect that they have
                    even the desire to do any harm. But this is not all.</p>
                <p n="3">3. They come, secondly, with an appearance of usefulness. Indeed to this,
                    to do good, they are particularly called. They are set apart for this very
                    thing. They are particularly commissioned to watch over your soul, and to train
                    you up to eternal life. ’Tis their whole business to ‘go about doing good, and
                    healing those that are oppressed of the devil’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14"
                        n="14"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 10:38.</p></note> And you have been
                    always accustomed to look upon them in this light, as messengers of God sent to
                    bring you a blessing.</p>
                <p n="4">4. They come, thirdly, with an appearance of religion. All they do is for
                    conscience’ sake! They assure you it is out of mere zeal for God that they are
                    making God a liar. It is out of pure concern for religion that they would
                    destroy it root and branch. All they speak is only from a love of truth, and a
                    fear lest it should suffer. And, it may be, from a regard for the church, and a
                    desire to defend her from all her enemies.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Above all, they come with an appearance of love. They take all these
                    pains only for <hi rend="italic">your</hi> good. They should not trouble
                    themselves about you, but that they have a kindness for you. They will make
                    large professions of their goodwill, of their concern for the danger you are in,
                    and of their earnest desire to preserve you from error, from being entangled in
                    new and mischievous doctrines. They should be very sorry to see one who <hi
                        rend="italic">means</hi> so well hurried into any extreme, perplexed with
                    strange and unintelligible notions, or deluded into enthusiasm Therefore it is
                    that they advise you to keep still in the plain middle way;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 27, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, VII’, §4 and n.</p></note> and to beware of ‘being righteous
                    overmuch’, lest you should ‘destroy yourself’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Eccles. 7:16. Cf. below, III.11. An oblique
                            reference to Joseph Trapp, whose four sermons on <hi rend="italic">The
                                Nature, Folly, Sin, and Danger of Being Righteous Overmuch</hi>
                            (1739) had ridiculed the Methodists and had, in turn, become an easy
                            target for their scornful retorts. Wesley’s description here of the
                            ideal ministerial character is perfectionistic enough so as to encourage
                            his people to expect more of their Church of England priests than they
                            could realistically expect from their own Methodist preachers or
                            class-leaders.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1"><pb n="01:680"/>III. 1. But how may we know what they really are,
                    notwithstanding their fair appearance? This was the third thing into which it
                    was proposed to inquire.</p>
                <p>Our blessed Lord saw how needful it was for all men to know false prophets,
                    however disguised. He saw likewise how unable most men were to deduce a truth
                    through a long train of consequences. He therefore gives us a short and plain
                    rule, easy to be understood by men of the meanest capacities, and easy to be
                    applied upon all occasions: ‘Ye shall know them by their fruits.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. Upon all occasions you may easily apply this rule. In order to know
                    whether any who speak in the name of God are false or true prophets it is easy
                    to observe, first, What are the fruits of their doctrine as to themselves? What
                    effect has it had upon their lives? Are they holy and unblameable in all things?
                    What effect has it had upon their hearts? Does it appear by the general tenor of
                    their conversation that their tempers are holy, heavenly, divine? That the mind
                    is in them which was in Christ Jesus?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Phil. 2:5.</p></note> That they are meek, lowly,
                    patient lovers of God and man, and zealous of good works?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. You may easily observe, secondly, what are the fruits of their doctrine
                    as to those that hear them—in many, at least, though not in all; for the
                    apostles themselves did not convert all that heard them. Have these the mind
                    that was in Christ? And do they walk as he also walked? And was it by hearing
                    these men that they began so to do? Were they inwardly and outwardly wicked till
                    they heard them? If so, it is a manifest proof that those are true prophets,
                    teachers sent of God. But if it is not so, if they do not effectually teach
                    either themselves or others to love and serve God, it is a manifest proof that
                    they are false prophets; that God hath not sent them.</p>
                <p n="4">4. An hard saying this! How few can bear it!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">See John 6:60.</p></note> This
                    our Lord was sensible of, and therefore condescends to prove it at large by
                    several clear and convincing arguments. ‘Do men’, says he, ‘gather grapes of
                    thorns, or figs of thistles?’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. 16 [of text].</p></note></hi> Do you expect
                    that <pb n="01:681"/>these evil men should bring forth good fruit? As well might
                    you expect that thorns should bring forth grapes, or that figs should grow upon
                    thistles! ‘Every good tree bringeth forth good fruit; but a corrupt tree
                    bringeth forth evil fruit.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. 17.</p></note></hi> Every true prophet,
                    every teacher whom I have sent, bringeth forth the good fruit of holiness. But a
                    false prophet, a teacher whom I have not sent, brings forth only sin and
                    wickedness. ‘A good tree cannot bring forth evil fruit; neither can a corrupt
                    tree bring forth good fruit.’ A true prophet, a teacher sent from God, does not
                    bring forth good fruit sometimes only, but always; not accidentally, but by a
                    kind of necessity. In like manner, a false prophet, one whom God hath not sent,
                    does not bring forth evil fruit accidentally or sometimes only, but always, and
                    of necessity. ‘Every tree that bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down and
                    cast into the fire.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. 19.</p></note></hi> Such infallibly will be
                    the lot of those prophets who bring not forth good fruit, who do not save souls
                    from sin, who do not bring sinners to repentance. ‘Wherefore’ let this stand as
                    an eternal rule: ‘By their fruits ye shall know them.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                20.</p></note></hi> They who in fact bring the proud, passionate,
                    unmerciful lovers of the world to be lowly, gentle lovers of God and man—they
                    are true prophets, they are sent from God, who therefore confirms their word. On
                    the other hand they whose hearers, if unrighteous before, remain unrighteous
                    still, or at least void of any righteousness which ‘exceeds the righteousness of
                    the scribes and Pharisees’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:20.</p></note>—they are false prophets;
                    they are not sent of God; therefore their word falls to the ground. And without
                    a miracle of grace they and their hearers together will fall into the bottomless
                    pit.</p>
                <p n="5">5. O ‘beware of’ these ‘false prophets’! For though they ‘come in sheep’s
                    clothing, yet inwardly they are ravening wolves’. They only destroy and devour
                    the flock: they tear them in pieces if there is none to help them. They will
                    not, cannot lead you in the way to heaven. How should they, when they know it
                    not themselves? O beware they do not turn you out of the way, and cause you to
                    ‘lose what you have wrought’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 John 8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. But perhaps you will ask, ‘If there is such danger in hearing <pb
                        n="682"/>them, ought I to hear them at all?’ It is a weighty question, such
                    as deserves the deepest consideration, and ought not to be answered but upon the
                    calmest thought, the most deliberate reflection. For many years I have been
                    almost afraid to speak at all concerning it; being unable to determine one way
                    or the other, or to give any judgment upon it. Many reasons there are which
                    readily occur, and incline me to say, ‘Hear them not.’ And yet what our Lord
                    speaks concerning the false prophets of his own times seems to imply the
                    contrary. ‘Then spake Jesus unto the multitude, and to his disciples, saying,
                    The scribes and the Pharisees sit in Moses’ seat,’ are the ordinary, stated
                    teachers in your church: ‘All therefore whatsoever they bid you observe, that
                    observe and do. But do not ye after their works; for they say and do not.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        23:1-3.</p></note> Now that these were false prophets in the highest sense
                    our Lord had shown during the whole course of his ministry, as indeed he does in
                    those very words, ‘they say and do not.’ Therefore by their fruits his disciples
                    could not but know them, seeing they were open to the view of all men.
                    Accordingly he warns them again and again to ‘beware of’ these ‘false prophets’.
                    And yet he does not forbid them to hear even these. Nay, he in effect commands
                    them so to do in those words: ‘All therefore whatsoever they bid you observe,
                    that observe and do.’ For unless they heard them they could not know, much less
                    ‘observe, whatsoever they bade them do’. Here then our Lord himself gives a
                    plain direction, both to his apostles and the whole multitude, in some
                    circumstances to hear even false prophets, known and acknowledged so to be.</p>
                <p n="7">7. But perhaps it will be said, he only directed to hear them when they
                    read the Scripture to the congregation. I answer, at the same time that they
                    thus read the Scripture they generally expounded it too. And here is no kind of
                    intimation that they were to hear the one and not the other also. Nay, the very
                    terms, ‘All things whatsoever they bid you observe’, exclude any such
                    limitation.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Again, unto them, unto false prophets, undeniably such, is frequently
                    committed (O grief to speak! for surely these things ought not so to be) the
                    administration of the sacraments also. To direct men, therefore, not to hear
                    them would be in effect to cut them off from the ordinance of God. But this we
                    dare not do, considering the validity of the ordinance doth not depend on the
                        <pb n="01:683"/>goodness of him that administers, but on the faithfulness of
                    him that ordained it; who will and doth meet us in his appointed ways.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Art. XXVI,
                            ‘Of the unworthiness of the ministers, which hinders not the effect of
                            the sacraments.’ The background here is the bitter controversy that
                            still centred in the Nonconformists’ contention that it was <hi
                                rend="italic">against conscience</hi> (and, therefore, <hi
                                rend="italic">sinful</hi>) to accept the ministrations of unworthy
                            priests or to participate in rituals that still smacked of popery.
                            Wesley’s toleration on this point was rooted in his ecclesiology. Cf.
                            the longer explanation of his ‘Reasons Against a Separation from the
                            Church of England’ in <hi rend="italic">A Preservative Against Unsettled
                                Notions in Religion</hi>. See also Nos. 97, ‘On Obedience to
                            Pastors’, where Wesley argues a distinction between ‘pastors’ (<hi
                                rend="italic">ex officio</hi>) and ‘spiritual guides’; and 104, ‘On
                            Attending the Church Service’, §27. His concerns to keep his people
                            within the sacramental environment of the Church of England and also to
                            warn them against ‘false prophets’ were carefully balanced.</p></note>
                    Therefore on this account likewise I scruple to say, ‘Hear not even the false
                    prophets.’ Even by these who are under a curse themselves God can and doth give
                    us his blessing. For the bread which they break we have experimentally known to
                    be ‘the communion of the body of Christ’; and the cup which God blessed, even by
                    their unhallowed lips, was to us the communion of the blood of Christ.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        10:16.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. All, therefore, which I can say is this: in any particular case wait
                    upon God by humble and earnest prayer, and then act according to the best light
                    you have. Act according to what you are persuaded upon the whole will be most
                    for your spiritual advantage. Take great care that you do not judge rashly; that
                    you do not lightly think any to be false prophets. And when you have full proof,
                    see that no anger or contempt have any place in your heart. After this, in the
                    presence and in the fear of God, determine for yourself. I can only say, if by
                    experience you find that the hearing them hurts your soul, then hear them not;
                    then quietly refrain, and hear those that profit you. If on the other hand you
                    find it does not hurt your soul, you then may hear them still. Only ‘take heed
                    how you hear.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Luke 8:18.</p></note> Beware of them and of their doctrine. Hear with
                    fear and trembling, lest <hi rend="italic">you</hi> should be deceived, and
                    given up like them to a strong delusion. As they continually mingle truth and
                    lies, how easily may you take in both together! Hear with fervent and continual
                    prayer to him who alone teacheth man wisdom. And see that you bring whatever you
                    hear ‘to the law and to the testimony’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Isa. 8:20.</p></note> Receive nothing untried,
                    nothing till it is weighed in ‘the balance of the sanctuary’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of
                            the Spirit, I’, II.8 and n.</p></note> Believe <pb n="01:684"/>nothing
                    they say unless it is clearly confirmed by plain passages of Holy Writ. Wholly
                    reject whatsoever differs therefrom, whatever is not confirmed thereby. And in
                    particular reject with the utmost abhorrence whatsoever is described as the way
                    of salvation that is either different from, or short of, the way our Lord has
                    marked out in the foregoing discourse.</p>
                <p n="10">10. I cannot conclude without addressing a few plain words to those of
                    whom we have now been speaking.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For still more ‘plain words’ to the Anglican
                            clergy, cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Address to the Clergy</hi>,
                            I.3-II.1, 3.</p></note> O ye false prophets, O ye dry bones, hear ye for
                    once the word of the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Ezek. 37:4.</p></note> How long will ye lie in the
                    name of God, saying God hath spoken, and God hath not spoken by you?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">See Ezek.
                            13:6-7.</p></note> How long will ye pervert the right ways of the
                        Lord,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Acts
                            13:10.</p></note> putting darkness for light, and light for
                        darkness?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Isa. 5:20.</p></note> How long will ye teach the way of death, and
                    call it the way of life? How long will ye deliver to Satan the souls whom you
                    profess to bring unto God?</p>
                <p n="11">11. ‘Woe unto you, ye blind leaders of the blind!’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 15:14;
                        23:16.</p></note> ‘For ye shut the kingdom of heaven against men: ye neither
                    go in yourselves, neither suffer ye them that are entering to go in.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        23:13.</p></note> Them that would strive to enter in at the strait gate ye
                    call back into the broad way. Them that have scarce gone one step in the ways of
                    God you devilishly caution against ‘going too far’. Them that just begin to
                    hunger and thirst after righteousness you warn not to be ‘righteous
                        overmuch’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. above, II.5 and n.</p></note> Thus you cause them to stumble at the
                    very threshold; yea, to fall and rise no more.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36"
                        n="36"><p rend="footnote text">Jer. 25:27.</p></note> O wherefore do ye
                    this? What profit is there in their blood when they go down to the pit?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                        30:9.</p></note> Miserable profit to <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. They ‘shall
                    perish in their iniquity; but their blood will God require at <hi rend="italic"
                        >your</hi> hands’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ezek. 3:18; 33:8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="12">12. Where are your eyes? Where is your understanding? Have ye deceived
                    others till you have deceived yourselves also? Who hath required this at your
                    hands, to <hi rend="italic">teach</hi> a way which ye never <hi rend="italic"
                        >knew</hi>? Are you ‘given up to’ so ‘strong a delusion’ that ye not only
                    teach but ‘believe a lie’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 81:12; 2 Thess. 2:11.</p></note> And can
                    you possibly believe that God <pb n="01:685"/>hath sent you? That ye are <hi
                        rend="italic">his</hi> messengers? Nay, if the Lord had sent you, the ‘work
                    of the Lord’, would ‘prosper in your hands’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40"
                        n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 53:10.</p></note> As the Lord
                    liveth, if ye were messengers of God he would ‘confirm the word of his
                        messengers’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Ezek. 13:6.</p></note> But the work of the Lord doth not prosper in
                    your hand: you bring no sinners to repentance. The Lord doth not confirm your
                    word, for you save no souls from death.</p>
                <p n="13">13. How can you possibly evade the force of our Lord’s words—so full, so
                    strong, so express? How can ye evade ‘knowing yourselves by your fruits’? Evil
                    fruits of evil trees! And how should it be otherwise? ‘Do men gather grapes of
                    thorns, or figs of thistles?’ Take this to yourselves, ye to whom it belongs. O
                    ye barren trees, why cumber ye the ground?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="42"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 13:7.</p></note> ‘Every good tree
                    bringeth forth good fruit.’ See ye not that here is no exception? Take
                    knowledge, then, ye are not good trees; for ye do not bring forth good fruit.
                    ‘But a corrupt tree bringeth forth evil fruit.’ And so have ye done from the
                    beginning. Your speaking as from God has only confirmed them that heard you in
                    the tempers, if not works, of the devil. O take warning of him in whose name ye
                    speak, before the sentence he hath pronounced take place. ‘Every tree which
                    bringeth not forth good fruit is hewn down, and cast into the fire.’</p>
                <p n="14">14. My dear brethren, harden not your hearts.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 95:8; Heb. 3:8.</p></note>
                    You have too long shut your eyes against the light. Open them now, before it is
                    too late; before you are cast into outer darkness.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 8:12;
                        22:13.</p></note> Let not any temporal consideration weigh with you; for
                    eternity is at stake. Ye have run before ye were sent. O go no farther. Do not
                    persist to damn yourselves and them that hear you! You have no fruit of your
                    labours. And why is this? Even because the Lord is not with you. But can you go
                    this warfare at your own cost?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor. 9:7.</p></note> It cannot be. Then
                    humble yourselves before him. Cry unto him out of the dust, that he may first
                    quicken <hi rend="italic">thy</hi> soul, give <hi rend="italic">thee</hi> the
                    faith that worketh by love; that is lowly and meek, pure and merciful, zealous
                    of good works;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Titus 2:14.</p></note> rejoicing in tribulation, in reproach, in
                    distress, in persecution for righteousness’ sake. So shall ‘the Spirit of glory
                    and of Christ rest upon thee’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 4:14.</p></note> and it shall appear <pb
                        n="686"/>that God hath sent thee. So shalt thou indeed ‘do the work of an
                    evangelist, and make full proof of thy ministry.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Tim. 4:5.</p></note> So
                    shall the word of God in thy mouth be ‘an hammer that breaketh the rocks in
                        pieces’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Jer. 23:29.</p></note> It shall then be known by thy fruits that thou
                    art a prophet of the Lord, even by the children whom God hath given thee.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">See Isa.
                            8:18.</p></note> And having ‘turned many to righteousness, thou shalt
                    shine as the stars for ever and ever’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Dan. 12:3.</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
