<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 13: On Sin in Believers</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon013</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 13: On Sin in Believers</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="314" to="334"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <pb n="314"/>
            </p>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [on Sermons 13-14]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>In the first edition of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I (1746), ‘The Witness of
                    the Spirit’ (Discourse I), was followed by a sermon on ‘The Means of Grace’ to
                    round out the volume. Two years later, Wesley placed his third university
                    sermon, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’ (from 1733), as the first sermon in his
                    second volume, following it with a new sermon on ‘The Great Privilege of those
                    that are Born of God’. The shared theme in this sequence (stressed in three of
                    the sermons and implied in ‘The Means of Grace’) concerned the power bestowed on
                    justified and regenerate believers <hi rend="italic">not to commit sin</hi>—a
                    crucial idea in the holy-living tradition, which then was given its climactic
                    statement, up to that date, in <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>
                    (1750); see No. 40.</p>
                <p>This idea of the Christian’s grace-bestowed power not to commit sin was, however,
                    bound to generate controversy and confusion among both critics and some
                    disciples. With their doctrines of the ineradicable ‘remains of sin’ (<hi rend="italic">fomes peccati</hi>), the Lutherans had taught that the
                    justified believer was <hi rend="italic">simul justus et peccator</hi> but also
                    that his repented sins were covered by the imputed righteousness of Christ and
                    thus inculpable; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Apology of the Augsburg
                        Confession</hi> (1531), Article II, ‘Original Sin’, especially §§35-45. With
                    similar premises with respect to the <hi rend="italic">fomes peccati</hi> (the
                    Christian is ‘a sinner saved by grace’), the Calvinists stressed rigorous
                    examination of consciences, repentance, the final perseverance of the elect, and
                    the perfect and immutable freedom ‘in the state of glory only’; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Westminster Confession</hi> VI.v, IX.v; see also
                    XIII-XVIII. On the other side, the Moravians and some of Wesley’s own disciples
                    (e.g., Thomas Maxfield, William Cudworth, James Relly) had taken the claim that
                    ‘those born of God do not commit sin’ to its antinomian extreme of sinless—even
                    guiltless—perfection, as if the power not to sin meant the extirpation of all
                    ‘remains of sin’. For an exposition of this view, see the Supplement to <hi rend="italic">The Christian Magazine for the Year 1762</hi>: ‘for all who
                    are united to Christ by the Holy Spirit’s dwelling in them are delivered from
                    the guilt, the power, or, in one word the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of <pb n="315"/>sin’ (p. 579; see also below, pp. 328-32). Moreover, they had
                    appealed to Wesley’s basic soteriology as the logical ground for their
                    interpretation.</p>
                <p>Wesley, caught in the controversy generated by these two polarities, reacted
                    typically and came up with what he regarded as a valid third alternative. Its
                    root notion was a distinction between ‘sin properly so called’ (i.e., ‘the
                    [deliberate] violation of a known law of God’—mortal if unrepented) and all
                    ‘involuntary transgressions’ (culpable only if unrepented and not discarded when
                    discerned or entertained). This distinction already had a history in Catholic
                    moral theory (‘mortal’ versus ‘venial’); cf. Claude Fleury, <hi rend="italic">Les Moeurs des Israélites</hi> (1683; cf. <hi rend="italic">The Manners of
                        the Ancient Israelites…</hi>, ed. Adam Clarke [1852], p. 306). But it had
                    also had a special development among Anglican moralists as well. Richard Lucas
                    had analyzed it in his <hi rend="italic">Enquiry After Happiness</hi> (1717),
                    III.299-301 (e.g., ‘Mortal sin is a deliberate transgression of a known law of
                    God tending to the dishonour of God and injury of our neighbour or the
                    deprivation of our own nature’). John Kettlewell, in <hi rend="italic">The
                        Measures of Christian Obedience</hi> (1681), had spoken of ‘voluntary’ and
                    ‘involuntary’ sins (see Bk. IV, chs. 3-4, pp. 330 ff., 335 ff.). Much more to
                    the same effect had been found in Samuel Bradford’s Boyle Lectures for 1699, <hi rend="italic">The Credibility of the Christian Revelation, from its
                        intrinsic evidence; in eight sermons</hi> (1700), Sermon II, p. 445; Hugh
                    Binning, <hi rend="italic">Fellowship With God</hi> (1671), pp. 216-18, and John
                    Weemse [Weemes], <hi rend="italic">The Portraiture of God in Man…</hi> (1627),
                    p. 326 (cf. Weemes’s formulation of the distinction as between ‘sins forgiven ’
                    and ‘sins passed by…’).</p>
                <p>Thus, there was an unstable tension between the claims that a Christian may be
                    delivered from sin’s bondage, and that ‘sin <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> but
                    no longer <hi rend="italic">reigns</hi>’ (see below, I.6 and n.); this continued
                    to plague Wesley in many ways, as one can see from his frequent references to
                    it; see below, II.3, III.1-9 and n.; and cf. Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation
                        by Faith</hi>, II.6; 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’, II.6, 9, III.4-5;
                    14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.2-3; 18, ‘The Marks of
                    the New Birth’, I.5-6; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born of God’,
                    II.8; 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.4-5; 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, III.6; 43, <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>, III.6-8; 46, ‘The Wilderness State’, II.6,
                    III.14; 58, <hi rend="italic">On Predestination</hi>, §7; 62, ‘The End of
                    Christ’s Coming’, III.3; 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our Neighbour’, III.14; 74,
                    ‘Of the Church’, §21; 76, ‘On Perfection’, II.9; 82, ‘On Temptation’, I.5; 104,
                    ‘On Attending the Church Service’, §18; 128, <pb n="316"/>‘The Deceitfulness of
                    the Human Heart’, II.5. Cf. also Wesley’s letters to John Hosmer, June 7, 1761,
                    to Mary Bishop, May 27, 1771, and to Mrs. Bennis, June 16, 1772.</p>
                <p>What matters most is that Wesley insisted on holding to both traditions—<hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi> and <hi rend="italic">holy living</hi>—without
                    forfeiting the good essence of either. Moreover, he saw no inconsistency in his
                    shifting from one emphasis to the other as circumstances seemed to require. He
                    was more concerned to face the dreadful realities of sin while never yielding to
                    any defeatist notion that God’s grace is intrinsically impotent to save souls
                    ‘to the utmost’, in this life. That enough of his comments on this twin concern
                    could have been misconstrued as a doctrine of ‘sinless perfection’ is apparent
                    both in its exaggerations in Cudworth and others, and also in nineteenth-century
                    developments—especially in American Methodism—in which ‘entire sanctification’
                    was interpreted as ‘a second and separate work of grace’ and normative for the
                    Christian life; cf. Peters, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection and American
                        Methodism</hi>.</p>
                <p>In 1763, in a needed effort to counter the distortions and bring the controversy
                    more nearly back to balance, Wesley wrote and published a sermon entitled <hi rend="italic">A Discourse on Sin in Believers</hi>, ‘in order to remove a
                    mistake which some were labouring to propagate: that there is no sin in any that
                    are justified’ (see JWJ, Mar. 28, and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 257).
                    In 1767 he wrote out its sequel, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                        Believers</hi>, and published it the following year (cf. JWJ, Apr. 17-24,
                    and <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 305).</p>
                <p>Here, we find an interesting version of Wesley’s doctrine of ‘entire
                    sanctification’; cf. Pt. II. Shortly after this, when he began to re-arrange the
                    sequence of Vol. I of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> for the edition of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, he quite deliberately inserted these two sermons
                    as Nos. 13 and 14, between ‘The Witness of Our Own Spirit’ and ‘The Means of
                    Grace’. They are designed, as he says, for the encouragement of ‘the weaker
                    brethren’ whose Christian assurance had been all too easily shaken by their
                    awareness of sin’s residues in their hearts, even in their uncertain pilgrimage
                    of grace toward ‘perfect love’.</p>
                <p>The present text of <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi> is based on the
                    first edition of 1763, and the text of <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                        Believers</hi> is from its first edition of 1767. For stemmata illustrating
                    text transmissions through the editions published in Wesley’s lifetime and the
                    list of substantive variant readings found in these successive editions, see
                    Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’, in Vol. IV.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="317"/>
            <head>On Sin in Believers</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>2 Corinthians 5:17</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">If any man be in Christ, he is a new creature.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. Is there then sin in him that is in Christ? Does sin remain in one
                    that ‘believes in him’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 9:36, 41.</p>
                    </note> Is there any sin in
                    them that are ‘born of God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9; 4:7, etc.</p>
                    </note> or are they wholly
                    delivered from it? Let no one imagine this to be a question of mere curiosity,
                    or that it is of little importance whether it be determined one way or the
                    other. Rather it is a point of the utmost moment to every serious Christian, the
                    resolving of which very nearly concerns both his present and eternal
                    happiness.</p>
                <p n="2">2. And yet I do not know that ever it was controverted in the primitive
                    Church. Indeed there was no room for disputing concerning it, as all Christians
                    were agreed. And so far as I have observed, the whole body of ancient Christians
                    who have left us anything in writing declare with one voice that even believers
                    in Christ, till they are ‘strong in the Lord, and in the power of his might’,
                    have need to ‘wrestle with flesh and blood’, with an evil nature, as well as
                    ‘with principalities and powers’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:10, 12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. And herein our own Church (as indeed in most points) exactly copies
                    after the primitive;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A typical example of Wesley’s unself-conscious
                            Anglican triumphalism. Cf. also No. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’,
                            III.1; ‘Farther Thoughts on Separation from the Church’, §1, dated Dec.
                            11, 1789 (<hi rend="italic">AM</hi>, 1790); and his letter to Sir Harry
                            Trelawney, Aug. 1780. He was ‘anti-Establishment’, to be sure, but never
                            ‘anti-Anglican’ or even ‘pro-Nonconformist’.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">The Thirty-nine Articles were a set of doctrinal formulae first adopted
                            by the Church of England in 1563. They gained full official approval in
                            1571, having evolved from a series of confessional statements in 1536
                            (‘Ten Articles’), 1537, 1539 (‘Six Articles’), 1543, and 1553
                            (‘Forty-two Articles’). By design, they were more Reformed and
                            anti-Roman than the Edwardian Homilies (1547) had been, and they had
                            been added to the Elizabethan Prayer Book as an appendix, since they
                            were never intended to be a ‘confession’ in the same sense as <hi rend="italic">The Augsburg Confession</hi> (1530), etc. Even so, it
                            was required that Anglican clergy, in Wesley’s day, and even down till
                            1865, should subscribe to them. In the prayer book prepared by Wesley
                            for the American Methodists in 1784 (<hi rend="italic">The Sunday
                                Service</hi>) he included a highly personal abridgement of them,
                            reducing their number from thirty-nine to twenty-four; a twenty-fifth
                            was added by the Americans. As in the BCP, Wesley’s Articles were placed
                            as an appendix; ‘Of Original or Birth Sin’ appears as Art. VII rather
                            than IX.</p>
                    </note> declaring (in her Ninth <pb n="318"/>Article),
                    Original sin […] is the corruption of the nature of every man, […] whereby man
                    is […] in his own nature inclined to evil, so that the flesh lusteth contrary to
                    the Spirit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 5:17.</p>
                    </note> […] And this infection of nature doth remain, yea,
                    in them that are regenerated; whereby the lust of the flesh, called in Greek
                    φρόνημα σαρκός,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’, I.2, and, below, IV.7; see
                            also No. 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>,
                            III.6.</p>
                    </note> […] is not subject to the law of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:7.</p>
                    </note> And although there is no condemnation for them that believe
                    […], yet this lust hath of itself the nature of sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. The Thirty-nine Articles,
                            Art. IX, ‘Of Original or Birth Sin’, and consider Wesley’s omissions.
                            For an even more drastic abridgement, cf. ‘The Twenty-five Articles’ of
                            the Methodists, Art. VII, in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Sunday
                                Service</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. The same testimony is given by all other churches; not only by the Greek
                    and Romish Church, but by every Reformed Church in Europe, of whatever
                    denomination. Indeed some of these seem to carry the thing too far; so
                    describing the corruption of heart in a believer as scarce to allow that he has
                    dominion over it, but rather is in bondage thereto.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 9, ‘The Spirit of
                            Bondage and of Adoption’. This is an obvious reference to the more
                            one-sided versions of the <hi rend="italic">simul justus et
                                peccator</hi> as formulated by Matthias Flacius Illyricus and also
                            as denounced by Trent, Session V.v. Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Formula of
                                Concord</hi> (Epitome), Art. I (‘On Original Sin’), ‘Affirmative’,
                            III: ‘And we do indeed affirm that no one is able to dissever this
                            [sinful] corruption of [human] nature from the nature itself except God
                            alone—which will fully come to pass by means of death in the
                            resurrection into blessedness,’ in Philip Schaff, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Creeds of Christendom</hi> (New York, Harper and Brothers, 1881-82),
                            III.100-101.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Incidentally, this notion of
                            sin’s being destroyed by death is affirmed by the early Wesley in two
                            sermons written before 1738 (cf. Nos. 109, <hi rend="italic">The Trouble
                                and Rest of Good Men</hi>, I, II.6; and 136, ‘On Mourning for the
                            Dead’, ¶5, but the notion never reappears afterward. William Tilly had
                            made the point in his sermon ‘On Grieving the Holy Spirit’ which Wesley
                            extracted. This idea had appeared in Luther’s <hi rend="italic">Treatise
                                on the Holy Sacrament of Baptism</hi> (1519), VII-VIII, XVII-XVIII,
                            and had then been developed in classical Lutheran eschatology; cf.
                            Schmid, <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Theology</hi>, pp. 625 ff. For
                            references to Luther in the Wesley corpus, cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.9 and n.</p>
                    </note> And by this
                    means they leave hardly any distinction between a believer and an
                    unbeliever.</p>
                <p n="5">5. To avoid this extreme many well-meaning men, particularly those under
                    the direction of the late Count Zinzendorf,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s relations with Count Ludwig von
                            Zinzendorf, the most prominent of the Moravians, were complex and
                            unfortunate; cf. ‘The Rift With the Moravians’ in LPT, <hi rend="italic">Wesley</hi>, pp. 347-76. The crucial difference between them, in
                            Wesley’s view, was that antinomianism was a natural consequence of the
                            Moravian doctrines of ‘perfect love’, whereas his own doctrine of
                            ‘perfection’ and ‘holiness’ was strongly moralized (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ‘love of God and neighbour’). Cf. below, III.9-10 and
                            V.1, as well as Nos. 48, ‘Self-denial’, III.2; 76, ‘On Perfection’,
                            III.12; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.3. See also JWJ, July 12, 1739, and
                            Sept. 3, 1741; Charles’s letter to the Count, Nov. 26, 1737, and John’s
                            letter of Sept. 6, 1745. See also, <hi rend="italic">Dialogue between an
                                Antinomian and his Friend</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No.
                            102, Vol. 13 of this edn.</p>
                    </note> ran into <pb n="319"/>another,
                    affirming that ‘all true believers are not only saved from the <hi rend="italic">dominion</hi> of sin but from the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of inward as
                    well as outward sin, so that it no longer <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> in
                    them.’ And from them, about twenty years ago, many of our countrymen imbibed the
                    same opinion, that even the corruption of nature <hi rend="italic">is no
                        more</hi> in those who believe in Christ.</p>
                <p n="6">6. It is true that when the Germans<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., the Moravians.</p>
                    </note> were pressed
                    upon this head they soon allowed (many of them at least) that sin did still
                    remain <hi rend="italic">in the flesh</hi>, but not <hi rend="italic">in the
                        heart</hi> of a believer. And after a time, when the absurdity of this was
                    shown, they fairly gave up the point; allowing that sin did still <hi rend="italic">remain</hi>, though not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>, in him
                    that is born of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by
                                Faith</hi>, II.6; 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.2; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those that are Born
                            of God’, II.2; 43, <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of
                            Salvation</hi>, III.6-8; 74, ‘Of the Church’, §21; and 128, ‘The
                            Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, II.5. See also Wesley’s account of
                            Christian David’s beliefs, in JWJ, Aug. 10, 1738, where the same phrase
                            occurs: ‘though it [sin] did not reign, it did remain in
                    me.’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. But the English who had received it from them (some directly, some at
                    second or third hand) were not so easily prevailed upon to part with a favourite
                    opinion. And even when the generality of them were convinced it was utterly
                    indefensible, a few could not be persuaded to give it up, but maintain it to
                    this day.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">E.g.,
                            John Gambold had been a lively member of the Holy Club and the author of
                            a fine sermon, ‘On the Holy Spirit’ (1736), which Jackson published as
                            Wesley’s own (in his edn. of <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, VII.508-20).
                            Subsequently, Gambold became a pastor of the Moravians in England and,
                            finally, their bishop. There is a poignant record of Wesley’s last visit
                            with him in JWJ, Nov. 5, 1763—very close to the date of the reference
                            above.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. For the sake of these who really fear God and desire to know ‘the
                    truth as it is in Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:21.</p>
                    </note> it may not be amiss to
                    consider the point with calmness and impartiality. In doing this I use
                    indifferently the words ‘regenerate’, ‘justified’, or ‘believers’; since, though
                    they have not precisely the same meaning (the first <pb n="320"/>implying an
                    inward, <hi rend="italic">actual</hi> change; the second a <hi rend="italic">relative</hi> one; and the third the means whereby both the one and the
                    other are wrought) yet they come to one and the same thing, as everyone that
                    ‘believes’ is both ‘justified’ and ‘born of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">But see below, No. 18, ‘The
                            Marks of the New Birth’, where significant nuances of differentiation
                            between these terms may be found.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. By ‘sin’ I here understand inward sin:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s inventory of ‘inward’ sins
                            corresponds to what he speaks of elsewhere as ‘involuntary’ (as the
                            Lutherans had in their <hi rend="italic">Formula of Concord</hi>) and to
                            what the Romans had grouped under the heading of ‘venial’ at Trent,
                            Session V; see above, intro. and I.4 and n.</p>
                    </note> any sinful
                    temper, passion, or affection; such as pride, self-will, love of the world, in
                    any kind or degree; such as lust, anger, peevishness; any disposition contrary
                    to the mind which was in Christ.</p>
                <p n="3">3. The question is not concerning <hi rend="italic">outward sin</hi>,
                    whether a child of God <hi rend="italic">commits sin</hi> or no. We all agree
                    and earnestly maintain, ‘He that committeth sin is of the devil.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        3:8.</p>
                    </note> We agree, ‘Whosoever is born of God doth not commit
                        sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John
                            3:9.</p>
                    </note> Neither do we now inquire whether inward sin will <hi rend="italic">always</hi> remain in the children of God; whether sin will
                    continue in the soul <hi rend="italic">as long as</hi> it continues in the body.
                    Nor yet do we inquire whether a justified person may <hi rend="italic">relapse</hi> either into inward or outward sin. But simply this: is a
                    justified or regenerate man freed from <hi rend="italic">all sin</hi> as soon as
                    he is justified? Is there then no sin in his heart? Nor ever after, unless he
                    fall from grace?</p>
                <p n="4">4. We allow that the state of a justified person is inexpressibly great and
                    glorious. He is ‘born again, not of blood, nor of the flesh, nor of the will of
                    man, but of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 1:13.</p>
                    </note> He is a child of God, a
                    member of Christ, an heir of the kingdom of heaven. ‘The peace of God which
                    passeth all understanding keepeth his heart and mind in Christ Jesus.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil.
                            4:7.</p>
                    </note> His very ‘body is a temple of the Holy Ghost’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            6:19.</p>
                    </note> and ‘an habitation of God through the Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        2:22.</p>
                    </note> He is ‘created anew in Christ Jesus’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:10.</p>
                    </note> he is
                        <hi rend="italic">washed</hi>; he is <hi rend="italic">sanctified</hi>. His
                    ‘heart is purified by faith’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 15:9.</p>
                    </note> he is cleansed from ‘the
                    corruption that is in the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 1:4.</p>
                    </note> ‘The love of God is shed
                    abroad in his heart by the Holy Ghost which is given unto him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        5:5.</p>
                    </note> And so long as he ‘walketh in love’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 5:2.</p>
                    </note> (which he
                    may always do) he ‘worships God in <pb n="321"/>spirit and in truth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 4:23,
                            24.</p>
                    </note> He ‘keepeth the commandments of God, and doth those
                    things that are pleasing in his sight’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:22.</p>
                    </note> so ‘exercising
                    himself as to have a conscience void of offence toward God and toward man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts
                            24:16.</p>
                    </note> And he has power both over outward and inward sin,
                    even from the moment he is justified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. ‘But was he not then “freed from all sin”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:7.</p>
                    </note> so that
                    there is no sin in his heart?’ I cannot say this: I cannot believe it, because
                    St. Paul says the contrary. He is speaking to believers, and describing the
                    state of believers in general, when he says, ‘The flesh lusteth against the
                    spirit, and the spirit against the flesh: these are contrary the one to the
                        other.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 5:17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Nothing can be more express. The Apostle
                    here directly affirms that ‘the flesh’, evil nature, opposes ‘the spirit’, even
                    in believers; that even in the regenerate there are two principles ‘contrary the
                    one to the other’.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Again: when he writes to the believers at Corinth, to those who were
                    ‘sanctified in Christ Jesus’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor. 1:2.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> he says: ‘I,
                    brethren, could not speak unto you as unto spiritual, but as unto carnal, as
                    unto babes in Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Babes’ or ‘children’, ‘young men’, and ‘fathers’
                            in Christ is a frequent theme throughout Wesley’s writings. E.g., cf.
                            Nos. 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, I.4; 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian
                                Perfection</hi>, II.1; 55, <hi rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>,
                            §17; 83, ‘On Patience’, §10. See also JWJ, July 17, 1741, where Wesley
                            records he preached a sermon from 1 Cor. 3: ‘The school at Kingswood was
                            throughly filled between eight and nine in the evening. I showed them
                            from the example of the Corinthians what need we have to bear one with
                            another, seeing we are not to expect “many fathers in Christ,” no, nor
                            young men among us, as yet. We then poured out our souls in prayer and
                            praise, and our Lord did not hide his face from us.’ Cf. also his letter
                            to the Revd. Mr. Plenderlieth, May 23, 1768; to Joseph Benson, Mar. 16,
                            1771; to Elizabeth Briggs, May 31, 1771; and to John Fletcher, Mar. 22,
                            1775, and June 1, 1776. In his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Heb.
                            5:13-14, Wesley distinguishes the ‘babes’, ‘who desire and can digest
                            nothing but the doctrine of justification and imputed righteousness’
                            from those ‘of full age’, who embrace the ‘sublimer truths relating to
                            “perfection”’.</p>
                    </note>…. Ye are yet carnal: for whereas there is
                    among you envying and strife, […] are ye not carnal?’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[1 Cor.]
                                3:1, 3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Now here the Apostle speaks unto those who
                    were unquestionably believers, whom in the same breath he styles his ‘brethren
                    in Christ’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col.
                            1:2.</p>
                    </note> as being still in a measure <hi rend="italic">carnal</hi>. He affirms there was ‘envying’ (an evil temper) occasioning
                    ‘strife’ among them, and yet does not give the least intimation that they had
                    lost their faith. Nay, he manifestly declares they had not; for then they would
                    not <pb n="322"/>have been ‘babes in Christ’. And (what is most remarkable of
                    all) he speaks of being ‘carnal’ and ‘babes in Christ’ as one and the same
                    thing; plainly showing that every believer is (in a degree) ‘carnal’ while he is
                    only a ‘babe in Christ’.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Indeed this grand point, that there are two contrary principles in
                    believers—nature and grace, the flesh and the spirit—runs through all the
                    epistles of St. Paul, yea, through all the Holy Scriptures.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">For a rather different view of
                            the tension between nature and prevenient grace, see below, No. 85, ‘On
                            Working Out Our Own Salvation’, III.3-4.</p>
                    </note> Almost all the
                    directions and exhortations therein are founded on this supposition, pointing at
                    wrong tempers or practices in those who are, notwithstanding, acknowledged by
                    the inspired writers to be believers. And they are continually exhorted to fight
                    with and conquer these, by the power of the faith which was in them.</p>
                <p n="4">4. And who can doubt but there was faith in the angel of the church of
                        Ephesus<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., the pastor and congregation considered as a single <hi rend="italic">persona</hi>; cf. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> for Rev. 2:2-4.</p>
                    </note> when our Lord said to him: ‘I
                    know thy works, and thy labour, and thy patience…. Thou hast patience, and for
                    my name’s sake hast laboured and hast not fainted.’ But was there meantime no
                    sin in his heart? Yea, or Christ would not have added, ‘Nevertheless I have
                    somewhat against thee, because thou hast left thy first love.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev.
                                2:2-4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> This was real sin<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">All the contemporary editions
                            have ‘a real sin’, but the errata sheet in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>
                            (1771) calls for the ‘a’ to be deleted, as does the MS correction in
                            Wesley’s personal copy.</p>
                    </note> which God saw in his heart, of which
                    accordingly he is exhorted to <hi rend="italic">repent</hi>. And yet we have no
                    authority to say that even then he had no faith.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Nay, the angel of the church at Pergamos also is exhorted to ‘repent’,
                    which implies sin, though our Lord expressly says, ‘Thou hast not denied my
                        faith.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 13, 16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And to the angel of the church in
                    Sardis he says, ‘Strengthen the things which remain that are ready to die.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Rev.]
                                3:2.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The good which remained was ‘ready to die’, but
                    was not actually dead. So there was still a spark of faith even in him; which he
                    is accordingly commanded to ‘hold fast’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver. 3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Once more: when the Apostle exhorts believers to ‘cleanse’ themselves
                    ‘from all filthiness of flesh and spirit’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor. 7:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> he
                    plainly <pb n="323"/>teaches that those believers were not yet cleansed
                    therefrom. Will you answer, ‘He that “abstains from all appearance of evil”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess.
                            5:22.</p>
                    </note> does <hi rend="italic">ipso facto</hi> cleanse himself
                    from all filthiness’? Not in any wise. For instance, a man reviles me; I feel
                    resentment, which is ‘filthiness of spirit’; yet I say not a word. Here I
                    ‘abstain from all appearance of evil’, but this does not cleanse me from that
                    filthiness of spirit, as I experience to my sorrow.</p>
                <p n="7">7. And as this position, ‘there is no sin in a believer, no carnal mind, no
                    bent to backsliding,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The last phrase here is from Hos. 11:7; the entire
                            quotation appears to be Wesley’s own paraphrase of an antinomian view
                            (as, e.g., from Cudworth and Relly).</p>
                    </note> is thus contrary to the
                    Word of God, so it is to the <hi rend="italic">experience</hi> of his children.
                    These continually feel an heart bent to backsliding, a natural tendency to evil,
                    a proneness to depart from God, and cleave to the things of earth. They are
                    daily sensible of sin remaining in their heart, pride, self-will, unbelief, and
                    of sin cleaving to all they speak and do, even their best actions and holiest
                    duties. Yet at the same time they ‘know that they are of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:19.</p>
                    </note>
                    they cannot doubt of it for a moment. They feel ‘his Spirit clearly witnessing
                    with their spirit that they are the children of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p>
                    </note> They
                    ‘rejoice in God through Christ Jesus, by whom they have now received the
                        atonement’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:11.</p>
                    </note> So that they are equally assured that sin is
                    in them and that ‘Christ is in them, the hope of glory.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 1:27. The same point
                            as Luther’s <hi rend="italic">simul justus et
                    peccator</hi>.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. ‘But can Christ be in the same heart where sin is?’ Undoubtedly he can;
                    otherwise it never could be saved therefrom. Where the sickness is, there is the
                    physician,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Carrying on his work within,</l>
                    <l>Striving till he cast out sin.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                            <p rend="footnote text">‘Hymn for Whitsunday’, st. 4, ll. 3-4, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1739), p. 214 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.188). The metaphors here of
                                Christ the physician and of salvation as healing are significant;
                                they distinguish Wesley’s essentially interpersonal, therapeutic
                                views of justification, regeneration, and sanctification from all
                                their forensic alternatives; cf. No. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the
                                Heart’, I.5.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>Christ indeed cannot <hi rend="italic">reign</hi> where sin <hi rend="italic">reigns</hi>; neither will he <hi rend="italic">dwell</hi> where any sin is
                        <hi rend="italic">allowed</hi>. But he <hi rend="italic">is</hi> and <hi rend="italic">dwells</hi> in the heart of every believer who is fighting
                    against all sin; although it be ‘not’ yet ‘purified according to the
                    purification of the sanctuary’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Chr. 30:19.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">
                    <pb n="324"/>9. It has been observed before, that the opposite doctrine,
                    ‘that there is no sin in believers’, is quite <hi rend="italic">new</hi> in the
                    church of Christ; that it was never heard of for seventeen hundred years, never
                    till it was discovered by Count Zinzendorf. I do not remember to have seen the
                    least intimation of it either in any ancient or modern writer, unless perhaps in
                    some of the wild, ranting antinomians.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Such as Johannes Agricola (1494-1566), Tobias
                            Crisp (1600-43; cf. <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>, ‘extremely unguarded in
                            his expressions’), and John Saltmarsh (d. 1647; cf. <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>, ‘champion of complete religious liberty’).</p>
                    </note> And
                    these likewise say and unsay, acknowledging there is sin ‘in their flesh’,
                    although no sin ‘in their heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See I.5 above.</p>
                    </note> But whatever doctrine is
                        <hi rend="italic">new</hi> must be <hi rend="italic">wrong</hi>; for the <hi rend="italic">old</hi> religion is the only <hi rend="italic">true</hi> one;
                    and no doctrine can be right unless it is the very same ‘which was from the
                        beginning’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:1. That Wesley took ‘Christian antiquity’ as a decisive
                            guideline in theology and ethics may be seen, early and late, throughout
                            the corpus. On Jan. 24, 1738 (see JWJ) he had invoked his own version of
                            the ‘canon’ of Vincent of Lerins (first half of the fifth century) as ‘a
                            sure rule of interpreting Scripture, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>: <hi rend="italic">Consensus veterum: quod ab omnibus, quod ubique, quod
                                semper creditum…</hi>’ (‘the ancient consensus: what has been
                            believed by all, everywhere and always…’); cf. <hi rend="italic">The
                                Commonitory</hi> of Vincent of Lerins (435), ch. II, §6. See also
                            John Goodman, <hi rend="italic">The Old Religion…</hi> (1684), ‘To the
                            Reader’. In No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>,
                            I.2, Wesley will list Scripture, reason, and Christian experience as his
                            doctrinal norms. But in the Preface to his collected <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I (1771), the list will read: ‘Scripture, reason, and
                            Christian antiquity’. See also his letter to Walter Churchey (June 20,
                            1789): ‘In religion I am for as few innovations as possible;’ for other
                            references to doctrinal ‘novelty’, cf. No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’,
                            §1 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. One argument more against this new, unscriptural doctrine may be drawn
                    from the dreadful consequences of it. One says, ‘I felt anger today.’ Must I
                    reply, ‘Then you have no faith’? Another says, ‘I know what you advise is good;
                    but my will is quite averse to it.’ Must I tell him, ‘Then you are an
                    unbeliever, under the wrath and the curse of God’? What will be the natural
                    consequence of this? Why, if he believe what I say, his soul will not only be
                    grieved and wounded but perhaps utterly destroyed; inasmuch as he will ‘cast
                    away that confidence which hath great recompense of reward’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 10:35.</p>
                    </note> And
                    having cast away his shield, how shall he ‘quench the fiery darts of the wicked
                        one’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                            6:16 (cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note> How shall he
                    overcome the world?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See John 16:33.</p>
                    </note> Seeing ‘this is the
                    victory that overcometh the world, even our faith.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 5:4.</p>
                    </note> He
                    stands disarmed in the midst of his enemies, <pb n="325"/>open to all their
                    assaults. What wonder then if he be utterly overthrown, if they take him captive
                    at their will; yea, if he fall from one wickedness to another, and never see
                    good any more? I cannot therefore by any means receive this assertion ‘that
                    there is no sin in a believer from the moment he is justified’. First, because
                    it is contrary to the whole tenor of Scripture; secondly, because it is contrary
                    to the experience of the children of God; thirdly, because it is absolutely new,
                    never heard of in the world till yesterday; and lastly, because it is naturally
                    attended with the most fatal consequences, not only grieving those whom God
                        hath<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Orig.,
                            ‘had’, altered to ‘hath’ in 1771 only.</p>
                    </note> not grieved, but
                    perhaps dragging them into everlasting perdition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. However, let us give a fair hearing to the chief arguments of those
                    who endeavour to support it. And it is, first, from Scripture they attempt to
                    prove that there is no sin in a believer. They argue thus: ‘The Scripture says
                    every believer is “born of God”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:9; 4:7.</p>
                    </note> is “clean”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 15:3,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> is “holy”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:4, etc.</p>
                    </note> is “sanctified”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 15:16,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> is “pure in heart”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 5:8.</p>
                    </note> has a new heart, is a
                    temple of the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 6:19.</p>
                    </note> Now, as “that which is born
                    of the flesh is flesh”, is altogether evil, so “that which is born of the Spirit
                    is spirit”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            3:6.</p>
                    </note> is altogether good. Again: a man cannot be clean,
                    sanctified, holy, and at the same time unclean, unsanctified, unholy. He cannot
                    be pure and impure, or have a new and an old heart together. Neither can his
                    soul be unholy while it is a temple of the Holy Ghost.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This pejorative summary of
                            Moravian teachings should be compared with Zinzendorf’s public teaching,
                            as in <hi rend="italic">Nine Public Lectures on Important Subjects in
                                Religion, Preached in Fetter Lane Chapel in London, 1746</hi>, ed.,
                            G. W. Forell (Iowa City, Iowa, University of Iowa Press, 1973); see
                            espec. Lecture IV, ‘Concerning Saving Faith’, and Lecture VII, ‘On the
                            Essential Character and Circumstances of the Life of a Christian’.
                            Zinzendorf’s words and Wesley’s interpretation of them leave ground for
                            pondering: was Wesley reading Zinzendorf in the light of the antinomian
                            views of the <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Moravians?</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->I have
                    put this objection as strong as possible, that its full weight may appear. Let
                    us now examine it, part by part. And (1). <pb n="326"/>‘“That which is born of
                    the Spirit is spirit,” is altogether good.’ I allow the text, but not the
                    comment; for the text affirms this, and no more, that every man who is ‘born of
                    the Spirit’ is a <hi rend="italic">spiritual man</hi>. He is so. But so he may
                    be, and yet not be <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi> spiritual.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An interesting
                            inversion of Wesley’s earlier doctrine of the <hi rend="italic">radical</hi> difference between ‘almost’ and ‘altogether’
                            Christians; cf. No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>,
                            proem.</p>
                    </note> The Christians at <hi rend="italic">Corinth</hi> were
                        <hi rend="italic">spiritual</hi> men; else they had been no Christians at
                    all. And yet they were not <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi> spiritual: they
                    were still (in part) <hi rend="italic">carnal</hi>. ‘But they were fallen from
                        grace.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 5:4.</p>
                    </note> St. Paul says, ‘No: they were even then “babes in
                        Christ”.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 3:1.</p>
                    </note> (2). ‘But a man cannot be clean, sanctified, holy,
                    and at the same time unclean, unsanctified, unholy.’ Indeed he may. So the
                    Corinthians were. ‘Ye are washed,’ says the Apostle, ‘ye are sanctified;’ namely
                    cleansed from ‘fornication, idolatry, drunkenness’, and all other outward
                        sin.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1
                                Cor 6:9, 10, 11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And yet at the same time, in
                    another sense of the word, they were <hi rend="italic">unsanctified</hi>: they
                    were not <hi rend="italic">washed</hi>, not inwardly <hi rend="italic">cleansed</hi> from envy, evil surmising, partiality. ‘But sure they had not
                    a new heart and an old heart together.’ It is most sure they had; for at that
                    very time their hearts were <hi rend="italic">truly</hi>, yet not <hi rend="italic">entirely</hi>, renewed. Their carnal mind was nailed to the
                    cross; yet it was not wholly destroyed. ‘But could they be <hi rend="italic">unholy</hi> while they were “temples of the Holy Ghost”?’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor.
                                6:19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Yes, that they were ‘temples of the Holy
                    Ghost’ is certain. And it is equally certain they were, in some degree, <hi rend="italic">carnal</hi>, that is, <hi rend="italic">unholy</hi>.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘However, there is one Scripture more which will put the matter out of
                    question: “If any man be (a believer) in Christ, he is a new creature. Old
                    things are passed away; behold all things are become new.”<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Cor.
                                5:17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Now certainly a man cannot be a <hi rend="italic">new creature</hi> and an <hi rend="italic">old creature</hi>
                    at once.’ Yes, he may: he may be <hi rend="italic">partly renewed</hi>, which
                    was the very case with those at Corinth. They were doubtless ‘renewed in the
                    spirit of their mind’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:23.</p>
                    </note> or they could not have been
                    so much as ‘babes in Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 3:1.</p>
                    </note> Yet they had not the whole
                    mind which was in Christ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> for they <hi rend="italic">envied</hi> one another. ‘But it is said expressly, “Old
                    things are passed away: all things <pb n="327"/>are become new.”’ But we must
                    not so interpret the Apostle’s words as to make him contradict himself. And if
                    we will make him consistent with himself the plain meaning of the words is this:
                    his <hi rend="italic">old judgment</hi> (concerning justification, holiness,
                    happiness, indeed concerning the things of God in general) is now ‘passed away’;
                    so are his <hi rend="italic">old desires</hi>, <hi rend="italic">designs</hi>,
                        <hi rend="italic">affections</hi>, <hi rend="italic">tempers</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">conversation</hi>. All these are undeniably ‘become new’,
                    greatly changed from what they were. And yet, though they are <hi rend="italic">new</hi>, they are not <hi rend="italic">wholly</hi> new. Still he feels,
                    to his sorrow and shame, remains of the ‘old man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:9.</p>
                    </note> too
                    manifest taints of his former tempers and affections, a law in his members which
                    frequently <hi rend="italic">fights</hi> against that law of his mind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rom.
                            7:23.</p>
                    </note> though it cannot ‘gain any advantage’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 2:11.</p>
                    </note> over
                    him as long as he ‘watches unto prayer’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 4:7.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. This whole argument, ‘If he is clean, he is clean,’ ‘if he is holy, he
                    is holy’ (and twenty more expressions of the same kind may easily be heaped
                    together) is really no better than playing upon words: it is the fallacy of
                    arguing from a <hi rend="italic">particular</hi> to a <hi rend="italic">general</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Yet another reminder of Wesley’s days as ‘Moderator
                            of the Classes’ (i.e., logical disputations) at Lincoln College. He had
                            mastered Dean Henry Aldrich’s <hi rend="italic">Artis Logicae
                                Compendiae</hi> (1691) and, indeed, had translated it into English
                            in 1750 for use in the Kingswood School; cf. <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 186 (Vol. 15 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note> of
                    inferring a general conclusion from particular premises. Propose the sentence
                    entire, and it runs thus: ‘If he is holy <hi rend="italic">at all</hi>, he is
                    holy <hi rend="italic">altogether</hi>.’ That does not follow: every babe in
                    Christ is holy, and yet not altogether so. He is saved from sin; yet not
                    entirely: it <hi rend="italic">remains</hi>, though it does not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>. If you think it does not <hi rend="italic">remain</hi> (in <hi rend="italic">babes</hi> at least, whatever be the case
                    with <hi rend="italic">young men</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">fathers</hi>) you
                    certainly have not considered the height and depth and length and breadth of the
                    law of God (even the law of love laid down by St. Paul in the thirteenth of
                    Corinthians); and that ‘every ἀνομία’, disconformity to, or deviation from this
                    law, ‘is sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 3:4.</p>
                    </note> Now, is there no disconformity to this in
                    the heart or life of a believer? What may be in an adult Christian is another
                    question. But what a stranger must he be to human nature who can possibly
                    imagine that this is the case with every babe in Christ!<pb n="328"/>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">What follows for some pages is an answer to a paper published in
                                the <hi rend="italic">Christian</hi>’s [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>]
                                    <hi rend="italic">Magazine</hi>, pp. 577-82. I am surprised Mr.
                                Dodd should give such a paper a place in his magazine which is
                                directly contrary to our Ninth Article.</p>
                            <p rend="endnote text">[William Dodd is more famous for the spectacularly tragic ending of
                                his career (his trial and execution as a forger) than for his
                                earlier successes as a popular Anglican preacher whose ‘eloquent and
                                touching’ sermons ‘in the French style’ were praised by Horace
                                Walpole (<hi rend="italic">Letters</hi>, III.282; cf. Leslie
                                Stephens’s biography of Dodd, <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>. Wesley had
                                known him since 1756, and there had been a running controversy
                                between them about Wesley’s doctrine of Christian perfection and
                                also about Wesley’s separatist tendencies. Wesley’s account of his
                                pastoral visits with Dr. Dodd during his last days and at his
                                execution was published in <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>, 1783, pp.
                                358-60 (see Vol. 14 of this edn.).</p>
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Dodd
                                was editor of the <hi rend="italic">Christian Magazine</hi>,
                                1760-67, and in its <hi rend="italic">Supplement…for the Year
                                    1762</hi> (pp. 577-82) published an article, ‘Thoughts on
                                Christianity’, by one ‘C.’ (does this signify ‘Christian’ or,
                                perhaps, William Cudworth?). Unsurprisingly, ‘C.’s’ arguments are
                                more carefully nuanced than one could guess from Wesley’s excerpts,
                                even though their essential consequence is not misrepresented by
                                much. And his stated aims (p. 582), to undercut hypocrisy, to
                                abolish ‘antinomianism’, and to end ‘the great contest about
                                inherent and imputed righteousness’, were not very different from
                                Wesley’s own, especially in his later years. What is most
                                significant here is that when Wesley was confronted with a clear and
                                forceful doctrine of sinless perfection, his repudiation of it was
                                immediate and vigorous.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘But believers “walk after
                    the Spirit”,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 8:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and the Spirit of God
                        <hi rend="italic">dwells</hi> in them. Consequently they are delivered from
                    the guilt, the power, <hi rend="italic">or</hi>,<hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve"> in one word</hi>, the being of
                        sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C.’s’
                            text (p. 579): ‘…all who are united to Christ by the holy spirits [<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>] dwelling in them are delivered from the
                            guilt, the power or, in one word, the being of sin.’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->These
                    are coupled together as if they were the same thing. But they are not the same
                    thing. The <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> is one thing, the <hi rend="italic">power</hi> another, and the <hi rend="italic">being</hi> yet another. That
                    believers are delivered from the <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">power</hi> of sin we allow; that they are delivered from the
                        <hi rend="italic">being</hi> of it we deny. Nor does it in any wise follow
                    from these texts. A man may have the Spirit of God <hi rend="italic">dwelling</hi> in him, and may ‘walk after the Spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:1.</p>
                    </note> though he
                    still feels ‘the flesh lusting against the Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘But the “church is the body of Christ”.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Col. 1:24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    This implies that its members are washed from all filthiness; otherwise it will
                    follow that Christ and Belial are incorporated with each other.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C’s’ text: ‘From
                            the church being called “the body of Christ” (Col. 1:24), which
                            undoubtedly implies that all the members of it are washed from all
                            filthiness, or else that blasphemous consequence would follow, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, Christ and Belial are not only connected
                            but in some sense incorporated with each other.’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->Nay, it
                    will not follow from hence—‘Those who are the mystical body of Christ still feel
                    the flesh lusting against the <pb n="329"/>Spirit’—that Christ has any
                    fellowship with the devil, or with that sin which he enables them to resist and
                    overcome.</p>
                <p n="6">6. ‘But are not Christians “come to the heavenly Jerusalem”, where “nothing
                    defiled can enter”?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 21:27. ‘C.’s’ text: ‘It seems by the
                            heavenly Jerusalem here we are to understand the Gospel church [i.e., on
                            earth]…since it is said (Hebrews 12:22) that the kings of the earth
                            shall bring their glory into this city, which cannot with propriety be
                            said of the church triumphant, they having there no more glory than the
                            meanest subject.’</p>
                    </note> Yes; ‘and to an innumerable company of
                    angels’, ‘and to the spirits of just men made perfect’:<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb.
                                12:22-23.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> that is,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Earth and heaven all agree,</l>
                    <l>All his one great family.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Cf. ‘The Communion of Saints, Pt. VI’, st. 1,
                                last quatrain, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi>
                                (1740), p. 198 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.364).
                                Orig.:</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                    <l>Him let earth and heaven proclaim,</l>
                    <l>Earth and heaven accord his name,</l>
                    <l>Let us both in this agree,</l>
                    <l>Both his one great family.</l>
                </lg>
                <p rend="footnote text">For quotations of other lines from this hymn, cf. Nos. 107,
                    ‘On God’s Vineyard’, II.6; and 132, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:1’, §6.</p>
                <p>And they are likewise holy and <hi rend="italic">undefiled</hi> while they ‘walk
                    after the Spirit’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:1.</p>
                    </note> although sensible there is
                    another principle in them, and that ‘these are contrary to each other’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal.
                        5:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. ‘But Christians are “reconciled to God”.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:10; 2 Cor.
                        5:20.</p>
                    </note> Now this could not be if any of the “carnal mind”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:7.</p>
                    </note> remained; for this “is enmity against God”. Consequently no
                    reconciliation can be effected but by its total destruction.’</p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->We ‘are
                    reconciled to God through the blood of the cross’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 1:20.</p>
                    </note> And
                    in that moment, the φρόνημα σαρκός,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:7; cf. I.3 above and n.</p>
                    </note> the
                    corruption of nature which is ‘enmity with God’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 4:4.</p>
                    </note> is put
                    under our feet. The flesh has ‘no more dominion over us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom 6:9.</p>
                    </note> But it
                    still <hi rend="italic">exists</hi>; and it is still in its nature enmity with
                    God, lusting against his Spirit.</p>
                <p n="8">8. ‘But “they that are Christ’s have crucified the flesh, with its
                    affections and lusts.”’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Gal. 5:24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> They have so; yet it
                    remains in them still, and often struggles to break from the cross. ‘Nay, but
                    they have <pb n="330"/>“put off the old man with his deeds.”’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Col.
                                3:9.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> They have; and in the sense above-described,
                    ‘old things are passed away; all things are become new.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:17.</p>
                    </note> An
                    hundred texts may be cited to the same effect. And they will all admit of the
                    same answer. ‘But, to say all in one word, “Christ gave himself for the church,
                    that…it might be holy and without blemish.”’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Eph. 5:25, 27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And so
                    it will be in the end: but it never was yet, from the beginning to this day.</p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘But let <hi rend="italic">experience</hi> speak: all who are justified
                    do at that time find an absolute freedom from all sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C.’s’ text (p. 581): ‘nine
                            out of ten, at least’.</p>
                    </note> That I doubt; but if they do, do they
                    find it ever after? Else you gain nothing. ‘If they do not, it is their own
                    fault.’ That remains to be proved.</p>
                <p n="10">10. ‘But, in the very nature of things, can a man have pride in him, and
                    not be proud? Anger, and yet not be angry?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C.’s’ text: ‘Suppose anyone should assert
                            that a man may have anger in him, yet not be angry; pride in him, yet
                            not be proud; the love of the world in him, yet not love the world; what
                            should we think of such an one’s understanding?’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->A man
                    may have <hi rend="italic">pride</hi> in him, may think of himself in <hi rend="italic">some particulars</hi> above what he ought to think (and so be
                        <hi rend="italic">proud</hi> in that particular) and yet not be a proud man
                    in his <hi rend="italic">general</hi> character. He may have <hi rend="italic">anger</hi> in him, yea, and a strong propensity to furious anger, without
                        <hi rend="italic">giving way</hi> to it. ‘But can anger and pride be in that
                    heart where <hi rend="italic">only</hi> meekness and humility are felt?’ No; but
                        <hi rend="italic">some</hi> pride and anger may be in that heart where there
                    is <hi rend="italic">much</hi> humility and meekness.</p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->‘It
                    avails not to say these tempers <hi rend="italic">are</hi> there, but they do
                    not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>; for sin cannot in any kind or degree <hi rend="italic">exist</hi> where it does not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>; for
                        <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">power</hi> are essential
                    properties of sin. Therefore where one of them is, all must be.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C.’s’ text (pp.
                            581-82): ‘It will not mend the matter at all to say, “these tempers <hi rend="italic">are</hi> there but they do not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>…”. [This] implies a contradiction, for it is an
                            infallible axiom that sin cannot, in any kind or degree, <hi rend="italic">exist</hi> where it does not <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>, no more than fire can live where it does not burn.
                            Guilt and power being essential properties of sin, it follows that where
                            one of them is they all necessarily must be, and where anyone is
                            wanting, none of them can be there; for to separate these is to separate
                            a thing from itself.’ ‘C.’s’ contention here is that conscious and
                            unconscious sinful tempers cannot be dichotomized; on the other hand,
                            such a dichotomy is one of Wesley’s crucial
                    presuppositions.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->Strange
                    indeed! ‘Sin cannot in any kind or degree <hi rend="italic">exist</hi> where it
                        <pb n="331"/>does not <hi rend="italic">reign’</hi>? Absolutely contrary
                    this to all experience, all Scripture, all common sense. Resentment of an
                    affront is sin. It is ἀνομία, disconformity to the law of love.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See IV.3
                            above.</p>
                    </note> This has existed in me a thousand times. Yet it did
                    not, and does not, <hi rend="italic">reign</hi>. But ‘<hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> and <hi rend="italic">power</hi> are essential properties of
                    sin; therefore where one is, all must be.’ No; in the instance before us, if the
                    resentment I feel is not yielded to, even for a moment, there is no <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> at all, no condemnation from God upon that account.
                    And in this case it has no <hi rend="italic">power</hi>: though it ‘lusteth
                    against the Spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:17.</p>
                    </note> it cannot prevail. Here,
                    therefore, as in ten thousand instances, there is <hi rend="italic">sin</hi>
                    without either <hi rend="italic">guilt</hi> or <hi rend="italic">power</hi>.</p>
                <p n="11">11. ‘But the supposing sin in a believer is pregnant with everything
                    frightful and discouraging. It implies the contending with a power that has the
                    possession of our strength, maintains his usurpation of our hearts, and there
                    prosecutes the war in defiance of our Redeemer.’ Not so. The supposing sin is
                        <hi rend="italic">in</hi> us does not imply that it has the possession of
                    our strength; no more than a man crucified has the possession of those that
                    crucify him. As little does it imply that sin ‘maintains its usurpation of our
                    hearts’. The usurper is dethroned. He <hi rend="italic">remains</hi> indeed
                    where he once reigned; but remains <hi rend="italic">in chains</hi>. So that he
                    does in some sense ‘prosecute the war’, yet he grows weaker and weaker, while
                    the believer goes on from strength to strength, conquering and to conquer.</p>
                <p n="12">12. ‘I am not satisfied yet. He that has sin in him is a slave to sin.
                    Therefore you suppose a man to be justified while he is a slave to sin. Now if
                    you allow men may be justified while they have pride, anger, or unbelief in
                    them—nay if you aver these are (at least for a time) in all that are
                    justified—what wonder that we have so many proud, angry, unbelieving
                        believers!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘C.’s’ text: ‘Is it to be wondered at if those who are prepossessed
                            with such apprehensions should either decline the Christian warfare or
                            faint in the day of battles; either not prepare to stand in the evil day
                            or, having done so, not be able to stand?’ Is Wesley’s quotation here a
                            very free paraphrase of his own, or is he quoting yet another source?
                            The same question may be asked of the remaining quotations, since none
                            of them appears verbatim in ‘C.’s’ text.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->I do
                    not suppose any man who is justified is a slave to sin. Yet I do suppose sin
                    remains (at least for a time) in all that are justified. ‘But if sin remains in
                    a believer he is a sinful man: if pride, for instance, then he is proud; if
                    self-will, then he is self-willed; if unbelief, then he is an
                    unbeliever—consequently, no believer at <pb n="332"/>all. How then does he
                    differ from unbelievers, from unregenerate men?’</p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->This is
                    still mere playing upon words. It means no more than, ‘If there is sin, pride,
                    self-will in him, then—there is sin, pride, self-will.’ And this nobody can
                    deny. In <hi rend="italic">that sense</hi>, then, he is proud or self-willed.
                    But he is not proud or self-willed in the same sense that unbelievers are, that
                    is, <hi rend="italic">governed</hi> by pride or self-will. Herein he differs
                    from unregenerate men. They <hi rend="italic">obey</hi> sin; he does not. Flesh
                    is in them both. But they ‘walk after the flesh’; he ‘walks after the
                    Spirit’.</p>
                <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->‘But
                    how can <hi rend="italic">unbelief</hi> be in a <hi rend="italic">believer</hi>?’ That word has two meanings. It means either <hi rend="italic">no faith</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">little faith</hi>; either the <hi rend="italic">absence</hi> of faith, or the <hi rend="italic">weakness</hi>
                    of it. In the former sense, unbelief is not in a believer; in the latter, it is
                    in all babes. Their faith is commonly mixed with doubt or fear, that is (in the
                    latter sense) with unbelief. ‘Why are ye fearful,’ says our Lord, ‘O ye of
                    little faith?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 8:26.</p>
                    </note> Again, ‘O thou of little faith, wherefore didst
                    thou doubt?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 14:31.</p>
                    </note> You see, here was <hi rend="italic">unbelief</hi> in <hi rend="italic">believers</hi>: little faith and much
                        unbelief.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. this defence of gradations [degrees] of faith (and the validity of
                            even a low degree of it) with No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost
                                Christian</hi> and with Wesley’s earlier either/or doctrine of
                            assurance. Cf. also JWJ, May 29, June 6, 1738; the <hi rend="italic">Minutes</hi>, Aug. 2, 1745 (answer to <hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> 5)
                            and June 16, 1747 (answer to <hi rend="italic">Q.</hi>2, 5); and his
                            letters to Richard Tompson, July 25, 1755, and Feb. 5,
                    1756.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. ‘But this doctrine—that sin remains in a believer, that a man may be
                    in the favour of God while he has sin in his heart—certainly tends to encourage
                    men in sin.’ Understand the proposition right, and no such consequence follows.
                    A man may be in God’s favour though he <hi rend="italic">feel</hi> sin; but not
                    if he <hi rend="italic">yields</hi> to it. <hi rend="italic">Having sin</hi>
                    does not forfeit the favour of God; <hi rend="italic">giving way to sin</hi>
                    does. Though the flesh in <hi rend="italic">you</hi> ‘lust against the Spirit’,
                    you may still be a child of God. But if you ‘walk after the flesh’, you are a
                    child of the devil. Now, this doctrine does not encourage to <hi rend="italic">obey</hi> sin, but to <hi rend="italic">resist</hi> it with all our
                    might.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p n="1">V. 1. The sum of all is this: there are in every person, even after he is
                    justified, two contrary principles, nature and grace, termed by St. Paul the
                    ‘flesh’ and the ‘spirit’. Hence although even babes in Christ are <hi rend="italic">sanctified</hi>, yet it is only <hi rend="italic">in
                    part</hi>. In a degree, according to the measure of their faith, they are <hi rend="italic">spiritual</hi>; yet in a degree they are <hi rend="italic">carnal</hi>. Accordingly, believers are continually exhorted to <pb n="333"/>watch against the flesh, as well as the world and the devil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Litany.</p>
                    </note> And to
                    this agrees the constant experience of the children of God. While they feel this
                    witness in themselves they feel a will not wholly resigned to the will of God.
                    They know they are in him, and yet find an heart ready to depart from him, a
                    proneness to evil in many instances, and a backwardness to that which is good.
                    The contrary doctrine is wholly <hi rend="italic">new</hi>; never heard of in
                    the church of Christ from the time of his coming into the world till the time of
                    Count Zinzendorf.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See above, I.5 and n., and III.9 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                    And it is attended with the most fatal consequences. It cuts off all watching
                    against our evil nature, against the Delilah which we are told is gone, though
                    she is still lying in our bosom.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Judg. 16. Cf. also Matthew Mead, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian Discovered</hi>, p. 107: ‘There is a natural
                            man, let him go never so far, let him go never so much in matters of
                            religion, but still he hath his Delilah, his bosom lust.’ For Wesley’s
                            use of ‘bosom sin’, cf. No. 48, ‘Self-denial’, II.2 and n.</p>
                    </note> It
                    tears away the shield of weak believers, deprives them of their faith,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            6:16.</p>
                    </note> and so leaves them exposed to all the assaults of the
                    world, the flesh, and the devil.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Let us therefore hold fast the sound doctrine ‘once delivered to the
                        saints’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jude 3.</p>
                    </note> and delivered down by them with the written word to
                    all succeeding generations: that although we are renewed, cleansed, purified,
                    sanctified, the moment we truly believe in Christ, yet we are not then renewed,
                    cleansed, purified altogether; but the flesh, the evil nature, still remains
                    (though subdued) and wars against the Spirit<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">As explicit a version of the ‘saved and yet
                            also a sinner at one and the same time’ as one might ask for. This
                            should be compared to other passages where Wesley himself comes closer
                            to claiming for Christians ‘the power not to sin’ or, indeed, close
                            enough to a doctrine of sinless perfection as to allow for its
                            development in some of his nineteenth-century followers, in his name.
                            Cf. Nos. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.20,
                            III.2; 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.1-30; 42,
                            ‘Satan’s Devices’, I.1; and see 109, <hi rend="italic">The Trouble and
                                Rest of Good Men</hi>, II.4 (which stands almost in contrast on this
                            point to the sermon on <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>). Cf.
                            also <hi rend="italic">A Plain Account of Christian Perfection</hi>; <hi rend="italic">The Principles of a Methodist</hi>, §§11-12; and <hi rend="italic">Some Remarks on a Defence of…Aspasio Vindicated</hi>,
                            §4. Wesley’s prefaces to the earliest editions of the <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> contain some of the strongest, least
                            nuanced statements of perfection in the Wesley corpus; without the
                            phrase itself, they come close to advocating ‘sinless perfection’ (see
                                <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, Nos. 13, 40, 54, and the text in
                            Vol. 12 of this edn.). Cf. also his letter to Revd. Mr. Plenderlieth,
                            May 23, 1768, and to Thomas Olivers, Mar. 24, 1757.</p>
                    </note> So much
                    the more let us use all diligence in ‘fighting the good fight of faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim.
                            6:12.</p>
                    </note> So much the <pb n="334"/>more earnestly let us ‘watch
                    and pray’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:41; Mark 13:33.</p>
                    </note> against the enemy within. The more
                    carefully let us ‘take to’ ourselves and ‘put on the whole armour of God’; that
                    although ‘we wrestle’ both with ‘flesh and blood, and with principalities and
                    powers, and wicked spirits in high places, we may be able to withstand in the
                    evil day, and having done all, to stand’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 6:11-13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>