<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 47: Heaviness through Manifold Temptations</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 47: Heaviness through Manifold
                                Temptations</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="202" to="204"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="222" to="235"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p n="">Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a
                combination of OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these
                docx into XML using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched
                them up manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:202"/>
            <introduction>
                <p><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 46-47]</hi></p>
                <p>Like that of true love, the course of true <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> never did
                    run smooth (cf. Thomas Goodwin, <hi rend="italic">A Child of Light Walking in
                        Darkness</hi> (1636); abridged by Wesley in the <hi rend="italic">Christian
                        Library</hi> (1751), Vol. XI; and Hugh Binning, <hi rend="italic">Fellowship
                        With God</hi>, especially Sermon XIV). There is, therefore, a natural
                    progress in following a sermon on conversion with two further comments on the
                    peaks and valleys in a Christian pilgrim’s progress. That is the point to this
                    particular pair of sermons, Nos. 46, ‘The Wilderness State’, and 47, ‘Heaviness
                    through Manifold Temptations’. By 1760 Wesley knew, from long experience, how
                    regularly any stress on the <hi rend="italic">necessity</hi> of assurance would
                    raise the levels of religious anxiety amongst his hearers and disciples. Even
                    earlier, he had pondered Thomas à Kempis’s generalization (<hi rend="italic"
                        >Imitation</hi>, II. ix. 7): ‘I never found anyone so religious and devout
                    that he had not sometimes a withdrawing of grace or felt not some decrease of
                    zeal.’ He also remembered how quickly the euphoria of his own Aldersgate
                    experience had passed (cf. JWJ, May 26, 1738, ‘My soul continued in peace, but
                    yet in heaviness because of manifold temptations,’ and May 28, ‘I waked in
                    peace, but not in joy’).</p>
                <p>Thus, wary though he was of allegorizing, he found himself turning to the Old
                    Testament story of the sojourn of the Children of Israel in the wilderness of
                    Sinai as a metaphor for the anxieties and depressions that follow upon ‘the new
                    birth’. This allegory was already a familiar one among the Puritans. There was,
                    e.g., Samuel Mather’s <hi rend="italic">Figures or Types of the Old
                        Testament</hi> (Dublin, 1683); Mather had understood ‘wilderness’ to mean
                    ‘the wilderness of this world’ through which ‘Christ directs and conducts his
                    people in their travels…to the true Canaan’ (p. 170; cf. p. 192). Thus it was
                    clear to him that just ‘as the Ark of God had led [the Israelites] through the
                    Wilderness, so we are to follow the guidance of Christ through the world’ (p.
                    510). Mather had also cited (pp. 200-201) a quite different interpretation in
                    Jeremiah Burroughs (whom Wesley also knew) in <hi rend="italic">The Excellency
                        of </hi><pb n="02:203"/><hi rend="italic">Holy Courage in Evil Times</hi>
                    (1661), where ‘the wilderness state’ is understood as ‘an unregenerate
                    condition’ before conversion (cf. chs. 25-26 and Burroughs’s comments on Heb.
                    11:27). In Robert Gell’s <hi rend="italic">Remaines</hi>, I.16, the reference
                    had been transferred from the wilderness of Sinai to Jesus’ experience of ‘forty
                    days and nights’ in the wilderness of Judea. Wesley had followed Gell in this,
                    at least once, in Bristol (cf. JWJ, March 28, 1740): ‘From these words, “Then
                    was Jesus led by the Spirit into the wilderness to be tempted of the devil,” I
                    took occasion to describe that wilderness state, that state of doubts and fears
                    and strong temptations which so many go through, though in different degrees,
                    after they have received remission of sins.’</p>
                <p>From none of these sources, however, could one have anticipated Wesley’s
                    uncommonly sharp distinction, now in 1760, between ‘the wilderness state’ as
                    ‘darkness’ (i.e., an actual ‘loss of faith’ and ‘a total loss of joy’; in
                    effect, a relapse from faith into unfaith that simply reverses the positive
                    processes of salvation) and ‘heaviness’ (religious depression) which is more or
                    less normal, and thus not a valid ground for prolonged anxiety or despair. But
                    this is the distinction which is expounded, along with its psychological
                    implications, in the two sermons here (and also, presumably, in his thirty-five
                    oral sermons on John 16:22). It had been summarized in the manuscript Minutes of
                    1744 (<hi rend="italic">Q.</hi> and <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> 10) and then
                    commented on in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>: ‘This [John 16:22] gives
                    us no manner of authority to assert that all believers <hi rend="italic"
                        >must</hi> come into a state of darkness. They never <hi rend="italic"
                        >need</hi> lose either their peace or their love, or the witness that they
                    are the children of God. They can never lose these, but either through sin, or
                    ignorance, or vehement temptation, or bodily disorders.’ This same idea will be
                    repeated in letters to Mrs. Marston, August 11, 1770, and to Rebecca Yeoman,
                    February 5, 1772 (who is urged to read ‘The Wilderness State’ in ‘the fourth
                    volume, and examine yourself thereby’). Charles Wesley, however, had understood
                    ‘the wilderness state’ rather as Gell had done: ‘that [condition] into which the
                    believer is generally led by the Spirit to be tempted as soon as he is baptized
                    by the Holy Ghost’ (CWJ, August 26, 1739).</p>
                <p>It would be interesting to know how John Wesley understood his own episodes of
                    acute religious anxiety. By 1780 he could ‘not remember to have felt lowness of
                    spirits for one quarter of an hour since I was born’ (see No. 77, ‘Spiritual
                    Worship’, III.2). Actually, though, he has been through <hi rend="italic"
                        >many</hi> such episodes both early and late (as in his letter to
                    ‘Varanese’, February 6, 1736; or, in JWJ, January 4, 1739; or, again, in a
                    letter to Elizabeth Hardy, May 1758: ‘I felt the wrath of God abiding on me. I
                    was afraid of dropping into hell;’ and another to Mrs. <pb n="02:204"/>Ryan,
                    November 4, 1758). The most remarkable of these is mirrored in an outburst to
                    his brother Charles, June 26, 1766: ‘In one of [[my]] last [letters] [[I]] was
                    saying, [[I]] do not feel the wrath of God abiding on [[me]]…. [[I do not love
                    God. I never did]]…. [[I have no]] direct witness… [[I]] have no more fear than
                    love. Or if [[I have any fear, it is not that of falling]] into hell, but of
                    falling into nothing.’ (The words within double brackets are transcribed from
                    shorthand.) Was this a case of ‘heaviness’ or ‘darkness’, or what?</p>
                <p>‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’ is the linked sequel to ‘The Wilderness
                    State’, designed to help believers avoid any further slide from depression into
                    ‘darkness’ or sinful despair. Thus, it seeks to lay out ‘the wide and essential
                    difference between “darkness” and “heaviness”’. He had already done this in
                    sixteen oral sermons on 1 Pet. 1:6 between 1754 and 1757, which suggests that
                    the problem of religious anxiety had become more widespread and urgent in and
                    after the upswing in ‘professors of perfection’ in 1755. At any rate, this
                    particular pair of sermons seems to have been written expressly for <hi
                        rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV (1760). They were reprinted in <hi rend="italic"
                        >Works</hi> (1771), IV, and again in <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, IV (1787),
                    but were not otherwise printed separately.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:222"/>
            <head>Heaviness through Manifold Temptations</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p n="">1 Peter 1:6</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Now for a season, if need be, ye are in heaviness through
                        manifold temptations.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">1. In the preceding discourse I have particularly spoken of that <hi
                        rend="italic">darkness</hi> of mind into which those are often observed to
                    fall who once walked in the light of God’s countenance. Nearly related to this
                    is the <hi rend="italic">heaviness</hi> of soul which is still more common, even
                    among believers; indeed almost all the children of God experience this in an
                    higher or lower degree. And so great is the resemblance between one and the
                    other that they are frequently confounded together; and we are apt to say
                    indifferently, ‘Such an one is in <hi rend="italic">darkness</hi>, or such an
                    one is in <hi rend="italic">heaviness</hi>,’ as if they were equivalent terms,
                    one of which implied no more than the other.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1"
                        n="1"><p rend="footnote text">Matthew Poole had not confounded the two
                            notions; his point was that ‘darkness’ has two different meanings that
                            ought to be distinguished by context: ‘Walking in darkness is
                            [sometimes] put for living in wickedness (John 1:6); [the other sense]
                            is being in misery, which also frequently cometh under the name of
                            “darkness”: that liveth in a most disconsolate and calamitous condition,
                            together with great despondency or dejection of spirit’ (<hi
                                rend="italic">Annotations</hi> on Isa. 50:10). But this is an
                            episode from which the steadfast believer can hope to be delivered,
                            ‘especially in the free grace, mercy, and faithfulness of the
                            Lord…’.</p></note> But they are far, very far from it. Darkness is one
                    thing; heaviness is another. There is a difference, yea a wide, an essential
                    difference, between the former and the latter. And such a difference it is as
                    all the children of God are deeply concerned to understand; otherwise nothing
                    will be more easy than for them to slide out of heaviness into darkness.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s letter
                            to Mary Bishop, Sept. 13, 1774: ‘The difference between heaviness and
                            darkness of soul (the wilderness state) should never be forgotten.
                            Darkness…seldom comes on us but by our own fault…. Heaviness…may be
                            occasioned by a thousand circumstances, such as frequently neither our
                            wisdom can foresee nor our power prevent? Cf. below, V.1.</p></note> In
                    order to prevent this I will endeavour to show,</p>
                <p>I. What manner of persons those were to whom the Apostle says, ‘Ye are in
                    heaviness.’</p>
                <p>II. What kind of ‘heaviness’ they were in.</p>
                <p>III. What were the causes, and</p>
                <p>IV. What were the ends of it.</p>
                <p>I shall conclude with some inferences.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1"><pb n="02:223"/>I. 1. I am in the first place to show what manner of
                    persons those were to whom the Apostle says, ‘Ye are in heaviness.’ And, first,
                    it is beyond all dispute that they were believers at the time the Apostle thus
                    addressed them. For so he expressly says, verse five: Ye ‘who are kept through
                    the power of God by <hi rend="italic">faith</hi> unto salvation’. Again, verse
                    seven, he mentions ‘the trial of their <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>, much more
                    precious than that of gold which perisheth’. And yet again, verse nine, he
                    speaks of their ‘receiving the end of their <hi rend="italic">faith</hi>, the
                    salvation of their souls’. At the same time, therefore, that they were ‘in
                    heaviness’, they were possessed of living faith. Their heaviness did not destroy
                    their faith; they still ‘endured, [as] seeing him that is invisible’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        11:27.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. Neither did their heaviness destroy their peace, the peace that passeth
                    all understanding,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Phil. 4:7.</p></note> which is inseparable from true, living faith.
                    This we may easily gather from the second verse, wherein the Apostle prays, not
                    that ‘grace and peace’ may be given them, but only that it may ‘be multiplied
                    unto them’; that the blessing which they already enjoyed might be more
                    abundantly bestowed upon them.</p>
                <p n="3">3. The persons to whom the Apostle here speaks were also full of a living
                    hope. For thus he speaks, verse three: ‘Blessed be the God and Father of our
                    Lord Jesus Christ, who according to his abundant mercy hath begotten us
                    again’—me and you, all of us who are ‘sanctified by the Spirit’, and enjoy the
                    ‘sprinkling of the blood of Jesus Christ’—‘unto a living hope, unto an
                    inheritance’, that is, unto a living hope of an inheritance, ‘incorruptible,
                    undefiled, and that fadeth not away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:2-4.</p></note> So that
                    notwithstanding their heaviness they still retained an hope full of
                    immortality.</p>
                <p n="4">4. And they still ‘rejoiced in hope of the glory of God’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:2.</p></note> They
                    were filled with joy in the Holy Ghost. So, verse eight, the Apostle having just
                    mentioned the final ‘revelation of Jesus Christ’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7"
                        n="7"><p rend="footnote text">The AV of 1 Pet. 1:7 reads, ‘the appearing of
                            Jesus Christ’. Wesley changes this in his translation in the <hi
                                rend="italic">Notes</hi> (as also in the tr. of James Moffatt and
                            the RSV). But in the text of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi> (1787) the
                            term, ‘revelation’, has been altered to ‘redemption’, which must have
                            been a printer’s error since no Greek scholar would have derived the
                            English ‘redemption’ from the original ἀποκαλύψει.</p></note>
                    <pb n="02:224"/>(namely, when he cometh to judge the world), immediately adds,
                    ‘In whom, though now ye see him not (not with your bodily eyes), yet believing,
                    ye rejoice with joy unspeakable and full of glory.’ Their heaviness therefore
                    was not only consistent with living hope, but also with ‘joy unspeakable’. At
                    the same time they were thus heavy they nevertheless rejoiced with ‘joy full of
                    glory’.</p>
                <p n="5">5. In the midst of their heaviness they likewise still enjoyed the love of
                    God which had been shed abroad in their hearts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8"
                        n="8"><p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 5:5.</p></note> ‘Whom’, says the
                    Apostle, ‘having not seen, ye love.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:8.</p></note> Though ye have not yet seen
                    him face to face, yet knowing him by faith ye have obeyed his word, ‘My son,
                    give me thy heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 23:26.</p></note> He is your God, and
                    your love, the desire of your eyes, and your ‘exceeding great reward’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                        15:1.</p></note> Ye have sought and found happiness in him; ye ‘delight in
                    the Lord, and he hath given you your heart’s desire.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 37:4
                    (BCP).</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. Once more. Though they were heavy, yet were they holy. They retained the
                    same power over sin. They were still ‘kept’ from this ‘by the power of God’.
                    They were ‘obedient children, not fashioned according to their former desires’,
                    but ‘as he that had called them is holy’, so were they ‘holy in all manner of
                    conversation…. Knowing they were redeemed by the precious blood of Christ, a
                    Lamb without spot and without blemish’, they had, through the ‘faith and hope
                    which they had in God’, ‘purified their souls by the Spirit’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:14-15, 19,
                            21-22.</p></note> So that upon the whole their heaviness well consisted
                    with faith, with hope, with love of God and man; with the peace of God, with joy
                    in the Holy Ghost, with inward and outward holiness. It did no way impair, much
                    less destroy, any part of the work of God in their hearts. It did not at all
                    interfere with that ‘sanctification of the Spirit’ which is the root of all true
                    ‘obedience’; neither with the happiness which must needs result from ‘grace and
                        peace’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 1:2.</p></note> reigning in the heart.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. Hence we may easily learn what kind of heaviness they were in—the
                    second thing which I shall endeavour to show. The word in the original is
                    λυπηθέντες, ‘made sorry’, ‘grieved’, from λύπη, ‘grief’ or ‘sorrow’. This is the
                    constant, literal meaning of the word: and this being observed, there is no
                    ambiguity in the expression, nor any difficulty in understanding it. The persons
                        <pb n="02:225"/>spoken of here were <hi rend="italic">grieved</hi>: the
                    heaviness they were in was neither more nor less than <hi rend="italic"
                        >sorrow</hi> or <hi rend="italic">grief</hi>—a passion which every child of
                    man is well acquainted with.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It is probable our translators rendered it ‘heaviness’ (though a less
                    common word) to denote two things: first, the degree; and next, the continuance
                    of it. It does indeed seem that it is not a slight or inconsiderable degree of
                    grief which is here spoken of, but such as makes a strong impression upon and
                    sinks deep into the soul. Neither does this appear to be a transient sorrow,
                    such as passes away in an hour; but rather such as having taken fast hold of the
                    heart is not presently shaken off, but continues for some time, as a settled
                    temper, rather than a passion—even in them that have living faith in Christ, and
                    the genuine love of God in their hearts.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Even in these this heaviness may sometimes be so deep as to overshadow
                    the whole soul, to give a colour, as it were, to all the affections, such as
                    will appear in the whole behaviour. It may likewise have an influence over the
                    body; particularly in those that are either of a naturally weak constitution, or
                    weakened by some accidental disorder, especially of the nervous kind. In many
                    cases we find ‘the corruptible body presses down the soul.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wisd. 9:15. Cf. also No.
                            41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, II.3 and n.</p></note> In
                    this the soul rather presses down the body, and weakens it more and more. Nay, I
                    will not say that deep and lasting sorrow of heart may not sometimes weaken a
                    strong constitution, and lay the foundation of such bodily disorders as are not
                    easily removed. And yet all this may consist with a measure of that ‘faith
                    which’ still ‘worketh by love’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:6. Cf. below, IV.5; and No. 2, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.6 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. This may well be termed a ‘fiery trial’:<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 4:12.</p></note> and
                    though it is not the same with that the Apostle speaks of in the fourth chapter,
                    yet many of the expressions there used concerning outward sufferings may be
                    accommodated to this inward affliction. They cannot indeed with any propriety be
                    applied to them that are <hi rend="italic">in darkness</hi>: these do not,
                    cannot, <hi rend="italic">rejoice</hi>; neither is it true that ‘the Spirit of
                    glory and of God resteth upon’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 4:14.</p></note> them. But he frequently
                    doth on those that are ‘in heaviness’, so that though ‘sorrowful, yet’ are they
                    ‘always rejoicing’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:10.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1"><pb n="02:226"/>III. 1. But to proceed to the third point. What are the
                    causes of such sorrow or heaviness in a true believer? The Apostle tells us
                    clearly: ‘Ye are in heaviness’, says he, ‘through manifold
                    temptations’—ποικίλοις, ‘manifold’; not only many in number, but of many kinds.
                    They may be varied and diversified a thousand ways by the change or addition of
                    numberless circumstances. And this very diversity and variety makes it more
                    difficult to guard against them. Among these we may rank all bodily disorders;
                    particularly acute diseases, and violent pain of every kind, whether affecting
                    the whole body or the smallest part of it. It is true, some who have enjoyed
                    uninterrupted health, and have felt none of these, may make light of them, and
                    wonder that sickness or pain of body should bring heaviness upon the mind. And
                    perhaps one in a thousand is of so peculiar a constitution as not to feel pain
                    like other men. So hath it pleased God to show his almighty power by producing
                    some of these prodigies of nature who have seemed not to regard pain at all,
                    though of the severest kind; if that contempt of pain was not owing partly to
                    the force of education, partly to a preternatural cause—to the power either of
                    good or evil spirits who raised those men above the state of mere nature. But
                    abstracting from<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. the earlier usage of this phrase as meaning ‘disregarding’ in No.
                            44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, I.5 and n.</p></note> these
                    particular cases, it is in general a just observation, that</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>…pain is perfect misery, and extreme</l>
                    <l>Quite overturns all patience.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi
                                rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, vi.462-64:</p><lg>
                            <l>But pain is perfect misery, the worst</l>
                            <l>Of evil, and, excessive, overturns</l>
                            <l>All patience.</l>
                        </lg></note>
                </lg>
                <p>And even where this is prevented by the grace of God, where men do ‘possess their
                    souls in patience’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 21:19.</p></note> it may nevertheless
                    occasion much inward heaviness, the soul sympathizing with the body.</p>
                <p n="2">2. All diseases of long continuance, though less painful, are apt to
                    produce the same effect. When God ‘appoints over us r consumption’ or ‘the
                    chilling and burning ague’, if it be not speedily removed it will not only
                    ‘consume the eyes’, but ‘cause sorrow of heart’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23"
                        n="23"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Lev. 26:16.</p></note>. This is eminently
                    the case with regard to all <hi n="02:227"/> those which are termed ‘nervous
                    disorders’. And faith does not overturn the course of nature: natural causes
                    still produce natural effects. Faith no more hinders the ‘sinking of the
                    spirits’ (as it is called) in an hysteric illness, than the rising of the pulse
                    in a fever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>, on ‘Hysteric Affections’;
                            he has no entry for ‘nervous disorders’. Johnson, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Dictionary</hi>, defines ‘nervous’ in the medical terms as, ‘Having
                            weak or diseased nerves’, and quotes Cheyne: ‘Poor, weak, nervous
                            creatures’. Cf. also Wesley’s ‘Thoughts on Nervous Disorders;
                            particularly that which is usually termed Lowness of Spirits’, in <hi
                                rend="italic">AM</hi> (1786), IX.52-54, 94-97; as well as his entry
                            No. 162, ‘Nervous Disorders’, in <hi rend="italic">Primitive
                                Physick</hi> (15th edn., 1772), pp. 105-6.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. Again, when ‘calamity cometh as a whirlwind,’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 1:26-27.</p></note>
                    and poverty ‘as an armed man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Prov. 24:34.</p></note> is this a little
                    temptation? Is it strange if it occasion sorrow and heaviness? Although this
                    also may appear but a small thing to those who stand at a distance, or who look
                    and ‘pass by on the other side’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 10:31, 32.</p></note> yet it is otherwise
                    to them who feel it. ‘Having food and raiment’ (indeed the latter word,
                    σκεπάσματα, implies lodging as well as apparel) we may, if the love of God is in
                    our hearts, ‘be therewith content’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:8. Cf. Wesley’s comment in his <hi
                                rend="italic">Notes</hi>: ‘That is, raiment and a house to cover
                            us’. This is an overblown inference from any of the noun and verb forms
                            of σκεπάζω, the participial forms of which can be stretched to connote
                            ‘shelter’ or even ‘protection’, but not ‘lodging’; see Liddell and
                            Scott, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>.</p></note> But what
                    shall they do who have none of these? Who as it were ‘embrace the rock for a
                        shelter’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Job 24:8.</p></note> Who have only the earth to lie upon, and only the
                    sky to cover them? Who have not a dry, or warm, much less a clean abode for
                    themselves and their little ones? No, nor clothing to keep themselves, or those
                    they love next themselves, from pinching cold, either by day or night? I laugh
                    at the stupid heathen, crying out,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Nil habet infelix paupertas durius in se</hi></l>
                    <l><hi rend="italic">Quam quod ridiculos homines facit!</hi></l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Juvenal,
                                <hi rend="italic">Satires</hi>, iii.152-53: ‘Poverty brings no
                            unhappiness worse than this: it exposes men to ridicule’ (cf. Loeb
                            91:42).</p></note>
                </lg>
                <p>Has poverty nothing worse in it than this, that it ‘makes men liable to be
                    laughed at’? ’Tis a sign this idle poet talked by rote of the things which he
                    knew not. Is not want of food something worse than this? God pronounced it as a
                    curse upon man that he should earn it by ‘the sweat of his brow’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gen.
                            3:19.</p></note> But how many are there in this <pb n="02:228"
                    />Christian country that toil and labour, and sweat, and have it not at last,
                    but struggle with weariness and hunger together? Is it not worse for one after
                    an hard day’s labour to come back to a poor, cold, dirty, uncomfortable lodging,
                    and to find there not even the food which is needful to repair his wasted
                    strength? You that live at ease in the earth, that want nothing but eyes to see,
                    ears to hear, and hearts to understand how well God has dealt with you—is it not
                    worse to seek bread day by day, and find none? Perhaps to find the comfort also
                    of five or six children, crying for what he has not to give. Were it not that he
                    is restrained by an unseen hand, would he not soon ‘curse God and die’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Job
                        2:9.</p></note> O want of bread! Want of bread!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p rend="footnote text">Amos 4:6.</p></note> Who can
                    tell what this means unless he hath felt it himself? I am astonished it
                    occasions no more than heaviness even in them that believe!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Another example (rare in his
                            time) of Wesley’s conscious identification with ‘Christ’s poor’. See No.
                            31, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XI’, I.6 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. Perhaps next to this we may place the death of those who were near and
                    dear unto us; of a tender parent, and one not much declined into the vale of
                        years;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>, III.iii.264-65: ‘I am
                            declin’d into a vale of years.’</p></note> of a beloved child just
                    rising into life, and clasping about our heart; of a friend that was as our own
                        soul<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            Sam. 18:1, 3; 20:17; cf. No. 73, ‘Of Hell’, I.2.</p></note>—next the
                    grace of God the last, best gift of heaven. And a thousand circumstances may
                    enhance the distress: perhaps the child, the friend, died in our embrace!
                    Perhaps was snatched away when we looked not for it! Flourishing, cut down like
                    a flower! In all these cases we not only may, but ought to be affected: it is
                    the design of God that we should. He would not have us stocks and stones. He
                    would have our affections regulated, not extinguished. Therefore</p>
                <l>…nature unreproved may drop a tear:</l>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Samuel Wesley,
                        Jun., ‘The Parish Priest’, ll. 5-6, <hi rend="italic">Poems on Several
                            Occasions</hi> (1736), p. 65.</p></note>
                <p>There may be sorrow without sin.</p>
                <p n="5">5. A still deeper sorrow we may feel for those who are dead while they
                    live, on account of the unkindness, ingratitude, apostasy of those who were
                    united to us in the closest ties. Who can express what a lover of souls may feel
                    for a friend, a brother dead to God? For an husband, a wife, a parent, a child,
                    rushing <hi n="02:229"/> into sin as an horse into the battle,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">See Jer. 8:6.</p></note> and
                    in spite of all arguments and persuasions hasting to work out his own damnation?
                    And this anguish of spirit maybe heightened to an inconceivable degree by the
                    consideration that he who is now posting to destruction once ran well in the way
                    of life. Whatever he was in time past serves now to no other purpose than to
                    make our reflections on what he is more piercing and afflictive.</p>
                <p n="6">6. In all these circumstances we may be assured our great adversary will
                    not be wanting to improve his opportunity. He who is always ‘walking about
                    seeking whom he may devour’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 5:8.</p></note> will then especially use
                    all his power, all his skill, if haply he may gain any advantage over the soul
                    that is already cast down. He will not be sparing of his fiery darts,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        6:16.</p></note> such as are most likely to find an entrance, and to fix
                    most deeply in the heart, by their suitableness to the temptation that assaults
                    it. He will labour to inject unbelieving, or blasphemous, or repining thoughts.
                    He will suggest that God does not regard, does not govern the earth; or at least
                    that he does not govern it aright, not by the rules of justice and mercy. He
                    will endeavour to stir up the heart against God, to renew our natural enmity
                    against him. And if we attempt to fight him with his own weapons, if we begin to
                        <hi rend="italic">reason</hi> with him, more and more heaviness will
                    undoubtedly ensue, if not utter darkness.</p>
                <p n="7">7. It has been frequently supposed that there is another cause (if not of
                    darkness, at least) of heaviness, namely, God’s withdrawing himself from the
                    soul because it is his sovereign will. Certainly he will do this if we grieve
                    his Holy Spirit, either by outward or inward sin; either by doing evil or
                    neglecting to do good; by giving way either to pride or anger, to spiritual
                    sloth, to foolish desire or inordinate affection.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:5.</p></note> But that
                    he ever withdraws himself because he <hi rend="italic">will</hi>, merely because
                    it is his good pleasure, I absolutely deny:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42"
                        n="42"><p rend="footnote text">Note this flat rejection of what Wesley
                            understood of the Lutheran doctrine of ‘the hiddenness of God’ (<hi
                                rend="italic">Deus absconditus</hi>).</p></note> there is no text in
                    all the Bible which gives any colour for such a supposition. Nay, it is a
                    supposition contrary not only to many particular texts, but to the whole tenor
                    of Scripture. It is repugnant to the very nature of God; it is utterly beneath
                    his majesty and wisdom (as an eminent writer strongly expresses it) <pb
                        n="02:230"/>‘to play at <hi rend="italic">bo-peep</hi> with his
                        creatures’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >I.e., to play a tantalizing game; cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> for a
                            variety of instances of the phrase, espec. in Daniel Defoe’s
                            denunciation of ‘men…that…do nothing but play at bo-peep with God
                            Almighty’, in <hi rend="italic">Enquiry Into the Occasional Conformity
                                of Dissenters</hi> (1697).</p></note> It is inconsistent both wick
                    his justice and mercy, and with the sound experience of all his children.</p>
                <p n="8">8. One more cause of heaviness is mentioned by many of those who are termed
                    mystic authors. And the notion has crept in, I know not how, even among plain
                    people who have no acquaintance with them. I cannot better explain this than in
                    the words of a late writer, who relates this as her own experience: ‘I continued
                    so happy in my Beloved, that although I should have been forced to live a
                    vagabond in a desert, I should have found no difficulty in it. This state had
                    not lasted long when in effect I found myself led into a desert…. I found myself
                    in a forlorn condition, altogether poor, wretched, and miserable…. The proper
                    source of this grief is the knowledge of ourselves, by which we find that there
                    is an extreme unlikeness between God and us. We see ourselves most opposite to
                    him, and that our inmost soul is entirely corrupted, depraved and full of all
                    kind of evil and malignity, of the world and the flesh and all sorts of
                        abominations.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p
                            rend="footnote text">π;</p></note> From hence it has been inferred that
                    the knowledge of ourselves, without which we should perish everlastingly, <hi
                        rend="italic">must</hi>, even after we have attained justifying faith,
                    occasion the deepest heaviness.</p>
                <p n="9">9. But upon this I would observe, (1). In the preceding paragraph this
                    writer says, ‘Hearing I had not a true faith in Christ, I offered myself up to
                    God, and immediately felt his love.’ It may be so; and yet it does not appear
                    that this was justification. ’Tis more probable it was no more than what are
                    usually termed the ‘drawings of the Father’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45"
                        n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>, ‘draw’,
                            II.26-28; and letter to Charles Wesley, Apr. 4, 1748: ‘So loving a
                            people have I scarce ever seen, nor so strong and general drawings from
                            above’ (26:302 in this edn., l. 33).</p></note> And if so, the heaviness
                    and darkness which followed was no other than conviction of sin, which in the
                    nature of things must precede that faith whereby we are justified. (2). Suppose
                    she was justified almost the same moment she was convinced of wanting faith,
                    there was then no time for that gradually increasing self-knowledge which uses
                    to precede justification. In this case therefore it came after, and was probably
                    the more severe the less it was expected. (3). It is allowed <pb n="02:231"
                    />there will be a far deeper, a far clearer and fuller knowledge of our inbred
                    sin, of our total corruption by nature, after justification, than ever there was
                    before it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Another explicit reference to the ‘remains of sin’ after justification;
                            see No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., I.6, and
                            III.8. Note here the phrase ‘inbred sin’ as synonymous with ‘in-being’
                            and ‘original’ sin in No. 44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>,
                            intro.</p></note> But this need not occasion darkness of soul. I will
                    not say that it <hi rend="italic">must</hi> bring us into heaviness. Were it so
                    the Apostle would not have used that expression, ‘if need be’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:6.</p></note> for
                    there would be an absolute, indispensable need of it, for all that would know
                    themselves; that is, in effect, for all that would know the perfect love of God,
                    and be thereby ‘made meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the saints in
                        light’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Col.
                            1:12.</p></note> But this is by no means the case. On the contrary, God
                    may increase the knowledge of ourselves to any degree, and increase in the same
                    proportion the knowledge of himself and the experience of his love.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">A proportionality
                            between repentance after justification (our self-knowledge) and faith
                            (our knowledge of God and of his grace).</p></note> And in this case
                    there would be no desert, no misery, no forlorn condition;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">See III.8, above.</p></note>
                    but love and peace and joy, gradually springing up into everlasting life.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text">John
                        4:14.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. For what ends, then (which was the fourth thing to be considered),
                    does God permit heaviness to befall so many of his children? The Apostle gives
                    us a plain and direct answer to this important question: ‘That the trial of
                    their faith, which is much more precious than gold that perisheth though it be
                    tried by fire, may be found unto praise and honour and glory, at the revelation
                    of Jesus Christ.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">[1 Pet. 1:] ver. 7.</p></note></hi> There may be
                    an allusion to this in that well-known passage of the fourth chapter (although
                    it primarily relates to quite another thing, as has been already observed):
                    ‘Think it not strange concerning the fiery trial which is to try you’, ‘but
                    rejoice that ye are partakers of the sufferings of Christ; that when his glory
                    shall be revealed ye may likewise rejoice with exceeding great joy.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver. 12,
                                etc.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="2">2. Hence we learn that the first and great end of God’s permitting the
                    temptations which bring heaviness on his children is the trial of their faith,
                    which is tried by these, even as gold by the <pb n="02:232"/>fire. Now we know
                    gold tried in the fire is purified thereby, is separated from its dross. And so
                    is faith in the fire of temptation; the more it is tried, the more it is
                    purified. Yea, and not only purified, but also strengthened, confirmed,
                    increased abundantly, by so many more proofs of the wisdom and power, the love
                    and faithfulness of God. This then—to increase our faith—is one gracious end of
                    God’s permitting those manifold temptations.</p>
                <p n="3">3. They serve to try, to purify, to confirm and increase that living hope
                    also, whereunto ‘the God and Father of our Lord Jesus Christ hath begotten us
                    again of his abundant mercy’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 1:3.</p></note> Indeed our hope cannot
                    but increase in the same proportion with our faith. On this foundation it
                    stands: believing in his name, living by faith in the Son of God, we hope for,
                    we have a confident expectation of, the glory which shall be revealed.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        8:18.</p></note> And consequently, whatever strengthens our faith increases
                    our hope also. At the same time it increases our joy in the Lord, which cannot
                    but attend an hope full of immortality.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 3:4.</p></note> In this view the Apostle
                    exhorts believers in the other chapter, ‘Rejoice that ye are partakers of the
                    sufferings of Christ.’ On this very account, ‘Happy are you; for the Spirit of
                    glory and of God resteth upon you.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 4:13-14.</p></note> And hereby ye are
                    enabled, even in the midst of sufferings, to ‘rejoice with joy unspeakable and
                    full of glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >1 Pet. 1:8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. They rejoice the more because the trials which increase their faith and
                    hope increase their love also; both their gratitude to God for all his mercies,
                    and their goodwill to all mankind. Accordingly the more deeply sensible they are
                    of the loving-kindness of God their Saviour, the more is their heart inflamed
                    with love to him who ‘first loved us’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">1 John 4:19.</p></note> The clearer and
                    stronger evidence they have of the glory that shall be revealed, the more do
                    they love him who hath purchased it for them, and ‘given them the earnest’
                    thereof ‘in their hearts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 1:22.</p></note> And this, the increase of
                    their love, is another end of the temptations permitted to come upon them.</p>
                <p n="5">5. Yet another is their advance in holiness, holiness of heart and holiness
                    of conversation; the latter naturally resulting from the former; for a good tree
                    will bring forth good fruit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:17.</p></note> And all inward holiness
                    is the immediate fruit of the faith that worketh by love.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">See Gal. 5:6. Cf. above, II.3;
                            and No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.6 and
                        n.</p></note>
                    <pb n="02:233"/>By this the blessed Spirit purifies the heart from pride,
                    self-will, passion; from love of the world, from foolish and hurtful
                        desires,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Tim. 6:9.</p></note> from vile and vain affections. Beside that,
                    sanctified afflictions have (through the grace of God) an immediate and direct
                    tendency to holiness. Through the operation of his Spirit they humble more and
                    more, and abase the soul before God. They calm and meeken<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text">A rare usage; cf. <hi
                                rend="italic">OED</hi> and also Charles Wes ley’s hymn on Matt. 5:5,
                            l. 1: ‘Meeken my soul, Thou heavenly Lamb’, in <hi rend="italic">Short
                                Hymns on Select Passages of Holy Scripture</hi>, 1762 (<hi
                                rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, X.162).</p></note> our turbulent
                    spirit, tame the fierceness of our nature, soften our obstinacy and self-will,
                    crucify us to the world, and bring us to expect all our strength from, and to
                    seek all our happiness in, God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. And all these terminate in that great end, that our faith, hope, love,
                    and holiness, ‘may be found’ (if it doth not yet appear) ‘unto praise’ from God
                    himself, ‘and honour’ from men and angels, ‘and glory’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:7.</p></note>
                    assigned by the great Judge to all that have endured to the end. And this will
                    be assigned in that awful day to every man ‘according to his works’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        16:27.</p></note> according to the work which God had wrought in his heart,
                    and the outward works which he has wrought for God; and likewise according to
                    what he had suffered; so that all these trials are unspeakable gain. So many
                    ways do these ‘light afflictions, which are but for a moment, work out for us a
                    far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory’!<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                    4:17.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. Add to this the advantage which others may receive by seeing our
                    behaviour under affliction. We find by experience, example frequently makes a
                    deeper impression upon us than precept. And what examples have a stronger
                    influence, not only on those who are partakers of like precious faith, but even
                    on them who have not known God, than that of a soul calm and serene in the midst
                    of storms, sorrowful, yet always rejoicing;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66"
                        n="66"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:10.</p></note> meekly accepting
                    whatever is the will of God, however grievous it may be to nature; saying, in
                    sickness and pain, ‘The cup which my Father hath given me, shall I not drink
                        it?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">John
                            18:11.</p></note> In loss or want, ‘The Lord gave; the Lord hath taken
                    away; blessed be the name of the Lord!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Job 1:21.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p n="1">V. 1. I am to conclude with some inferences. And, first, how wide is the
                    difference between <hi rend="italic">darkness</hi> of soul and <hi rend="italic"
                        >heaviness</hi>! <pb n="02:234"/>Which nevertheless are so generally
                    confounded with each other, even by experienced Christians! Darkness, or the
                    wilderness state, implies a total loss of joy in the Holy Ghost; heaviness does
                    not; in the midst of this we may ‘rejoice with joy unspeakable’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        1:8.</p></note> They that are in darkness have lost the peace of God; they
                    that are in heaviness have not. So far from it that at the very time ‘peace’ as
                    well as ‘grace’ may ‘be multiplied unto’ them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70"
                        n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:2.</p></note> In the former the
                    love of God is waxed cold, if it be not utterly extinguished; in the latter it
                    retains its full force, or rather increases daily. In these faith itself, if not
                    totally lost, is however grievously decayed. Their evidence and conviction of
                    things not seen,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Heb. 11:1.</p></note> particularly of the pardoning love of God, is
                    not so clear or strong as in time past; and their trust in him is proportionably
                    weakened. Those, though they see him not, yet have a clear, unshaken confidence
                    in God, and an abiding evidence of that love whereby all their sins are blotted
                        out.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Acts 3:19.</p></note> So that as long as we can distinguish faith from
                    unbelief, hope from despair, peace from war, the love of God from the love of
                    the world, we may infallibly distinguish <hi rend="italic">heaviness</hi> from
                        <hi rend="italic">darkness</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.1 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. We may learn from hence, secondly, that there may be need of <hi
                        rend="italic">heaviness</hi>, but there can be no need of <hi rend="italic"
                        >darkness</hi>. There may be need of our being in ‘heaviness for a season’,
                    in order to the ends above recited; at least in this sense, as it is a natural
                    result of those ‘manifold temptations’ which are needful to try and increase our
                    faith, to confirm and enlarge our hope, to purify our heart from all unholy
                    tempers, and to perfect us in love. And by consequence they are needful in order
                    to brighten our crown, and add to our eternal weight of glory.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:17.</p></note> But we
                    cannot say that darkness is needful in order to any of these ends. It is no way
                    conducive to them: the loss of faith, hope, love, is surely neither conducive to
                    holiness nor to the increase of that reward in heaven which will be in
                    proportion to our holiness on earth.</p>
                <p n="3">3. From the Apostle’s manner of speaking we may gather, thirdly, that even
                    heaviness is not <hi rend="italic">always</hi> needful. ‘Now, for a season, if
                    need be’; so it is not needful for <hi rend="italic">all persons</hi>; nor for
                    any person at <hi rend="italic">all times</hi>. God is able, he has both power
                    and wisdom, <hi n="02:235"/> to work when he pleases the same work of grace, in
                    any soul, by other means. And in some instances he does so: he causes those whom
                    it pleaseth him to go on from strength to strength, even till they ‘perfect
                    holiness in his fear’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1.</p></note> with scarce any
                    heaviness at all; as having an absolute power over the heart of man, and moving
                    all the springs of it at his pleasure. But these cases are rare: God generally
                    sees good to try ‘acceptable men in the furnace of affliction’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus.
                            2:5.</p></note> so that manifold temptations and heaviness, more or
                    less, are usually the portion of his dearest children.</p>
                <p n="4">4. We ought therefore, lastly, to watch and pray,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 26:41.</p></note> and
                    use our utmost endeavours to avoid falling into darkness. But we need not be
                    solicitous how to avoid, so much as how to improve by heaviness. Our great care
                    should be so to behave ourselves under it, so to wait upon the Lord therein,
                    that it may fully answer all the design of his love in permitting it to come
                    upon us; that it may be a means of increasing our faith, of confirming our hope,
                    of perfecting us in all holiness. Whenever it comes, let us have an eye to these
                    gracious ends for which it is permitted, and use all diligence that we may not
                    ‘make void the counsel of’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Jer. 19:7.</p></note> God ‘against ourselves’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                            7:30.</p></note> Let us earnestly ‘work together with him’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            6:1.</p></note> by the grace which he is continually giving us, in
                    ‘purifying ourselves from all pollution both of flesh and spirit’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 7:1
                                (<hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p></note> and daily ‘growing in the
                    grace of our Lord Jesus Christ’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:18.</p></note> till we are received
                    into his everlasting kingdom!</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
