<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 15: The Great Assize</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon015</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 15: The Great Assize</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="354" to="375"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="354"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entry for <date when="1758-02-27">February 27,
                        1758</date>, identifies the origins of this sermon: ‘Having a sermon to
                    write against the Assizes at Bedford, I retired for a few days to
                    Lewisham’—i.e., to the home of his friend and benefactor, Ebenezer Blackwell.
                    There he wrote his only published sermon <hi rend="italic">ad magistratum</hi>
                    (to a civil court) and also the only one in what may fairly be labelled an
                    ornate style. The occasion had been arranged by the High Sheriff of
                    Bedfordshire, William Cole, and the sermon itself was preached in Bedford’s
                    finest church, St. Paul’s, on Friday, March 10, before the presiding Judge of
                    Common Pleas, Sir Edward Clive (1704-71). Mr. Justice Clive, incidentally,
                    appears in William Hogarth’s scornful caricature, ‘The Bench’, 1758; cf. Ronald
                    Paulson, <hi rend="italic">Hogarth’s Graphic Works</hi> (New Haven and London,
                    Yale University Press, 1965), Vol. I, No. 205; Vol. II, Nos. 226-27; note that
                    Paulson and Sugden have different identifications of Hogarth’s characters (see
                    Sugden, II.399). Of the service itself, Wesley reports (JWJ): ‘The congregation
                    at St. Paul’s was very large and attentive. The Judge, immediately after sermon,
                    sent me an invitation to dine with him; but having no time [since he was already
                    late for an appointment the next day in Epworth, some ninety miles away], I was
                    obliged to send my excuse, and set out between one and two….’ The sermon was
                    published, by request, in the summer of 1758 and then inserted into the 1771
                    edn. of <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, I. Twenty years later (JWJ, Sept. 1, 1778),
                    Wesley remembered the sermon with some satisfaction, avowing that even then he
                    could not ‘write a better sermon on the Great Assize than I did [in 1758]’.</p>
                <p>The most striking feature of this sermon is the ease with which Wesley has
                    accommodated his carefully cultivated ‘plain style’ to a new and special
                    occasion; very little of the revival preacher appears here. There are no
                    hymn-quotations, and, save for the controlling analogy between an earthly court
                    in Bedford and God’s Final Judgment, there is scant recourse to any evangelical
                    emphasis. There are no polemics, no reference to Methodism, and only a passing
                    hat-tipping to ‘faith alone’ (II.11). Virgil and Ovid are quoted once apiece,
                    and the then widely popular Edward Young is quoted twice. The analogy between
                    earthly assizes and <pb n="355"/>‘the Great Assize’ was at least as old in
                    English preaching as <hi rend="italic">The Pricke of Conscience</hi>, line 5514,
                    formerly attributed to Richard Rolle of Hampole (c. 1300-1349). The rhetoric of
                    the introduction and conclusion is frankly exalted, and an earthly commonplace
                    becomes the analogue for the cosmic climax of human destiny and the occasion for
                    Wesley’s most explicit exposition of his eschatology.</p>
                <p>This, of course, is the central concern of the sermon: Wesley’s vivid sense of
                    the Christian life as lived under God’s constant judgment and oriented toward
                    his Final Judgment. The dominant metaphors are all forensic, and Wesley’s
                    depiction of the end-time is as stark and decisive as he could make it. The
                    reader must judge as to the consonance of Wesley’s views of ‘The Last Day ’ with
                    New Testament and traditional Christian eschatologies as they have evolved. But
                    it would be well to recognize the influence of Joseph Mede and J. A. Bengel, his
                    main sources for eschatology besides the Scriptures. ‘The Great Assize’ may
                    better be appraised as an implicit statement about the Christian <hi rend="italic">ordo salutis</hi> rather than a speculation reaching out
                    beyond faith’s basic surety that God’s final purposes for his human creation are
                    already validly revealed in Jesus Christ.</p>
                <p>The edited text here is based on the first edition of 1758. For a stemma showing
                    its textual history, together with a list of variant readings in the nine
                    editions published in Wesley’s lifetime, see Vol. IV, Appendix, ‘Wesley’s Text’.
                    For bibliographical details, see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 224.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Great Assize</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 14:10</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">We shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="section">
                <p n="1">1. How many circumstances concur to raise the awfulness of the present
                    solemnity! The general concourse of people of every age, sex, rank, and
                    condition of life, willingly or unwillingly gathered together, not only from the
                    neighbouring, but from distant parts: <hi rend="italic">criminals</hi>, speedily
                    to be brought forth, and having no way to escape; <hi rend="italic">officers</hi>, waiting in their various posts to execute the orders which
                    shall be given; and the <hi rend="italic">representative</hi> of our <pb n="356"/>gracious Sovereign, whom we so highly reverence and honour.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This is more than the nominal
                            profession of a lifelong Tory. Wesley had special reasons for gratitude
                            to the aging George II, who would die two years later in 1760, aged
                            seventy-eight. Much earlier, in 1741, George II had ordered the
                            Middlesex magistrates to protect the Methodists from persecuting mobs
                            and had declared, in Council, that there would be no persecution in his
                            dominions on account of religion while he sat on the throne (cf. Moore,
                            II.2-3). During the agitations preceding the Stuart ‘Rising of ’45’, the
                            loyalties of the Methodists were suspect and Wesley composed an ‘Humble
                            Address’ to the King, avowing his own loyalty and that of the Methodist
                            people to both Crown and Church (JWJ, Mar. 5, 1744); Charles persuaded
                            him that such a letter might have the unintended effect of setting the
                            Methodists apart more separately from the Church of England than they
                            actually were and so the address was never sent. When George died,
                            Wesley recorded a pathetic valedictory (JWJ, Oct. 25, 1760): ‘King
                            George was gathered to his fathers. When will England have a better
                            Prince?’ A strange question about the man whose private life was less
                            than exemplary and who had abetted Robert Walpole’s venalities. Cf. Nos.
                            107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, IV.2; and 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’,
                            §14.</p>
                    </note> The <hi rend="italic">occasion</hi> likewise of this
                    assembly adds not a little to the solemnity of it: to hear and determine causes
                    of every kind, some of which are of the most important nature; on which depends
                    no less than life or death—death, that uncovers the face of eternity! It was
                    doubtless in order to increase the serious sense of these things, and not in the
                    minds of the vulgar only, that the wisdom of our forefathers did not disdain to
                    appoint even several minute circumstances of this solemnity. For these also, by
                    means of the eye or ear, may more deeply affect the heart. And when viewed in
                    this light, trumpets, staves, apparel, are no longer trifling or insignificant,
                    but subservient in their kind and degree to the most valuable ends of
                    society.</p>
                <p n="2">2. But as awful as this solemnity is, one far more awful is at hand. For
                    yet a little while and ‘we shall all stand before the judgment seat of Christ.
                    For, As I live, saith the Lord, every knee shall bow to me, and every tongue
                    shall confess to God.’ And in that day ‘every one of us shall give account of
                    himself to God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:10-12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. Had all men a deep sense of this, how effectually would it secure the
                    interests of society! For what more forcible motive can be conceived to the
                    practice of genuine morality? To a steady pursuit of solid virtue, an uniform
                    walking in justice, mercy, and truth? What could strengthen our hands in all
                    that is good, and deter us from all evil, like a strong conviction of this—‘The
                    judge standeth at the door,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 5:9.</p>
                    </note> and we are shortly to <hi rend="italic">stand before</hi> him?</p>
                <p n="4">4. It may not therefore be improper, or unsuitable to the design of the
                    present assembly, to consider,</p>
                <p>
                    <pb n="357"/>I. The chief circumstances which will precede our standing before
                    the judgment seat of Christ.</p>
                <p>II. The judgment itself, and</p>
                <p>III. A few of the circumstances which will follow it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>I. Let us, in the first place, consider the chief circumstances which will
                    precede our standing before the judgment seat of Christ.</p>
                <p n="1">And first, 1. ‘God will show signs in the earth beneath:’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                2:19.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> particularly, he will ‘arise to shake terribly
                    the earth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa.
                            2:19.</p>
                    </note> ‘The earth shall reel to and fro like a drunkard, and
                    shall be removed like a cottage.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 24:20.</p>
                    </note> ‘There shall be earthquakes
                    κατὰ τόπους (not in divers only, but) ‘in all places’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke
                                21:11. [The suggestion here that κατὰ τόπους means ‘in all places’
                                is eccentric; in the <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> Wesley translates
                                it literally, ‘in divers places’.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—not in one only,
                    or a few, but in every part of the habitable world—even ‘such as were not since
                    men were upon the earth, so mighty earthquakes and so great’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 16:18. The eighteenth
                            century’s interest in earthquakes was intense; there had been major
                            quakes in Sicily and Jamaica in 1692; one in Lima, Peru, on Oct. 28,
                            1746; two in London in 1750 (Feb. 8 and Mar. 8); and another in Lisbon,
                            Nov. 1, 1755. Cf. Burnet, <hi rend="italic">History of His Own
                                Times</hi>, II.101; and John Ray, <hi rend="italic">Three
                                Physico-Theological Discourses</hi> (1693). In 1750 Charles Wesley
                            had written a sermon on ‘The Cause and Cure of Earthquakes’ upon the
                            occasion of the London shocks. That John shared Charles’s interest and
                            views in this matter may be seen in his <hi rend="italic">Serious
                                Thoughts Occasioned by the Late Earthquake at Lisbon</hi> (1755);
                            cf. <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 213 and Vol. 15 of this edn.
                            There are obvious parallels between the essay and the sermon. Another
                            stimulus to this preoccupation with earthquakes came from the infant
                            science of geology and theological reactions to it, as in Whiston’s <hi rend="italic">A New Theory of the Earth</hi> and Burnet’s <hi rend="italic">Sacred Theory of the Earth</hi> and the controversies
                            engendered by them. (Burnet had been Master of Charterhouse during
                            Wesley’s time there).</p>
                    </note> In one of these ‘every island shall
                    flee away, and the mountains will not be found.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev. 16:20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    Meantime all the waters of the terraqueous globe<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An eighteenth-century cliché and a favourite
                            of Wesley’s; see below, III.3; and Nos. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His
                            Works’, I.8, 10; 69, ‘The Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, I.8; 103,
                            ‘What is Man? Ps. 8:3-4’, I.2. Also, Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, III.3; IV.55.</p>
                    </note> will feel the violence of
                    those concussions: ‘the sea and waves roaring’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke 21:25.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    with such an agitation as had never been known before since the hour that ‘the
                    fountains of the great deep were broken up,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 7:11.</p>
                    </note> to destroy the earth
                    which then ‘stood out of the water and in the water’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:5.</p>
                    </note> The
                    air will be all storm and tempest, full of dark <pb n="358"/>‘vapours and
                    pillars of smoke’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Joel 2:30 [cf. Acts 2:19].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    resounding with thunder from pole to pole, and torn with ten thousand
                    lightnings. But the commotion will not stop in the region of the air: ‘The
                    powers of heaven also shall be shaken.’ ‘There shall be signs in the sun and in
                    the moon and in the stars’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Luke 21:25, 26.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>—those fixed as
                    well as those that move round them. ‘The sun shall be turned into darkness and
                    the moon into blood, before the great and terrible day of the Lord come.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Joel
                                2:31.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘The stars shall withdraw their shining,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Joel
                                3:15.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> yea and ‘fall from heaven’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 24:29.</p>
                    </note> being
                    thrown out of their orbits. And then shall be heard the universal ‘shout’ from
                    all the companies of heaven, followed by ‘the voice of the archangel’
                    proclaiming the approach of the Son of God and man, ‘and the trumpet of God’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Thess.
                                4:16.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> sounding an alarm to all ‘that sleep in the
                    dust of the earth’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Dan. 12:2.</p>
                    </note> In consequence of this all
                    the graves shall open, and the bodies of men arise.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ezek. 37:12-13; Matt.
                            27:52-53.</p>
                    </note> ‘The sea also shall give up the dead which are
                        therein,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev. 20:13.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> and everyone shall
                    rise <hi rend="italic">with his own body</hi>—his own in substance, although so
                    changed in its properties as we cannot now conceive. For ‘this corruptible will
                    then put on incorruption, and this mortal put on immortality.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Cor.
                                15:53.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Yea, ‘death and Hades’, the invisible world,
                    shall ‘deliver up the dead that are in them’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev. 20:13.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> so that
                    all who ever lived and died since God created man shall be raised incorruptible
                    and immortal.</p>
                <p n="2">2. At the same time ‘the Son of man shall send forth his angels’ over all
                    the earth, ‘and they shall gather his elect from the four winds, from one end of
                    heaven to the other.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 24:31.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And the Lord
                    himself shall ‘come with clouds,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 24:30, etc.</p>
                    </note> in his own glory
                    and the glory of his Father,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 9:26.</p>
                    </note> with ten thousand of his
                        saints,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jude
                            14.</p>
                    </note> even myriads of angels’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 12:22.</p>
                    </note> and ‘shall sit
                    upon the throne of his glory. And before him shall be gathered all nations, and
                    he shall separate them one from another, and shall set the sheep’ (the good) ‘on
                    his right hand, and the goats’ (the wicked) ‘upon the left.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt.
                                25:31-33.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Concerning this general assembly it is
                    that the beloved disciple speaks thus: ‘I saw the dead’ (all that had been dead)
                    ‘small and great, stand before <pb n="359"/>God. And the books were opened (a
                    figurative expression, plainly referring to the manner of proceeding among men),
                    and the dead were judged out of those things which were written in the books
                    according to their works.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev. 20:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>II. These are the chief circumstances which are recorded in the oracles of God as
                    preceding the general judgment. We are, secondly, to consider the judgment
                    itself, so far as it hath pleased God to reveal it.</p>
                <p n="1">1. The person by whom God ‘will judge the world’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:6; 1 Cor.
                        6:2.</p>
                    </note> is his only-begotten Son, whose ‘goings forth are from
                        everlasting’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mic. 5:2.</p>
                    </note> ‘who is God over all,
                    blessed for ever’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 9:5.</p>
                    </note> Unto him, ‘being the
                    out-beaming of his Father’s glory, the express image of his person’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 1:3
                                [This translation of ἀπαύγασμα as ‘out-beaming’ appealed to Wesley.
                                Although he does not use it in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, it
                                appears in Nos. 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, §1; and 34, ‘The
                                Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law’, II.3. Cf. Poole’s
                                    <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc.
                                    cit.</hi>].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> the Father ‘hath committed all
                    judgment, […] because he is the Son of man’;<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John 5:22, 27.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                    because, though he was ‘in the form of God, and thought it not robbery to be
                    equal with God, yet he emptied himself, taking upon him the form of a servant,
                    being made in the likeness of men’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Phil. 2:6-7.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Yea,
                    because ‘being found in fashion as a man, he humbled himself’ yet farther,
                    ‘becoming obedient unto death, even the death of the cross. Wherefore God hath
                    highly exalted him,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:8-9.</p>
                    </note> even in his human
                    nature, and ‘ordained him’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 17:31.</p>
                    </note> as man to try the
                    children of men, to be the ‘judge both of the quick and dead’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 4:5.</p>
                    </note>
                    both of those who shall be found alive at his coming, and of those who were
                    before ‘gathered to their fathers’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Judg. 2:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. The time termed by the prophet ‘the great and the terrible day’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Joel
                        2:31.</p>
                    </note> is usually in Scripture styled ‘the day of the Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Joel 1:15,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> The space from the creation of man upon the earth to the
                    end of all things is <hi rend="italic">the day of the sons of men</hi>. The time
                    that is now passing over us is properly our day. When this is ended, the day of
                    the Lord will begin. But who can say how long it will continue? ‘With <pb n="360"/>the Lord one day is as a thousand years, and a thousand years as
                    one day.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2
                                Pet. 3:8.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And from this very expression some of the
                    ancient Fathers drew that inference, that what is commonly called ‘the day of
                        judgment’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 10:15, etc.</p>
                    </note> would be indeed a thousand years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">As in the
                            ‘Epistle of Barnabas’ (xv), Justin Martyr (<hi rend="italic">Dialogue
                                with Trypho</hi>, 1xx), Melito of Sardis (in Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">Ecclesiastical History</hi>, xxiv. 5), Papias (in
                            Irenaeus, <hi rend="italic">Against Heresies</hi>, V.xxxiii, and
                            Eusebius, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>, III.xxxix), Irenaeus (<hi rend="italic">Against Heresies</hi>, V.xxxii), Methodius of Olympus
                                (<hi rend="italic">Symposium</hi>, Disc. 9 and 10), Lactantius (<hi rend="italic">Epitome of the Divine Institutes</hi>, LXXI-LXXII).
                            Origen had criticized these chiliastic interpretations of Rev. 20:1-15,
                            and St. Augustine, having championed such a view (as in <hi rend="italic">De Civ. Dei</hi>, xx.7), abandoned it in Sermon CCLIX
                            (Migne, <hi rend="italic">PL</hi>, XXXVIII.1197). Apocalyptic visions
                            continued throughout the Middle Ages, but chiliasm proper had few
                            explicit champions. It was, however, renewed in the ‘radical
                            reformation’ (Hoffman and the Munsterites in Cromwell’s England and
                            thereafter (Jane Leade), and in the writings of Joseph Mede and J. A.
                            Bengel; for Bengel’s influence on Wesley, cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, Preface, §7, and Rev. 20:1-15.</p>
                    </note> And it seems
                    they did not go beyond the truth; nay, probably they did not come up to it. For
                    if we consider the number of persons who are to be judged, and of actions which
                    are to be inquired into, it does not appear that a thousand years will suffice
                    for the transactions of that day. So that it may not improbably comprise several
                    thousand years. But God shall reveal this also in its season.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s reticence here is as
                            significant as his proposed revision of chiliastic thought, since he
                            knew the history of millenarianism and had a sympathetic interest in
                            Montanus; cf. Nos. 61, ‘The Mystery of Iniquity’, §24; and 68, ‘The
                            Wisdom of God’s Counsels’, §9; see also ‘The Real Character of Montanus’
                            (Vol. 12 of this edn.). His reaction to Jurieu and ‘the French Prophets’
                            was cautious. He also knew, but chose to ignore, William Whiston’s
                            prediction that the ‘Last Day’ was scheduled in the year 1720, as in his
                            essay on the <hi rend="italic">Revelation of St. John</hi> (1706). He
                            had already used in his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> (1755) Bengel’s <hi rend="italic">Erklärte Offenbarung Johannis…</hi> (1740; Eng. tr.,
                            1757), with its predicted date for the millennium as 1836, and indeed
                            reproduced Bengel’s chronological appendix in his own
                    work.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. With regard to the place where mankind will be judged we have no
                    explicit account in Scripture. An eminent writer<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Boston, State IV, Head IV;
                            and Bengel, <hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi> (on Rev. 20), §§3-11; see also
                            Joseph Mede, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, III.430-32, and espec. his
                            chart, pp. 431-32 (‘ΒΙΒΛΑΡΙΔΙΟΝ’).</p>
                    </note> (but not he alone; many
                    have been of the same opinion) supposes it will be on earth, where the works
                    were done according to which they shall be judged, and that God will in order
                    thereto employ the angels of his strength,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>To smooth and lengthen out the boundless space,</l>
                    <l>And spread an area for all human race.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Young, <hi rend="italic">Last Day</hi>,
                                ii.19-20; orig. ‘th’ unbounded space’; cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi> (1744),
                            II.76.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="">But perhaps it is more agreeable to our Lord’s own account of his ‘coming in
                    the clouds’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 24:30; Mark 13:26.</p>
                    </note> to suppose it will be above the
                    earth, if not ‘twice a planetary height’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Young, <hi rend="italic">Last Day</hi>,
                            ii.274; cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection of Moral and Sacred
                                Poems</hi>, II.82.</p>
                    </note> And this supposition is not a little
                    favoured by what St. Paul writes to the Thessalonians. ‘The dead in Christ shall
                    rise first. Then we who remain alive shall be caught up together with them, in
                    the clouds, to meet the Lord in the air.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 Thess. 4:16-17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> So
                    that it seems most probable the ‘great white throne’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 20:11.</p>
                    </note> will be
                    high exalted above the earth.</p>
                <p n="4">4. The persons to be judged who can count, any more than the drops of rain
                    or the sands of the sea? I beheld, saith St. John, ‘a great multitude which no
                    man can number, clothed with white robes, and palms in their hands’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                        7:9.</p>
                    </note> How immense then must be the total multitude of all nations,
                    and kindreds, and people, and tongues!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                        </p>
                    </note> Of all
                    that have sprung from the loins of Adam since the world began, till time shall
                    be no more! If we admit the common supposition, which seems noways absurd, that
                    the earth bears at any one time no less than four hundred millions of living
                    souls—men, women, and children—what a congregation must all those generations
                    make who have succeeded each other for seven thousand years!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley had found this ‘common
                            supposition’ in Brerewood’s <hi rend="italic">Enquiries</hi>, pp.
                            120-45. It would be repeated by Richard Price, in a letter to Benjamin
                            Franklin published in <hi rend="italic">Philosophical Transactions</hi>
                            (of the Royal Society) in 1768. Current estimates of the world’s
                            population in 1750 are based largely on the work of A. M. Carr-Saunders,
                                <hi rend="italic">World Population</hi> (Oxford, Oxford University
                            Press, 1936), p. 42; W. S. Thompson, <hi rend="italic">Population and
                                Progress in the Far East</hi> (Chicago, University of Chicago Press,
                            1959), p. 12; and W. F. Willcox, <hi rend="italic">Studies in American
                                Demography</hi> (Ithaca, N. Y., Cornell University Press, 1940), p.
                            45. The average of their estimates would put the round figure of world
                            population in 1750 at seven hundred millions. Cf. W. D. Borrie, <hi rend="italic">The Growth and Control of World Population</hi>
                            (London, Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1970), pp. 6-7; Gerhard and Jean
                            Lenski, <hi rend="italic">Human Societies</hi> (New York, McGraw Hill,
                            1974), p. 319; and Annabelle Desmond, ‘How Many People Have Ever Lived
                            on Earth?’ in <hi rend="italic">Population Bulletin</hi>, 18:1 (Feb.
                            1962), pp. 1-19. For some of Wesley’s other references to population,
                            cf. Nos. 63, ‘The General Spread of the Gospel’, §1; 69, ‘The
                            Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, II.8; 103, ‘What is Man? Ps. 8:3-4’,
                            I.2; 122, ‘Causes of the Inefficacy of Christianity’, §3. Cf. also, <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Original Sin</hi>, II.1; <hi rend="italic">Some Observations on Liberty</hi>, §11; his letter to
                            the Bishop of Gloucester, Nov. 26, 1762; and JWJ, Sept. 9,
                        1776.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Great Xerxes’ world in arms, proud Cannae’s host, …</l>
                    <l>They all are here, and here they all are lost:</l>
                    <l>Their numbers swell to be discerned in vain;</l>
                    <l>Lost as a drop in the unbounded main.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Young, <hi rend="italic">Last Day</hi>, ii.189, 194-96; orig., ‘Their millions
                            swell’ and ‘Lost as a billow in th’ unbounded main’. Cf. Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>, II.80. See
                            also No. 103, ‘What is Man? Ps. 8:3-4’, I.1, where Wesley uses this last
                            line again.</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p>Every man, every woman, every infant of days that ever breathed the vital air
                    will then hear the voice of the Son of God, and start into life, and appear
                    before him. And this seems to be the natural import of that expression, ‘the
                    dead, small and great’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 20:12.</p>
                    </note> all universally, all without
                    exception, all of every age, sex, or degree; all that ever lived and died, or
                    underwent such a change as will be equivalent with death. For long before that
                    day the phantom of human greatness disappears and sinks into nothing. Even in
                    the moment of death that vanishes away. Who is rich or great in the grave?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The grave as a
                            great ‘leveller’ was a commonplace theme in poetry and preaching, as in
                            Thomas Gray’s contemporary <hi rend="italic">Elegy Written in a Country
                                Churchyard</hi> just seven years previously.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. And every man shall there ‘give an account of his own works’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:2;
                            Rom. 14:12; Rev. 20:12.</p>
                    </note> yea, a full and true account of all
                    that he ever did while in the body, whether it was good or evil. O what a scene
                    will then be disclosed in the sight of angels and men! While not the fabled
                    Rhadamanthus, but the Lord God Almighty, who knoweth all things in heaven and
                    earth,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Castigatque, auditque dolos; subigitque fateri</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Quae quis apud superos, furto laetatus inani,</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Distulit in seram commissa piacula mortem.</hi>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, vi.567-69; Wesley offers no translation, but
                        in the ‘Explanation of the Latin Sentences’ added to Vol. 32 of his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1774) Wesley prefixed the preceding line, ‘<hi rend="italic">Haec Rhadamanthus habet durissima regna</hi>’, and
                        furnished his own translation of the quatrain:</p>
                    <lg>
                        <l>O’er these drear realms stem Rhadamanthus reigns,</l>
                        <l>Detects each artful villain, and constrains</l>
                        <l>To own the crimes, long veiled from human sight:</l>
                        <l>In vain! Now all stand forth in hated light.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p rend="footnote text">See above, Intro., pp. 71-72, for evidence that
                        Wesley continued to read Virgil ‘for pleasure’, even into his old age. Thus,
                        he may have had a copy of the <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi> at hand, which
                        would explain this rare verbatim quotation.</p>
                </note>
                <p>Nor will all the actions alone of every child of man be then brought to open
                    view, but all their words, seeing ‘every idle word <pb n="363"/>which men shall
                    speak, they shall give account thereof in the day of judgment.’ So that, ‘By thy
                    words’ (as well as works) ‘thou shalt be justified; or by thy words thou shalt
                    be condemned’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 12:36-37.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Will not God
                    then bring to light every circumstance also that accompanied every word or
                    action, and if not altered the nature, yet lessened or increased the goodness or
                    badness of them? And how easy is this to him who is ‘about our bed and about our
                    path, and spieth out all our ways’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 139:2 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> We know ‘the darkness
                    is no darkness to him, but the night shineth as the day.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An interesting conflation of
                            Ps. 139:11-12: ver. 11 is from the BCP; ver. 12 is AV.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. Yea, he ‘will bring to light’ not ‘the hidden works of darkness’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            4:5.</p>
                    </note> only, but the very ‘thoughts and intents of the
                        heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            4:12.</p>
                    </note> And what marvel? For he ‘searcheth the reins’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        2:23.</p>
                    </note> and ‘understandeth all our thoughts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 139:2 (AV).</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘All things are naked and open to the eyes of him with whom we have to do.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            4:13.</p>
                    </note> ‘Hell and destruction are before him’ without a
                    covering; ‘how much more the hearts of the children of men!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov.
                    15:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="7">7. And in that day shall be discovered every inward working of every human
                    soul: every appetite, passion, inclination, affection, with the various
                    combinations of them, with every temper and disposition that constitute the
                    whole complex character of each individual. So shall it be clearly and
                    infallibly seen who was righteous, and who unrighteous; and in what degree every
                    action or person or character was either good or evil.</p>
                <p n="8">8. ‘Then the king will say to them upon his right hand, Come, ye blessed of
                    my Father. For I was hungry and ye gave me meat; thirsty and ye gave me drink; I
                    was a stranger and ye took me in; naked and ye clothed me.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:34-36.</p>
                    </note>
                    In like manner, all the good they did upon earth will be recited before men and
                    angels: whatsoever they had done either ‘in word or deed, in the name’, or for
                    the sake ‘of the Lord Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:17.</p>
                    </note> All their good desires,
                    intentions, thoughts, all their holy dispositions, will also be then remembered;
                    and it will appear that though they were unknown or forgotten among men, yet God
                    ‘noted’ them ‘in his book’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 30:8.</p>
                    </note> All <pb n="364"/>their
                    sufferings likewise for the name of Jesus and for the testimony of a good
                    conscience will be displayed, unto their <hi rend="italic">praise</hi> from the
                    righteous judge,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Tim. 4:8.</p>
                    </note> their <hi rend="italic">honour</hi> before
                    saints and angels, and the increase of that ‘far more exceeding and eternal
                    weight of glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">9. But will their evil deeds too—since if we take in his whole life ‘there
                    is not a man on earth that liveth and sinneth not’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eccles.
                    7:20.</p>
                    </note>—will these be remembered in that day, and mentioned in the
                    great congregation? Many believe they will not, and ask, ‘Would not this imply
                    that their sufferings were not at an end, even when life ended? Seeing they
                    would still have sorrow, and shame, and confusion of face to endure?’ They ask
                    farther, ‘How can this be reconciled with God’s declaration by the Prophet, “If
                    the wicked will turn from all his sins that he hath committed, and keep all my
                    statutes, and do that which is lawful and right; …all his transgressions that he
                    hath committed, they shall not be once mentioned unto him”?<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ezek.
                                18:21-22.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> How is it consistent with the promise
                    which God has made to all who accept of the gospel covenant, “I will forgive
                    their iniquities, and remember their sin no more”?<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Jer. 31:34.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Or
                    as the Apostle expresses it, “I will be merciful to their unrighteousness, and
                    their sins and iniquities will I remember no more”?’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 8:12 [cf. Boston, State
                                IV, Head V, ‘The Kingdom of Heaven’].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. It may be answered, it is apparently and absolutely necessary, for the
                    full display of the glory of God, for the clear and perfect manifestation of his
                    wisdom, justice, power, and mercy toward the heirs of salvation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        1:14.</p>
                    </note> that all the circumstances of their life should be placed
                    in open view, together with all their tempers, and all the desires, thoughts,
                    and intents of their hearts.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 4:12.</p>
                    </note> Otherwise how would it appear
                    out of what a depth of sin and misery the grace of God had delivered them? And,
                    indeed, if the whole lives of all the children of men were not manifestly
                    discovered, the whole amazing contexture of divine providence could not be
                    manifested; nor should we yet be able in a thousand <pb n="365"/>instances to
                    ‘justify the ways of God to man’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>,
                            i. 26. Cf. also Nos. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’, II.3; 57, ‘On
                            the Fall of Man’, §2; and 140, ‘The Promise of Understanding’, I.1. See
                            also Wesley’s letter to Elizabeth Ritchie, Jan. 17, 1775.</p>
                    </note>
                    Unless our Lord’s words were fulfilled in their utmost sense, without any
                    restriction or limitation, ‘there is nothing covered that shall not be revealed,
                    or hid that shall not be known,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 10:26.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> abundance of
                    God’s dispensations under the sun would still appear without their reasons. And
                    then only when God hath brought to light all the hidden things of darkness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor.
                        4:5.</p>
                    </note> whosoever were the actors therein, will it be seen that wise
                    and good were all his ways; that he ‘saw through the thick cloud’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A paraphrase of
                            Job 22:12-14, espec. ver. 13.</p>
                    </note> and governed all things by the
                    wise ‘counsel of his own will’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:11.</p>
                    </note> that nothing was left to
                    chance or the caprice of men, but God disposed all ‘strongly and sweetly’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. George
                            Herbert, <hi rend="italic">The Temple</hi>, ‘Providence’, ll. 1-2 and,
                            espec., 29-32:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>We all acknowledge both thy power and love</l>
                            <l>To be exact, transcendent, and divine;</l>
                            <l>Who dost so strongly and so sweetly move,</l>
                            <l>While all things have their will, yet none but thine.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also Kempis, IV.i.8: ‘How sweetly and graciously
                            dost thou dispose of all things with thine elect, … This strongly
                            draweth the hearts of the devout…’. See Nos. 118, ‘On the Omnipresence
                            of God’, II.2, where Wesley again pairs ‘strongly and sweetly’ in
                            speaking of God’s influencing his creatures without destroying their
                            liberty; and 66, ‘The Signs of the Times’, II.9, where he speaks of the
                            grace of God, ‘strongly and sweetly working on every side’.</p> and
                        wrought all into one connected chain of justice, mercy, and
                    truth.</note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. And in the discovery of the divine perfections the righteous will
                    rejoice with joy unspeakable; far from feeling any painful sorrow or shame for
                    any of those past transgressions which were long since blotted out as a
                        cloud,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Isa. 44:22.</p>
                    </note> washed away by the blood of the Lamb.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        12:11.</p>
                    </note> It will be abundantly sufficient for them that ‘all the
                    transgressions which they had committed shall not be once mentioned unto
                        them’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ezek. 18:22.</p>
                    </note> to their disadvantage; that ‘their sins and
                    transgressions and iniquities shall be remembered no more’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 8:12;
                        10:17.</p>
                    </note> to their condemnation. This is the plain meaning of the
                    promise; and this all the children of God shall find true, to their everlasting
                    comfort.</p>
                <p n="12">
                    <pb n="366"/>12. After the righteous are judged, the king will turn to
                    them upon his left hand, and they shall also be judged, every man ‘according to
                    his works’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 16:27.</p>
                    </note> But not only their outward works will be
                    brought into the account, but all the evil words which they have ever spoken;
                    yea, all the evil desires, affections, tempers, which have or have had a place
                    in their souls, and all the evil thoughts or designs which were ever cherished
                    in their hearts. The joyful sentence of acquittal will then be pronounced upon
                    those on the right hand, the dreadful sentence of condemnation upon those on the
                    left—both of which must remain fixed and immovable as the throne of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. We may, in the third place, consider a few of the circumstances
                    which will follow the general judgment. And the first is the execution of the
                    sentence pronounced on the evil and on the good. ‘These shall go away into
                    eternal punishment, and the righteous into life eternal.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:46.</p>
                    </note> It
                    should be observed, it is the very same word which is used both in the former
                    and the latter clause: it follows that either the punishment lasts for ever, or
                    the reward too will come to an end.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s doctrine of ‘a middle state’ for souls
                            after death but before the Final Judgment (as in No. 115, ‘Dives and
                            Lazarus’, I.3 and n.) did not allow for further amelioration of the
                            state of those who died in unrepented (‘mortal’) sins; human destinies
                            are, therefore, predetermined at death and thus before ‘The Great
                            Assize’.</p>
                    </note> No, never, unless God could come to an end, or his
                    mercy and truth could fail. ‘Then shall the righteous shine forth as the sun in
                    the kingdom of their Father,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 13:43.</p>
                    </note> and shall ‘drink of those
                    rivers of pleasure which are at God’s right hand for evermore’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Pss. 16:11;
                            36:8.</p>
                    </note> But here all description falls short; all human
                    language fails! Only one who is caught up into the third heaven<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor.
                        12:2.</p>
                    </note> can have a just conception of it. But even such an one
                    cannot express what he hath seen—these things ‘it is not possible for man to
                        utter.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 12:4 (cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>‘The wicked’, meantime, ‘shall be turned into hell,’ even ‘all the people that
                    forget God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Ps. 9:17 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> They will be ‘punished with everlasting
                    destruction from the presence of the Lord, and from the glory of his
                        power’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Thess. 1:9.</p>
                    </note> They will be ‘cast into the lake of fire burning
                    with brimstone’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 19:20.</p>
                    </note> originally ‘prepared for the devil and <pb n="367"/>his angels’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:41.</p>
                    </note> where they will ‘gnaw their
                        tongues’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 16:10.</p>
                    </note> for anguish and pain; they will ‘curse God, and
                    look upward’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 8:21.</p>
                    </note> there the dogs of hell<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An odd metaphor, as if Wesley
                            had confused the three <hi rend="italic">heads</hi> of Cerberus (cf.
                            Homer, <hi rend="italic">Iliad</hi> viii. 367; Euripides, <hi rend="italic">Hercules Furens</hi>, 611; and Virgil, <hi rend="italic">Aeneid</hi>, vi. 417-22) with three dogs. In any case,
                            there is no correlation between the roles of Cerberus and of the ‘worms’
                            (cf. Isa. 66:24; Judith 16:17; and Mark 9:44-49). In his <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Mark 9:44 Wesley had recently written of
                            the ‘worm’ (of conscience) ‘that gnaweth the soul (pride, self-will,
                            desire, malice, envy, shame, sorrow, despair)’. For a classic text on
                            the eternity of divine punishments, see St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">De Civ. Dei</hi>, xxi. chs. 9-14. Cf. Nos. 73, ‘Of Hell’, II.2; and
                            84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, III. 10; also <hi rend="italic">Advice to a Soldier</hi>, §4, <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 72 (Vol. 14 of this edn.). See also Milton, <hi rend="italic">Paradise Lost</hi>, x.616, and Henry Brooke, <hi rend="italic">Gustavus Vasa</hi>, Act IV, sc.
                        2.</p>
                    </note>—pride,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, I.3 and n.</p>
                    </note> malice, revenge, rage, horror,
                    despair—continually devour them. There ‘they have no rest day or night, but the
                    smoke of their torment ascendeth for ever and ever.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev. 14:11.</p>
                    </note>
                    ‘For their worm dieth not, and the fire is not quenched.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 9:44; cf. also No.
                            73, ‘Of Hell’, III.3, where endless torment is also
                    affirmed.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Then the heavens will be shrivelled up ‘as a parchment scroll’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                            6:14.</p>
                    </note> and ‘pass away with a great noise’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 3:10.</p>
                    </note> they
                    will ‘flee from the face of him that sitteth on the throne, and there will be
                    found no place for them’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Cf.] Rev. 20:11.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The very
                    manner of their passing away is disclosed to us by the Apostle Peter: ‘In the
                    day of God, the heavens, being on fire, shall be dissolved.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Pet.
                                3:12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The whole beautiful fabric will be overthrown
                    by that raging element, the connection of all its parts destroyed, and every
                    atom torn asunder from the others. By the same ‘the earth also and the works
                    that are therein shall be burnt up.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">2 Pet. 3:10.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The
                    enormous works of nature, ‘the everlasting hills’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 49:26.</p>
                    </note>
                    mountains that have defied the rage of time, and stood unmoved so many thousand
                    years, will sink down in fiery ruin. How much less will the works of art, though
                    of the most durable kind, the utmost efforts of human industry—tombs, pillars,
                    triumphal arches, castles, pyramids—be able to withstand the flaming conqueror.
                    All, all will die, perish, vanish away, like a dream when one awaketh!</p>
                <p n="3">3. It has indeed been imagined by some great and good men that as it
                    requires that same almighty power to annihilate things as to create, to speak
                    into nothing or out of nothing; so no part of, no <pb n="368"/>atom in the
                    universe will be totally or finally destroyed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Seventeenth- and eighteenth-century
                            scientists were agreed on the principle of ‘the conservation of matter’;
                            cf. Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi> on ‘Matter’, and
                            Singer, <hi rend="italic">Scientific Ideas</hi>, pp. 332-33 (for
                            citations of Francis Bacon, Robert Boyle, and Sir Isaac Newton); see
                            also pp. 271-72. Wesley returns frequently to the point, as in Nos. 26,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’, III.7; 60, ‘The General Deliverance’, I.1;
                            68, ‘The Wisdom of God’s Counsels’, §4; 70, ‘The Case of Reason
                            Impartially Considered’, II.2; 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, I.5; 118, ‘On
                            the Omnipresence of God’, II.3. See also ‘Some Thoughts on an Expression
                            of St. Paul in the First Epistle to the Thessalonians…’, <hi rend="italic">AM</hi>, 1786, 543-44; <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on
                            Act 17:18 (‘The stoics held that matter was eternal…’), and <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, I.178.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">But cf.
                            Laurence Echard, <hi rend="italic">A General Ecclesiastical History</hi>
                            (5th edn., 1719), III. iii. 345, for a reminder that when Hermogenes
                                (<hi rend="italic">c.</hi> A.D. 178) first proposed the idea as
                            valid for a Christian doctrine of creation, he was denounced (by
                            Tertullian and others) as an ‘heresiarch’. Indeed, the obvious conflict
                            between the doctrines of the eternity of matter, on the one side, and of
                            the ‘creation from nothing’, on the other, has been a long-standing
                            problem for Christian theologians.</p>
                    </note> Rather, they suppose that
                    as the last operation of fire which we have yet been able to observe is to
                    reduce into glass what by a smaller force it had reduced to ashes; so in the day
                    God hath ordained the whole earth, if not the material heavens also, will
                    undergo this change, after which the fire can have no farther power over them.
                    And they believe this is intimated by that expression in the Revelation made to
                    St. John: ‘Before the throne there was a sea of glass like unto crystal.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Rev.]
                                4:6. [But see also Rev. 15:2 and Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on these two verses. For a further reference to
                                Jacob Behmen (Wesley’s preferred spelling for Jakob Boehme) and his
                                apocalyptic vision based on these verses, see No. 64, ‘The New
                                Creation’, §13 and n. See also Wesley’s letter to William Law, Jan.
                                6, 1756, in which he had criticized Law’s dependence on Boehme and
                                had denounced his ‘superfluous, uncertain, dangerous, irrational,
                                unscriptural philosophy’.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> We cannot now either
                    affirm or deny this; but we shall know hereafter.</p>
                <p n="4">4. If it be inquired by the scoffers, the minute philosophers:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Cicero, <hi rend="italic">De Senectute (On Old Age)</hi>, xxiii. 85: ‘<hi rend="italic">quidam minuti philosophi</hi>’ (‘certain petty
                            philosophers’). See also Berkeley’s description and appraisal of these
                            narrow-visioned thinkers in <hi rend="italic">Alciphron, or the Minute
                                Philosopher</hi> (1732; in the 3rd edn. [1752], Dial. I.ii, he says
                            of them, ‘They are, amongst the great thinkers, as the Dutch painters
                            are amongst the men of the grand style’). Wesley mentions them again in
                            No. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’, II.1; <hi rend="italic">A
                                Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. II, II.14 (11:226-27 of this edn.); and <hi rend="italic">Thoughts Upon Necessity</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 351 (Vol. 12 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note> ‘How can
                    these things be? Whence should come such an immense quantity of fire<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The primeval
                            element of fire had, in Wesley’s time, come to be often identified as
                            ‘ethereal fire’; cf. William Jones, <hi rend="italic">An Essay on the
                                First Principles of Natural Philosophy</hi> (1762), p. 210, where
                            Zoroaster is cited as the source of the idea. See also Shakespeare, <hi rend="italic">Othello</hi>, V.ii.280, ‘steep-down gulfs of liquid
                            fire’. Wesley was much interested in such popular scientific notions as
                            ‘ethereal fire’ and the newly discovered phenomena of ‘electric fire’
                            and electricity; cf. Nos. 54, ‘On Eternity’, §7; 55, <hi rend="italic">On the Trinity</hi>, §9; 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His Works’, I.8;
                            57, ‘On the Fall of Man’, II.1; 64, ‘The New Creation’, §10; 69, ‘The
                            Imperfection of Human Knowledge’, I.7; 77, ‘Spiritual Worship’, I.5;
                            116, ‘What is Man? Ps. 8:4’, §§2, 8; 124, ‘Human Life a Dream’, §7. See
                            also Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, III.186, 246; ‘Some
                            Thoughts’ on 1 Thess. (<hi rend="italic">AM</hi>, 1786, 543); ‘Thought
                            on Nervous Disorders’, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>, 54; <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, V.235-55.</p>
                    </note> as would consume the
                    heavens and the <pb n="369"/>whole terraqueous globe?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.1 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> we would beg leave, first, to remind them that this difficulty
                    is not peculiar to the Christian system. The same opinion almost universally
                    obtained among the <hi rend="italic">unbigoted</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s spelling:
                            ‘unbigotted’; but cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> for spelling variations
                            in the seventeenth and eighteenth centuries.</p>
                    </note> heathens. So one
                    of those celebrated ‘free-thinkers’ speaks according to the generally received
                    sentiment:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Esse quoque in fatis reminiscitur, affore tempus,</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Quo mare, quo tellus, correptaque regia coeli</hi>
                    </l>
                    <l>
                        <hi rend="italic">Ardeat, et mundi moles operosa laboret.</hi>
                        <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi>, i. 256-58: ‘He remembered also
                                that ’twas in the fates that a time would come when sea and land,
                                the unkindled palace of the sky, and the beleaguered structure of
                                the universe, should be destroyed by fire.’</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="">But, secondly, it is easy to answer, even from our slight and superficial
                    acquaintance with natural things, that there are abundant magazines of fire
                    ready prepared, and treasured up against the day of the Lord. How soon may a
                    comet, commissioned by him, travel down from the most distant parts of the
                    universe? And were it to fix upon the earth in its return from the sun, when it
                    is some thousand times hotter than a red-hot cannon-ball,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on 2 Pet. 3:10, where Wesley uses almost the same words
                            as here in this paragraph. Cf. also No. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His
                            Works’, I.10 and n.</p>
                    </note> who does not see what must be the
                    immediate consequence? But, not to ascend so high as the ethereal heavens, might
                    not the same lightnings which give ‘shine to the world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 97:4 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> if
                    commanded by the Lord of nature give ruin and utter destruction? Or, to go no
                    farther than the globe itself, who knows what huge reservoirs of liquid fire are
                    from age to age contained in the bowels of the earth? Aetna, Hecla,
                        Vesuvius,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s ‘favourite’ volcanoes. The phrase, ‘burning mountains’, goes
                            back to Pliny the Elder, <hi rend="italic">Natural History</hi>,
                            II.106-7, and to Macarius, <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Homilies</hi>,
                            XIV.212. It occurs in Goldsmith’s <hi rend="italic">History of the Earth
                                and Animated Nature</hi> (1774), I.291 (where Buffon is cited). Cf.
                            the long passage on ‘burning mountains’ in Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Survey</hi>, III.107-52, where the ‘fire in caverns of the earth’
                            (p. 131) is correlated with the phenomena of volcanoes. Isaac Watts also
                            used the term in his <hi rend="italic">Ruin and Recovery of Mankind</hi>
                            (p. 15), which Wesley quoted in his <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of
                                Original Sin</hi>. Cf. also Nos. 56, ‘God’s Approbation of His
                            Works’, I.3; 64, ‘The New Creation’, §15; and 69, ‘The Imperfection of
                            Human Knowledge’, I.8.</p>
                    </note> and all the <pb n="370"/>other
                    volcanoes that belch out flames and coals of fire, what are they but so many
                    proofs and mouths of those fiery furnaces? And at the same time so many
                    evidences that God hath in readiness wherewith to fulfil his word. Yea, were we
                    to observe no more than the surface of the earth, and the things that surround
                    us on every side, it is most certain (as a thousand experiments prove beyond all
                    possibility of denial) that we ourselves, our whole bodies, are full of fire, as
                    well as everything round about us. Is it not easy to make this ethereal fire
                    visible even to the naked eye? And to produce thereby the very same effects on
                    combustible matter which are produced by culinary fire? Needs there then any
                    more than for God to unloose that secret chain whereby this irresistible agent
                    is now bound down, and lies quiescent in every particle of matter? And how soon
                    would it tear the universal frame in pieces, and involve all in one common
                    ruin?</p>
                <p n="5">5. There is one circumstance more which will follow the judgment that
                    deserves our serious consideration. ‘We look’, says the Apostle, ‘according to
                    his promise, for new heavens and a new earth, wherein dwelleth
                        righteousness.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[2 Pet.] 3:13.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> The promise
                    stands in the prophecy of Isaiah: ‘Behold, I create new heavens and a new earth.
                    And the former shall not be remembered;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Isa.] 65:17.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> so
                    great shall the glory of the latter be. These St. John did behold in the visions
                    of God. ‘I saw’, saith he, ‘a new heaven and a new earth; for the first heaven
                    and the first earth were passed away.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rev. 21:1.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And only
                    ‘righteousness dwelt therein.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:13.</p>
                    </note> Accordingly he adds,
                    ‘And I heard a great voice from’ the third ‘heaven, saying, Behold, the
                    tabernacle of God is with men, and he will dwell with them, and they shall be
                    his people, and God himself shall be with them, and be their God.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Of necessity, therefore, they will all be happy:
                    ‘God shall wipe away all tears from their eyes, and there shall be no more
                    death, neither sorrow, nor crying; neither shall there be any more pain.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> ‘There shall be no more curse; but […] they shall
                    see his face,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">[Rev.] 22:3, 4.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> shall have the
                    nearest access to, and thence the <pb n="371"/>highest resemblance of him. This
                    is the strongest expression in the language of Scripture to denote the most
                    perfect happiness. ‘And his name shall be on their foreheads.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 22:4.</p>
                    </note> They
                    shall be openly acknowledged as God’s own property; and his glorious nature
                    shall most visibly shine forth in them. ‘And there shall be no night there; and
                    they need no candle, neither light of the sun; for the Lord God giveth them
                    light, and they shall reign for ever and ever.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 22:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>IV. It remains only to apply the preceding considerations to all who are here
                    before God. And are we not directly led so to do by the present solemnity, which
                    so naturally points us to that day when the Lord ‘will judge the world in
                        righteousness’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 9:8.</p>
                    </note> This, therefore, by
                    reminding us of that more awful season, may furnish many lessons of instruction.
                    A few of these I may be permitted just to touch on. May God write them on all
                    our hearts!</p>
                <p n="1">1. And, first, ‘how beautiful are the feet’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 52:7.</p>
                    </note> of
                    those who are sent by the wise and gracious providence of God to execute justice
                    on earth, to defend the injured, and punish the wrongdoer! Are they not ‘the
                    ministers of God to us for good’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 13:4.</p>
                    </note> the grand supporters of
                    the public tranquillity, the patrons of innocence and virtue, the great security
                    of all our temporal blessings? And does not every one of these represent not
                    only an earthly prince, but the Judge of the earth;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 94:2.</p>
                    </note> him
                    whose ‘name is written upon his thigh, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                            19:16.</p>
                    </note> O that all these sons ‘of the right hand of the Most
                        High’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps.
                            77:10.</p>
                    </note> may be holy as he is holy!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet.
                        1:15-16.</p>
                    </note> Wise with the ‘wisdom that sitteth by his throne’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wisd.
                        9:4.</p>
                    </note> like him who is the eternal wisdom of the Father! No
                    respecters of persons, as he is none; but ‘rendering to every man according to
                    his works’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Prov. 24:12; Matt. 16:27.</p>
                    </note> like him inflexibly, inexorably
                    just, though pitiful and of tender mercy!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas. 5:11.</p>
                    </note> So shall they be
                    terrible indeed to them that do evil, as ‘not bearing the sword in vain’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            13:4.</p>
                    </note> So shall the laws of our land have their full use and
                    due honour, and the throne of our King be still ‘established in
                        righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Prov. 25:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">
                    <pb n="372"/>2. Ye truly honourable men, whom God and the King have
                    commissioned in a lower degree to administer justice, may not ye be compared to
                    those ministering spirits who will attend the Judge coming in the clouds? May
                    you, like them, burn with love to God and man! May you love righteousness and
                    hate iniquity!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 1:9.</p>
                    </note> May ye all minister in your several spheres
                    (such honour hath God given you also!) to them that shall be heirs of
                        salvation,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 1:14.</p>
                    </note> and to the glory of your great Sovereign! May
                    ye remain the establishers of peace, the blessing and ornaments of your country,
                    the protectors of a guilty land, the guardian angels of all that are round about
                    you!</p>
                <p n="3">3. You whose office it is to execute what is given you in charge by him
                    before whom you stand, how nearly are you concerned to resemble those that stand
                    before the face of the Son of man! Those ‘servants of his that do his
                        pleasure’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 103:21 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> ‘and hearken to the voice of his
                        words’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 103:20 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Does it not highly import <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to be as uncorrupt as <hi rend="italic">them</hi>? To
                    approve yourselves the servants of God? To do justly and love mercy;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mic.
                        6:8.</p>
                    </note> to do to all as ye would they should do to you?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:12;
                            Luke 6:31.</p>
                    </note> So shall that great Judge, under whose eye you
                    continually stand, say to you also, ‘Well done, good and faithful servants:
                    enter ye into the joy of your Lord!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn117" n="117">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:21, 23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. Suffer me to add a few words to all of you who are this day present
                    before the Lord. Should not you bear it in your minds all the day long that a
                    more awful day is coming? A large assembly this! But what is it to that which
                    every eye will then behold—the general assembly of all the children of men that
                    ever lived on the face of the whole earth!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn118" n="118">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Tertullian, <hi rend="italic">De
                                spectaculis</hi>, xxx.</p>
                    </note> A few will stand at the judgment
                    seat this day, to be judged touching what shall be laid to their charge. And
                    they are now reserved in prison, perhaps in chains, till they are brought forth
                    to be tried and sentenced. But we shall all, I that speak and you that hear,
                    ‘stand at the judgment seat of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn119" n="119">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 14:10.</p>
                    </note> And we are now
                    reserved on this earth, which is not our home,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn120" n="120">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou
                                That Steepest’</hi>, II.5 and n.</p>
                    </note> in this prison of flesh
                    and blood, perhaps many of us in chains of darkness too,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn121" n="121">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 2:4.</p>
                    </note> till
                    we are ordered to be brought forth. Here a <pb n="373"/>man is questioned
                    concerning one or two facts<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn122" n="122">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An already obsolescent synonym for ‘acts’ or
                            ‘deeds’; cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> and Johnson’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>.</p>
                    </note> which he is supposed to have committed.
                    There we are to give an account of all our works, from the cradle to the
                        grave:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn123" n="123">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John Dyer, ‘Grongar Hill’ (1726), line 89.</p>
                    </note> of all our words;
                    of all our desires and tempers, all the thoughts and intents of our hearts;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn124" n="124">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb.
                            4:12.</p>
                    </note> of all the use we have made of our various talents,
                    whether of mind, body, or fortune, till God said, ‘Give an account of thy
                    stewardship; for thou mayest be no longer steward.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn125" n="125">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 16:2.</p>
                    </note> In
                    this court it is possible some who are guilty may escape for want of evidence.
                    But there is no want of evidence in that court. All men with whom you had the
                    most secret intercourse, who were privy to all your designs and actions, are
                    ready before your face. So are all the spirits of darkness, who inspired evil
                    designs, and assisted in the execution of them. So are all the angels of
                    God—those ‘eyes of the Lord that run to and fro over all the earth’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn126" n="126">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Zech.
                            4:10.</p>
                    </note>—who watched over your soul, and laboured for your good
                    so far as you would permit. So is your own conscience, a thousand witnesses in
                        one,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn127" n="127">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Quintillian, <hi rend="italic">Institui. Oratoriae</hi>, V. xi. 41
                            (quoting a proverb): ‘<hi rend="italic">Conscientiam mille testes</hi>’
                            (‘conscience is a thousand witnesses’). Cf. Robert Greene, <hi rend="italic">Philomela</hi> (1592), and Thomas Fuller, <hi rend="italic">The Holy State of Recreations</hi> (1642), ‘He that
                            sinnes against his conscience sinnes with a witness.’ There was an old
                            Latin tag, ‘<hi rend="italic">in foro conscientiae</hi>’ (‘in
                            conscience’s court’); see also No. 105, ‘On Conscience’, espec. I.7 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> now no more capable of being either blinded or silenced,
                    but constrained to know and to speak the naked truth touching all your thoughts
                    and words and actions. And is conscience as a thousand witnesses? Yea, but God
                    is as a thousand consciences! O who can stand before the face of ‘the great God,
                    even our Saviour, Jesus Christ’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn128" n="128">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 2:13.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>See, see! He cometh! He maketh the clouds his chariots. He rideth upon the wings
                    of the wind! A devouring fire goeth before him, and after him a flame burneth!
                    See, he sitteth upon his throne, clothed with light as with a garment, arrayed
                    with majesty and honour!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn129" n="129">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 104:1-3.</p>
                    </note> Behold his eyes are as
                    a flame of fire, his voice as the sound of many waters!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn130" n="130">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev.
                    1:14-15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>How will ye escape? Will ye call to the mountains to fall on you, the rocks to
                    cover you?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn131" n="131">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rev. 6:16.</p>
                    </note> Alas, the mountains themselves, the <pb n="374"/>rocks, the earth, the heavens, are just ready to flee away! Can ye prevent the
                    sentence? Wherewith? With all the substance of thy house,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn132" n="132">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Prov. 6:31; S. of S.
                            8:7.</p>
                    </note> with thousands of gold and silver? Blind wretch! Thou
                    camest naked from thy mother’s womb, and [shalt move]<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn133" n="133">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Orig., ‘and more naked’ (as
                            also the text of 1771), altered in the separate edns. of 1782 and
                            thereafter to ‘shalt go’. But it seems likely that the printer had
                            omitted ‘shalt’ in error, that ‘move’ was then misprinted as ‘more’, and
                            this then had gone unnoticed by Wesley.</p>
                    </note> naked into
                        eternity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn134" n="134">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Job 1:21.</p>
                    </note> Hear the Lord, the Judge! ‘Come ye blessed of
                    my Father! Inherit the kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the
                        world.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn135" n="135">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:34.</p>
                    </note> Joyful sound! How widely different from that
                    voice which echoes through the expanse of heaven, ‘Depart, ye cursed, into
                    everlasting fire, prepared for the devil and his angels!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn136" n="136">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 25:41.</p>
                    </note> And
                    who is he that can prevent or retard the full execution of either sentence? Vain
                    hope! Lo, ‘hell is moved from beneath’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn137" n="137">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 14:9.</p>
                    </note> to receive those who
                    are ripe for destruction! And the ‘everlasting doors lift up their heads’ that
                    the heirs of glory may come in!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn138" n="138">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 24:7, 9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘What manner of persons (then) ought we to be, in all holy conversation
                    and godliness?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn139" n="139">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:11.</p>
                    </note> We know it cannot be
                    long before the Lord will descend ‘with the voice of the archangel, and the
                    trumpet of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn140" n="140">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess. 4:16.</p>
                    </note> when every one of us
                    shall appear before him and ‘give account of his own works’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn141" n="141">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 16:2; Rev.
                            20:12.</p>
                    </note> ‘Wherefore, beloved, seeing ye look for these
                        things’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn142" n="142">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Pet. 3:14.</p>
                    </note> seeing ye know he will come and will not
                        tarry,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn143" n="143">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 10:37.</p>
                    </note> ‘be diligent that ye may be found of him in
                    peace, without spot, and blameless.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn144" n="144">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:14.</p>
                    </note> Why should ye not?
                    Why should one of you be found on the left hand at his appearing? He ‘willeth
                    not that any should perish, but that all should come to <hi rend="italic">repentance</hi>’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn145" n="145">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 3:9.</p>
                    </note> by repentance to faith
                    in a bleeding Lord; by faith to spotless love, to the full image of God renewed
                    in the heart, and producing all holiness of conversation. Can you doubt of this
                        <pb n="375"/>when you remember the Judge of all<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn146" n="146">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 12:23.</p>
                    </note> is
                    likewise ‘the Saviour of all’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn147" n="147">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 4:10.</p>
                    </note> Hath he not bought you with
                    his own blood,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn148" n="148">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 20:28.</p>
                    </note> that ye might ‘not perish, but have
                    everlasting life’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn149" n="149">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John 3:16.</p>
                    </note> O make proof of his mercy
                    rather than his justice! Of his love rather than the thunder of his power!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn150" n="150">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Job
                        26:14.</p>
                    </note> ‘He is not far from every one of us;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn151" n="151">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 17:27.</p>
                    </note>
                    and he is now come, ‘not to condemn, but to save the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn152" n="152">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:17.</p>
                    </note> He
                    standeth in the midst! Sinner, doth he not now, even now, knock at the door of
                    thy heart?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn153" n="153">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Rev. 3:20.</p>
                    </note> O that thou mayst know, at least ‘<hi rend="italic">in this thy day’</hi>, the things that belong unto thy
                        peace!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn154" n="154">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Luke 19:42.</p>
                    </note> O that ye may now give yourselves to him who
                    ‘gave himself for you’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn155" n="155">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 2:20.</p>
                    </note> in humble faith, in holy,
                    active, patient love! So shall ye rejoice with exceeding joy<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn156" n="156">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 2:10.</p>
                    </note>
                    <hi rend="italic">in his day</hi>, when he cometh in the clouds of heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn157" n="157">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt.
                            24:30, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>