<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 20: The Lord Our Righteousness</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-25</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon020</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 20: The Lord Our Righteousness</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="444" to="465"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="444"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The preceding sermon had been written in 1747 or 1748 and for <hi rend="italic">SOSO</hi>, II (1748); there it had been followed directly by Wesley’s
                    thirteen-sermon series ‘Upon our Lord’s Sermon on the Mount’. At that time, it
                    seemed natural enough to progress directly from the negative powers of faith
                    (‘not to sin’) to an extended comment on faith’s positive fruits. This present
                    sermon, from a later period, was inserted in this particular place by Wesley in
                    his collected <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771), II, and, at first glance, it
                    might seem intrusive. A closer look, however, suggests that in 1771 Wesley could
                    see the need for a clearer soteriological restatement between his sermon on
                    faith’s ‘privileges’ and his series on its ‘duties’. There would be a good
                    reason for this: in the interval between 1748 and 1771 the conflict with the
                    Calvinists had worsened, and there was an obvious need at this particular
                    juncture for a clearer statement of his counterposition on ‘imputation’ and
                    ‘importation’ in justification by faith.</p>
                <p>The conflict stretched back to the breach between the Wesleys and George
                    Whitefield, with John’s sermon on <hi rend="italic">Free Grace</hi> (1739) and
                    Charles’s thirty-six stanza poem, ‘The Horrible Decree’. Characteristically,
                    Wesley never understood why the Calvinists should have taken offence at his
                    criticisms, and thus continued to repeat his sincere but unrealistic appeals to
                    them for closer fellowship, as in his letter to Henry Venn, June 22, 1763: ‘I
                    desire to have a league offensive and defensive with every soldier of Christ.’
                    It baffled him that, in response, he got more criticism than cooperation.</p>
                <p>The criticism came from such men as Jonathan Warne and John Cennick and was
                    climaxed in 1755 by a three-volume ‘dialogue’ by a former pupil and fellow
                    ‘Oxford Methodist’, James Hervey, since turned Calvinist, and rector of Weston
                    Flavell. Hervey was already well known for his <hi rend="italic">Meditations
                        Among the Tombs</hi>. Now, in his long, drawn-out <hi rend="italic">Theron
                        and Aspasio</hi>, he had laid out the differences between ‘Theron’ (his
                    eponym for Arminians, generally) and ‘Aspasio’ (i.e., himself as a
                    representative English Calvinist arguing plausibly for ‘the imputed
                    righteousness of Christ’ as the prime reality in justification); needless to <pb n="445"/>say, ‘Theron’ comes off rather badly in the ‘dialogue’. Hervey had
                    sent a pre-publication copy of his manuscript to Wesley who, like an old tutor
                    attempting to improve the revision, had dashed off a set of critical annotations
                    for Hervey’s private eyes. The dialogues appeared unrevised and Wesley, somewhat
                    peevishly, proceeded to publish his annotations on them, as ‘A Letter to the
                    Rev. Mr. —’, in his <hi rend="italic">Preservative Against Unsettled Notions in
                        Religion</hi> (1758), pp. 211-36.</p>
                <p>This unexpected attack wounded the gentle-spirited Hervey and prompted him to
                    reply in a series of long letters to Wesley that he wisely left unposted and
                    unpublished at his death in 1758 (with explicit instructions that they should
                    never be published). However, they fell into the hands of William Cudworth, who
                    promptly put them in print in a form, as Hervey’s brother William complained,
                    ‘so faulty and incorrect that little judgment can be formed from it of the
                    propriety and force of my brother’s answers to Mr. Westley’. Hence, an
                    ‘official’ edition of <hi rend="italic">Eleven Letters from the late Rev. Mr.
                        Hervey to the Rev. Mr. John Wesley; containing an Answer to that Gentleman’s
                        Remarks on</hi> Theron and Aspasio (1765). <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our
                        Righteousness</hi> was Wesley’s prompt response.</p>
                <p>It was preached on Sunday, November 24, 1765, in the chapel in West Street, near
                    Seven Dials (a chapel which belonged to the parish of St. Clement Dane’s;
                    earlier, it had been loaned to the Huguenots and then to the Methodists; its old
                    pulpit is still preserved in the nearby church of St. Giles-in-the-Fields). This
                    sermon represents Wesley in as irenic a mood as the circumstances allowed, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, given the need for an unmistakable rejection of all
                    one-sided emphases on ‘imputation’.</p>
                <p>There was, of course, much more at stake in this affair than an unhappy rift
                    between two former friends. Its central issue was whether Christ’s atoning death
                    is to be understood as the ‘formal’ or the ‘meritorious’ cause of a sinner’s
                    justification. This had divided British theologians since the days of Davenant
                    and Downame; cf. C. F. Allison, <hi rend="italic">The Rise of Moralism</hi>
                    (chs. 1-3); but see also Alexander Hamilton’s obscure <hi rend="italic">Cordial
                        for Christians Travelling Heavenward</hi> (1696), p. 69. The doctrine of
                    ‘formal cause’ implied some sort of correlated view of predestination and
                    irresistible grace. The idea of ‘meritorious cause’, while still ‘evangelical’,
                    allowed for prevenience, free will, and ‘universal redemption’. To the
                    Calvinists, however, this was merely a subtler form of works-righteousness,
                    indeed of ‘popery’ or something very like it. For his part, Hervey is generous
                    enough to discount the insinuations he had heard, ‘that Mr. Wesley is a Jesuit
                    in disguise’ (p. 122). Yet he felt it proper to suggest that Wesley’s principles
                    halt <pb n="446"/>‘between Protestantism and Popery’ (p. 123), that ‘Wesley is
                    pleased to associate with the Papists in ascribing our salvation partly to
                    inherent, partly to imputed, righteousness’ (p. 228), that Wesley’s views are
                    markedly similar to those of Bellarmine (p. 228, n.). Finally, Hervey stresses
                    the contrast between Wesley’s misleading notion that ‘God’s great end is to
                    impart happiness to his creatures’ and the Calvinist vision of man’s chief end
                    as the enhancement of God’s glory (p. 291).</p>
                <p>Hervey and his friends had found abundant evidence of Wesley’s synergism,
                    particularly in ‘The Marks of the New Birth’ and ‘The Great Privilege of those
                    that are Born of God’ (cf. <hi rend="italic">Eleven Letters</hi>, p. 197, ‘Sin
                    remains in us till the Day of Judgment’). In 1771, therefore, when the breach
                    with the Calvinists had become irreparable, it seemed urgent for Wesley to place
                        <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our Righteousness</hi> between ‘The Great
                    Privilege…’ and the discourses on the Sermon on the Mount, out of chronological
                    order but in response to a pressing need for clarity on a particular point. He
                    begins with an assertion of the premises of faith alone which is as clear and
                    forceful as any he had ever made before. And yet his conclusions develop quite
                    differently from anything in the Lutheran and Calvinist traditions based on
                    those same premises. It is in this sense, then, that <hi rend="italic">The Lord
                        Our Righteousness</hi> may be reckoned as yet another ‘landmark sermon’. It
                    signals the end of Wesley’s efforts to avoid an open rift with the Calvinists;
                    it signals the beginning of that stage in his career that we have labelled ‘the
                    later Wesley’. Moreover, in its own right, it is a revealing sample of Wesley’s
                    earnest, even if largely unavailing, efforts to agree and disagree in matters of
                    ‘theological opinions’ while still holding fast to the Christian unity made
                    possible by shared beliefs in what he understood to be the <hi rend="italic">essentials</hi> of Christian doctrine.</p>
                <p>The present text is based on that of the first edition of 1766. For a stemma
                    illustrating the textual history of the nine extant editions issued during
                    Wesley’s lifetime and a list of substantive variant readings, see Appendix,
                    ‘Wesley’s Text’, Vol. IV. See also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 295.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="449"/>
            <head>The Lord Our Righteousness</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Jeremiah 23:6</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">This is his name whereby he shall be called, The Lord our
                        righteousness.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. How dreadful and how innumerable are the contests which have arisen
                    about religion! And not only among the children of this world,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke 16:8; 20:34. See also No.
                            4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural Christianity</hi>, II.5 and n., for an
                            equivalent phrase, ‘saints of the world’ (Juán de Valdés’s ‘<hi rend="italic">santos del mundo</hi>’).</p>
                    </note> among those who
                    knew not what true religion was; but even among the children of God, those who
                    had experienced ‘the kingdom of God within them’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 17:21.</p>
                    </note> who
                    had tasted of ‘righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        14:17.</p>
                    </note> How many of these in all ages, instead of joining together
                    against the common enemy, have turned their weapons against each other, and so
                    not only wasted their precious time but hurt one another’s spirits, weakened
                    each other’s hands, and so hindered the great work of their common Master! How
                    many of the weak have hereby been offended! How many of the ‘lame turned out of
                    the way’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                            12:13.</p>
                    </note> How many sinners confirmed in their disregard of all
                    religion, and their contempt of those that profess it! And how many of ‘the
                    excellent ones upon earth’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 16:3.</p>
                    </note> have been constrained to
                    ‘weep in secret places’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jer. 13:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. What would not every lover of God and his neighbour do, what would he
                    not suffer, to remedy this sore evil? To remove contention from the children of
                    God? To restore or preserve peace among them? What but a good conscience would
                    he think too dear to part with in order to promote this valuable end? And
                    suppose we cannot ‘make these wars to cease in all the world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 46:9 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                    suppose we cannot reconcile all the children of God to each other; however, let
                    each do what he can, let him contribute if it be but two mites toward it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Mark
                            12:41-44.</p>
                    </note> Happy are they who are able in any <pb n="450"/>degree to promote ‘peace and goodwill among men’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 2:14.</p>
                    </note>
                    Especially among good men; among those that are all listed under the banner of
                    ‘the Prince of Peace’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 9:6.</p>
                    </note> and are therefore peculiarly
                    engaged, ‘as much as lies in them, to live peaceably with all men’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            12:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. It would be a considerable step toward this glorious end if we could
                    bring good men to understand one another. Abundance of disputes arise purely
                    from the want of this, from mere misapprehension. Frequently neither of the
                    contending parties understands what his opponent means; whence it follows that
                    each violently attacks the other while there is no real difference between
                        them.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An
                            echo of John Locke’s account of the motivations for his <hi rend="italic">Essay Concerning Human Understanding</hi> (see his
                            ‘Epistle to the Reader’, dated 1689, pp. xlvi-xlvii); <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, that more confusion results from misunderstanding than
                            from actual disagreement. A marginal note in James Tyrrell’s copy of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Essay</hi> reports that the whole project was
                            prompted by a discussion amongst Locke’s ‘group of friends’ concerning
                            the issues of ‘morality and revealed religion’. It was Locke’s hope to
                            show that misunderstandings can usually be reduced if the disputants
                            will agree on their terms and eschew their biases.</p>
                    </note> And yet it
                    is not always an easy matter to convince them of this. Particularly when their
                    passions are moved: it is then attended with the utmost difficulty. However, it
                    is not impossible; especially when we attempt it, not trusting in ourselves, but
                    having all our dependence upon him with whom all things are possible.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 19:26,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> How soon is he able to disperse the cloud, to shine upon
                    their hearts, and to enable them both to understand each other and ‘the truth as
                    it is in Jesus’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:21.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. One very considerable article of this truth is contained in the words
                    above recited, ‘This is his name whereby he shall be called, The Lord our
                    righteousness:’ a truth this which enters deep into the nature of Christianity,
                    and in a manner supports the whole frame of it. Of this undoubtedly may be
                    affirmed what Luther affirms of a truth closely connected with it: it is <hi rend="italic">articulus stantis vel cadentis ecclesiae</hi>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘The doctrine on
                            which the church stands or falls’. Wesley’s attribution of this famous
                            aphorism to Luther is an interesting sidelight on the life history of
                            such aphorisms. He is obviously repeating a commonplace which he may
                            have read in John Flavel’s <hi rend="italic">Πλανηλογία</hi>, published
                            in <hi rend="italic">Mr. John Flavel’s Remains…</hi> (1691), p. 318:
                            ‘The article of justification is deservedly styled by our divines <hi rend="italic">articulus stantis vel cadentis religionis</hi>’, or in
                            Michael Harrison, <hi rend="italic">Christ’s Righteousness Imputed…</hi>
                            (n.d. but <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 1690), p. 1, where it is attributed
                            to Chemnitz. In WHS, V.51, C. L. Ford has a note which cites ‘Bp. Harold
                            Browne, Article XI’ as having found it in Luther, with a further note by
                            one ‘F. R.’, ‘I have not found it <hi rend="italic">earlier</hi> than
                            Luther.’ Franz Hildebrandt, <hi rend="italic">From Luther to
                            Wesley</hi>, p. 16n., cites it as from ‘Luther, <hi rend="italic">Art.
                                Smalcaldi</hi>, Pt. II, §1’, without noting that its sense is
                            affirmed in the <hi rend="italic">Smalkald Articles</hi> (in II, XIII,
                            etc.) but not the literal text.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley will
                            repeat the phrase, without an attribution, JWJ, Dec. 1, 1767; cf. his
                            letter to William Law, Jan. 6, 1756; his <hi rend="italic">Remarks</hi>
                            on Hill’s <hi rend="italic">Review</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Farrago
                                Double-Distilled</hi>.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">On the point of
                            Luther’s coining of the aphorism, Friedrich Loofs tried to puzzle it out
                            in a notable essay, ‘<hi rend="italic">Der articulus stantis vel
                                cadentis ecclesiae</hi>’ in <hi rend="italic">Theologisches Studien
                                und Kritiken</hi> (1917), 90:323-420. Having found its sense in many
                            places throughout the Luther corpus (e.g., his ‘Argument of the Epistle
                            to the Galatians’ [<hi rend="italic">W.A.</hi>, Vol. 40, Pt. I, p. 49]),
                            he concludes that its <hi rend="italic">verbatim</hi> text is not there.
                            Then, following a review of the Lutheran dogmaticians (ignoring
                            Harrison’s attribution, above), Loofs concludes (pp. 344-45) that the
                            phrase as such first appears (and clearly he means in Lutheran circles)
                            in one Valentin E. Löscher, <hi rend="italic">Timotheus Verinus</hi>
                            (1712), pp. 1027-28, and, again, in <hi rend="italic">Völlständiger
                                Timotheus Verinus</hi> (1718), pp. 342-43. Löscher was involved with
                            Zinzendorf, the Moravians, and the Halle pietists, though not a pietist
                            himself; cf. <hi rend="italic">The New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of
                                Religious Knowledge</hi> (New York, Funk and Wagnalls Company,
                            1908-12), <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi> Would Wesley have heard the
                            aphorism in Herrnhut, associated with Luther?</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">The ‘Bp. Browne’ noted above was Bishop Harold Browne, whose assertion
                            (without citation) in his <hi rend="italic">Exposition of the
                                Thirty-nine Articles</hi> (1871) illustrates the persistence of the
                            slogan: ‘Luther strongly propounded his doctrine [of <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi>] in its strongest possible form, as the <hi rend="italic">articulus stantis aut cadentis ecclesiae</hi>.’ None
                            of this would have troubled Wesley or many of his first readers,
                            although Hervey was speaking for others besides himself in his comment
                            that ‘Mr. Wesley is so unfair in his quotations and so magisterial in
                            his manner that I find it no small difficulty to preserve the decency of
                            the gentleman and the meekness of the Christian in my intended answer’
                            (cf. <hi rend="italic">Eleven Letters</hi>, Pref., p.
                    v.).</p>
                    </note>—the Christian church stands or falls with it. It is <pb n="451"/>certainly the pillar and ground of that faith of which alone cometh
                    salvation—of that <hi rend="italic">catholic</hi> or universal faith which is
                    found in all the children of God, and which ‘unless a man keep whole and
                    undefiled, without doubt he shall perish everlastingly’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the so-called Athanasian
                            Creed or <hi rend="italic">Quicunque Vult</hi> (BCP), and Schaff, <hi rend="italic">Creeds</hi>, II.66.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. Might not one therefore reasonably expect, that however they differed in
                    others, all those who name the name of Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 2:19.</p>
                    </note> should agree in
                    this point? But how far is this from being the case! There is scarce any wherein
                    they are so little agreed, wherein those who all profess to follow Christ seem
                    so widely and irreconcilably to differ. I say ‘seem’, because I am throughly
                    convinced that many of them only seem to differ. The disagreement is more in
                    words than in sentiments: they are much nearer in judgment than in language. And
                    a wide difference in language there certainly is, not only between Protestants
                    and Papists, but between Protestant and Protestant; yea, even between those who
                    all believe justification by faith, who agree as well in this as every other
                    fundamental doctrine of the gospel.</p>
                <p n="6">6. But if the difference be more in <hi rend="italic">opinion</hi> than
                    real <hi rend="italic">experience</hi>, and more in <hi rend="italic">expression</hi> than in <hi rend="italic">opinion</hi>, how can it be that
                    even the <pb n="452"/>children of God should so vehemently contend with each
                    other on the point? Several reasons may be assigned for this: the chief is their
                    not understanding one another, joined with too keen an attachment to their <hi rend="italic">opinions</hi> and particular modes of <hi rend="italic">expression</hi>.</p>
                <p>In order to remove this, at least in some measure, in order to our understanding
                    one another on this head, I shall by the help of God endeavour to show,</p>
                <p>I. What is the righteousness of Christ;</p>
                <p>II. When, and in what sense, it is imputed to us;</p>
                <p>And conclude with a short and plain application.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>And, I. What is the righteousness of Christ? It is twofold, either his divine or
                    his human righteousness.</p>
                <p n="1">1. His divine righteousness belongs to his divine nature, as he is ὁ ὤν,
                    ‘He that existeth, over all, God, blessed for ever:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 9:5.</p>
                    </note> the
                    supreme, the eternal, ‘equal with the Father as touching his godhead, though
                    inferior to the Father as touching his manhood’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the Athanasian Creed, §33
                            (Schaff, <hi rend="italic">Creeds</hi>, II.69); but see also the
                            significantly different affirmation in the Definition of Chalcedon, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, that the Son is ‘of the same οὐσία as the
                            Father touching his godhead, and of the same οὐσία as we ourselves,
                            touching his manhood’ (Schaff, <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>,
                        II.62).</p>
                    </note> Now this is his eternal, essential, immutable holiness;
                    his infinite justice, mercy, and truth: in all which ‘he and the Father are
                        one.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 10:30.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>But I do not apprehend that the divine righteousness of Christ is immediately
                    concerned in the present question. I believe few, if any, do now contend for the
                        <hi rend="italic">imputation</hi> of <hi rend="italic">this</hi>
                    righteousness to us. Whoever believes the doctrine of imputation understands it
                    chiefly, if not solely, of his human righteousness.</p>
                <p n="2">2. The <hi rend="italic">human righteousness</hi> of Christ belongs to him
                    in his human nature, as he is ‘the mediator between God and man, the man Christ
                        Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            1 Tim. 2:5. See No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, §4 and
                            n.</p>
                    </note> This is either internal or external. His internal
                    righteousness is the image of God<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 1:27; 9:6; 2 Cor. 4:4. See No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note> stamped
                    on every power and faculty of his soul. It is a copy of his divine
                    righteousness, as far as it can be imparted to a human spirit. It is a
                    transcript of the divine purity, the divine justice, mercy, and truth. It
                    includes love, reverence, resignation to his Father; humility, meekness,
                    gentleness; love to lost mankind, and every other holy and <pb n="453"/>heavenly
                    temper: and all these in the highest degree, without any defect, or mixture of
                    unholiness.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It was the least part of his <hi rend="italic">external
                        righteousness</hi> that he did nothing amiss; that he knew no outward sin of
                    any kind, ‘neither was guile found in his mouth’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 2:22.</p>
                    </note> that
                    he never spoke one improper word, nor did one improper action. Thus far it is
                    only a <hi rend="italic">negative</hi> righteousness, though such an one as
                    never did nor ever can belong to anyone that is born of a woman, save himself
                    alone. But even his outward righteousness was <hi rend="italic">positive</hi>
                    too. ‘He did all things well.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mark 7:37.</p>
                    </note> In every word of his
                    tongue, in every work of his hands, he did precisely the ‘will of him that sent
                        him’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 4:34; 6:38.</p>
                    </note> In the whole course of his life he did the
                    will of God on earth as the angels do it in heaven.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of the Lord’s Prayer,
                            Matt. 6:10.</p>
                    </note> All he acted and spoke was exactly right in every
                    circumstance. The whole and every part of his obedience was complete. ‘He
                    fulfilled all righteousness.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 3:15.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">4. But his obedience implied more than all this. It implied not only doing,
                    but suffering: suffering the whole will of God from the time he came into the
                    world till ‘he bore our sins in his own body upon the tree;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 2:24.</p>
                    </note>
                    yea, till having made a full atonement for them ‘he bowed his head and gave up
                    the ghost.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John
                            19:30.</p>
                    </note> This is usually termed the <hi rend="italic">passive</hi> righteousness of Christ, the former, his <hi rend="italic">active</hi> righteousness. But as the active and passive righteousness of
                    Christ were never in fact separated from each other, so we never need separate
                    them at all, either in speaking or even in thinking. And it is with regard to
                    both these conjointly that Jesus is called, ‘the Lord our righteousness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A popular
                            restatement of a controversial issue between the Lutherans and
                            Calvinists, on the one side, and the Anglicans on the other—<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, ‘the active and passive obedience of
                            Christ’ and its import for soteriology. The former stressed Christ’s
                            passive obedience (his vicarious satisfaction of God’s just judgment
                            against sinful mankind) as the sole ground of our salvation (cf. Schmid,
                                <hi rend="italic">Doctrinal Theology</hi>, pp. 355-70, 449; see also
                            Heppe, <hi rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, ch. xviii). The
                            Anglicans sought to avoid any separation between Christ’s active
                            obedience (Wesley: Christ’s ‘external righteousness’) and his ‘passive
                            righteousness’ (I.3-4); cf. More and Cross, <hi rend="italic">Anglicanism</hi>, pp. 283-316. Puritans like William Perkins had
                            maintained a strong Anselmian doctrine of ‘substitutionary atonement’;
                            Richard Baxter and John Goodwin, even more (cf. <hi rend="italic">Imputatio Fidei</hi>), sound almost like Anglicans on this point
                            (cf. Goodwin’s ‘Preface’, pp. 22-23, and Pts. I. 36-37, and II. 230).
                            The point here is that Wesley is well aware that he is having to thread
                            a careful way through a soteriological minefield.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>II. But when is it that any of us may truly say, ‘the Lord our righteousness’? In
                    other words, when is it that the righteousness of Christ is <hi rend="italic">imputed</hi> to us, and in what sense is it imputed?</p>
                <p n="1">
                    <pb n="454"/>1. Look through all the world, and all the men therein are
                    either believers or unbelievers. The first thing then which admits of no dispute
                    among reasonable men is this: to all believers the righteousness of Christ is
                    imputed; to unbelievers it is not.</p>
                <p>‘But when is it imputed?’ When they believe. In that very hour the righteousness
                    of Christ is theirs. It is imputed to every one that believes, as soon as he
                    believes: faith and the righteousness of Christ are inseparable. For if he
                    believes according to Scripture, he believes in the righteousness of Christ.
                    There is no true faith, that is, justifying faith, which hath not the
                    righteousness of Christ for its object.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It is true believers may not all speak alike; they may not all use the
                    same language. It is not to be expected that they should; we cannot reasonably
                    require it of them. A thousand circumstances may cause them to vary from each
                    other in the manner of expressing themselves. But a difference of expression
                    does not necessarily imply a difference of sentiment. Different persons may use
                    different expressions, and yet mean the same thing. Nothing is more common than
                    this, although we seldom make sufficient allowance for it. Nay, it is not easy
                    for the same persons, when they speak of the same thing at a considerable
                    distance of time, to use exactly the same expressions, even though they retain
                    the same sentiments. How then can we be rigorous in requiring others to use just
                    the same expressions with us?</p>
                <p n="3">3. We may go a step farther yet. Men may differ from us in their opinions
                    as well as their expressions, and nevertheless be partakers with us of the same
                    precious faith. ’Tis possible they may not have a <hi rend="italic">distinct
                        apprehension</hi> of the very blessing which they enjoy. Their <hi rend="italic">ideas</hi> may not be so <hi rend="italic">clear</hi>, and yet
                    their experience maybe as sound as ours. There is a wide difference between the
                    natural faculties of men, their understandings in particular. And that
                    difference is exceedingly increased by the manner of their education. Indeed,
                    this alone may occasion an inconceivable difference in their opinions of various
                    kinds. And why not upon this head as well as on any other? But still, though
                    their opinions as well as expressions may be confused and inaccurate, their
                    hearts may cleave to God through the Son of his love, and be truly interested in
                    his righteousness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">In part, this is a sample of Wesley’s understanding
                            of what ‘catholic spirit’ means in theological dialogue (see No. 39,
                            ‘Catholic Spirit’; cf. also No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6 and
                            n.). But it also reflects his ideas about the radical ambiguity of
                            religious language: no single form of words, in Wesley’s view, could
                            ever suffice to exhaust, or even accurately express, the full meaning of
                            an authentic religious truth, to the exclusion of other equally valid
                            statements.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="4">
                    <pb n="455"/>4. Let us then make all that allowance to others which, were
                    we in their place, we would desire for ourselves. Who is ignorant (to touch
                    again on that circumstance only) of the amazing power of education? And who that
                    knows it can expect, suppose, a member of the Church of Rome either to think or
                    speak clearly on this subject? And yet if we had heard even dying Bellarmine cry
                    out, when he was asked, ‘Unto which of the saints wilt thou turn?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job
                        5:1.</p>
                    </note>—‘<hi rend="italic">Fidere mentis Christi tutissimum</hi>: It
                    is safest to trust in the merits of Christ’—would we have affirmed that
                    notwithstanding his wrong opinions he had no share in his righteousness?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">None of
                            Bellarmine’s biographers records these as his ‘dying words’; cf. Edward
                            Coffin, S. J.,<hi rend="italic">A True Relation of the Last Sickness and
                                Death of Cardinal Bellarmine. Who dyed in Rome the seavententh day
                                of September 1621. And of such things as happened in, or since, his
                                Buriall</hi> (1623). But the story had become folklore at least by
                            the time of Christopher Nesse; cf. <hi rend="italic">A Protestant
                                Antidote Against the Poyson of Popery…</hi> (1679), ch. 3, pp.
                            80-81: ‘…such as those though they live papists, yet they dye
                            protestants, to wit, to the principal foundation of our faith. This
                            Bellarmine himself (their great champion) was driven to for succour when
                            the terrors of death were upon him…’. Nesse’s reference here is to
                            Bellarmine, <hi rend="italic">De Justificatione</hi>, lib. 5, cap. 7;
                            but the only relevant passage in that chapter (or elsewhere in the
                            essay) reads: ‘<hi rend="italic">Sit tertia propositio: “Propter
                                incertitudinem propriae justitiae, et periculum inanis gloriae
                                tutissimum est, fiduciam totam in sola Dei misericordia et
                                benignitate reponere”</hi>’ (‘A third proposition: “Because of the
                            uncertainty of our own true righteousness and the danger of our ‘glory’
                            turning out to be empty, our safest course by far is to rest our entire
                            trust solely in the mercy of God and in his lovingkindness”’); see
                            Bellarmine, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1873), 6:359.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. ‘But in what sense is this righteousness imputed to believers?’ In this:
                    all believers are forgiven and accepted, not for the sake of anything in them,
                    or of anything that ever was, that is, or ever can be done by them, but wholly
                    and solely for the sake of what Christ hath done and suffered for them. I say
                    again, not for the sake of anything in them or done by them, of their own
                    righteousness or works. ‘Not for works of righteousness which we have done, but
                    of his own mercy he saved us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Titus 3:5.</p>
                    </note> ‘By grace ye are saved
                    through faith…. Not of works, lest any man should boast;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:8-9.</p>
                    </note> but
                    wholly and solely for the sake of what Christ hath done and suffered for us. We
                    are ‘justified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jesus
                        Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 3:24.</p>
                    </note> And this is not only the means of our <hi rend="italic">obtaining</hi> the favour of God, but of our <pb n="456"/>continuing therein. It is thus we come to God at first: it is by the same we
                    come unto him ever after. We walk in one and the same ‘new and living way’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        10:20.</p>
                    </note> till our spirit returns to God.</p>
                <p n="6">6. And this is the doctrine which I have constantly believed and taught for
                    near eight and twenty years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note Wesley’s insistence on his unswerving fidelity
                            to the doctrine of justification by faith since 1738, despite all
                            Calvinist charges to the contrary. But note also his grounding of that
                            doctrine, yet once again, in the Anglican standards of
                        doctrine.</p>
                    </note> This I published to all the world in the year 1738, and
                    ten or twelve times since, in those words, and many others to the same effect,
                    extracted from the <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> of our Church:</p>
                <quote>These things must necessarily go together in our justification: upon God’s
                    part his great mercy and grace, upon Christ’s part the satisfaction of God’s
                    justice, and on our part faith in the merits of Christ. So that the grace of God
                    doth not shut out the righteousness of God in our justification, but only
                    shutteth out the righteousness of man, as to <hi rend="italic">deserving</hi>
                    our justification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Salvation,
                                Faith, and Good Works</hi>, I.5. See the original text in the homily
                            ‘Of the Salvation of All Mankind’, Pt. I, in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, pp. 19-20. At least fifteen edns. of Wesley’s
                            abridgement were extant when this sermon was
                    preached.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <quote>That we are justified by faith alone is spoken to take away clearly all merit
                    of our works, and wholly to ascribe the <hi rend="italic">merit</hi> and <hi rend="italic">deserving</hi> of our justification to Christ only. Our
                    justification comes freely of the mere mercy of God. For whereas all the world
                    was not able to pay any part toward our ransom, it pleased him, without any of
                    our deserving, to prepare for us Christ’s body and blood, whereby our ransom
                    might be paid, and his justice satisfied. Christ therefore is now the
                    righteousness of all them that truly believe in him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>,
                            I.7.</p>
                    </note>
                </quote>
                <p n="7">7. The hymns published a year or two after this, and since republished
                    several times (a clear testimony that my judgment was still the same) speak full
                    to the same purpose. To cite all the passages to this effect would be to
                    transcribe a great part of the volumes. Take one for all, which was reprinted
                    seven years ago, five years ago, two years ago, and some months since:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Jesu, thy blood and righteousness</l>
                    <l>My beauty are, my glorious dress:</l>
                    <l>Midst flaming worlds in these arrayed</l>
                    <l>With joy shall I lift up my head.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                            <p rend="footnote text">John Wesley, ‘The Believer’s Triumph’, st. 1
                                (tr. from Zinzendorf’s German), in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and
                                    Sacred Poems</hi> (1740), p. 177 (<hi rend="italic">Poet.
                                    Wks.</hi>, I.346).</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="">The whole expresses the same sentiment from the beginning to the end.</p>
                <p n="8">
                    <pb n="457"/>8. In the sermon on justification published nineteen, and
                    again seven or eight years ago, I express the same thing in these words:</p>
                <quote>In consideration of this, that the Son of God hath ‘tasted death for every
                        man’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 2:9.</p>
                    </note> God hath now ‘reconciled the world unto himself,
                    not imputing to them their former trespasses’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 5:19.</p>
                    </note> […] So that for
                    the sake of his well-beloved Son, of what he hath done and suffered for us, God
                    now vouchsafes on one only condition (which himself also enables us to perform)
                    both to remit the punishment due to our sins, to reinstate us in his favour, and
                    to restore our dead souls to spiritual life, as the earnest of life eternal.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">p. 87 [<hi rend="italic">Sermons on Several Occasions</hi> I (1746); cf.
                                No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, I.8; 2nd edn., by W. Bowyer,
                                1754).</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </quote>
                <p n="9">9. This is more largely and particularly expressed in the <hi rend="italic">Treatise on Justification</hi> which I published last year:</p>
                <quote>If we take the phrase of ‘imputing Christ’s righteousness’ for the bestowing
                    (as it were) the righteousness of Christ, including his obedience, as well
                    passive as active, in the return of it—that is, in the privileges, blessings,
                    and benefits purchased by it—so a believer may be said to be justified by <hi rend="italic">the righteousness of Christ imputed</hi>. The meaning is, God
                    justifies the believer for the sake of Christ’s righteousness, and not for any
                    righteousness of his own. […] So Calvin: ‘Christ by his obedience procured and
                    merited for us grace or favour with God the Father.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">
                                <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi> [Vol. I], II.xvii. [3; cf. LCC, Vol.
                                XX.530-31].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Again, ‘Christ by his obedience procured
                    or purchased righteousness for us.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">
                            <hi rend="italic">Institutes</hi>, III. xiv. 17
                            (LCC, Vol. XX.784). But note Calvin’s full text: ‘Surely the material
                            cause [of justification] is Christ, with his [passive] obedience,
                            through which he acquired righteousness for us. What shall we say is the
                                <hi rend="italic">formal</hi> or instrumental cause but faith?’ It
                            is this thesis that Wesley is here rejecting.</p>
                    </note> And yet again:
                    ‘All such expressions as these—that we are justified by the grace of God, that
                    Christ is our righteousness, that righteousness was procured for us by the death
                    and resurrection of Christ—import the same thing:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s translation of
                            Calvin’s commentary on Gal. 3:6; cf. William Pringle’s translation, <hi rend="italic">Commentaries on the Epistles of Paul to the Galatians
                                and Ephesians</hi> (1849), p. 85. See also Goodwin’s translation of
                            the same passage, p. 9.</p>
                    </note> namely, that the righteousness of
                    Christ, both his active and passive righteousness, is the meritorious cause<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley has here
                            altered Goodwin to his own purpose. Goodwin reads: ‘the righteousness of
                            Christ, meaning chiefly his <hi rend="italic">passive</hi> obedience or
                            righteousness, is the meritorious cause….’ But Wesley is concerned to
                            include ‘<hi rend="italic">both</hi> his active <hi rend="italic">and</hi> passive righteousness as the meritorious cause…’. In this
                            way he reasserts his Anglican ‘both/and’ and also rejects Calvin’s
                            thesis about ‘formal or instrumental cause’ which, in Wesley’s view,
                            carried predestination as a necessary implication.</p>
                    </note> of our
                    justification, and has procured for us at God’s hand that upon our believing we
                    should be accounted righteous by him.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">p. 5. [Not Wesley’s own work but an
                                abridgement of John Goodwin’s <hi rend="italic">Imputatio Fidei</hi>
                                (1642); cf. <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 266. Wesley’s
                                unusually long Preface registers his basic agreement with Goodwin
                                against his detractors—and ignores Toplady’s reference to ‘that
                                Arminian Ranter and Fifth Monarchy Man’ (see Augustus M. Toplady,
                                    <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, II.342-43). Wesley’s quotation
                                here is further abridgement from his original extract; its locus in
                                Goodwin is pp. 8-10.]</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </quote>
                <p n="10">
                    <pb n="458"/>10. But perhaps some will object, ‘Nay, but you affirm that
                    “faith is imputed to us for righteousness.”’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 4:22.</p>
                    </note> St. Paul affirms
                    this over and over; therefore I affirm it too. Faith is imputed for
                    righteousness to every believer; namely, faith in the righteousness of Christ.
                    But this is exactly the same thing which has been said before. For by that
                    expression I mean neither more nor less than that we are justified by faith, not
                    by works;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Gal. 2:16.</p>
                    </note> or that every believer is forgiven and accepted
                    merely for the sake of what Christ has done and suffered.</p>
                <p n="11">11. ‘But is not a believer invested or clothed with the righteousness of
                    Christ?’ Undoubtedly he is. And accordingly the words above-recited are the
                    language of every believing heart:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Jesu, thy blood and righteousness</l>
                    <l>My beauty are, my glorious dress.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                            <p rend="footnote text">See above, II.7 and n.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p>That is, for the sake of thy active and passive righteousness I am forgiven and
                    accepted of God.</p>
                <p>‘But must not we put off the filthy rags of our own righteousness<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 64:6.
                            See also No. 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’.</p>
                    </note> before we can put
                    on the spotless righteousness of Christ?’ Certainly we must; that is, in plain
                    terms, we must ‘repent’ before we can ‘believe the gospel’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 1:15.</p>
                    </note> We must
                    be cut off from dependence upon ourselves before we can truly depend upon
                    Christ. We must cast away all confidence in our own righteousness, or we cannot
                    have a true confidence in his. Till we are delivered from trusting in anything
                    that we do, we cannot throughly trust in what he has done and suffered. First
                    ‘we receive the sentence of death in ourselves;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 1:9.</p>
                    </note>
                    then we trust in him that lived and died for us.</p>
                <p n="12">12. ‘But do not you believe <hi rend="italic">inherent</hi>
                    righteousness?’ Yes, in its proper place; not as the <hi rend="italic">ground</hi> of our acceptance with God, but as the <hi rend="italic">fruit</hi> of it; not in the place of <hi rend="italic">imputed</hi>
                    righteousness, but as consequent upon it. That is, I believe God <hi rend="italic">implants</hi> righteousness in every one to whom he has <hi rend="italic">imputed</hi> it. I believe ‘Jesus Christ is <pb n="459"/>made
                    of God unto us sanctification’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 1:30.</p>
                    </note> as well as
                    righteousness; or that God sanctifies, as well as justifies, all them that
                    believe in him. They to whom the righteousness of Christ is imputed are made
                    righteous by the spirit of Christ, are renewed in the image of God ‘after the
                    likeness wherein they were created, in righteousness and true holiness’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph.
                            4:24.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. ‘But do not you put faith in the room of Christ, or of his
                    righteousness?’ By no means. I take particular care to put each of these in its
                    proper place. The righteousness of Christ is the whole and sole <hi rend="italic">foundation</hi> of all our hope. It is by faith that the Holy
                    Ghost enables us to build upon this foundation. God gives this faith. In that
                    moment we are accepted of God; and yet not for the sake of that faith, but of
                    what Christ has done and suffered for us. You see, each of these has its proper
                    place, and neither clashes with the other: we believe, we love; we endeavour to
                    walk in all the commandments of the Lord blameless.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:6.</p>
                    </note>
                    Yet,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>While thus we bestow</l>
                    <l>Our moments below,</l>
                    <l>Ourselves we forsake,</l>
                    <l>And refuge in Jesus’s righteousness take.</l>
                    <l>His passion alone,</l>
                    <l>The foundation we own:</l>
                    <l>And pardon we claim,</l>
                    <l>And eternal redemption in Jesus’s name.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                            <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘Hymns for Christian
                                Friends’, No. 14, st. 4, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred
                                    Poems</hi> (1749), II.281 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                                V.424). Orig., ‘Thus while we bestow’, and ‘<hi rend="italic">The
                                    foundation</hi>’.</p>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                </lg>
                <p n="14">14. I therefore no more deny the righteousness of Christ than I deny the
                    godhead of Christ. And a man may full as justly charge me with denying the one
                    as the other. Neither do I deny <hi rend="italic">imputed righteousness</hi>:
                    this is another unkind and unjust accusation. I always did, and do still
                    continually affirm, that the righteousness of Christ is imputed to every
                    believer. But who do deny it? Why, all <hi rend="italic">infidels</hi>, whether
                    baptized or unbaptized; all who affirm the glorious gospel of our Lord Jesus
                        Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Cor. 4:4. Here again is Wesley’s prime thesis: that ‘imputation’ is
                            normally followed by ‘implantation’. Thus the typical fruit of imputed
                            righteousness (i.e., pardon) is a ‘renewal [of the soul] in the image of
                            God’ (i.e., holy living).</p>
                    </note> to be a <hi rend="italic">cunningly</hi> devised fable;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 1:16.</p>
                    </note> all Socinians and
                        Arians;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">The
                            followers of Lelio (1525-67) and Faustus Socinus (1539-1604), who had
                            rejected trinitarian orthodoxy and had expounded a unitarian Christology
                            and a moralistic soteriology; they were dubbed ‘Arians’ by their
                            orthodox critics, although they themselves rejected the label. Their
                            views are best summarized in the <hi rend="italic">Racovian
                                Catechism</hi> (1605, 1608, 1609); cf. Earl Morse Wilbur, <hi rend="italic">A History of Unitarianism</hi> (Cambridge, Mass.,
                            Harvard University Press, 1945), chs. xxix-xxxii. John Biddle (1615-62)
                            is reckoned as ‘the father of English Unitarianism’; in Wesley’s time
                            its most prominent spokesmen were John Taylor of Norwich and Joseph
                            Priestley (see below, II.16, and n. 65).</p>
                    </note> all who deny the <pb n="460"/>supreme godhead of the Lord that bought them. They of consequence
                    deny his divine righteousness, as they suppose him to be a mere creature. And
                    they deny his human righteousness as imputed to any man, seeing they believe
                    everyone is accepted <hi rend="italic">for his own righteousness</hi>.</p>
                <p n="15">15. The human righteousness of Christ, at least the imputation of it as
                    the whole and sole meritorious cause of the justification of a sinner before
                    God, is likewise denied by the members of the Church of Rome—by all of them who
                    are true to the principles of their own church.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">How Wesley got this from the canons of Trent
                            (Session Six, ch. vii) is not clear. That text reads: ‘Justification is
                            not merely the remission of sins but also the renewal of the inward man
                            [Wesley’s point about ‘the renewed image’]…. Its meritorious cause is
                            God’s most beloved, only-begotten Son, our Lord Jesus Christ, who, when
                            we were enemies…merited justification for us by his most holy passion on
                            the wood of the cross and made satisfaction for us unto God his
                            Father….’ Is Wesley’s complaint here more than that Trent had declined
                            the absolute designation, ‘whole and sole’?</p>
                    </note> But undoubtedly
                    there are many among them whose experience goes beyond their principles; who,
                    though they are far from expressing themselves justly, yet feel what they know
                    not how to express. Yea, although their conceptions of this great truth be as
                    crude as their expressions, yet ‘with their heart they believe’; they rest on
                    Christ alone, both ‘unto’ present and eternal ‘salvation’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 10:10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="16">16. With these we may rank those even in the Reformed Churches who are
                    usually termed <hi rend="italic">mystics</hi>. One of the chief of these in the
                    present century (at least in England) was Mr. Law.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">William Law had just recently
                            died (1761). As early as 1739, he had turned against ‘faith alone’ in
                                <hi rend="italic">The Grounds and Reasons of Christian
                                Regeneration</hi>. Then, as he grew older, he had been drawn more
                            and more into the orbit of Jacob Boehme. The books that Wesley has here
                            in mind are <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of Prayer</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Spirit of Love</hi> (1752, 1754), <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, VIII.3-133, where Law stresses ‘the
                            indwelling Christ in the soul’ to the exclusion of the doctrine of
                            justification by faith.</p>
                    </note> It is well known that he absolutely
                    and zealously denied the imputation of the righteousness of Christ; as zealously
                    as Robert Barclay, who scruples not to say, ‘Imputed righteousness, imputed
                        nonsense!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">It is well known that Robert Barclay rejected ‘imputed righteousness’
                            out of hand (cf. his <hi rend="italic">Apology</hi>, I.141-44, 188-90;
                            III.360-74, 410-22); in his <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>
                            (1718),I.142,there is a marginal rubric: ‘Imputed righteousness a cloak
                            for wickedness.’ But Professors Hugh Barbour and Elton Trueblood, both
                            Barclay specialists, agree that Wesley’s quotation is not in Barclay’s
                            text nor even in Barclay’s style.</p>
                    </note> The body of the people
                    known by the name <pb n="461"/>of Quakers espouse the same sentiment. Nay, the
                    generality of those who profess themselves members of the Church of England are
                    either totally ignorant of the matter and know nothing about <hi rend="italic">imputed righteousness</hi>, or deny this and justification by faith
                    together as destructive of good works. To these we may add a considerable number
                    of the people vulgarly styled Anabaptists,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Anabaptists’: a blanket term for radical
                            Protestants of various sorts who rejected the official churches and
                            coercive social institutions; cf. Williams, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Radical Reformation</hi>, ch. 33; and Claus-Peter Clasen, <hi rend="italic">Anabaptism: A Social History</hi> (Ithaca, N.Y.,
                            Cornell University Press, 1972). They had flourished in England during
                            the tumults of the Civil War and had survived into Wesley’s time as
                            Baptists, Congregationalists, Familists, etc. The ‘Strict and Particular
                            Baptists’ taught a rigorous doctrine of election and imputation while
                            the ‘General Baptists’ allowed for universal redemption as a possibility
                            by Christ’s atonement. Cf. A. C. Underwood, <hi rend="italic">History of
                                the English Baptists</hi> (London, Kingsgate Press,
                        1947).</p>
                    </note> together with thousands of Presbyterians and Independents
                    lately enlightened by the writings of Dr. Taylor.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Dr. John Taylor of Norwich, a
                            leader in the development of eighteenth-century Dissent from orthodoxy
                            to the sort of unitarianism that one may see full blown in Joseph
                            Priestley, Richard Price, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>; cf. Gerald R.
                            Cragg, <hi rend="italic">The Church and the Age of Reason
                                (1648-1789)</hi>, (Baltimore, Md., Penguin Books, 1960). Taylor and
                            Wesley had dueled over their contrary views of original sin; see above,
                            II.14, and n. 59.</p>
                    </note> On the last I am not called to pass any
                    sentence: I leave them to him that made them. But will anyone dare to affirm
                    that all mystics (such as was Mr. Law in particular), all Quakers, all
                    Presbyterians or Independents, and all members of the Church of England, who are
                    not clear in their opinions or expressions, are void of all Christian
                    experience? That consequently they are all in a state of damnation, ‘without
                    hope, without God in the world’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:12.</p>
                    </note> However confused their
                    ideas may be, however improper their language, may there not be many of them
                    whose heart is right toward God and who effectually know ‘the Lord our
                    righteousness’?</p>
                <p n="17">17. But, blessed be God, we are not among those who are so dark in their
                    conceptions and expressions. We no more deny the <hi rend="italic">phrase</hi>
                    than the <hi rend="italic">thing</hi>; but we are unwilling to obtrude it on
                    other men. Let them use either this or such other expressions as they judge to
                    be more exactly scriptural, provided their <hi rend="italic">heart</hi> rests
                    only on what Christ hath done and suffered for pardon, grace, and glory. I
                    cannot express this better than in Mr. Hervey’s words, worthy to be wrote in
                    letters of gold: ‘We are not solicitous as to <pb n="462"/>any <hi rend="italic">particular set of phrases</hi>. Only let men be humbled as repenting
                    criminals at Christ’s feet, let them rely as devoted pensioners on his merits,
                    and they are undoubtedly in the way to a blessed immortality.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. James Hervey, <hi rend="italic">Theron and Aspasio</hi>, Dial. II (4th edn., 1761,
                            I.55); this is clearly an olive branch to Hervey’s memory, a reconciling
                            gesture to his friends.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="18">18. Is there any need, is there any possibility of saying more? Let us
                    only abide by this declaration, and all the contention about this or that
                    ‘particular phrase’ is torn up by the roots. Keep to this: ‘All who are humbled
                    as repenting criminals at Christ’s feet and rely as devoted pensioners on his
                    merits are in the way to a blessed immortality.’ And what room for dispute? Who
                    denies this? Do we not all meet on this ground? What then shall we wrangle
                    about? A man of peace here proposes terms of accommodation to all the contending
                    parties. We desire no better. We accept of the terms. We subscribe to them with
                    heart and hand. Whoever refuses so to do, set a mark upon that man! He is an
                    enemy of peace, and a troubler of Israel,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Chr. 2:7.</p>
                    </note> a disturber of the
                    church of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of Canon II of the Dedication Council of Antioch, A.D. 341 (<hi rend="italic">In Encaeniis</hi>); cf. No. 27, ‘Sermon an the Mount,
                            VII’, III.7 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="19">19. In the meantime what we are afraid of is this: lest any should use the
                    phrase, ‘the righteousness of Christ’, or, ‘the righteousness of Christ is
                    “imputed to me”,’ as a cover for his unrighteousness. We have known this done a
                    thousand times. A man has been reproved, suppose, for drunkenness. ‘Oh, said he,
                    I pretend to no righteousness of <hi rend="italic">my own</hi>: Christ is <hi rend="italic">my righteousness</hi>.’ Another has been told that ‘the
                    extortioner, the unjust, shall not inherit the kingdom of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            6:9-10.</p>
                    </note> He replies with all assurance, ‘I am unjust in
                    myself, but I have a spotless righteousness in Christ.’ And thus though a man be
                    as far from the practice as from the tempers of a Christian, though he neither
                    has the mind which was in Christ<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 2:5.</p>
                    </note> nor in any respect walks
                    as he walked, yet he has armour of proof against all conviction in what he calls
                    the ‘righteousness of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="20">20. It is the seeing so many deplorable instances of this kind which makes
                    us sparing in the use of these expressions. And I cannot but call upon all of
                    you who use them frequently, and <pb n="463"/>beseech you in the name of God our
                    Saviour, whose you are and whom you serve,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 27:23.</p>
                    </note> earnestly to guard
                    all that hear you against this accursed abuse of it. O warn them (it may be they
                    will hear <hi rend="italic">your</hi> voice) against ‘continuing in sin that
                    grace may abound’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 6:1.</p>
                    </note> Warn them against making
                    ‘Christ the minister of sin’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:17.</p>
                    </note> Against making void that
                    solemn decree of God, ‘without holiness no man shall see the Lord,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                            12:14.</p>
                    </note> by a vain imagination of being <hi rend="italic">holy
                        in Christ</hi>. O warn them that if they remain unrighteous, the
                    righteousness of Christ will profit them nothing! Cry aloud (is there not a
                    cause?) that for this very end the righteousness of Christ is imputed to us,
                    that ‘the righteousness of the law may be fulfilled in us,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:4. Cf. Nos. 34, ‘The
                            Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law’; and 35 and 36, ‘The
                            Law Established through Faith’, Discourses I and II.</p>
                    </note> and that
                    we may ‘live soberly, religiously, and godly in this present world.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus
                        2:12.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p>It remains only to make a short and plain application.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by
                            Faith’, IV.9 and n.</p>
                    </note> And first I would address myself to you
                    who violently oppose these expressions, and are ready to condemn all that use
                    them as antinomians. But is not this bending the bow too much the other
                        way?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. the
                            memorandum of Jan. 25, 1738, noted in JWJ. See also Echard, <hi rend="italic">Eccles. Hist.</hi>, III.vi.426: ‘He bent the stick too
                            much the contrary way.’</p>
                    </note> Why should you condemn all who do not
                    speak just as you do? Why should you quarrel with <hi rend="italic">them</hi>
                    for using the phrases they like, any more than they with <hi rend="italic">you</hi> for taking the same liberty? Or if they do quarrel with you upon
                    that account, do not imitate the bigotry which you blame. At least allow <hi rend="italic">them</hi> the liberty which they ought to allow <hi rend="italic">you</hi>. And why should you be angry at an <hi rend="italic">expression</hi>? ‘Oh, it has been abused.’ And what expression has not?
                    However, the abuse may be removed, and at the same time the use remain.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">This aphorism on
                            ‘use and abuse’ is a favourite of Wesley’s; cf., e.g., Nos. 24, ‘Sermon
                            on the Mount, IV’, III.6; 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, II.2; 42,
                            ‘Satan’s Devices’, II.8; 78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, I.14; 108, ‘On
                            Riches’, II.12. It appears often in seventeenth- and eighteenth-century
                            literature. Cf. George Chapman’s translation of Homer’s <hi rend="italic">Odyssey</hi> (Bk. xxiv), p. 526:</p>
                        <lg>
                            <l>It is the ground of age, when cares abuse it,</l>
                            <l>To know life’s end, and, as ’tis sweet so use it.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also Richard Graves, <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Quixote</hi> (1772), Vol. II, ch. 2 (see 1820 edn.,
                            II.7): ‘Our master does not deny us the use but only the abuse of his
                            good creatures.’</p>
                    </note> Above all be sure to retain the important
                    sense which is couched under that expression. All the blessings I enjoy, <pb n="464"/>all I hope for in time and in eternity, are given wholly and solely
                    for the sake of what Christ has done and suffered for me.</p>
                <p>I would, secondly, add a few words to you who are fond of these expressions. And
                    permit me to ask, Do not I allow enough? What can any reasonable man desire
                    more? I allow the whole <hi rend="italic">sense</hi> which you contend for: that
                    we have every blessing ‘through the righteousness of God our Saviour’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet.
                            1:1.</p>
                    </note> I allow <hi rend="italic">you</hi> to use whatever
                    expressions you choose, and that a thousand times over; only guarding them
                    against that dreadful abuse which you are as deeply concerned to prevent as I
                    am. I myself frequently use the expression in question, ‘imputed righteousness’;
                    and often put this and the like expressions into the mouth of a whole
                    congregation. But allow me liberty of conscience herein: allow me the right of
                    private judgment.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. JWJ, Mar. 25, 1743; see also <hi rend="italic">The Old Whig: Or, the Consistent Protestant</hi> (1739), No. 4, in
                            Vol. I, pp. 32-33.</p>
                    </note> Allow me to use it just as often as I
                    judge it preferable to any other expression. And be not angry with me if I
                    cannot judge it proper to use any one expression every two minutes. <hi rend="italic">You</hi> may if you please; but do not condemn me because I do
                    not. Do not for this represent me as a Papist, or ‘an enemy to the righteousness
                    of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Wesley’s letter to John Erskine, Apr. 24, 1765; see also his <hi rend="italic">Remarks on A Defence of…Aspasio
                        Vindicated</hi>.</p>
                    </note> Bear with <hi rend="italic">me</hi>, as I do
                    with <hi rend="italic">you</hi>; else how shall we ‘fulfil the law of
                        Christ’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 6:2.</p>
                    </note> Do not make tragical outcries, as though I was
                    ‘subverting the very foundations of Christianity’. Whoever does this does me
                    much wrong: the Lord lay it not to his charge!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Acts 7:60.</p>
                    </note> I lay, and have
                    done for many years, the very same foundation with you. And indeed ‘other
                    foundation can no man lay than that which is laid, even Jesus Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor.
                            3:11.</p>
                    </note> I build inward and outward holiness thereon, as you do,
                    even by faith. Do not therefore suffer any distaste, or unkindness, no, nor any
                    shyness or coldness in your heart. If there were <hi rend="italic">a difference
                        of opinion</hi>, where is our religion if we cannot <hi rend="italic">think
                        and let think</hi>?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 7, ‘The Way to the Kingdom’, I.6 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> What hinders but you may forgive <hi rend="italic">me</hi> as
                    easily as I may forgive <hi rend="italic">you</hi>? How much more when there is
                    only <hi rend="italic">a difference of expression</hi>? Nay, hardly so much as
                    that—all the dispute being only whether a particular mode of expression shall be
                    used <hi rend="italic">more or less frequently</hi>! <pb n="465"/>Surely we must
                    earnestly desire to contend with one another before we can make this a bone of
                    contention! O let us not any more for such very trifles as these give our common
                    enemies room to blaspheme!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Sam. 12:14.</p>
                    </note> Rather let us at
                    length cut off occasion from them that seek occasion!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 11:12.</p>
                    </note>
                    Let us at length (O why was it not done before?) join hearts and hands in the
                    service of our great Master. As we have ‘one Lord, one faith, one hope of our
                        calling’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:4-5.</p>
                    </note> let us all strengthen each other’s hands in
                    God, and with one heart and one mouth declare to all mankind, ‘the Lord our
                    righteousness’.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>