<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 34: The Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-26</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 34: The Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of
                                the Law</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:001"/>
            <introduction>
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment [to Sermons 34-36]</hi>
                </head>
                <p>The most patent danger in Wesley’s delicate balancing of faith alone and holy
                    living was its possible tilt toward moralism (‘<hi rend="italic">inherent</hi>
                    righteousness’); something of this sort did eventually occur in Methodism after
                    Wesley’s death, despite all his earnest efforts to safeguard his gospel against
                    it. But the opposite extreme, antinomianism, was already a clear and present
                    danger among the Methodists; several versions of it were even then being
                    vigorously asserted, as if antinomianism were a valid consequence of ‘faith
                    alone’. This controversy had emerged with the Revival itself, in Wesley’s
                    disagreements with the Moravians (cf. JWJ, November 1, 1739, April 19-26, 1740).
                    It had been carried forward by the reckless rhetoric of men like William
                    Cudworth, minister of the Grey Eagle Street Church in London, although Wesley
                    had found its substance in the more sophisticated teachings of James Hervey and
                    others.</p>
                <p>In 1741 (September 3) Wesley had debated the issue of faith and good works with
                    Count von Zinzendorf in London. Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> record
                    of this passage at arms, along with his earlier denunciations of Whitefield’s
                    ‘Calvinism ’, etc., had drawn fire from the antinomians (and from some
                    Calvinists). In 1745, Cudworth had published a twenty-five page <hi
                        rend="italic">Dialogue Between a Preacher of God’s Righteousness and a
                        Preacher of Inherent Righteousness</hi>, in which he spoke ‘for God’ and
                    allowed Wesley to speak for ‘inherent righteousness’; cf. <hi rend="italic"
                        >Christ Alone Exalted</hi> (1747), in which Cudworth’s tract is No. VIII.
                    The urgency of this is evident from the manuscript Minutes of the second Annual
                    Conference in Bristol, August 2,1745, in Questions 24-26 and their answers:</p>
                <quote>Q. 24. Wherein may we come to the very edge of antinomianism?</quote>
                <quote>A. (1). In exalting the merits and love of Christ.</quote>
                <quote>(2). In rejoicing evermore.</quote>
                <quote>><pb n="02:002"/>Q. 25. What can we do to stop the progress of
                    antinomianism?</quote>
                <quote>A. (1). Pray without ceasing that God would speak for himself.</quote>
                <quote>(2). Write one or two more dialogues.</quote>
                <quote>Q. 26. Doth faith supersede (set aside the necessity of holiness or good
                    works?</quote>
                <quote>A. <hi rend="italic">In no wise. So far from it that it implies both, as a
                        cause doth its effects.</hi></quote>
                <p>The proposed ‘one or two more dialogues’ promptly appeared in the same year: <hi
                        rend="italic">A Dialogue between an Antinomian and his Friend</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">A Second Dialogue between an Antinomian and his Friend</hi>.
                    The first dialogue was a sort of reenactment of the 1741 debate with Zinzendorf,
                    with Zinzendorf’s original words now translated from the Latin and with Wesley’s
                    original replies revised. The second pamphlet was Wesley’s rejoinder to
                    Cudworth’s <hi rend="italic">Dialogue</hi>; it concludes with what was intended
                    to be a recapitulation of the discussion as a whole. Unsurprisingly, though,
                    these dialogues had not concluded the affair, as we see from many <hi
                        rend="italic">Journal</hi> entries over the ensuing five years (see
                    especially October 30 and December 11, 1749, etc.). It was, therefore, both
                    urgent and appropriate for Wesley to follow his thirteen sermons on the Sermon
                    on the Mount with three additional sermonic essays on the complex, dynamic
                    interdependence of ‘Law and Gospel’ in his doctrine of salvation. This was the
                    aim and occasion of the following sermons.</p>
                <p>Despite their complex development, the sermon outlines are plain and simple. The
                    ‘original’ of the Law is man’s inborn moral sense—not ‘natural’ in the deist
                    sense but, rather, as an aspect of the residual <hi rend="italic">imago
                    Dei</hi>. The ‘nature’ of the Law is <hi rend="italic">Christological</hi>, as
                    if Torah and Christ are in some sense to be equated. The ‘properties’ of the Law
                    are threefold, and here Wesley follows the standard Puritan exegesis of Rom.
                    7:12 as to the Law’s holiness and its instrumentality in the delineation of the
                    just and the good. Incidentally, seven of the eight contemporary editions of
                    this sermon here read ‘properties’, in the plural; only the text of <hi
                        rend="italic">Works</hi> (1771) has ‘property’ (but both Jackson and Sugden
                    seem to have preferred the singular). Wesley’s brief discussion of the ‘uses of
                    the Law’ ignores the fact of the extended debate over ‘the <hi rend="italic"
                        >third</hi> use of the Law’ between the Lutherans and the Calvinists, and
                    obscures the further fact that Wesley has come down squarely on the Puritan side
                    of the argument: the threefold ‘use’ of the Law is to convict, convert, <hi
                        rend="italic">and sustain the believer</hi>—in and after justification (see
                    below, No. 34, IV.1 and n.).</p>
                <p><pb n="02:003"/>The twin discourses entitled ‘The Law Established through Faith’
                    amount to a single essay in two parts. In the first, Wesley turns on his critics
                    and charges them with ‘voiding the Law’ by (1) ‘not preaching it at all’, and
                    (2) by preaching ‘faith’ so as to ‘supersede the necessity of holiness’. In the
                    second part, he argues that the Law is and ought to be ‘established <hi
                        rend="italic">by faith</hi>’: (1) by a doctrine in which salvation by faith
                    is understood as the foundation on which the whole enterprise of Christian
                    living must rest; (2) by preaching ‘faith alone’ so as to promote ‘holiness’
                    rather than to supersede or subordinate it; and (3) by the manifestation of holy
                    living in Christian hearts and lives.</p>
                <p>What we have here, then, is a further variation on the central theme of the
                    preceding thirteen sermons: the distinctive character of evangelical ethics in
                    which the <hi rend="italic">fides caritate formata</hi> is always the consequent
                    of the <hi rend="italic">sola fide</hi>, never its alternative. They also have
                    in them (Discourse II, II.1-6) one of Wesley’s most interesting and original
                    proposals: that ‘faith is in order to love’ and, therefore, that ‘love will
                    exist after faith’—which may or may not be an amendment of 1 Cor. 13:13; cf.
                    Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on this verse: ‘Faith, hope, and love are
                    the sum of perfection on earth; love alone is the sum of perfection in
                    heaven.’</p>
                <p>These sermons were ‘tracts for the times’ and not the distillate of oral
                    preaching. This appears from the fact that we have no record of Wesley’s having
                    preached on Rom. 7:12, ever, and there are only two clear references to his use
                    of Rom. 3:31 (June 27 and August 2, 1741). A possible third reference may be in
                    the <hi rend="italic">Journal</hi> entry for April 25, 1745: ‘I preached at
                    Little Horton and Bradford.’ Here I ‘could not but observe how God has made void
                    all their labour who “make void the law through faith”.’ More than likely,
                    though, this is either a comment on a local circumstance or, at most, one of the
                    ‘heads’ in a sermon with another, unspecified text. For a publishing history of
                    Nos. 34-36 and a list of variant readings in their successive texts, see
                    Appendix, Vol. 4; see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 130.</p>
            </introduction>
            <pb n="02:004"/>
            <head>The Original, Nature, Properties, and Use of the Law</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Romans 7:12</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just,
                        and good.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Perhaps there are few subjects within the whole compass of religion so
                    little understood as this. The reader of this Epistle is usually told, ‘By “the
                    law” St. Paul means the Jewish law;’ and so, apprehending himself to have no
                    concern therewith, passes on without farther thought about it. Indeed some are
                    not satisfied with this account; but observing the Epistle is directed to the
                    Romans, thence infer that the Apostle in the beginning of this chapter alludes
                    to the old Roman law. But as they have no more concern with this than with the
                    ceremonial law of Moses, so they spend not much thought on what they suppose is
                    occasionally mentioned, barely to illustrate another thing.</p>
                <p n="2">2. But a careful observer of the Apostle’s discourse will not be content
                    with those slight explications of it. And the more he weighs the words, the more
                    convinced he will be that St. Paul, by ‘the law’ mentioned in this chapter, does
                    not mean either the ancient law of Rome or the ceremonial law of Moses. This
                    will clearly appear to all who attentively consider the tenor of his discourse.
                    He begins the chapter, ‘Know ye not, brethren (for I speak to them that know the
                    law)’—to them who have been instructed therein from their youth—‘that the law
                    hath dominion over a man as long as he liveth?’<hi rend="endnote_reference"
                            ><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">[Rom. 7,] ver.
                        1.</p></note></hi> What? The law of Rome only, or the ceremonial law? No,
                    surely; but the <hi rend="italic">moral</hi> law. ‘For’, to give a plain
                    instance, ‘the woman that hath an husband is bound by the (moral) law to her
                    husband as long as he liveth. But if her husband be dead, she is loosed from the
                    law of her husband.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. 2.</p></note></hi> ‘So, then, if while her
                    husband liveth she be married to another man, she shall <pb n="02:005"/> be
                    called an adulteress: but if her husband be dead she is free from that law, so
                    that she is no adulteress, though she be married to another man.’<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                3.</p></note></hi> From this particular instance the Apostle
                    proceeds to draw that general conclusion: ‘Wherefore, my brethren’, by a plain
                    parity of reason, ‘ye also are become dead to the law’, the whole Mosaic
                    institution, ‘by the body of Christ’ offered for you, and bringing you under a
                    new dispensation: ‘that ye should’ without any blame ‘be married to another,
                    even to him who is raised from the dead’, and hath thereby given proof of his
                    authority to make the change, ‘that ye should bring forth fruit unto God’.<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                4.</p></note></hi> And this we can do now, whereas before we could
                    not: ‘For when we were in the flesh’, under the power of the flesh, that is, of
                    corrupt nature (which was necessarily the case till we knew the power of
                    Christ’s resurrection)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Phil. 3:10.</p></note>, ‘the motions of sins
                    which were by the law’, which were shown and inflamed by the Mosaic law, not
                    conquered, ‘did work in our members’, broke out various ways, ‘to bring forth
                    fruit unto death.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Ver. 5.</p></note></hi> ‘But now we are
                    delivered from the law’, from that whole moral as well as ceremonial economy;
                    ‘that being dead whereby we were held’—that entire institution being now as it
                    were dead, and having no more authority over us than the husband when dead hath
                    over his wife—‘that we should serve’ him who died for us and rose again ‘in
                    newness of spirit’, in a new spiritual dispensation, ‘and not in the oldness of
                    the letter’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                >Ver. 6.</p></note></hi>—with a bare outward service, according to
                    the letter of the Mosaic institution.</p>
                <p n="3">3. The Apostle having gone thus far in proving that the Christian had set
                    aside the Jewish dispensation, and that the moral law itself, though it could
                    never pass away, yet stood on a different foundation from what it did before,
                    now stops to propose and answer an objection. ‘What shall we say then? Is the
                    law sin?’ So some might infer from a misapprehension of those words, ‘the
                    motions of sin which were by the law’. ‘God forbid!’ saith the Apostle, that we
                    should say so. ‘Nay’, the law is an irreconcilable enemy to sin, searching it
                    out wherever it is. ‘I had not known sin but by the law. I had not known lust’,
                    evil desire, to be sin, ‘except the law had said, Thou shalt not covet’.<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">Ver.
                                7.</p></note></hi> After opening this farther in the four following
                    verses, he subjoins this <pb n="02:006"/>general conclusion with regard more
                    especially to the moral law, from which the preceding instance was taken:
                    ‘Wherefore the law is holy, and the commandment holy, and just, and good.’</p>
                <p n="4">4. In order to explain and enforce these deep words, so little regarded
                    because so little understood, I shall endeavour to show, first, the original of
                    this law; secondly, the nature thereof; thirdly, the properties, that it is
                    ‘holy, and just, and good’; and fourthly, the uses of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. I shall, first, endeavour to show the original of the moral law,
                    often called ‘the law’ by way of eminence.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">‘In its highest degree’; cf. this seventeenth-
                            eighteenth-century usage of ‘eminence’ in <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>,
                            8c.</p></note> Now this is not, as some may possibly have imagined, of
                    so late an institution as the time of Moses. Noah declared it to men long before
                    that time, and Enoch before him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The notion of the revelation of the moral law to
                            Noah is reflected in the decision of ‘the council of Jerusalem’ (Acts
                            15:1-20, echoing Gen. 9:12-17; cf. 2 Pet 2:5 and Heb. 11:7). Enoch’s
                            special place in covenant history may be seen in Wisd. 4:10; Jude 14; in
                            the apocryphal book of Enoch, 106-7; and in Ecclus. 44:16, ‘a sign of
                            knowledge [of the Law] to all generations’.</p></note> But we may trace
                    its original higher still, even beyond the foundation of the world to that
                    period, unknown indeed to men, but doubtless enrolled in the annals of eternity,
                    when ‘the morning stars’ first ‘sang together’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4"
                        n="4"><p rend="footnote text">Job 38:7.</p></note> being newly called into
                    existence. It pleased the great Creator to make these his first-born sons
                    intelligent beings, that they might know him that created them. For this end he
                    endued them with understanding, to discern truth from falsehood, good from evil;
                    and as a necessary result of this, with liberty, a capacity of choosing the one
                    and refusing the other. By this they were likewise enabled to offer him a free
                    and willing service: a service rewardable in itself, as well as most acceptable
                    to their gracious Master.</p>
                <p n="2">2. To employ all the faculties which he had given them, particularly their
                    understanding and liberty, he gave them a law, a complete model of all truth, so
                    far as was intelligible to a finite being, and of all good, so far as angelic
                    minds were capable of embracing it. It was also the design of their beneficent
                    Governor herein to make way for a continual increase of their happiness; seeing
                    every instance of obedience to that law would both add to the perfection of
                    their nature and entitle them to an higher reward, which the righteous Judge
                    would give in its season.</p>
                <p n="3"><pb n="02:007"/>3. In like manner, when God in his appointed time had
                    created a new order of intelligent beings, when he had raised man from the dust
                    of the earth, breathed into him the breath of life, and caused him to become a
                    living soul,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Gen.
                            2:7.</p></note> endued with power to choose good or evil, he gave to
                    this free, intelligent creature the same law as to his first-born children<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">I.e., the angels,
                            as in Gen. 6:2, 4; Job 38:7; and Ps. 82:6; cf. No. 141, ‘The Image of
                            God’, for Wesley’s early view of God’s gift of the Law to
                        Adam.</p></note>—not wrote indeed upon tables of stone, or any corruptible
                    substance, but engraven on his heart by the finger of God, wrote in the inmost
                    spirit both of men and of angels—to the intent it might never be far off, never
                    hard to be understood; but always at hand, and always shining with clear light,
                    even as the sun in the midst of heaven.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Such was the original of the law of God. With regard to man, it was
                    coeval with his nature. But with regard to the elder sons of God, it shone in
                    its full splendour ‘or ever the mountains were brought forth, or the earth and
                    the round world were made’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 90:2 (BCP).</p></note> But it was not long
                    before man rebelled against God, and by breaking this glorious law wellnigh
                    effaced it out of his heart; ‘the eyes of his understanding’ being <hi
                        rend="italic">darkened</hi><note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 1:18.</p></note> in the same measure as
                    his soul was ‘alienated from the life of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9"
                        n="9"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:18. Cf. also Charles Wesley, ‘The
                            Beatitudes’, ‘Alien from the life of God’, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns
                                and Sacred Poems</hi> (1749), I.35, 37.</p></note> And yet God did
                    not despise the work of his own hands; but being reconciled to man through the
                    Son of his love, he in some measure re-inscribed the law on the heart of his
                    dark, sinful creature.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p
                            rend="footnote text">This notion of ‘re-inscription’ is crucial for
                            Wesley’s doctrine of the human <hi rend="italic">in se</hi> as a divine
                            gift (exceeding ‘nature’) and of ‘prevenient grace’.</p></note> ‘He’
                    again ‘showed thee, O man, what is good’ (although not as in the beginning),
                    ‘even to do justly, and to love mercy, and to walk humbly with thy God.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Mic.
                        6:8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. And this he showed not only to our first parents, but likewise to all
                    their posterity, by ‘that true light which enlightens every man that cometh into
                    the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 1:9; cf. this illuminist motif with similar ideas in No. 10,‘The
                            Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p></note> But notwithstanding
                    this light, all flesh had in process of time ‘corrupted their way before
                        him’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gen. 6:12.</p></note> till he chose out of mankind a peculiar
                        people,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 2:9.</p></note> to whom he gave a more perfect knowledge of his
                    law. And the heads of this, because <pb n="02:008"/> they were slow of
                    understanding, he wrote on two tables of stone; which he commanded the fathers
                    to teach their children through all succeeding generations.</p>
                <p n="6">6. And thus it is that the law of God is now made known to them that know
                    not God. They hear, with the hearing of the ear, the things that were written
                    aforetime for our instruction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Rom. 15:4.</p></note> But this does not
                    suffice. They cannot by this means comprehend the height and depth and length
                    and breadth thereof.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Eph. 3:18.</p></note> God alone can reveal this
                    by his Spirit. And so he does to all that truly believe, in consequence of that
                    gracious promise made to all the Israel of God: ‘Behold, the days come, saith
                    the Lord, that I will make a new covenant with the house of Israel…. And this
                    shall be the covenant that I will make…. I will put my law in their inward
                    parts, and write it in their hearts; and I will be their God, and they shall be
                    my people.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                >Jer. 31:31, 33.</p></note></hi></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. The nature of that law which was originally given to angels in
                    heaven and man in paradise, and which God has so mercifully promised to write
                    afresh in the hearts of all true believers, was the second thing I proposed to
                    show. In order to which I would first observe that although ‘the law’ and ‘the
                    commandment’ are sometimes differently taken (the commandment meaning but a part
                    of the law) yet in the text they are used as equivalent terms, implying one and
                    the same thing. But we cannot understand here, either by one or the other, the
                    ceremonial law. ’Tis not the ceremonial law whereof the Apostle says, in the
                    words above recited, ‘I had not known sin but by the law:’ this is too plain to
                    need a proof. Neither is it the ceremonial law which saith, in the words
                    immediately subjoined, ‘Thou shalt not covet.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17"
                        n="17"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:7; cf. Exod. 20:17.</p></note>
                    Therefore the ceremonial law has no place in the present question.</p>
                <p n="2">2. Neither can we understand by the law mentioned in the text the Mosaic
                    dispensation. ’Tis true the word is sometimes so understood: as when the Apostle
                    says, speaking to the Galatians, ‘The covenant which was confirmed before’
                    (namely with Abraham the father of the faithful), ‘the law’, i.e. the Mosaic
                    dispensation, ‘which was four hundred and thirty years after, <pb n="02:009"
                    />cannot disannul.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p
                                rend="endnote text">Chap. 3, ver. 17.</p></note></hi> But it cannot
                    be so understood in the text; for the Apostle never bestows so high
                    commendations as these upon that imperfect and shadowy dispensation. He nowhere
                    affirms the Mosaic to be a <hi rend="italic">spiritual</hi> law; or that it is
                    ‘holy, and just, and good’. Neither is it true that God ‘will write that law in
                    the hearts’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jer. 31:33.</p></note> of them whose ‘iniquities he remembers no
                        more’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 6:12; 10:17.</p></note> It remains that ‘the law’, eminently so
                    termed, is no other than the moral law.</p>
                <p n="3">3. Now this law is an incorruptible picture of the high and holy One that
                    inhabiteth eternity.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Isa. 57:15. This view of the moral law as a
                            divine hypostasis is a prime factor in Wesley’s Christology (i.e.,
                            Christ as Torah incarnate), soteriology (i.e., the <hi rend="italic"
                                >justice</hi> of justification), and ethics (i.e., the correlation
                            of the moral law and holy living).</p></note> It is he whom in his
                    essence no man hath seen or can see, made visible to men and angels. It is the
                    face of God unveiled; God manifested to his creatures as they are able to bear
                    it; manifested to give and not to destroy life; that they may see God and live.
                    It is the heart of God disclosed to man. Yea, in some sense we may apply to this
                    law what the Apostle says of his Son—it is ‘the streaming forth’ or outbeaming
                    ‘of his glory, the express image of his person’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn21" n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 1:3. Wesley’s text of
                            1771 quotes the Greek orig. here. Cf. No. 15, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Great Assise</hi>, II.1 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. ‘If virtue’, said the ancient heathen, ‘could assume such a shape as
                    that we could behold her with our eyes, what wonderful love would she excite in
                        us!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Cicero, <hi rend="italic">De Officiis (On Moral Obligations)</hi>, I.5:
                            ‘You see here…the true form of virtue; “and if”, as Plato says, “it
                            could be seen with the bodily eye it would awaken a marvellous love of
                            wisdom”—cf. <hi rend="italic">Phaedrus</hi>, 250<hi rend="italic"
                                >d:</hi> ‘[wisdom’s] loveliness would be transporting if only there
                            were a visible image of her.’ Note the comment in the Elizabethan
                            Homily, ‘On Repentance’, Pt. ΙII (<hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi>, p.
                            486): ‘Plato doth in a certain place write that if virtue could be seen
                            with bodily eyes, all men would be wonderfully inflamed and kindled with
                            the love of it.’ Cf. Samuel Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Discourse
                                Concerning the Unchangeable Obligations of Natural Religion and the
                                Truth and Certainty of the Christian Revelation</hi> (1706), p. 89,
                            where in place of wisdom and virtue Clarke prefers the phrase ‘universal
                            justice’. See also <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt II,
                            ΙII.22 (11:269 in this edn.).</p></note> If virtue could do this! It is
                    done already. The law of God is all virtues in one, in such a shape as to be
                    beheld with open face by all those whose eyes God hath enlightened. What is the
                    law but divine virtue and wisdom assuming a visible form? What is it but the
                    original ideas of truth and good, which were lodged in the uncreated mind from
                        <pb n="02:010"/>eternity, now drawn forth and clothed with such a vehicle as
                    to appear even to human understanding?</p>
                <p n="5">5. If we survey the law of God in another point of view, it is supreme,
                    unchangeable reason; it is unalterable rectitude; it is the everlasting fitness
                    of all things<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Clarke, <hi rend="italic">Demonstration of the Being and Attributes of
                                God</hi>, Prop. XII. But see No. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the
                            Heart’, II.3, where Wesley had denounced the notion of ‘everlasting
                            fitness’.</p></note> that are or ever were created. I am sensible what a
                    shortness, and even impropriety, there is in these and all other human
                    expressions, when we endeavour by these faint pictures to shadow out the deep
                    things of God. Nevertheless we have no better, indeed no other way, during this
                    our infant state of existence. As ‘we’ now ‘know’ but ‘in part’, so we are
                    constrained to ‘prophesy’, i.e. speak of the things of God, ‘in part’ also.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p rend="footnote text">See 1 Cor.
                            13:9.</p></note> ‘We cannot order our speech by reason of darkness’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">Job
                        37:19.</p></note> while we are in this house of clay.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">See Job 4:19. Cf. also No. 28,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, VIII’, §21 and n.</p></note> While I am ‘a child’
                    I must ‘speak as a child’. But I shall soon ‘put away childish things’. For
                    ‘when that which is perfect is come, that which is in part shall be done
                        away.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 13:10, 11.</p></note></p>
                <p n="6">6. But to return. The law of God (speaking after the manner of men) is a
                    copy of the eternal mind, a transcript of the divine nature; yea, it is the
                    fairest offspring of the everlasting Father, the brightest efflux of his
                    essential wisdom, the visible beauty of the Most High.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 1:15-19, for a
                            striking parallel between Wesley’s characterizations of the Law and the
                            Christological metaphors in Colossians.</p></note> It is the delight and
                    wonder of cherubim and seraphim and all the company of heaven,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Communion,
                            Sanctus.</p></note> and the glory and joy of every wise believer, every
                    well instructed child of God upon earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. Such is the nature of the ever-blessed law of God. I am, in the
                    third place, to show the properties of it. Not all, for that would exceed the
                    wisdom of an angel; but those only which are mentioned in the text. These are
                    three: It is ‘holy, just, and good’. And first, ‘the law is holy.’</p>
                <p n="2">2. In this expression the Apostle does not appear to speak of its effects,
                    but rather of its nature. As St. James, speaking of the same thing under another
                    name, says, ‘The wisdom from above’ (which <pb n="02:011"/>is no other than this
                    law, written in our heart) ‘is first pure,’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note
                            place="end"><p rend="endnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi> [Jas.
                                3:17].</p></note></hi> ἁγνή—chaste, spotless, internally and
                    essentially holy.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text">All nine edns. in Wesley’s lifetime read
                            ‘internally’, and this would seem to mean ‘inherently’, or something
                            like that. Jackson, sensing that ‘eternally’ would fit Wesley’s argument
                            more consistently (by adding a temporal dimension), changed the reading
                            either conjecturally or on the basis of a MS <hi rend="italic"
                                >erratum</hi> now lost. Sugden followed Jackson here without
                            comment; it is a reasonable guess that Wesley had written ‘eternally’,
                            and that his printer had misread him, although his writing in 1750 was
                            perfectly legible.</p></note> And consequently, when it is transcribed
                    into the life, as well as the soul, it is (as the same Apostle terms it),
                    θρησκεία καθαρὰ καὶ ἀμίαντος, ‘pure religion and undefiled’;<hi
                        rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text">[Jas.]
                                1:27.</p></note></hi> or, the pure, clean, unpolluted worship of
                    God.</p>
                <p n="3">3. It is indeed in the highest degree pure, chaste, clean, holy. Otherwise
                    it could not be the immediate offspring, and much less the express resemblance
                    of God, who is essential holiness. It is pure from all sin, clean and unspotted
                    from any touch of evil. It is a chaste virgin, incapable of any defilement, of
                    any mixture with that which is unclean or unholy. It has no fellowship with sin
                    of any kind; for ‘what communion hath light with darkness?’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:14.</p></note> As sin
                    is in its very nature enmity to God, so his law is enmity to sin.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Therefore it is that the Apostle rejects with such abhorrence that
                    blasphemous supposition that the law of God is either sin itself or the cause of
                    sin. ‘God forbid’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:7.</p></note> that we should suppose it is
                    the cause of sin because it is the discoverer of it; because it detects the
                    hidden things of darkness,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 4:5.</p></note> and drags them out into open
                    day. ’Tis true, by this means (as the Apostle observes, verse 13) ‘sin appears
                    to be sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Rom. 7:13.</p></note> All its disguises are torn away, and it appears in
                    its native deformity. ’Tis true likewise that ‘sin by the commandment becomes
                    exceeding sinful.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi></p></note> Being
                    now committed against light and knowledge, being stripped even of the poor plea
                    of ignorance, it loses its excuse as well as disguise, and becomes far more
                    odious both to God and man. Yea, and it is true that ‘sin worketh death by that
                    which is good,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi></p></note> which in itself is pure and
                    holy. When it is dragged out to light it rages the more: when it is restrained
                    it bursts out with greater violence. Thus the Apostle, speaking in the person of
                    one who was convinced of sin but not yet delivered from it, ‘sin taking occasion
                    by the <pb n="02:012"/>commandment’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:11.</p></note> detecting and endeavouring to
                    restrain it, disdained the restraint, and so much the more ‘wrought in me all
                    manner of concupiscence’ (verse 8)—all manner of foolish and hurtful
                        desire,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 Tim. 6:9.</p></note> which that commandment sought to restrain. Thus
                    ‘when the commandment came, sin revived’ (verse 9). It fretted and raged the
                    more. But this is no stain on the commandment. Though it is abused it cannot be
                    defiled. This only proves that ‘the heart’ of man ‘is desperately wicked.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">Jer.
                        17:9.</p></note> But ‘the law’ of God ‘is holy’ still.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:12.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. And it is, secondly, <hi rend="italic">just</hi>. It renders to all
                    their due. It prescribes exactly what is right, precisely what ought to be done,
                    said, or thought, both with regard to the Author of our being, with regard to
                    ourselves, and with regard to every creature which he has made. It is adapted in
                    all respects to the nature of things, of the whole universe and every
                    individual. It is suited to all the circumstances of each, and to all their
                    mutual relations, whether such as have existed from the beginning, or such as
                    commenced in any following period. It is exactly agreeable to the fitnesses of
                    things, whether essential or accidental. It clashes with none of these in any
                    degree, nor is ever unconnected with them. If the word be taken in that sense,
                    there is nothing <hi rend="italic">arbitrary</hi> in the law of God: although
                    still the whole and every part thereof is totally dependent upon his will, so
                    that ‘Thy will be done’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Matt. 6:10; 26:42.</p></note> is the supreme
                    universal law both in earth and heaven.</p>
                <p n="6">6. ‘But is the will of God the cause of his law? Is his will the original
                    of right and wrong? Is a thing therefore right because God wills it? Or does he
                    will it because it is right?’</p>
                <p>I fear this celebrated question<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                            rend="footnote text">‘Celebrated’, indeed, at least since Plato, who
                            understood ‘God’ as the Supreme Agent of the Supreme Good, as in the <hi
                                rend="italic">Philebus</hi> 230, ‘the <hi rend="italic">cause</hi>
                            of the [cosmic] mixture’, or the <hi rend="italic">Timaeus</hi> 28<hi
                                rend="italic">c</hi>-29<hi rend="italic">c</hi>, ‘the <hi
                                rend="italic">Maker</hi> and Father of this universe’. In the
                            tradition of Christian Platonism (from Origen to St. Bonaventura—and on
                            to Descartes, Malebranche to John Norris) God’s will and ‘the good’ had
                            been understood as reciprocals. Scotus, Ockham, Calvin were concerned to
                            stress God’s freedom from extrinsic norms of any sort and tended to
                            define ‘the good’ in terms of God’s untrammelled will. The deists and
                            ‘natural law’ moralists (Fiddes, Shaftesbury, Clarke, and even Butler)
                            point to ‘the good’ as the norm by which even God is bound. The
                            Calvinists (Ames, Perkins, Whitaker, Twisse) argued in retort that God
                            is unbeholden to any norm or power other than his own will. Cf. Heinrich
                            Heppe’s extensive collection of quotations to this same effect from the
                            classical Reformed dogmaticians in <hi rend="italic">Reformed
                                Dogmatics</hi> (London, George Allen and Unwin, 1950), ch. V,
                            §§18-39, pp. 81-100.</p></note> is more curious than useful. <pb
                        n="02:013"/>And perhaps in the manner it is usually treated of it does not
                    so well consist with the regard that is due from a creature to the Creator and
                    Governor of all things. ’Tis hardly decent for man to call the supreme God to
                    give an account to him! Nevertheless, with awe and reverence we may speak a
                    little. The Lord pardon us if we speak amiss!</p>
                <p n="7">7. It seems, then, that the whole difficulty arises from considering God’s
                    will as distinct from God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s later pamphlet on this point, <hi
                                rend="italic">Thoughts upon God’s Sovereignty</hi>, 1777 (<hi
                                rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 367; Vol. 12 of this
                        edn.).</p></note> Otherwise it vanishes away. For none can doubt but God is
                    the cause of the law of God. But the will of God is God himself. It is God
                    considered as willing thus or thus. Consequently, to say that the will of God,
                    or that God himself, is the cause of the law, is one and the same thing.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Again: if the law, the immutable rule of right and wrong, depends on the
                    nature and fitnesses of things, and on their essential relations to each other
                    (I do not say their eternal relations; because the eternal relations of things
                    existing in time is little less than a contradiction); if, I say, this depends
                    on the nature and relations of things, then it must depend on God, or the will
                    of God; because those things themselves, with all their relations, are the work
                    of his hands. By his will, ‘for his pleasure’ alone, they all ‘are and were
                        created’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Rev. 4:11.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. And yet it may be granted (which is probably all that a considerate
                    person would contend for) that in every particular case God wills this or this
                    (suppose that men should honour their parents) because it is right, agreeable to
                    the fitness of things, to the relation wherein they stand.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">Note this effort to assimilate
                            the good essence of rationalism into an ethical theory, partly to avoid
                            notions of sovereignty which might lend support to the
                        antinomians.</p></note></p>
                <p n="10">10. The law then is right and just concerning all things. And it is <hi
                        rend="italic">good</hi> as well as <hi rend="italic">just</hi>. This we may
                    easily infer from the fountain whence it flowed. For what was this but the
                    goodness of God? What but goodness alone inclined him to impart that divine copy
                    of himself to the holy angels? To what else can we impute his bestowing upon man
                    the same transcript of his own nature? And what but tender love constrained him
                    afresh to manifest his will to fallen man? Either to Adam or any of his seed,
                    who like him were <pb n="02:014"/>‘come short of the glory of God’?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:23.</p></note> Was it not mere love that moved him to publish his law,
                    after the understandings of men were darkened?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47"
                        n="47"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 4:18.</p></note> And to send his
                    prophets to declare that law to the blind, thoughtless children of men?
                    Doubtless his goodness it was which raised up Enoch and Noah to be preachers of
                    righteousness; which caused Abraham, his friend, and Isaac and Jacob, to bear
                    witness to his truth. It was his goodness alone which, when ‘darkness’ had
                    ‘covered the earth, and thick darkness the people’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 60:2.</p></note> gave
                    a written law to Moses, and through him to the nation whom he had chosen. It was
                    his love which explained these living oracles by David and all the prophets that
                    followed; until, when the fullness of time was come, he sent his only-begotten
                    Son, ‘not to destroy the law, but to fulfil’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49"
                        n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 5:17.</p></note> to confirm every
                    jot and tittle thereof, till having wrote it in the hearts of all his children,
                    and put all his enemies under his feet, ‘he shall deliver up’ his mediatorial
                    ‘kingdom to the Father’, ‘that God may be all in all’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn50" n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 15:24,
                        28.</p></note></p>
                <p n="11">11. And this law which the goodness of God gave at first, and has
                    preserved through all ages, is, like the fountain from whence it springs, full
                    of goodness and benignity. It is mild and kind; it is (as the Psalmist expresses
                    it) ‘sweeter than honey and the honeycomb’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51"
                        n="51"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 19:10.</p></note> It is winning and
                    amiable. It includes ‘whatsoever things are lovely or of good report. If there
                    be any virtue, if there be any praise’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:8.</p></note> before God and his
                    holy angels, they are all comprised in this: wherein are hid all the treasures
                    of the divine wisdom and knowledge and love.</p>
                <p n="12">12. And it is <hi rend="italic">good</hi> in its effects, as well as in
                    its nature. As the tree is, so are its fruits. The fruits of the law of God
                    written in the heart are ‘righteousness and peace and assurance for ever’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            32:17.</p></note> Or rather, the law itself is righteousness, filling
                    the soul with a peace that passeth all understanding,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 4:7.</p></note> and
                    causing us to rejoice evermore in the testimony of a good conscience toward
                        God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">See 2
                            Cor. 1:12; 1 Pet. 3:21.</p></note> It is not so properly a pledge as an
                    ‘earnest of our inheritance’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 1:14.</p></note> being a part of the purchased
                    possession. It is God made manifest in our flesh, and bringing with him eternal
                    life; assuring us by that pure and perfect love that we are ‘sealed unto the day
                    of <pb n="02:015"/>redemption’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Eph. 4:30.</p></note> that he will ‘spare us, as a
                    man spareth his own son that serveth him, in the day when he maketh up his
                        jewels’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Mal. 3:17.</p></note> and that there remaineth for us ‘a crown of glory
                    which fadeth not away’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet. 5:4. Note here, again, the high
                            correlations between the law and the saving work of Christ. Salvation
                                <hi rend="italic">through</hi> Christ is, therefore, <hi
                                rend="italic">to</hi> the law (i.e., holy living).</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p n="1">IV. 1. It remains only to show, in the fourth and last place, the uses of
                    the law.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Calvin
                            had long since focused this problem of the uses of the law in <hi
                                rend="italic">Institutes</hi>, II.vii: ‘(1) to convict of
                            unrighteousness (§6); (2) the restraint of wickedness (§10); (3) to
                            teach believers “the nature of the Lord’s will to which they aspire and
                            to confirm them in the understanding of it”.’ Cf. Heppe, <hi
                                rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, XIII.281-300. Lutherans had
                            tended to deemphasize this third use; cf. Heinrich Schmid, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Doctrinal Theology of the Evangelical Lutheran
                                Church</hi>, pp. 512-20. The Anglicans had transformed it into a
                            basic premise of their ethics of benevolence and virtue (as in Hammond,
                            Butler, <hi rend="italic">et al.</hi>). Wesley’s revised order, (1) to
                            convince, (2) to convert, (3) to sustain, seems to have been his
                            own.</p></note> And the first use of it, without question, is to
                    convince the world of sin. This is indeed the peculiar work of the Holy Ghost,
                    who can work it without any means at all, or by whatever means it pleaseth him,
                    however insufficient in themselves, or even improper to produce such an effect.
                    And accordingly, some there are whose hearts have been broken in pieces in a
                    moment, either in sickness or in health, without any visible cause, or any
                    outward means whatever. And others (one in an age) have been awakened to a sense
                    of ‘the wrath of God abiding on them’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:36.</p></note> by hearing that ‘God was
                    in Christ, reconciling the world unto himself’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62"
                        n="62"><p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 5:19.</p></note> But it is the
                    ordinary method of the Spirit of God to convict sinners by the law. It is this
                    which, being set home on the conscience, generally breaketh the rocks in pieces.
                    It is more especially this part of ‘the word of God’ which ‘is’ ζῶν […] καὶ
                    ἐνεργής, ‘quick and powerful’, full of life and energy, ‘and sharper than any
                    two-edged sword’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 4:12.</p></note> This, in the hand of God and
                    of those whom he hath sent, ‘pierces’ through all the folds of a deceitful
                    heart, and ‘divides asunder even the soul and spirit’, yea, as it were, the very
                    ‘joints and marrow’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p
                            rend="footnote text"><hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> By this is
                    the sinner discovered to himself. All his fig leaves are torn away, and he sees
                    that he is ‘wretched, and poor, and miserable, and blind, and naked’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rev.
                            3:17.</p></note> The law flashes conviction on every side. He feels
                    himself a mere sinner. He has nothing to pay. His ‘mouth is stopped,’ and he
                    stands ‘guilty before God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:19.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2"><pb n="02:016"/>2. To slay the sinner is then the first use of the law; to
                    destroy the life and strength wherein he trusts, and convince him that he is
                    dead while he liveth; not only under sentence of death, but actually dead unto
                    God, void of all spiritual life, ‘dead in trespasses and sins’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        2:1.</p></note> The second use of it is to bring him unto life, unto Christ,
                    that he may live. ’Tis true, in performing both these offices it acts the part
                    of a severe schoolmaster. It drives us by force, rather than draws us by
                        love.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            No. 47, ‘Heaviness through Manifold Temptations’, III.9.</p></note> And
                    yet love is the spring of all. It is the spirit of love which, by this painful
                    means, tears away our confidence in the flesh, which leaves us no broken reed
                    whereon to trust, and so constrains the sinner, stripped of all, to cry out in
                    the bitterness of his soul, or groan in the depth of his heart,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>I give up every plea beside</l>
                    <l>‘Lord, I am damned—but thou hast died.’</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John and Charles Wesley, <hi rend="italic">Hymns and
                                Sacred Poems</hi> (1739), p. 94 (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>,
                            I.85). See No. 11, <hi rend="italic">The Witness of the Spirit</hi>, II,
                            III.7 and n.</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p n="3">3. The third use of the law is to keep us alive.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">This greater stress on the
                            third use (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the moral influence) of the law
                            is significant; it supports a positive evangelical ethic.</p></note> It
                    is the grand means whereby the blessed Spirit prepares the believer for larger
                    communications of the life of God.</p>
                <p>I am afraid this great and important truth is little understood, not only by the
                    world, but even by many whom God hath taken out of the world, who are real
                    children of God by faith. Many of these lay it down as an unquestioned truth
                    that when we come to Christ we have done with the law; and that in <hi
                        rend="italic">this</hi> sense, ‘Christ is the end of the law…to everyone
                    that believeth.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 10:4.</p></note> ‘The end of the law’. So he is, ‘for
                    righteousness’, for justification, ‘to everyone that believeth’. Herein the law
                    is at an end. It justifies none, but only brings them to Christ; who is also, in
                    another respect, ‘the end’ or scope ‘of the law’—the point at which it
                    continually aims. But when it has brought us to him it has yet a farther office,
                    namely, to keep us with him. For it is continually exciting all believers, the
                    more they see of its height and depth and length and breadth,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 3:18.</p></note> to
                    exhort one another so much the more:</p>
                <lg>
                    <l><pb n="02:017"/>Closer and closer let us cleave</l>
                    <l>To his beloved embrace;</l>
                    <l>Expect his fullness to receive,</l>
                    <l>And grace to answer grace.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">John and Charles Wesley, ‘At Parting’, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 160 (<hi
                                rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, II.222).</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p n="4">4. Allowing then that every believer has done with the law, as it means the
                    Jewish ceremonial law, or the entire Mosaic dispensation (for these Christ ‘hath
                    taken out of the way’);<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Thess. 2:7.</p></note> yea, allowing we have
                    done with the moral law as a means of procuring our justification (for we are
                    ‘justified freely by his grace, through the redemption that is in Jesus’);<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                        3:24.</p></note> yet in another sense we have not done with this law. For it
                    is still of unspeakable use, first, in convincing us of the sin that yet remains
                    both in our hearts and lives, and thereby keeping us close to Christ, that his
                    blood may cleanse us every moment; secondly, in deriving strength from our Head
                    into his living members, whereby he empowers them to do what his law commands;
                    and thirdly, in confirming our hope of whatsoever it commands and we have not
                    yet attained, of receiving grace upon grace,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76"
                        n="76"><p rend="footnote text">See John 1:16.</p></note> till we are in
                    actual possession of the fullness of his promises.</p>
                <p n="5">5. How clearly does this agree with the experience of every true believer!
                    While he cries out: ‘O what love have I unto thy law! All the day long is my
                    study in it,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. Ps. 119:97 (BCP).</p></note> he sees daily in that divine mirror
                    more and more of his own sinfulness. He sees more and more clearly that he is
                    still a sinner in all things; that neither his heart nor his ways are right
                    before God; and that every moment sends him to Christ. This shows him the
                    meaning of what is written: ‘Thou shalt make a plate of pure gold, and grave
                    upon it, Holiness to the Lord. And it shall be upon Aaron’s forehead’ (the type
                    of our great High Priest) ‘that Aaron may bear the iniquities of the holy
                    things, which the children of Israel shall hallow in all their holy gifts’ (so
                    far are our prayers or holy things from atoning for the rest of our sins); ‘and
                    it shall be always upon his forehead, that they may be accepted before the
                        Lord.’<hi rend="endnote_reference"><note place="end"><p rend="endnote text"
                                >Exod. 28:36, 38.</p></note></hi></p>
                <p n="6">6. To explain this by a single instance. The law says, ‘Thou <pb n="02:018"
                    />shalt not kill,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Exod. 20:13; Deut. 5:17.</p></note> and hereby (as
                    our Lord teaches) forbids not only outward acts but every unkind word or
                        thought.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Matt. 5:21-22.</p></note> Now the more I look into this perfect law, the
                    more I feel how far I come short of it; and the more I feel this, the more I
                    feel my need of his blood to atone for all my sin, and of his Spirit to purify
                    my heart, and make me ‘perfect and entire, lacking nothing’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 1:4.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. Therefore I cannot spare the law one moment, no more than I can spare
                    Christ; seeing I now want it as much to keep me to Christ as ever I wanted it to
                    bring me to him. Otherwise this ‘evil heart of unbelief’ would immediately
                    ‘depart from the living God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 3:12.</p></note> Indeed each is
                    continually sending me to the other—the law to Christ, and Christ to the law. On
                    the one hand, the height and depth of the law constrain me to fly to the love of
                    God in Christ; on the other, the love of God in Christ endears the law to me
                    ‘above gold or precious stones’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 119:127 (BCP).</p></note> seeing I know
                    every part of it is a gracious promise, which my Lord will fulfil in its
                    season.</p>
                <p n="8">8. Who art thou then, O man, that ‘judgest the law, and speakest evil of
                    the law’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Jas. 4:11.</p></note> That rankest it with sin, Satan, and death, and
                    sendest them all to hell together? The Apostle James esteemed ‘judging’ or
                    ‘speaking evil of the law’ so enormous a piece of wickedness that he knew not
                    how to aggravate the guilt of judging our brethren more than by showing it
                    included this. So now, says he, ‘thou art not a doer of the law but a
                        judge!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text"><hi
                                rend="italic">Ibid.</hi></p></note> A judge of that which God hath
                    ordained to judge thee. So thou hast set up thyself in the judgment seat of
                    Christ, and cast down the rule whereby he will judge the world! O take knowledge
                    what advantage Satan hath gained over thee!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85"
                        n="85"><p rend="footnote text">See 2 Cor. 2:11.</p></note> And for the time
                    to come never think or speak lightly of, much less dress up as a scarecrow, this
                    blessed instrument of the grace of God. Yea, love and value it for the sake of
                    him from whom it came, and of him to whom it leads. Let it be thy glory and joy,
                    next to the cross of Christ. Declare its praise, and make it honourable before
                    all men.</p>
                <p n="9">9. And if thou art throughly convinced that it is the offspring of God,
                    that it is the copy of all his imitable perfections, and that it ‘is <pb
                        n="02:019"/>holy, and just, and good’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86"
                        n="86"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:12.</p></note> but especially to them
                    that believe; then instead of casting it away as a polluted thing, see that thou
                    cleave to it more and more. Never let the law of mercy and truth, of love to God
                    and man, of lowliness, meekness, and purity forsake thee. ‘Bind it about thy
                    neck: write it on the table of thy heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87"
                        n="87"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 3:3.</p></note> Keep close to the
                    law if thou wilt keep close to Christ; hold it fast; let it not go. Let this
                    continually lead thee to the atoning blood, continually confirm thy hope, till
                    all ‘the righteousness of the law is fulfilled in thee’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn88" n="88"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:4.</p></note> and
                    thou art ‘filled with all the fullness of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89"
                        n="89"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 3:19.</p></note></p>
                <p n="10">10. And if thy Lord hath already fulfilled his word, if he hath already
                    ‘written his law in thy heart’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 2:15.</p></note> then ‘stand fast in the
                    liberty wherewith Christ hath made thee free.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91"
                        n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:1.</p></note> Thou art not only
                    made free from Jewish ceremonies, from the guilt of sin and the fear of hell
                    (these are so far from being the whole, that they are the least and lowest part
                    of Christian liberty), but what is infinitely more, from the power of sin, from
                    serving the devil, from offending God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Note this claim to a freedom from the power of
                            sin (<hi rend="italic">posse non peccare</hi>); cf. intro. to No. 13,
                                <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>. Cf. also No. 40, <hi
                                rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.2.</p></note> O stand
                    fast in this liberty, in comparison of which all the rest is not even worthy to
                    be named. Stand fast in loving God with all thy heart and serving him with all
                    thy strength. This is perfect freedom;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Cf. the ‘Collect for Peace’, BCP, Morning
                            Prayer: ‘O God…whose service is perfect freedom’.</p></note> thus to
                    keep his law and to walk in all his commandments blameless.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">See Luke 1:6.</p></note> ‘Be
                    not entangled again with the yoke of bondage.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95"
                        n="95"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:1.</p></note> I do not mean of Jewish
                    bondage; nor yet of bondage to the fear of hell: these, I trust, are far from
                    thee. But beware of being entangled again with the yoke of sin, of any inward or
                    outward transgression of the law. Abhor sin far more than death or hell; abhor
                    sin itself far more than the punishment of it. Beware of the bondage of pride,
                    of desire, of anger; of every evil temper or word or work. ‘Look unto
                        Jesus’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Heb. 12:1</p></note> and in order thereto ‘look’ more and more ‘into the
                    perfect law, the law of liberty’, and ‘continue therein’;<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn97" n="97"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 1:25.</p></note> so
                    shalt thou daily ‘grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus
                        Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            2 Pet. 3:18.</p></note></p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
