<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 43: The Scripture Way of Salvation</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-27</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 43: The Scripture Way of Salvation</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume II: Sermons II,
                                34-70</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="1985-11-01">1985-11-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="2"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="153" to="169"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="02:153"/>
            <introduction>
                <head><hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi></head>
                <p>In 1750 Wesley had concluded the third volume of his <hi rend="italic">Sermons on
                        Several Occasions: In Three Volumes</hi> with the sermon on ‘Satan’s
                    Devices’. Ten years later, he decided to publish yet another, fourth, volume and
                    to open it with his sermon on <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>. During that
                    decade, however, he had become embroiled in an unpleasant controversy with a
                    Scottish dissenter, Robert Sandeman, and his disciples, on the relative merits
                    of ‘a faith of <hi rend="italic">adherence</hi>’ (Sandeman’s notion of faith as
                    an act of will) and ‘a faith of <hi rend="italic">assurance</hi>’ (Wesley’s
                    ‘heart religion’). In 1757 Sandeman had expounded his views in two volumes, <hi
                        rend="italic">Letters on Theron and Aspasio, Addressed to the Author</hi>
                    (James Hervey), under the pen name ‘Palaemon’. His advocacy of salvation by
                    assent had seemed dangerous to Wesley; already it had encouraged Thomas Maxfield
                    and George Bell in their rush into antinomianism. Wesley’s reaction was,
                    therefore, as vehement as anything he ever published: <hi rend="italic">A
                        Sufficient Answer to the Letters to the Author of Theron and Aspasio</hi>
                    (1757; reprinted in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, 1773, Vol. XX). He followed
                    this up in 1762 with three pamphlets in the same vein: <hi rend="italic"
                        >Thoughts on the Imputed Righteousness of Christ</hi>; <hi rend="italic">A
                        Blow at the Root: or Christ Stabbed in the House of His Friends</hi>; and
                        <hi rend="italic">Cautions and Directions given to the Greatest Professors
                        in the Methodist Societies</hi>. In 1763 he continued with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Farther Thoughts Upon Christian Perfection</hi>.</p>
                <p>The controversy, of course, had a history. Nathaniel Culverwell had explored it a
                    century before in ‘The White Stone’, a chapter in <hi rend="italic">A Discourse
                        on the Light of Nature</hi> (1st edn., 1652; 3rd. edn., 1661):</p>
                <quote>Assurance is the top and triumph of faith. Faith—that’s our victory ‘by which
                    we overcome the world’. But assurance—that’s our triumph by which ‘we are more
                    than conquerors’. ’Tis <hi rend="italic">flos fidei</hi>, the very lustre and
                    eminency of faith. Faith—that’s the root; assurance the top-branch, the
                    flourishing of faith. Justifying faith—that does not only dwell in the
                    understanding, <hi rend="italic">in nudo assensus</hi>; but requires an act of
                    the will, to which must embrace a promise. Indeed, it calls for an act resulting
                    from the whole soul, which must receive Christ offered unto it. But now,
                    assurance consists only in the mind, and so there you have the difference
                    between the Faith of Adherence and the Faith of Assurance…. When I say that
                    every believer may be assured of his salvation, I don’t <pb n="02:154"/>say that
                    every believer is assured of it…. A man may be a true child of God and certainly
                    saved, though he have not assurance he may be in a safe though in a sad
                    condition. ’Tis required to the <hi rend="italic">bene esse</hi>, not to the <hi
                        rend="italic">esse</hi> of a believer (p. 103).</quote>
                <p>Wesley could never have agreed, after 1738, that assurance ‘consists only in the
                    mind’; when he published his extract from Culverwell in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >Christian Library</hi> (1752), Vol. XVII, he omitted the passage just
                    quoted.</p>
                <p>He would also have known of William Allen’s threefold distinction in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Glass of Justification</hi> (1658): ‘Faith, as it
                    justifies, hath three acts: credence, adherence, confidence’ (p. 43); this is
                    very close to his own idea. And he also knew the famous summary of the question
                    in Arthur Bedford’s <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Assurance</hi> (1738),
                    Appendix, p. 36:</p>
                <quote>To put this controversy into as clear a light as I can, I shall only add that
                    there is a ‘faith of <hi rend="italic">adherence</hi>’ and a ‘faith of <hi
                        rend="italic">assurance</hi>’. The ‘faith of adherence’ is a saving faith,
                    wrought in the heart of a sinner by the Spirit and Word of God, whereby he is
                    convinced of his sin and misery and of his disability in himself and all other
                    creatures, to recover him out of his lost condition—[he] not only assenteth to
                    the truth of the promise of the Gospel, but receives and rests on the death and
                    righteousness of Christ Jesus, therein held for pardon of sin and for the
                    accepting and accounting of his person as righteous in the sight of God. And
                    thus he <hi rend="italic">hopes</hi>, though he hath no certainty. The ‘faith of
                    assurance’ is that whereby a man absolutely knows all this to be true in his own
                    particular case. So that the faith of adherence is general but the faith of
                    assurance is particular. Now this ‘faith of adherence’ alone is sufficient to
                    bring a man to heaven, because the promises are given in general to every one
                    who believes. And, therefore, to limit salvation to a particular degree of faith
                    is to destroy all those promises on which thousands of Christians have hitherto
                    depended for their eternal comfort. From which ‘uncharitableness, false doctrine
                    and heresy, Good Lord, deliver us!’</quote>
                <p>Given, however, the still unsettled state of mind among the Methodists in 1765,
                    Wesley decided to sum up the matter yet once more: to correlate the faith that
                    saves with the faith that sanctifies. This was the task he set himself in <hi
                        rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>. In it, he gathered up the
                    best residues of earlier sermons—<hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>,
                    ‘Justification by Faith’, and ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’. Here he could
                    reemphasize the point that in the Christian life all is of grace—‘preventing’,
                    ‘justifying’, ‘accompanying’, and ‘sanctifying’. He could have made Henry
                    Smith’s point yet again, that ‘good works are the <hi rend="italic">way</hi> to
                    come to heaven, though they be not the <hi rend="italic">cause why</hi> we shall
                    come to heaven.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See <hi rend="italic">Sermons</hi>, ed. by Thomas Fuller (1675), p.
                            562.</p></note> The result is the most successful summary of the
                    Wesleyan vision of the <hi rend="italic">ordo salutis</hi> in the entire sermon
                    corpus.</p>
                <p>When, therefore, he was reordering and republishing his <hi rend="italic"
                        >Sermons</hi>
                    <pb n="02:155"/>in 1771, he could see the logic of adding <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scripture Way of Salvation</hi> to the sequence of <hi rend="italic"
                        >Christian Perfection</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, and
                    ‘Satan’s Devices’. Later, in 1787, he would revert to the order of 1760 and, in
                    effect, discard <hi rend="italic">The Scripture Way of Salvation</hi>. Clearly,
                    whatever the gain here in terms of the legal function of <hi rend="italic"
                        >SOSO</hi>, its effect was an obvious loss in terms of doctrinal
                    substance.</p>
                <p>Of all the written sermons, this one had the most extensive history of oral
                    preaching behind it: forty instances of his using Eph. 2:8 before 1765, nine in
                    1738, including the first written sermon on it (No. 1, <hi rend="italic"
                        >Salvation by Faith</hi>). The text continued to be a favourite: twenty
                    recorded instances in the quarter century following 1765. <hi rend="italic">The
                        Scripture Way of Salvation</hi> went through five further editions in
                    Wesley’s lifetime. For its publishing history and a list of variant readings,
                    see Appendix, Vol. 4; see also <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 265.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Scripture Way of Salvation</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Ephesians 2:8</p>
                <p><hi rend="italic">Ye are saved through faith.</hi></p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p n="1">1. Nothing can be more intricate, complex, and hard to be understood, than
                    religion as it has been often described. And this is not only true concerning
                    the religion of the heathens, even many of the wisest of them, but concerning
                    the religion of those also who were in some sense Christians; yea, and men of
                    great name in the Christian world, men ‘who seemed to be pillars’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:9, οἵ
                            δοκοῦντες στύλοι εἶναι…. Later, in No. 82, ‘On Temptation’, §2, Wesley
                            will argue for a different translation: ‘by a careful consideration of
                            every text in the New Testament wherein this word [δόκειν] occurs, I am
                            fully convinced that it nowhere lessens, but everywhere strengthens, the
                            sense of the word to which it is annexed. Accordingly, ὁ δόκει ἔχειν
                            does not mean “what he <hi rend="italic">seems</hi> to have” but on the
                            contrary, “who he <hi rend="italic">assuredly</hi> hath”.’ Cf. his
                            translation to this same effect in the <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>, and
                            see also Nos. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’, IIΙ.7; 90, ‘An
                            Israelite Indeed’, I.5; 128, ‘The Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’,
                            III.3. He nowhere notices the irony of Paul’s use of δοκοῦντες in Gal.
                            2:9.</p></note> thereof. Yet how easy to be understood, how plain and
                    simple a thing, is the genuine religion of Jesus Christ! Provided only that <pb
                        n="02:156"/>we take it in its native form, just as it is described in the
                    oracles of God. It is exactly suited by the wise Creator and Governor of the
                    world to the weak understanding and narrow capacity of man in his present state.
                    How observable is this both with regard to the end it proposes and the means to
                    attain that end! The end is, in one word, salvation: the means to attain it,
                    faith.</p>
                <p n="2">2. It is easily discerned that these two little words—I mean faith and
                    salvation—include the substance of all the Bible, the marrow, as it were, of the
                    whole Scripture. So much the more should we take all possible care to avoid all
                    mistake concerning them, and to form a true and accurate judgment concerning
                    both the one and the other.</p>
                <p>Let us then seriously inquire,</p>
                <p>I. What is salvation?</p>
                <p>II. What is that faith whereby we are saved? And</p>
                <p>ΙII. How we are saved by it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p n="1">I. 1. And first let us inquire, What is <hi rend="italic">salvation</hi>?
                    The salvation which is here spoken of is not what is frequently understood by
                    that word, the going to heaven, eternal happiness. It is not the soul’s going to
                    paradise, termed by our Lord ‘Abraham’s bosom’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3"
                        n="3"><p rend="footnote text">Luke 16:22. Cf. the Talmudic tractate <hi
                                rend="italic">Kiddushin</hi>, 72<hi rend="italic">b</hi>, and the
                            comment of Kaufmann Kohler in <hi rend="italic">The Jewish
                                Encyclopedia</hi>, ‘Abraham’s Bosom’. Bengel, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Gnomon</hi>, <hi rend="italic">loc. cit.</hi>, comments that ‘the
                            Jews used to call the state of the righteous dead “the bosom of Abraham”
                            and “the Garden of Eden”.’ See No. 115, ‘Dives and Lazarus’, I.3 and
                            n.</p></note> It is not a blessing which lies on the other side death,
                    or (as we usually speak) in the other world. The very words of the text itself
                    put this beyond all question. ‘Ye <hi rend="italic">are</hi> saved.’ It is not
                    something at a distance: it is a present thing, a blessing which, through the
                    free mercy of God, ye are now in possession of. Nay, the words may be rendered,
                    and that with equal propriety, ‘Ye <hi rend="italic">have been</hi> saved.’ So
                    that the salvation which is here spoken of might be extended to the entire work
                    of God, from the first dawning of grace in the soul till it is consummated in
                    glory.</p>
                <p n="2">2. If we take this in its utmost extent it will include all that is wrought
                    in the soul by what is frequently termed ‘natural conscience’, but more
                    properly, ‘preventing grace’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4"><p
                            rend="footnote text">A special gracious activity of the Holy Spirit in
                            the heart and will, always in anticipation (<hi rend="italic"
                                >praeveniens</hi>) of any human initiative or act of choice.
                            ‘Pre-venting’ grace (distantly kin to what the Calvinists called ‘common
                            grace’, save that it is uniquely the work of the Holy Spirit) ‘goes
                            before’ conscious awareness of one’s condition, to ‘turn’, to ‘draw’, to
                            stir up ‘the desires after God…all the convictions which the Holy
                            Spirit…works in every child of man.’ Thus, it displaces ‘natural
                            conscience’ (the notion of which presupposes human autonomy and free
                            will); it signifies the divine initiative in all human ‘re-actions’ that
                            aspire to faith. Thus, ‘preventing’ (prevenient) grace is the
                            theological principle that assigns an absolute priority to the
                            indwelling Spirit and yet allows for actual and valid human involvement,
                            since the actions of the Holy Spirit are ‘resistible’, as the decrees of
                            the Father are not (cf. the canons of the Second Council of Orange, A.D.
                            529).</p><p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s teaching here reaches back to
                            Jerome, at least (cf. <hi rend="italic">Epistles</hi>, 31, 33, 34, 62),
                            and thence through the Middle Ages to Martin Bucer, Johann Gropper, and
                                <hi rend="italic">The King’s Book</hi> (<hi rend="italic">A
                                Necessary Doctrine and Erudition for Any Christian Man</hi>, ‘The
                            Article of Free Will’) to Fénelon (<hi rend="italic">Christian
                                Counsel</hi>, ch. XXI). But it assumes an even more crucial role in
                            Wesley’s thought, especially in his stress upon the Holy Spirit as its
                            agent and on its transformation of ‘natural conscience’ (e.g., the
                            analogue between its role in Wesley’s ethics to the role of ‘conscience’
                            in Joseph Butler’s <hi rend="italic">Fifteen Sermons</hi>, II and III).
                            It was in this sense that John Fletcher could rightly ‘deny that Mr.
                            Wesley is an Arminian’, since ‘Arminius held that man hath a will to
                            turn to God <hi rend="italic">before</hi> grace prevents him’ (<hi
                                rend="italic">Works</hi>, 1825, I.229), whereas, for Wesley, it is
                            the Spirit’s prevenient motion by which ‘we ever are moved and inspired
                            to <hi rend="italic">any</hi> good thing’. The early Wesley tended to
                            ground ‘preventing grace’ in baptism; the mature Wesley linked it more
                            closely to repentance; the late Wesley correlates it with the order of
                            salvation as a whole; cf. No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own Salvation’,
                            I.21 (‘God <hi rend="italic">breathes</hi> into us every good desire,
                            and brings every good desire to good effect’), and III.3-4, Wesley’s
                            most compact and complete statement of the doctrine and its import. But
                            see also <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Rom. 2:14, together with the
                            comment in <hi rend="italic">Predestination Calmly Considered</hi>
                            (1752), §45; and yet another comment in <hi rend="italic">Some Remarks
                                on Mr. Hill’s Review</hi> (1712), 12:xvi. Cf. Charles Rogers’s Duke
                            University dissertation, <hi rend="italic">The Doctrine of Prevenient
                                Grace in John Wesley</hi>. For other references to will and liberty,
                            cf. No. 60, ‘The General Deliverance’, I.4 and n.</p></note> all the <pb
                        n="02:157"/>‘drawings’ of ‘the Father’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5"
                        n="5"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 6:44; and below, No. 47, ‘Heaviness
                            through Manifold Temptations’, IIΙ.9 and n.</p></note> the desires after
                    God, which, if we yield to them, increase more and more; all that ‘light’
                    wherewith the Son of God ‘enlighteneth everyone that cometh into the
                        world’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            John 1:9.</p></note>
                    <hi rend="italic">showing</hi> every man ‘to do justly, to love mercy, and to
                    walk humbly with his God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Mic. 6:8.</p></note> all the <hi rend="italic"
                        >convictions</hi> which his Spirit from time to time works in every child of
                    man. Although it is true the generality of men stifle them as soon as possible,
                    and after a while forget, or at least deny, that ever they had them at all.</p>
                <p n="3">3. But we are at present concerned only with that salvation which the
                    Apostle is directly speaking of. And this consists of two general parts,
                    justification and sanctification.</p>
                <p>Justification is another word for pardon.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">See No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, II.5 and
                            n.</p></note> It is the forgiveness of all our sins, and (what is
                    necessarily implied therein) our acceptance with God. The price whereby this
                    hath been procured for us (commonly termed the ‘meritorious cause’ of our
                        justification)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >An echo of the bitter controversy about the ‘causes’ of justification
                            between the Roman Catholics, the Calvinists, and the Anglicans; cf. Nos.
                            5, ‘Justification by Faith’, II.5; and 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord
                                Our Righteousness</hi>, intro.; see also C. F. Allison, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Rise of Moralism</hi>, ch. 1.</p><p
                            rend="footnote text">Session VI of Trent (ch. VII) had listed five
                            distinguishable ‘causes’ of justification and had specified ‘“the
                            meritorious cause” as the atoning Passion and death of Jesus Christ who
                            “merited our justification…unto God the Father”’. The Calvinists had
                            countered this by insisting on the atonement as the <hi rend="italic"
                                >formal</hi> cause of the justification of <hi rend="italic">the
                                elect</hi> (as in Davenant, Downham, and others). This had focused
                            the issue: the idea of ‘formal cause’ entailed a doctrine of
                            predestination on the one hand and irresistible grace on the other; the
                            notion of ‘meritorious cause’ did not. Wesley had tried to hold to the
                            good intentions of both views but finally was forced to come down on the
                            side of ‘meritorious cause’ (as in No. 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord
                                Our Righteousness</hi>). No other single point (which embraces the
                            correlative issue of ‘good works after faith’) so excited the Calvinist
                            polemic against him from 1765, both until and after his
                        death.</p></note> is the blood and righteousness of Christ, or (to <pb
                        n="02:158"/>express it a little more clearly) all that Christ hath done and
                    suffered for us till ‘he poured out his soul for the transgressors.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            53:12.</p></note> The immediate effects of justification are, the peace
                    of God, a ‘peace that passeth all understanding’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn11" n="11"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 4:7.</p></note> and
                    a ‘rejoicing in <hi rend="italic">hope</hi> of the glory of God’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        5:2.</p></note> ‘with <hi rend="italic">joy</hi> unspeakable and full of
                        glory’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Pet. 1:8.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. And at the same time that we are justified, yea, in that very moment,
                        <hi rend="italic">sanctification</hi> begins. In that instant we are ‘born
                    again’, ‘born from above’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14"><p
                            rend="footnote text">John 3:3, 7. Cf. No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake,
                                Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, I.2 and n.</p></note> ‘born of the
                        Spirit’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >John 3:6, 8.</p></note> There is a <hi rend="italic">real</hi> as well
                    as a <hi rend="italic">relative</hi> change.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16"
                        n="16"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 19, ‘The Great Privilege of those
                            that are Born of God’, I.1 and n. The ‘relative change’ denotes the new
                            relationship between God and his pardoned child; the ‘real change’ is in
                            the actual heart and will of the justified one, which is the equivalent
                            of regeneration, ‘the new birth’—which in turn is the beginning of a new
                            lifelong process of sanctification or holy living; cf. Nos. 18, ‘The
                            Marks of the New Birth’; and 45, ‘The New Birth’.</p></note> We are
                    inwardly renewed by the power of God. We feel the ‘love of God shed abroad in
                    our heart by the Holy Ghost which is given unto us’,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn17" n="17"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:5. Cf. No. 3, <hi
                                rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>, II.10 and
                        n.</p></note> producing love to all mankind, and more especially to the
                    children of God; expelling the love of the world, the love of pleasure, of ease,
                    of honour, of money; together with pride, anger, self-will, and every other evil
                    temper—in a word, changing the ‘earthly, sensual, devilish’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn18" n="18"><p rend="footnote text">Jas. 3:15.</p></note> mind
                    into ‘the mind which was in Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19"
                        n="19"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p></note></p>
                <p n="5">5. How naturally do those who experience such a change imagine that all sin
                    is gone! That it is utterly rooted out of their heart, and has no more any place
                    therein! How easily do they draw that inference, ‘I <hi rend="italic">feel</hi>
                    no sin; therefore I <hi rend="italic">have</hi> none.’ It does not <hi
                        rend="italic">stir</hi>; therefore it does not <hi rend="italic">exist</hi>:
                    it has no <hi rend="italic">motion</hi>; therefore it has no <hi rend="italic"
                        >being</hi>.</p>
                <p n="6"><pb n="02:159"/>6. But it is seldom long before they are undeceived,
                    finding sin was only suspended, not destroyed. Temptations return and sin
                    revives, showing it was but stunned before, not dead. They now feel two
                    principles in themselves, plainly contrary to each other: ‘the flesh lusting
                    against the spirit’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:17.</p></note>, nature opposing the
                    grace of God. They cannot deny that although they still feel power to believe in
                    Christ and to love God, and although his ‘Spirit’ still ‘witnesses with’ their
                    ‘spirits that’ they ‘are the children of God’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21"
                        n="21"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:16.</p></note> yet they feel in
                    themselves, sometimes pride or self-will, sometimes anger or unbelief. They find
                    one or more of these frequently <hi rend="italic">stirring</hi> in their heart,
                    though not <hi rend="italic">conquering</hi>; yea, perhaps ‘thrusting sore at
                    them, that they’ may ‘fall; but the Lord is’ their ‘help’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn22" n="22"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 118:13 (BCP). See Nos.
                            13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>; 14, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Repentance of Believers</hi>; and 41, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Wandering Thoughts</hi>.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. How exactly did Macarius, fourteen hundred years ago, describe the
                    present experience of the children of God! ‘The unskilful (or unexperienced),
                    when grace operates, presently imagine they have no more sin. Whereas they that
                    have discretion cannot deny that even we who have the grace of God may be
                    molested again…. For we have often had instances of some among the brethren who
                    have experienced such grace as to affirm that they had no sin in them. And yet
                    after all, when they thought themselves entirely freed from it, the corruption
                    that lurked within was stirred up anew, and they were wellnigh burnt up.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23"><p rend="footnote text">There was a
                            fourth-century Egyptian hermit with this name who was renowned for his
                            miracles and spiritual counsel. He was, however, probably not the author
                            of the homilies and other pieces attributed to him in Migne, <hi
                                rend="italic">PG</hi>, XXXIV; neither Palladius nor Rufinus makes
                            any mention of them. Cf. Werner Jaeger, <hi rend="italic">Two
                                Rediscovered Works of Ancient Christian Literature: Gregory of Nyssa
                                and Macarius</hi> (Leiden, E. J. Brill, 1954). Still, Wesley knew
                            and loved the ‘Macarian homilies’; he extracted and published twenty-two
                            of them in Vol. I of the <hi rend="italic">Christian Lib.</hi> (1749);
                            for the passage cited here, cf. Homily IX, pp. 95-97. But cf. Migne, <hi
                                rend="italic">PG</hi>, XXXIV.623-34, and the Eng. tr. (which Wesley
                            knew), ‘By a Presbyter of the Church of England’, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Spiritual Homilies of Macarius the Egyptian</hi> (1721), Homily
                            XVII, ‘Concerning the Spiritual Unction and Glory of Christians. And
                            that without Christ it is Impossible to be Saved, or to be made Partaker
                            of Eternal Life’, p. 267: ‘But the unsteady and unskilful, whenever
                            grace operates, tho’ but in part, imagine presently they have no more
                            sin. Whereas they that have discretion and are prudent, never have the
                            confidence to deny that we who even have the grace of God, are molested
                            with obscene and filthy thoughts. For we have often had instances of
                            some among the brethren, that have experienced such a degree of joy and
                            grace, as to affirm that for five or six years running, concupiscence
                            had withered quite away; and yet after all, when they thought themselves
                            freed entirely from it, the corruption that lurked within, was stirred
                            up anew, and they were even burnt up.’ See also No. 112, <hi
                                rend="italic">On Laying the Foundation of the New Chapel</hi>,
                            II.3.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8"><pb n="02:160"/>8. From the time of our being ‘born again’ the gradual work
                    of sanctification takes place. We are enabled ‘by the Spirit’ to ‘mortify the
                    deeds of the body’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:13.</p></note> of our evil nature. And
                    as we are more and more dead to sin, we are more and more alive to God. We go on
                    from grace to grace, while we are careful to ‘abstain from all appearance of
                        evil’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25"><p rend="footnote text">1
                            Thess. 5:22.</p></note> and are ‘zealous of good works’,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26"><p rend="footnote text">Titus
                        2:14.</p></note> ‘as we have opportunity doing good to all men’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                            6:10.</p></note> while we walk in all his ordinances blameless,<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke
                        1:6.</p></note> therein worshipping him in spirit and in truth;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29"><p rend="footnote text">See John 4:23,
                            24.</p></note> while we take up our cross and deny ourselves every
                    pleasure that does not lead us to God.</p>
                <p n="9">9. It is thus that we wait for entire sanctification, for a full salvation
                    from all our sins, from pride, sell-will, anger, unbelief, or, as the Apostle
                    expresses it, ‘Go on to perfection.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 6:1.</p></note> But what is perfection? The
                    word has various senses: here it means perfect love. It is love excluding sin;
                    love filling the heart, taking up the whole capacity of the soul. It is love
                    ‘rejoicing evermore, praying without ceasing, in everything giving thanks’.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Thess.
                            5:16-18.</p></note></p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>II. But what is that ‘faith through which we are saved’?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn32" n="32"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:8.</p></note> This
                    is the second point to be considered.</p>
                <p n="1">1. Faith in general is defined by the Apostle, ἔλεγχος πραγμάτων οὐ
                    βλεπομένων—‘an evidence’, a divine ‘evidence and conviction’ (the word means
                    both), ‘of things not seen’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb. 11:1; this, obviously, is a quotation from
                            memory, since even <hi rend="italic">TR</hi> here reads πραγμάτων
                            ἔλεγχος. See No. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That Sleepest’</hi>,
                            I.1 and n.; also, <hi rend="italic">An Earnest Appeal</hi>, §§6-7
                            (11:46-47 in this edn.).</p></note>—not visible, not perceivable either
                    by sight or by any other of the external senses. It implies both a supernatural
                        <hi rend="italic">evidence</hi> of God and of the things of God, a kind of
                    spiritual <hi rend="italic">light</hi> exhibited to the soul, and a supernatural
                        <hi rend="italic">sight</hi> or perception thereof. Accordingly the
                    Scripture speaks sometimes of God’s giving light, sometimes a power of
                    discerning it. So St. Paul: ‘God, who commanded light to shine out of darkness,
                    hath shined in our hearts, to give us the light of the knowledge of the glory of
                    God in the face of Jesus <hi n="02:161"/> Christ.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn34" n="34"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 4:6.</p></note> And
                    elsewhere the same Apostle speaks ‘of the eyes of our ‘understanding being
                        opened’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Eph. 1:18.</p></note> By this twofold operation of the Holy
                    Spirit—having the eyes of our soul both <hi rend="italic">opened</hi> and <hi
                        rend="italic">enlightened</hi>—we see the things which the natural ‘eye hath
                    not seen, neither the ear heard’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 2:9.</p></note> We have a prospect of
                    the invisible things of God. We see the <hi rend="italic">spiritual world</hi>,
                    which is all round about us, and yet no more discerned by our natural faculties
                    than if it had no being; and we see the <hi rend="italic">eternal world</hi>,
                    piercing through the veil which hangs between time and eternity. Clouds and
                    darkness then rest upon it no more,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37"><p
                            rend="footnote text">An echo of Addison’s <hi rend="italic">Cato</hi>;
                            cf. No. 117, ‘On the Discoveries of Faith’, §8 and n.</p></note> but we
                    already see the glory which shall be revealed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38"
                        n="38"><p rend="footnote text">Rom. 8:18. Yet another instance of the theory
                            that our knowledge ‘of God and the things of God’ is a sort of <hi
                                rend="italic">sight</hi>, a direct intuition of ‘the eternal world’.
                            See No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="2">2. Taking the word in a more particular sense, faith is a divine evidence
                    and conviction, not only that ‘God was in Christ, reconciling the world unto
                        himself,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39"><p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 5:19.</p></note> but also that Christ ‘loved <hi rend="italic"
                        >me</hi>, and gave himself for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn40" n="40"><p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:20.</p></note> It is by
                    this faith (whether we term it the <hi rend="italic">essence</hi>, or rather a
                        <hi rend="italic">property</hi> thereof) that we ‘receive Christ’;<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 2:6.Cf.
                            Col. 2:6.</p></note> that we receive him in all his offices, as our
                    Prophet, Priest, and King.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42"><p
                            rend="footnote text">For this Reformed concept of ‘offices’ and its
                            import for Wesley’s Christology, see Deschner, <hi rend="italic"
                                >Wesley’s Christology</hi>, chs. ΙII-VI.</p></note> It is by this
                    that he ‘is made of God unto us wisdom, and righteousness, and sanctification,
                    and redemption’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 Cor. 1:30.</p></note></p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘But is this the “faith of assurance” or “faith of adherence”?’ The
                    Scripture mentions no such distinction. The Apostle says: ‘There is one faith,
                    and one hope of our calling,’ one Christian, saving faith, as ‘there is one
                    Lord’ in whom we believe, and ‘one God and Father of us all.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn44" n="44"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:4-6.</p></note> And
                    it is certain this faith necessarily implies an <hi rend="italic">assurance</hi>
                    (which is here only another word for <hi rend="italic">evidence</hi>, it being
                    hard to tell the difference between them) that ‘Christ loved <hi rend="italic"
                        >me</hi>, and gave himself for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>.’ For ‘he that
                    believeth’ with the true, living faith, ‘hath the witness in himself.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45"><p rend="footnote text">1 John
                        5:10.</p></note> ‘The Spirit witnesseth with his spirit that he is a child
                    of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46"><p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            8:16.</p></note> ‘Because he <pb n="02:162"/>is a son, God hath sent
                    forth the Spirit of his Son into his heart, crying, Abba, Father;’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal.
                        4:6.</p></note> giving him an assurance that he is so, and a childlike
                    confidence in him. But let it be observed that, in the very nature of the thing,
                    the assurance goes before the confidence. For a man cannot have a childlike
                    confidence in God till he knows he is a child of God. Therefore confidence,
                    trust, reliance, adherence, or whatever else it be called, is not the first, as
                    some have supposed, but the second branch or act of faith.</p>
                <p n="4">4. It is by this faith we ‘are saved’, justified and sanctified, taking
                    that word in its highest sense. But how are we justified and sanctified by
                    faith? This is our third head of inquiry. And this being the main point in
                    question, and a point of no ordinary importance, it will not be improper to give
                    it a more distinct and particular consideration.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p n="1">III. 1. And first, how are we justified by faith? In what sense is this to
                    be understood? I answer, faith is the condition, and the only condition, of
                    justification. It is the condition: none is justified but he that believes;
                    without faith no man is justified. And it is the only condition: this alone is
                    sufficient for justification. Everyone that believes is justified, whatever else
                    he has or has not. In other words: no man is justified till he believes; every
                    man when he believes is justified.</p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘But does not God command us to <hi rend="italic">repent</hi> also? Yea,
                    and to “bring forth fruits meet for repentance”?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn48" n="48"><p rend="footnote text">Matt. 3:8.</p></note> To
                    “cease”, for instance, “from doing evil”, and “learn to do well”?<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa.
                            1:16-17.</p></note> And is not both the one and the other of the utmost
                    necessity? Insomuch that if we willingly neglect either we cannot reasonably
                    expect to be justified at all? But if this be so, how can it be said that faith
                    is the only condition of justification?’</p>
                <p>God does undoubtedly command us both to repent and to bring forth fruits meet for
                    repentance; which if we willingly neglect we cannot reasonably expect to be
                    justified at all. Therefore both repentance and fruits meet for repentance are
                    in some sense necessary to justification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50"
                        n="50"><p rend="footnote text">Elsewhere, Wesley stresses repentance as the
                            normal preparatory state for the reception of justifying faith and, in
                            that sense, ‘necessary’; cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, II.6 and n. See also Law’s insistence in <hi
                                rend="italic">A Practical Treatise upon Christian Perfection</hi>
                            (1726), in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi> (1762), III.84-86, that
                            ‘Repentance and sorrow for sin are [strictly] necessary to
                            salvation.’</p></note> But they are not necessary <pb n="02:163"/>in the
                        <hi rend="italic">same sense</hi> with faith, nor in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >same degree</hi>. Not in the <hi rend="italic">same degree</hi>; for those
                    fruits are only necessary <hi rend="italic">conditionally</hi>, if there be time
                    and opportunity for them. Otherwise a man may be justified without them, as was
                    the ‘thief’ upon the cross (if we may call him so; for a late writer has
                    discovered that he was no thief, but a very honest and respectable
                        person!).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >See Matt. 27:38 and Mark 15:27. The ‘late writer’ was not Bengel,
                            Burkitt, Heylyn, Henry, or Poole—and Wesley makes nothing of the idea
                            that one of the λῃσταί was ‘very honest and respectable’. This
                            interpretation goes back, of course, to Josephus’s account of the
                            Zealots in his <hi rend="italic">Jewish War</hi>, II. Josephus’s first
                            English translator, William Whiston (1737), may have been Wesley’s ‘late
                            writer’; cf. his <hi rend="italic">Six Dissertations</hi> (1734), No. I.
                            See also Karl Rengstorf’s article on λῃστής in Gerhard Kittel, ed., <hi
                                rend="italic">Theological Dictionary of the New Testament</hi>,
                            IV.262: ‘When Jesus was crucified and was thus punished as a political
                            rebel against Rome, two others condemned as λῃσταί suffered with him.
                            The title on the cross marked him as one of them.’ Cf. also Haim Cohn,
                                <hi rend="italic">The Trial and Death of Jesus</hi> (New York,
                            Harper and Row, 1967), p. 208.</p></note> But he cannot be justified
                    without faith: this is impossible. Likewise let a man have ever so much
                    repentance, or ever so many of the fruits meet for repentance, yet all this does
                    not at all avail: he is not justified till he believes. But the moment he
                    believes, with or without those fruits, yea, with more or less repentance, he is
                    justified. Not in the <hi rend="italic">same sense</hi>: for repentance and its
                    fruits are only <hi rend="italic">remotely</hi> necessary, necessary in order to
                    faith; whereas faith is <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >directly</hi> necessary to justification. It remains that faith is the only
                    condition which is <hi rend="italic">immediately</hi> and <hi rend="italic"
                        >proximately</hi> necessary to justification.</p>
                <p n="3">3. ‘But do you believe we are sanctified by faith? We know you believe that
                    we are justified by faith; but do not you believe, and accordingly teach, that
                    we are sanctified by our works?’</p>
                <p>So it has been roundly and vehemently affirmed for these five and twenty
                        years.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52"><p rend="footnote text">I.e.,
                            approximately from 1739, with Wesley’s insistence in his preface to <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> on good works following
                            upon faith (see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 13; and Vol. 12 of
                            this edn.).</p></note> But I have constantly declared just the contrary,
                    and that in all manner of ways. I have continually testified in private and in
                    public that we are sanctified, as well as justified, by faith. And indeed the
                    one of these great truths does exceedingly illustrate the other. Exactly as we
                    are justified by faith, so are we sanctified by faith. Faith is the condition,
                    and the only condition of sanctification, exactly as it is of justification. It
                    is the condition: none is sanctified but he that believes; without faith no man
                    is sanctified. And it is the only condition: this alone is sufficient for
                    sanctification. Everyone that believes is sanctified, <pb n="02:164"/>whatever
                    else he has or has not. In other words: no man is sanctified till he believes;
                    every man when he believes is sanctified.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53"
                        n="53"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley’s repetition of this emphasis on
                            the close correlation between justification and sanctification in No.
                            107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.5-6.</p></note></p>
                <p n="4">4. ‘But is there not a repentance consequent upon, as well as a repentance
                    previous to, justification? And is it not incumbent on all that are justified to
                    be “zealous of good works”?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Titus 2:14.</p></note> Yea, are not these so
                    necessary that if a man willingly neglect them he cannot reasonably expect that
                    he shall ever be sanctified in the full sense, that is, “perfected in
                        love”?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                            John 2:5; 4:12, 18.</p></note> Nay, can he “grow” at all “in grace, in
                    the” loving “knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ”?<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn56" n="56"><p rend="footnote text">2 Pet. 3:18.</p></note> Yea,
                    can he retain the grace which God has already given him? Can he continue in the
                    faith which he has received, or in the favour of God? Do not you yourself allow
                    all this, and continually assert it? But if this be so, how can it be said that
                    faith is the only condition of sanctification?’</p>
                <p n="5">5. I do allow all this, and continually maintain it as the truth of God. I
                    allow there is a repentance consequent upon, as well as a repentance previous
                    to, justification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See Nos. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of
                                Believers</hi>, proem, §2, and n.; 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>; and 8, ‘The First-fruits of the Spirit’, for other
                            versions of this notion of ‘repentance consequent upon justification’.
                            The idea goes back to the <hi rend="italic">poenitentia secunda</hi> of
                            Tertullian (at least) and is a correlate of the doctrine of double
                            justification.</p></note> It is incumbent on all that are justified to
                    be zealous of good works. And these are so necessary that if a man willingly
                    neglect them, he cannot reasonably expect that he shall ever be sanctified. He
                    cannot ‘grow in grace’, in the image of God, the mind which was in Christ
                        Jesus;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Phil. 2:5.</p></note> nay, he cannot retain the grace he has received,
                    he cannot continue in faith, or in the favour of God.</p>
                <p>What is the inference we must draw herefrom? Why, that both repentance, rightly
                    understood, and the practice of all good works, works of piety, as well as works
                    of mercy (now property so called, since they spring from faith) are in some
                    sense necessary to sanctification.</p>
                <p n="6">6. I say ‘repentance rightly understood’; for this must not be confounded
                    with the former repentance. The repentance consequent upon justification is
                    widely different from that which is antecedent to it. This implies no guilt, no
                    sense of condemnation, no consciousness of the wrath of God. It does not <pb
                        n="02:165"/>suppose any doubt of the favour of God, or any ‘fear that hath
                        torment’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. 1 John 4:18.</p></note> It is properly a conviction wrought by the
                    Holy Ghost of the ‘sin’ which still ‘remains’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60"
                        n="60"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 9:41.</p></note> in our heart, of
                    the φρόνημα σαρκός,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                                Believers</hi>, intro., I.3, III.1-9, and IV.1.</p></note> ‘the
                    carnal mind’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 8:7.</p></note> which ‘does still <hi rend="italic">remain</hi>’,
                    as our Church speaks, ‘even in them that are regenerate’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn63" n="63"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Art. IX, ‘Of Original or
                            Birth Sin’.</p></note>—although it does no longer <hi rend="italic"
                        >reign</hi>,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Cf. No. 13, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in Believers</hi>, intro., I.6,
                            and n. This distinction between ‘voluntary’ and ‘involuntary’ sins is
                            crucial. Voluntary sins (‘sins properly so called’) generate guilt and
                            alienation; their ‘reign’ must be broken by God’s pardoning mercy. The
                            φρόνημα σαρκός remains, but has lost its dominion in the believer’s
                            heart; it does not, therefore, annul his assurance that God will pardon
                            subsequent sins on the basis of ‘consequent repentance’.</p></note> it
                    has not now dominion over them. It is a conviction of our proneness to evil, of
                    an heart ‘bent to backsliding’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Hos. 11:7.</p></note> of the still continuing
                    tendency of the ‘flesh’ to ‘lust against the Spirit’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn66" n="66"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:17.</p></note>
                    Sometimes, unless we continually watch and pray, it lusteth to pride, sometimes
                    to anger, sometimes to love of the world, love of ease, love of honour, or love
                    of pleasure more than of God. It is a conviction of the tendency of our heart to
                    self-will, to atheism, or idolatry; and above all to unbelief, whereby in a
                    thousand ways, and under a thousand pretences, we are ever ‘departing’ more or
                    less ‘from the living God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Heb. 3:12.</p></note></p>
                <p n="7">7. With this conviction of the sin <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> in our
                    hearts there is joined a clear conviction of the sin remaining in our lives,
                    still <hi rend="italic">cleaving</hi> to all our words and actions. In the best
                    of these we now discern a mixture of evil, either in the spirit, the matter, or
                    the manner of them; something that could not endure the righteous judgment of
                    God, were he ‘extreme to mark what is done amiss’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn68" n="68"><p rend="footnote text">Ps. 130:3 (BCP).</p></note>
                    Where we least suspected it we find a taint of pride of self-will, of unbelief
                    or idolatry; so that we are now more ashamed of our best duties than formerly of
                    our worst sins. And hence we cannot but feel that these are so far from having
                    anything meritorious in them, yea, so far from being able to stand in sight of
                    the divine justice, that for those also we should be guilty before God were it
                    not for the blood of the covenant.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Exod. 24:8; Heb. 10:29.</p></note></p>
                <p n="8"><pb n="02:166"/>8. Experience shows that together with this conviction of
                    sin <hi rend="italic">remaining</hi> our hearts and <hi rend="italic"
                        >cleaving</hi> to all our words and actions, as well as the guilt which on
                    account thereof we should incur were we not continually sprinkled with the
                    atoning blood, one thing more is implied in this repentance, namely, a
                    conviction of our helplessness, of our utter inability to think one good
                    thought, or to form one good desire; and much more to speak one word aright, or
                    to perform one good action but through his free, almighty grace, first
                    preventing us, and then accompanying us every moment.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn70" n="70"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, I.2 and
                        n.</p></note></p>
                <p n="9">9. ‘But what good works are those, the practice of which you affirm to be
                    necessary to sanctification?’ First, all works of piety,<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn71" n="71"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 14, <hi rend="italic"
                                >The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.13 and n.</p></note> such as
                    public prayer, family prayer, and praying in our closet; receiving the Supper of
                    the Lord; searching the Scriptures by hearing, reading, meditating; and using
                    such a measure of fasting or abstinence as our bodily health allows.</p>
                <p n="10">10. Secondly, all works of mercy, whether they relate to the bodies or
                    souls of men; such as feeding the hungry, clothing the naked, entertaining the
                    stranger, visiting those that are in prison, or sick, or variously afflicted;
                    such as the endeavouring to instruct the ignorant, to awaken the stupid sinner,
                    to quicken the lukewarm, to confirm the wavering, to comfort the
                        feebleminded,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:14.</p></note> to succour the
                        tempted,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73"><p rend="footnote text">See
                            Heb. 2:18.</p></note> or contribute in any manner to the saving of souls
                    from death. This is the repentance, and these the fruits meet for repentance,
                    which are necessary to full sanctification. This is the way wherein God hath
                    appointed his children to wait for complete salvation.</p>
                <p n="11">11. Hence may appear the extreme mischievousness of that seemingly
                    innocent opinion that ‘there is no sin in a believer; that all sin is destroyed,
                    root and branch, the moment a man is justified.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn74" n="74"><p rend="footnote text">I.e., the view of men like
                            Philip Molther (and, thereafter, of William Cudworth and James Relly);
                            cf. No. 40, <hi rend="italic">Christian Perfection</hi>, II.10 and n.
                            And, since it denied the necessity of a ‘second repentance’, Wesley
                            regarded it as a premise for antinomianism.</p></note> By totally
                    preventing that repentance<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75"><p
                            rend="footnote text">I.e., ‘second repentance’; cf. No. 14, <hi
                                rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, proem, §§1-3, <hi
                                rend="italic">et seq.</hi></p></note> it quite blocks up the way to
                    sanctification. There is no place for repentance in him who believes there is no
                    sin either in his life or heart. Consequently there is no place for his being
                    ‘perfected in love’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 4:18. to which that repentance is
                            indispensably necessary.</p></note></p>
                <p n="12"><pb n="02:167"/>12. Hence it may likewise appear that there is no possible
                    danger in <hi rend="italic">thus</hi> expecting full salvation. For suppose we
                    were mistaken, suppose no such blessing ever was or can be attained, yet we lose
                    nothing. Nay, that very expectation quickens us in using all the talents which
                    God has given us; yea, in improving them all, so that when our Lord cometh he
                    will ‘receive his own with increase’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 25:27.</p></note></p>
                <p n="13">13. But to return. Though it be allowed that both this repentance and its
                    fruits are necessary to full salvation, yet they are not necessary either in the
                        <hi rend="italic">same sense</hi> with faith or in the <hi rend="italic"
                        >same degree</hi>. Not in the same degree; for these fruits are only
                    necessary <hi rend="italic">conditionally</hi>, if there be time and opportunity
                    for them. Otherwise a man may be sanctified without them. But he cannot be
                    sanctified without faith. Likewise let a man have ever so much of this
                    repentance, or ever so many good works, yet all this does not at all avail: he
                    is not sanctified till he believes. But the moment he believes, with or without
                    those fruits, yea, with more or less of this repentance, he is sanctified. Not
                    in the <hi rend="italic">same sense</hi>; for this repentance and these fruits
                    are only <hi rend="italic">remotely</hi> necessary, necessary in order to the
                    continuance of his faith, as well as the increase of it; whereas faith is <hi
                        rend="italic">immediately</hi> and <hi rend="italic">directly</hi> necessary
                    to sanctification. It remains that faith is the only condition which is <hi
                        rend="italic">immediately</hi> and <hi rend="italic">proximately</hi>
                    necessary to sanctification.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78"><p
                            rend="footnote text">The parallel here between faith and repentance in
                            relation to both justification and sanctification is important for
                            Wesley’s solution to his problem of ‘the remains of sin’; it is his
                            alternative to the Lutheran <hi rend="italic">simul justus et
                                peccator</hi>. Faith is the only and equally necessary condition in
                            both cases.</p></note></p>
                <p n="14">14. ‘But what is that faith whereby we are sanctified, saved from sin and
                    perfected in love?’ It is a divine evidence and conviction, first, that God hath
                    promised it in the Holy Scripture. Till we are thoroughly satisfied of this
                    there is no moving one step farther. And one would imagine there needed not one
                    word more to satisfy a reasonable man of this than the ancient promise, ‘Then
                    will I circumcise thy heart, and the heart of thy seed, to love the Lord your
                    God with all your heart, and with all your soul.’<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn79" n="79"><p rend="footnote text">Deut. 30:6. An echo of No. 17,
                            ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’.</p></note> How clearly does this
                    express the being perfected in love! How strongly imply the being saved from all
                    sin! For as long as love takes up the whole heart, what room is there for sin
                    therein?</p>
                <p n="15">15. It is a divine evidence and conviction, secondly, that what <pb
                        n="02:168"/>God hath promised he is <hi rend="italic">able</hi> to perform.
                    Admitting therefore that ‘with men it is impossible’ to bring a clean thing out
                    of an unclean, to purify the heart from all sin, and to fill it with all
                    holiness, yet this creates no difficulty in the case, seeing ‘with God all
                    things are possible.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 19:26, etc.</p></note> And surely no one
                    ever imagined it was possible to any power less than that of the Almighty! But
                    if God speaks, it shall be done. God saith, ‘Let there be light: and there is
                        light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gen. 1:3.</p></note></p>
                <p n="16">16. It is, thirdly, a divine evidence and conviction that he is able and
                    willing to do it <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. And why not? Is not a moment to him
                    the same as a thousand years?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82"><p
                            rend="footnote text">See 2 Pet. 3:8; Ps. 90:4.</p></note> He cannot want
                    more time to accomplish whatever is his will. And he cannot want or stay for any
                    more <hi rend="italic">worthiness</hi> of <hi rend="italic">fitness</hi> in the
                    persons he is pleased to honour. We may therefore boldly say, at any point of
                    time, ‘Now is the day of salvation.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83"><p
                            rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 6:2.</p></note> ‘<hi rend="italic"
                        >Today</hi> if ye will hear his voice, harden not your hearts.’<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84"><p rend="footnote text">Heb.
                        4:7.</p></note> ‘Behold! all things are now ready! Come unto the
                        marriage!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Matt. 22:4.</p></note></p>
                <p n="17">17. To this confidence, that God is both able and willing to sanctify us
                        <hi rend="italic">now</hi>, there needs to be added one thing more, a divine
                    evidence and conviction that <hi rend="italic">he doth it</hi>. In that hour it
                    is done. God says to the inmost soul, ‘According to thy faith be it unto
                        thee!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86"><p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Matt. 9:29.</p></note> Then the soul is pure from every spot of sin; ‘it
                    is clean from all unrighteousness.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87"><p
                            rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 1:9.</p></note> The believer then
                    experiences the deep meaning of those solemn words, ‘If we walk in the light, as
                    he is in the light, we have fellowship one with another, and the blood of Jesus
                    Christ his Son cleanseth us from all sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88"
                        n="88"><p rend="footnote text">1 John 1:7.</p></note></p>
                <p n="18">18. ‘But does God work this great work in the soul <hi rend="italic"
                        >gradually</hi> or <hi rend="italic">instantaneously</hi>?’ Perhaps it may
                    be gradually wrought in some. I mean in this sense—they do not advert to the
                    particular moment wherein sin ceases to be. But it is infinitely desirable, were
                    it the will of God, that it should be done instantaneously; that the Lord should
                    destroy sin ‘by the breath of his mouth’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89"
                            ><p rend="footnote text">Job 15:30; Ps. 33:6.</p></note> in a moment, in
                    the twinkling of an eye.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90"><p
                            rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 15:52.</p></note> And so he generally does,
                    a plain fact of <pb n="02:169"/>which there is evidence enough to satisfy any
                    unprejudiced person. <hi rend="italic">Thou</hi> therefore look for it every
                    moment. Look for it in the way above described; in all those ‘good works’
                    whereunto thou art ‘created anew in Christ Jesus’.<note place="foot"
                        xml:id="ftn91" n="91"><p rend="footnote text">Eph. 2:10.</p></note> There is
                    then no danger. You can be no worse, if you are no better for that expectation.
                    For were you to be disappointed of your hope, still you lose nothing. But you
                    shall not be disappointed of your hope: it will come, and will not tarry.<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92"><p rend="footnote text">See Heb.
                            10:37.</p></note> Look for it then every day, every hour, every moment.
                    Why not this hour, this moment? Certainly you may look for it <hi rend="italic"
                        >now</hi>, if you believe it is by faith. And by this token may you surely
                    know whether you seek it by faith or by works. If by works, you want something
                    to be done <hi rend="italic">first</hi>, <hi rend="italic">before</hi> you are
                    sanctified. You think, ‘I must first <hi rend="italic">be</hi> or <hi
                        rend="italic">do</hi> thus or thus.’ Then you are seeking it by works unto
                    this day. If you seek it by faith, you may expect it <hi rend="italic">as you
                        are</hi>: and if as you are, then expect it <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. It
                    is of importance to observe that there is an inseparable connection between
                    these three points—expect it <hi rend="italic">by faith</hi>, expect it <hi
                        rend="italic">as you are</hi>, and expect it <hi rend="italic">now</hi>! To
                    deny one of them is to deny them all: to allow one is to allow them all. Do <hi
                        rend="italic">you</hi> believe we are sanctified by faith? Be true then to
                    your principle, and look for this blessing just as you are, neither better, nor
                    worse; as a poor sinner that has still nothing to pay, nothing to plead but
                    ‘Christ died.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93"><p rend="footnote text"
                            >Rom. 5:6, 8, etc.</p></note> And if you look for it as you are, then
                    expect it <hi rend="italic">now</hi>. Stay for nothing. Why should you? Christ
                    is ready. And he is all you want. He is waiting for you. He is at the door!<note
                        place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94"><p rend="footnote text">See Rev.
                            3:20.</p></note> Let your inmost soul cry out,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Come in, come in, thou heavenly Guest!</l>
                    <l>Nor hence again remove:</l>
                    <l>But sup with me, and let the feast</l>
                    <l>Be everlasting love.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95"><p rend="footnote text">Cf. Wesley, <hi
                                rend="italic">Hymns on God’s Everlasting Love</hi> (II), London,
                            Strahan, 1742 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 47), Hymn 8, p. 25
                                (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, III.66); the orig. has been
                            slightly retouched.</p></note>
                </lg>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
