<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 7: The Way to the Kingdom</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon007</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 7: The Way to the Kingdom</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="217" to="232"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>
                <pb n="217"/>
            </p>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>This sermon has a double text. The second one (Rom. 14:17) is invoked informally
                    in I.1, and reminds us of Wesley’s first ‘tombstone sermon’ at Epworth, June 6,
                    1742, which was never published but probably has its residues here (cf.
                    JWJ):</p>
                <quote>After [the rector’s] sermon [against ‘enthusiasm’] John Taylor stood in the
                    churchyard, and gave notice as the people were coming out, ‘Mr. Wesley, not
                    being permitted to preach in the church, designs to preach here at six
                    o’clock.’</quote>
                <quote>Accordingly at six I came, and found such a congregation as I believe Epworth
                    never saw before. I stood near the east end of the church, upon my father’s
                    tombstone, and cried, ‘The Kingdom of heaven is not meats and drinks, but
                    righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost.’</quote>
                <p>Wesley records having preached from Rom. 14:17 seventeen times in the half-decade
                    of 1739-43, and only twelve times thereafter (the last in 1791).</p>
                <p>The formal text here is Mark 1:15, a favourite of Wesley’s in his oral preaching
                    (he records having used it one hundred and ninety times in the forty-eight-year
                    span, 1742-90). The result, however, is a single sermon with an integrated,
                    cumulative argument that progresses from a negative comment on what true
                    religion is not (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, correct praxis and doctrine) to a
                    positive definition of it (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, love of God and
                    neighbour, both as empowered by grace). These lead into an exhortation to
                    repentance and belief which includes another summary statement about repentance
                    as true self-knowledge and authentic contrition (as in No. 6, ‘The Righteousness
                    of Faith’, II.6). Belief is never ‘bare assent’ but rather an assenting trust
                    whose first-fruits are reconciliation and peace. All this points to the
                    conclusion: a celebration of Christian joy ‘in the Holy Ghost’.</p>
                <p>It is worth comparing this sermon with Wesley’s later published sermon on the
                    same text (No. 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>). The
                    latter makes the rather different point that becomes important once the sola
                    fide has been accepted (especially if also misconstrued), <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, that the Christian’s progress in sanctification does not
                    preclude repentance. Indeed, since repentance means self-knowledge, the farther
                    Christians are along their way to sanctification, the more sensitive they are to
                    their shortfalls in faith, hope, and love.</p>
            </introduction>
            <p>
                <pb n="218"/>
            </p>
            <head>The Way to the Kingdom</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>Mark 1:15</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">The kingdom of God is at hand: repent ye, and believe the
                        gospel.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
                <p>These words naturally lead us to consider, first, the nature of true religion,
                    here termed by our Lord ‘the kingdom of God’, which, saith he, ‘is at hand’; and
                    secondly, the way thereto, which he points out in those words, ‘Repent ye, and
                    believe the gospel.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <p n="1">I. 1. We are, first, to consider the nature of true religion, here termed
                    by our Lord ‘the kingdom of God’. The same expression the great Apostle uses in
                    his Epistle to the Romans, where he likewise explains his Lord’s words, saying,
                    ‘The kingdom of God is not meat and drink; but righteousness, and peace, and joy
                    in the Holy Ghost.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Rom. 14:17 [cf. 2 Tim. 2:22; Heb.
                            12:11].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. ‘The kingdom of God’, or true religion, ‘is not meat and drink.’ It is
                    well known that not only the unconverted Jews, but great numbers of those who
                    had received the faith of Christ, were notwithstanding ‘zealous of the law’,<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                                21:20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> even the ceremonial law of Moses. Whatsoever
                    therefore they found written therein, either concerning meat and drink
                    offerings, or the distinction between clean and unclean meats, they not only
                    observed themselves, but vehemently pressed the same even on those ‘among the
                    Gentiles’ (or heathens) ‘who were turned to God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 15:19.</p>
                    </note> Yea,
                    to such a degree that some of them taught, wheresoever they came among them,
                    ‘Except ye be circumcised, and keep the law’ (the whole ritual law), ‘ye cannot
                    be saved.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Acts 15:1, 24.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. In opposition to these the Apostle declares, both here and in many other
                    places, that true religion does not consist in <hi rend="italic">meat</hi> and
                        <hi rend="italic">drink</hi>, or in any ritual observances; nor indeed in
                    any outward thing whatever, in anything exterior to the heart; the whole <pb n="219"/>substance thereof lying in ‘righteousness, peace, and joy in the
                    Holy Ghost’.</p>
                <p n="4">4. Not in any <hi rend="italic">outward thing</hi>, such as <hi rend="italic">forms</hi> or <hi rend="italic">ceremonies</hi>, even of the
                    most excellent kind. Supposing these to be ever so decent and significant, ever
                    so expressive of inward things; supposing them ever so helpful, not only to the
                    vulgar, whose thought reaches little farther than their sight, but even to men
                    of understanding, men of strong capacities, as doubtless they may sometimes be;
                    yea, supposing them, as in the case of the Jews, to be appointed by God himself;
                    yet even during the period of time wherein that appointment remains in force,
                    true religion does not principally consist therein—nay, strictly speaking, not
                    at all. How much more must this hold concerning such rites and forms as are only
                    of human appointment! The religion of Christ rises infinitely higher and lies
                    immensely deeper than all these. These are good in their place; just so far as
                    they are in fact subservient to true religion.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                        <p rend="footnote text">That Wesley himself did not dispense with
                            symbols and ceremonials would appear from his insistence on wearing his
                            gown and cassock both for his field preaching and in his meetings with
                            the societies; see JWJ, Sept. 9, 1743. His exhortations to ‘use all the
                            means of grace’ were turned into the third of his <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi> for all Methodists. This is a reflection of his
                            firm distinction between vestments and ceremonies being used, and their
                            being relied on; cf. George Whitefield, <hi rend="italic">A Short
                                Account of God’s Dealings with the Reverend Mr. Whitefield</hi>
                            (London, Strahan, 1740), p. 44. It was also a sign of Wesley’s quiet
                            negation of the famous Puritan rejection of vestments, prelacy, and the
                            BCP as ‘popish remnants’. Thus, he could deny all <hi rend="italic">intrinsic</hi> value to any external sign and still avoid any
                            radical iconoclasm.</p>
                    </note> And it were superstition to object
                    against them while they are applied only as occasional helps to human weakness.
                    But let no man carry them farther. Let no man dream that they have any intrinsic
                    worth; or that religion cannot subsist without them. This were to make them an
                    abomination to the Lord.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Deut. 7:25, etc.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="5">5. The nature of religion is so far from consisting in these, in forms of
                    worship, or rites and ceremonies, that it does not properly consist in any
                    outward actions of what kind so ever.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A parallel rejection of moralism, on the one hand,
                            and of antinomianism, on the other.</p>
                    </note> It is true a man cannot
                    have any religion who is guilty of vicious, immoral actions; or who does to
                    others what he would not they should do to him if he were in the same
                    circumstance. And it is also true that he can have no real religion who ‘knows
                    to do good, and doth it not’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas. 4:17.</p>
                    </note> Yet may a man both
                    abstain from outward evil, and do good, and still have no religion. Yea, two
                    persons may do <pb n="220"/>the same outward work—suppose, feeding the hungry,
                    or clothing the naked—and in the meantime one of these may be truly religious
                    and the other have no religion at all; for the one may act from the love of God,
                    and the other from the love of praise. So manifest it is that although true
                    religion naturally leads to every good word and work, yet the real nature
                    thereof lies deeper still, even in ‘the hidden man of the heart’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet.
                        3:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. I say of the <hi rend="italic">heart</hi>. For neither does religion
                    consist in <hi rend="italic">orthodoxy</hi> or <hi rend="italic">right
                        opinions</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s attitudes toward ‘orthodoxy’ and ‘heresy’ were complex. Here,
                            his thesis is that orthodoxy—like ceremonialism and moralism—is not of
                            the essence of true religion, and he belabours the point that the devil
                            is more orthodox than the soundest Christian theologian. This is a
                            favourite point with him, as in Nos. 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’,
                            III.1; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, III.5; 120, ‘The Unity of the
                            Divine Being’, §15; 127, ‘On the Wedding Garment’, §15. Cf. also
                            Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Plain Account of the People called
                                Methodists</hi>, I.2; and his letters to James Clark, July 3 and
                            Sept. 18, 1756; Bishop Warburton, Nov. 26, 1762; and John Erskine, Apr.
                            24, 1765. Cf. also <hi rend="italic">Some Remarks on a Defence
                                of…Aspasio Vindicated</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 296,
                            Vol. 13 of this edn.) See also Glanvill, <hi rend="italic">Defence of
                                Preaching</hi>, p. 83; and Norris, <hi rend="italic">Miscellanies</hi>, pp. 173-202.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">To these
                            may be added his slogan for theological pluralism (‘to think and let
                            think’): cf. Nos. 20, <hi rend="italic">The Lord Our Righteousness</hi>,
                            II.20; 37, ‘The Nature of Enthusiasm’, §36; 38, ‘A Caution against
                            Bigotry’, II.3; 39, ‘Catholic Spirit’ (entire); 53, <hi rend="italic">On
                                the Death of George Whitefield</hi>, III.1; 55, <hi rend="italic">On
                                the Trinity</hi>, §2; 74, ‘Of the Church’, §19; 127, ‘On the Wedding
                            Garment’, §14; 130, ‘On Living without God’, §15. See also JWJ, May 29,
                            1745; Dec. 3, 1776; Oct. 3, 1783; and Wesley’s letters to Miss March,
                            Mar. 29, 1760; Dr. Warburton, Nov. 26, 1762; Henry Venn, June 22, 1763;
                            John Newton, Apr. 9,1765; Philothea Briggs, June 20, 1772; Thomas Wride,
                            Mar. 9, 1780; Joseph Benson, May 21, 1781; Mr. Howton, Oct. 3, 1783; Dr.
                            Tomline, Mar. 1790. See also <hi rend="italic">The Character of a
                                Methodist</hi>, §1; and <hi rend="italic">Some Observations on
                                Liberty</hi>, §1 (<hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 360, Vol. 15
                            of this edn.).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">To conclude from all this,
                            however, that Wesley was indifferent to the issues involved in sound
                            doctrine is to misunderstand him. He had a clear view of heresy as
                            deviation from the core of ‘standing revelation’; and had no hesitation
                            in denouncing views that threatened this core. See his <hi rend="italic">Doctrine of Original Sin</hi>, III.i, vii; IV. iv (‘First Essay’).
                            If Methodism may rightly be charged with theological indifferentism,
                            this has no valid grounds in Wesley himself.</p>
                    </note> which, although
                    they are not properly outward things, are not in the heart, but the
                    understanding. A man may be orthodox in every point; he may not only espouse
                    right opinions, but zealously defend them against all opposers; he may think
                    justly concerning the incarnation of our Lord, concerning the ever blessed
                    Trinity, and every other doctrine contained in the oracles of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 5,
                            ‘Justification by Faith’, §2 and n.</p>
                    </note> He may assent to all the
                    three creeds—that called the Apostles’, the Nicene, and the Athanasian—and yet
                    ’tis possible he may have no religion at all, no more than a Jew, Turk, or
                    pagan. He may be almost as orthodox as the devil (though indeed not altogether;
                    for every man errs in <pb n="221"/>something, whereas we can’t well conceive
                        him<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                        <p rend="footnote text">I.e., the
                            devil.</p>
                    </note> to hold any erroneous opinion) and may all the while
                    be as great a stranger as he to the religion of the heart.</p>
                <p n="7">7. This alone is religion, truly so called: this alone is in the sight of
                    God of great price. The Apostle sums it all up in three
                    particulars—‘righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            14:17.</p>
                    </note> And first, <hi rend="italic">righteousness</hi>.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 29,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, IX’, §20.</p>
                    </note> We cannot be at a loss
                    concerning this if we remember the words of our Lord describing the two grand
                    branches thereof, on which ‘hang all the law and the prophets’:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        22:40.</p>
                    </note> ‘Thou shalt love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and
                    with all thy mind, and with all thy soul, and with all thy strength. This is the
                    first and great commandment,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Mark 12:30 [actually Matt.
                        22:37-38].</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> the first and great branch of Christian
                    righteousness. Thou shalt delight thyself in the Lord thy God; thou shalt seek
                    and find all happiness in him. He shall be ‘thy shield, and thy exceeding great
                        reward’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 15:1.</p>
                    </note> in time and in eternity. All thy bones shall say,
                    ‘Whom have I in heaven but thee? And there is none upon earth that I desire
                    beside thee!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 73:25.</p>
                    </note> Thou shalt hear and fulfil his word who saith,
                    ‘My son, give me thy heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Prov. 23:26.</p>
                    </note> And having given him
                    thy heart, thy inmost soul, to reign there without a rival, thou mayest well cry
                    out in the fullness of thy heart, ‘I will love thee, O Lord, my strength. The
                    Lord is my strong rock and my defence: my Saviour, my God, and my might, in whom
                    I will trust; my buckler, the horn also of my salvation, and my refuge.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 18:1
                            (BCP), where the text reads ‘stony rock’, and Ps. 31:3 (BCP), ‘And be
                            thou my strong rock, and house of defence….’</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="8">8. And the second commandment is like unto this; the second great branch of
                    Christian righteousness is closely and inseparably connected therewith, even
                    ‘Thou shalt love thy neighbour as thyself.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt. 22:39, etc.</p>
                    </note> ‘Thou shalt
                    love’—thou shalt embrace with the most tender goodwill, the most earnest and
                    cordial affection, the most inflamed desires of preventing or removing all evil
                    and procuring for him every possible good—‘thy neighbour’; that is, not only thy
                    friend, thy kinsman, or thy acquaintance; not only the <pb n="222"/>virtuous,
                    the friendly, him that loves thee, that prevents<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note in this one paragraph the
                            use of ‘preventing’ in the sense of <hi rend="italic">hinder</hi> and of
                            ‘prevent’ in its more literal sense of <hi rend="italic">precede</hi>.</p>
                    </note> or returns thy kindness; but every child of
                    man, every human creature,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s standard definition of neighbour, as
                            appears from Nos. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, II.2;
                            18, ‘The Marks of the New Birth’, III.3; 52, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Reformation of Manners</hi>, III.8; 65, ‘The Duty of Reproving our
                            Neighbour’, II.2; 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>,
                            III.2; 100, ‘On Pleasing All Men’, §1; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.9;
                            112, <hi rend="italic">On Laying the Foundation of the New Chapel</hi>,
                            II.1; 114, <hi rend="italic">On the Death of John Fletcher</hi>,
                            I.3.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">No such definition appears in the <hi rend="italic">OED</hi>. But Wesley could have found it in Thomas
                            Sprat, <hi rend="italic">Sermons Preached on Several Occasions</hi>
                            (1722), p. 101; in Poole’s <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi> (on Ps.
                            15:3); in Law’s <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV.188, 216-25); and in Fleury, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Manners…of the Christians</hi>, p. 19.</p>
                    </note> every soul which
                    God hath made: not excepting him whom thou never hast seen in the flesh, whom
                    thou knowest not either by face or name; not excepting him whom thou knowest to
                    be evil and unthankful, him that still despitefully uses and persecutes
                        thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                            5:44.</p>
                    </note> Him thou shalt ‘love as thyself’; with the same
                    invariable thirst after his happiness in every kind,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Note here the ‘socialization’
                            of eudaemonism: the subjective ‘thirst for happiness’ is understood as
                            interdependent with the Christian’s readiness to seek and serve his
                            neighbour’s ‘happiness in every kind’ … ‘procuring for him every
                            possible good’. Cf. No. 5, ‘Justification by Faith’, I.4 and n. This
                            premise of Wesley’s social ethic was revolutionary in both its intention
                            and partial effect; cf. Semmel, <hi rend="italic">Methodist
                                Revolution</hi>, chs. 1 and 3.</p>
                    </note> the same unwearied care to
                    screen him from whatever might grieve or hurt either his soul or body.</p>
                <p n="9">9. Now is not this love ‘the fulfilling of the law’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:10.</p>
                    </note> The sum
                    of all Christian righteousness? Of all inward righteousness; for it necessarily
                    implies ‘bowels of mercies, humbleness of mind’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> (seeing ‘love is not
                    puffed up’),<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 13:4; note Wesley’s preference for ‘love’ instead of the AV’s
                            ‘charity’; cf. No. 17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2 and
                        n.</p>
                    </note> ‘gentleness, meekness, long-suffering’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 3:12.</p>
                    </note> (for
                    love ‘is not provoked’, but ‘believeth, hopeth, endureth all things’):<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 13:5,
                            7.</p>
                    </note> and of all outward righteousness, for ‘love worketh no
                    evil to his neighbour’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 13:10.</p>
                    </note> either by word or deed. It
                    cannot willingly either hurt or grieve anyone. And it is zealous of good
                        works.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Titus
                            2:14.</p>
                    </note> Every lover of mankind, as he hath opportunity, ‘doth
                    good unto all men’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 6:10.</p>
                    </note> being (‘without
                    partiality and without hypocrisy’) ‘full of mercy and good fruits’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Jas.
                        3:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">
                    <pb n="2xx"/>10. But true religion, or a heart right toward God and man,
                    implies happiness as well as holiness.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Holiness’, here and everywhere in Wesley,
                            denotes <hi rend="italic">active love</hi>—to God (‘inward holiness’)
                            and to neighbour (‘outward holiness’). Such love yields happiness less
                            as an end product than as a by-product; see below, I.11-12. Cf. Nos. 6,
                            ‘The Righteousness of Faith’, II.9 and n.; 18, ‘The Marks of the New
                            Birth’, III.3; 24, ‘Sermon on the Mount, IV’, III.1; 45, ‘The New
                            Birth’, III.1; 83, ‘On Patience’, §§9, 10; 84, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Important Question</hi>, III.2; 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own
                            Salvation’, I.2; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, I.9; and 112, <hi rend="italic">On Laying the Foundation of the New Chapel</hi>,
                            II.1.</p>
                    </note> For it is not only righteousness, but also ‘peace and
                    joy in the Holy Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note> What peace? ‘The peace of
                    God’, which God only can give, and the world cannot take away; the peace ‘which
                    passeth all understanding’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 4:7.</p>
                    </note> all (barely) rational
                    conception; being a supernatural sensation, a divine taste of ‘the powers of the
                    world to come’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 6:5.</p>
                    </note> such as the natural man knoweth not, how wise
                    soever in the things of this world; nor, indeed, can he know it in his present
                    state, ‘because it is spiritually discerned’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 2:14.</p>
                    </note> It is a peace
                    that banishes all doubt, all painful uncertainty, the Spirit of God ‘bearing
                    witness with the spirit’ of a Christian that he is ‘a child of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                            8:16.</p>
                    </note> And it banishes fear, all such fear as hath
                        torment;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            1 John 4:18.</p>
                    </note> the fear of the wrath of God, the fear of hell,
                    the fear of the devil, and, in particular, the fear of death: he that hath the
                    peace of God ‘desiring’ (if it were the will of God) ‘to depart and to be with
                        Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Phil. 1:23.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. With this peace of God, wherever it is fixed in the soul, there is
                    also ‘joy in the Holy Ghost’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note> joy wrought in the heart by
                    the Holy Ghost, by the ever-blessed Spirit of God. He it is that worketh in us
                    that calm, humble rejoicing in God, through Christ Jesus, ‘by whom we have now
                    received the atonement’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:11.</p>
                    </note> καταλλαγήν, the
                    reconciliation with God; and that enables us boldly to confirm the truth of the
                    royal Psalmist’s declaration, ‘Blessed is the man’ (or rather, <hi rend="italic">happy</hi>, אשדי
                    היש)<!--Mark this Hebrew with an xml:lang later, as well as any
                            other instances of foreign language.--> ‘whose
                    unrighteousness is forgiven, and whose sin is covered.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 32:1 (BCP). Wesley
                            would appear to be quoting here from memory or else ‘back-translating’,
                            since the Hebrew text omits היש (‘the one’), presumably as understood;
                            cf. Rudolf Kittel, ed., <hi rend="italic">Biblia Hebraica</hi> (New
                            York, American Bible Society, 1937), and his <hi rend="italic">apparatus
                                technicus</hi>. In the pamphlet editions of this sermon, in <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, and in Benson, Jackson, and Sugden, the
                            Hebrew phrase is omitted altogether. For further comments on Wesley’s
                            use of Hebrew, cf. <hi rend="italic">A Farther Appeal</hi>, Pt. I, I.6,
                            III.5 (11:108, 125 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note> He it is <pb n="224"/>that
                    inspires the Christian soul with that even, solid joy which arises from the
                    testimony of the Spirit that he is a child of God; and that gives him to
                    ‘rejoice with joy unspeakable’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘in hope of the glory of
                        God’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            5:2.</p>
                    </note>—hope both of the glorious image of God, which is in part
                    and shall be fully ‘revealed in him’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:18.</p>
                    </note> and of that crown of
                    glory which fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 1:4;
                    5:4.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. This holiness and happiness, joined in one, are sometimes styled in
                    the inspired writings, ‘the kingdom of God’ (as by our Lord in the text), and
                    sometimes, ‘the kingdom of heaven’. It is termed ‘the kingdom of God’ because it
                    is the immediate fruit of God’s reigning in the soul. So soon as ever he takes
                    unto himself his mighty power, and sets up his throne in our hearts, they are
                    instantly filled with this ‘righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy
                        Ghost’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom.
                            14:17.</p>
                    </note> It is called ‘the kingdom of heaven’ because it is (in
                    a degree) heaven opened in the soul.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. above, No. 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, III.5 and n.</p>
                    </note> For whosoever they are
                    that experience this, they can aver before angels and men,</p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Everlasting life is won:</l>
                    <l>Glory is on earth begun</l>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Charles Wesley, ‘Hymn After the Sacrament,’ st. 6,
                            ll. 3-4, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi>, 1739, p. 191
                                (<hi rend="italic">Poet. Wks.</hi>, I.170).</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p>according to the constant tenor of Scripture, which everywhere bears record, ‘God
                    hath given unto us eternal life, and this life is in his Son. He that hath the
                    Son’ (reigning in his heart) ‘hath life,’ even life everlasting.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">1 John
                                5:11-12.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> For ‘this is life eternal, to know thee,
                    the only true God, and Jesus Christ, whom thou hast sent….’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">John
                                17:3.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> And they to whom this is given may confidently
                    address God, though they were in the midst of a fiery furnace,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Dan.
                    3:8-30.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <lg>
                    <l>Thee…, Lord, safe-shielded by thy power,</l>
                    <l>Thee, Son of God, Jehovah, we adore,</l>
                    <l>In form of man descending to appear:</l>
                    <l>To thee be ceaseless hallelujahs given.</l>
                    <l>Praise, as in heaven thy throne, we offer here;</l>
                    <l>For where thy presence is displayed, is heaven.</l>
                    <note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark Le Pla (1650-1715), vicar of Finchingfield
                            (Essex), <hi rend="italic">A Paraphrase on the Song of the Three
                                Children</hi> (1724), concluding stanza. John Wesley included it in
                                <hi rend="italic">A Collection of Moral and Sacred Poems</hi>,
                            II.101-34. This quotation appears in ‘O Ananias, Azarias, and Misael…’,
                            st. xliv, ll. 14-19, p. 134.</p>
                    </note>
                </lg>
                <p>
                    <pb n="228"/>13. And this ‘kingdom of God’, or of heaven, ‘is at hand’. As these
                    words were originally spoken they implied that ‘the time’ was then
                        ‘fulfilled’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 1:15.</p>
                    </note> God being made ‘manifest in the flesh’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                        3:16.</p>
                    </note> when he would set up his kingdom among men, and reign in
                    the hearts of his people. And is not the time now fulfilled? For ‘Lo (saith he),
                    I am with you always’, you who preach remission of sins in my name, ‘even unto
                    the end of the world.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                        <note place="end">
                            <p rend="endnote text">Matt. 28:20.</p>
                        </note>
                    </hi> Wheresoever
                    therefore the gospel of Christ is preached, this his ‘kingdom is nigh at
                        hand’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Luke
                            21:31.</p>
                    </note> It is not far from every one of you. Ye may this hour
                    enter thereinto, if so be ye hearken to his voice, ‘Repent ye, and believe the
                    gospel.’</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p n="1">II. 1. This is the way: walk ye in it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 30:21.</p>
                    </note> And first, repent,
                    that is, know yourselves.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s distinctive view of repentance as that
                            self-knowledge which leads to contrition and to casting oneself on God’s
                            pardoning mercy in Christ (‘trust’ rather than ‘assent’). Variations on
                            this basic theme may be seen in Nos. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou
                                That Sleepest’</hi>, II.1; 6, ‘The Righteousness of Faith’, II.6;
                            14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, III.2; 17, ‘The
                            Circumcision of the Heart’, I.2; 21, ‘Sermon on the Mount, I’, I.4; 30,
                            ‘Sermon on the Mount, X’, §7; 33, ‘Sermon on the Mount, XIII’, III.6;
                            78, ‘Spiritual Idolatry’, II.4; see also, below, II.6-7; and Wesley’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on Matt. 5:3. In No. 79, ‘On
                            Dissipation’, §19, Wesley comments on William Law’s inversion of faith
                            and repentance in the <hi rend="italic">ordo salutis</hi> in Law’s <hi rend="italic">Spirit of Prayer</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                            VII.3-143). For Wesley’s denunciation of Bishop Bull’s doctrine of
                            repentance, see Nos. 150 and 151, ‘Hypocrisy in Oxford’ (Eng. text, I.7;
                            Lat. text, I.6).</p>
                    </note> This is the first repentance, previous to
                    faith, even conviction, or self-knowledge. Awake, then, thou that sleepest.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Eph.
                        5:14.</p>
                    </note> Know thyself to be a sinner, and what manner of sinner thou
                    art. Know that corruption of thy inmost nature, whereby thou art very far gone
                    from original righteousness, whereby ‘the flesh lusteth’ always ‘contrary to the
                        Spirit’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Gal. 5:17.</p>
                    </note> through that ‘carnal mind which is enmity against
                    God’, which ‘is not subject to the law of God, neither indeed can be’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom.
                        8:7.</p>
                    </note> Know that thou art corrupted in every power, in every
                    faculty of thy soul, that thou art totally corrupted in every one of these, all
                    the foundations being out of course. The eyes of thine understanding are
                    darkened, so that they cannot discern God or the things of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 1:18;
                            4:18.</p>
                    </note> The clouds <pb n="226"/>of ignorance and error rest
                    upon thee, and cover thee with the shadow of death. Thou knowest nothing yet as
                    thou oughtest to know, neither God, nor the world, nor thyself. Thy will is no
                    longer the will of God, but is utterly perverse and distorted, averse from all
                    good, from all which God loves, and prone to all evil, to every abomination
                    which God hateth. Thy affections are alienated from God, and scattered abroad
                    over all the earth. All thy passions, both thy desires and aversions, thy joys
                    and sorrows, thy hopes and fears, are out of frame, are either undue in their
                    degree, or placed on undue objects. So that there is no soundness in thy soul,
                    but ‘from the crown of the head to the sole of the foot’ (to use the strong
                    expression of the prophet) there are only ‘wounds, and bruises, and putrefying
                        sores’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                            Isa. 1:6.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="2">2. Such is the inbred corruption of thy heart, of thy very inmost nature.
                    And what manner of branches canst thou expect to grow from such an evil root?
                    Hence springs unbelief, ever departing from the living God; saying, ‘Who is the
                    Lord that I should serve him?’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Judg. 9:28, 38; Job 21:15.</p>
                    </note> ‘Tush!
                    Thou, God, carest not for it.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 10:14 (BCP).</p>
                    </note> Hence independence,
                    affecting to be like the Most High; hence pride, in all its forms, teaching thee
                    to say, ‘I am rich, and increased in goods, and have need of nothing.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev.
                        3:17.</p>
                    </note> From this evil fountain flow forth the bitter streams of
                    vanity, thirst of praise, ambition, covetousness, the lust of the flesh, the
                    lust of the eye, and the pride of life.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 John 2:16. Wesley’s favourite blanket
                            reference to what St. Augustine had already identified as the <hi rend="italic">triplex concupiscentia</hi> which, as he and Wesley
                            agreed, ‘includes all sin’ (cf. St. Augustine, <hi rend="italic">Confessions</hi>, X. xxx. 41, <hi rend="italic">et seq.</hi>, and
                                <hi rend="italic">Expositions on the Psalms</hi>, VIII. 13; see also
                            the letter, CCXX, to Boniface [427], §§5-9; and <hi rend="italic">On
                                Patience</hi>, 14-16, ‘the concupiscence of the bad’). Wesley
                            repeats the text tirelessly, and its suggestion to him that sin is
                            overreach of what in themselves are innocent appetites (as in the
                            animals) reinforced his notion of our human responsibility in all sin.
                            For this text related especially to the greed for money, cf. John
                            Cardinal Bona, <hi rend="italic">Precepts and Practical Rules for a
                                Truly Christian Life</hi>, p. 38. See also Law, <hi rend="italic">Serious Call</hi>, (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, IV, 18,
                            178).</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. also Nos. 2, <hi rend="italic">The
                                Almost Christian</hi>, II. (i.) 1; 4, <hi rend="italic">Scriptural
                                Christianity</hi>, I.6; 9, ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’,
                            I.5, III.7; 14, <hi rend="italic">The Repentance of Believers</hi>, I.5;
                            17, ‘The Circumcision of the Heart’, I.13, II.9; 28, ‘Sermon on the
                            Mount, VIII’, §14; 41, <hi rend="italic">Wandering Thoughts</hi>, III.4;
                            44, <hi rend="italic">Original Sin</hi>, II.9, 10; 50, ‘The Use of
                            Money’, II.1-2; 68, ‘The Wisdom of God’s Counsels’, §16; 78, ‘Spiritual
                            Idolatry’, I.5-15; 80, ‘On Friendship with the World’, §16; 81, ‘In What
                            Sense we are to Leave the World’, §11; 83, ‘On Patience’, §9; 84, <hi rend="italic">The Important Question</hi>, I.3, III.10; 86, <hi rend="italic">A Call to Backsliders</hi>, §4; 87, ‘The Danger of
                            Riches’, I.12-16; 90, ‘An Israelite Indeed’, I.1; 95, ‘On the Education
                            of Children’, §§8, 19; 107, ‘On God’s Vineyard’, V.3; 108, ‘On Riches’,
                            II.2-3; 109, <hi rend="italic">The Trouble and Rest of Good Men</hi>,
                            I.3; 119, ‘Walking by Sight and Walking by Faith’, §17; 120, ‘The Unity
                            of the Divine Being’, §12; 122, ‘Causes of the Inefficacy of
                            Christianity’, §8; 125, ‘On a Single Eye’, II.1; 128, ‘The Deceitfulness
                            of the Human Heart’, I.4; 131, ‘The Danger of Increasing Riches’, I.9,
                            10, 12, 15; 143, ‘Public Diversions Denounced’, III.2.</p>
                        <p rend="footnote text">See also Wesley’s <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi> on 1
                            John 2:16, and his letters to Mrs. Pendarves, Feb. 11, 1731; to Dr.
                            Burton, Oct. 10, 1735; to his brother Samuel, Oct. 15, 1735; and to
                            James Hutton, Apr. 30, 1739.</p>
                    </note>
                    <pb n="227"/>From this arise anger, hatred, malice, revenge, envy, jealousy,
                    evil surmisings;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 6:4.</p>
                    </note> from this, all the foolish and hurtful lusts
                    that now ‘pierce thee through with many sorrows’, and if not timely prevented
                    will at length ‘drown thy soul in everlasting perdition’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 6:9,
                    10.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="3">3. And what fruits can grow on such branches as these? Only such as are
                    bitter and evil continually. Of pride cometh contention,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Prov. 13:10.</p>
                    </note> vain
                    boasting, seeking and receiving praise of men, and so robbing God of that glory
                    which he cannot give unto another. Of the lust of the flesh come gluttony or
                    drunkenness, luxury or sensuality, fornication, uncleanness, variously defiling
                    that body which was designed for a temple of the Holy Ghost:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 6:19.</p>
                    </note> of
                    unbelief, every evil word and work. But the time would fail, shouldst thou
                    reckon up all; all the idle words thou hast spoken, provoking the Most High,
                    grieving the Holy One of Israel; all the evil works thou hast done, either
                    wholly evil in themselves, or at least not done to the glory of God. For thy
                    actual sins are more than thou art able to express, more than the hairs of thy
                    head. Who can number the sands of the sea, or the drops of rain, or thy
                    iniquities?</p>
                <p n="4">4. And knowest thou not that ‘the wages of sin is death’?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:23.</p>
                    </note>—death
                    not only temporal, but eternal. ‘The soul that sinneth, it shall die;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ezek. 18:4,
                            20.</p>
                    </note> for the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 1:20,
                            etc.</p>
                    </note> It shall die the second death.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Rev. 2:11; 20:6, 14;
                            21:8.</p>
                    </note> This is the sentence, to ‘be punished’ with
                    never-ending death, ‘with everlasting destruction from the presence of the Lord,
                    and from the glory of his power’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Thess. 1:9.</p>
                    </note> Knowest thou not that
                    every sinner ἔνοχος ἔστι τῃ γέεννῃν τοῦ πυρός, not properly is ‘in danger of
                        hell-fire’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt 5:22; another quotation from memory since Wesley’s own Greek
                            text (<hi rend="italic">TR</hi>) read ἔνοχος ἔσται εἰς τὴν γέενναν τοῦ
                            πυρός. It would seem that ἐστι for ἔσται and τῃ γεέννῃ for τὴν γέενναν
                            are typographical errors left reverently uncorrected by subsequent
                            printers and editors. But translating ἔνοχος as ‘under the sentence of
                            hell-fire’—‘doomed already’—ignores the <hi rend="italic">future</hi>
                            tense of ἔσται. For Wesley’s more typical translation or exegeses of
                            ἔνοχος (i.e., ‘obnoxious’ or ‘liable to’, ‘subject to’), see Nos. 9,
                            ‘The Spirit of Bondage and of Adoption’, II.2; 22, ‘Sermon on the Mount,
                            II’, I.7, 9, 10; 62, ‘The End of Christ’s Coming’, I.10; 92, ‘On Zeal’,
                            III.1-4. The same usage may be found in Robert Gell’s <hi rend="italic">Remaines: Or Several Select Scriptures of the New Testament Opened
                                and Explained</hi> (1676), I.44; and Offspring Blackall, <hi rend="italic">Works</hi>, I.221. See also St. Thomas, <hi rend="italic">Summa Theologica</hi>, II. ii, Q. 158. A.5, obj. 3,
                            ‘Of Anger’; and Macarius, Homily XXVIII, in <hi rend="italic">Homilies</hi> (1721), p. 362. Cf. <hi rend="italic">OED</hi> for
                            the diversity of meanings for ‘obnoxious’.</p>
                    </note>—that expression
                        <pb n="228"/>is far too weak—but rather, ‘is under the sentence of
                    hell-fire’; doomed already, just dragging to execution? Thou art guilty of
                    everlasting death. It is the just reward of thy inward and outward wickedness.
                    It is just that the sentence should now take place. Dost thou see, dost thou
                    feel this? Art thou throughly convinced that thou deservest God’s wrath and
                    everlasting damnation? Would God do thee any wrong if he now commanded the earth
                    to open and swallow thee up? If thou wert now to go down quick into the
                        pit,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See
                            Num. 16:30.</p>
                    </note> into the fire that never shall be quenched?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark 9:43,
                            45.</p>
                    </note> If God hath given thee truly to repent, thou hast a deep
                    sense that these things are so; and that it is of his mere mercy thou art not
                    consumed, swept away from the face of the earth.</p>
                <p n="5">5. And what wilt thou do to appease the wrath of God, to atone for all thy
                    sins, and to escape the punishment thou hast so justly deserved? Alas, thou
                    canst do nothing; nothing that will in any wise make amends to God for one evil
                    work or word or thought. If thou couldst now do all things well, if from this
                    very hour, till thy soul should return to God, thou couldst perform perfect,
                    uninterrupted obedience, even this would not atone for what is past. The not
                    increasing thy debt would not discharge it. It would still remain as great as
                    ever. Yea, the present and future obedience of all the men upon earth, and all
                    the angels in heaven, would never make satisfaction to the justice of God for
                    one single sin. How vain then was the thought of atoning for thy own sins by
                    anything thou couldst do! It costeth far more to redeem one soul than all
                    mankind is able to pay. So that were there no other help for a guilty sinner,
                    without doubt he must have perished everlastingly.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Echoes here from Anselm, <hi rend="italic">Cur Deus Homo?</hi>, Bk. I, chs. xix-xxv; note there,
                            and elsewhere in Anselm, a similar equation of holiness and happiness,
                            as later in Wesley.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="6">6. But suppose perfect obedience for the time to come could atone for the
                    sins that are past, this would profit thee nothing; for thou art not able to
                    perform it; no, not in any one point. Begin now. Make the trial. Shake off that
                    outward sin that so easily besetteth thee.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 12:1.</p>
                    </note> Thou canst not. How
                    then wilt thou change thy life from all evil to all good? Indeed, it is
                    impossible to be done, <pb n="229"/>unless first thy heart be changed. For so
                    long as the tree remains evil, it cannot bring forth good fruit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:18;
                            Luke 6:43.</p>
                    </note> But art thou able to change thy own heart from all
                    sin to all holiness? To quicken a soul that is dead in sin?<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Eph. 2:1, 5.</p>
                    </note>
                    Dead to God and alive only to the world? No more than thou art able to quicken a
                    dead body, to raise to life him that lieth in the grave. Yea, thou art not able
                    to quicken thy soul in any degree, no more than to give any degree of life to
                    the dead body. Thou canst do nothing, more or less, in this matter; thou art
                    utterly without strength. To be deeply sensible of this, how helpless thou art,
                    as well as how guilty and how sinful, this is that ‘repentance not to be
                    repented of’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2
                            Cor. 7:10. Cf. above, II.1 and n.</p>
                    </note> which is the forerunner of
                    the kingdom of God.</p>
                <p n="7">7. If to this lively conviction of thy inward and outward sins, of thy
                    utter guiltiness and helplessness, there be added suitable affections—sorrow of
                    heart for having despised thy own mercies; remorse and self-condemnation, having
                    the mouth stopped, shame to lift up thine eyes to heaven;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Luke 18:13.</p>
                    </note>
                    fear of the wrath of God abiding on thee, of his curse hanging over thy head,
                    and of the fiery indignation ready to devour those who forget God and obey not
                    our Lord Jesus Christ; earnest desire to escape from that indignation, to cease
                    from evil and learn to do well<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 1:16, 17.</p>
                    </note>—then I say unto thee,
                    in the name of the Lord, ‘Thou art not far from the kingdom of God.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Mark
                        12:34.</p>
                    </note> One step more and thou shalt enter in. Thou dost ‘repent’.
                    Now, ‘believe the gospel’.</p>
                <p n="8">8. ‘The gospel’ (that is, good tidings, good news for guilty, helpless
                    sinners) in the largest sense of the word means the whole revelation made to men
                    by Jesus Christ; and sometimes the whole account of what our Lord did and
                    suffered while he tabernacled among men.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A literal rendering of the ἐσκήνωσεν of John
                            1:14 (from σκῆνος, ‘tent’ or ‘tabernacle’).</p>
                    </note> The substance of
                    all is, ‘Jesus Christ came into the world to save sinners;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Tim. 1:15.</p>
                    </note>
                    or, ‘God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten Son, to the end we
                    might not perish, but have everlasting life;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. John 3:16.</p>
                    </note> or, ‘He was bruised
                    for our transgressions, he was wounded for our iniquities; the chastisement of
                    our peace was upon him, and with his stripes we are healed.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 53:5.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="9">
                    <pb n="230"/>9. Believe this, and the kingdom of God is thine. By faith
                    thou attainest the promise: ‘He pardoneth and absolveth all that truly repent
                    and unfeignedly believe his holy gospel.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                        <p rend="footnote text">BCP, Morning Prayer, Absolution
                        (4).</p>
                    </note> As soon as ever God hath spoken to thy heart, ‘Be of good
                    cheer, thy sins are forgiven thee,’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Matt. 9:2.</p>
                    </note> his kingdom comes; thou
                    hast righteousness, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="10">10. Only beware thou do not deceive thy own soul with regard to the nature
                    of this faith. It is not (as some have fondly conceived) a bare assent to the
                    truth of the Bible, of the articles of our creed, or of all that is contained in
                    the Old and New Testament.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. here the doctrines of John Glas (1695-1773) and
                            Robert Sandeman (1718-71), Scottish independents who had rejected both
                            the Calvinist doctrine of ‘final perseverance’ and the Methodist
                            doctrine of ‘conversion’. Faith, they taught, was the clear-headed
                            intellectual acceptance of ‘the Gospel history’ as recorded in the New
                            Testament, and this in itself was saving. Wesley knew of them from
                            Glas’s <hi rend="italic">A Plea for Pure and Undefiled Religion</hi>
                            (1741) and <hi rend="italic">A Treatise on the Lord’s Supper</hi>
                            (1743). Wesley’s diary of Mar. 8, 1741, records that he had ‘read Glas’.
                            Later, Sandeman (under the pseudonym of ‘Palaemon’) would expound his
                            soteriology in <hi rend="italic">Letters on Theron and Aspasio</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Addressed to the Author</hi> [James Hervey] (1757),
                            which drew an extended reply from Wesley in a letter dated Nov. 1, 1757,
                            in which the notion of faith as bare assent is sharply denounced as
                            ‘stark, staring nonsense’ (see <hi rend="italic">Bibliog</hi>, No. 221,
                            Vol. 13 of this edn.).</p>
                    </note> The devils believe<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Jas. 2:19.</p>
                    </note>
                    this, as well as I or thou; and yet they are devils still. But it is, over and
                    above this, a sure trust in the mercy of God through Christ Jesus.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Homily, ‘Of
                            Faith’, and I.6-7, above.</p>
                    </note> It is a confidence in a pardoning
                    God. It is a divine evidence or conviction that ‘God was in Christ, reconciling
                    the world to himself, not imputing to them their former trespasses;’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                            5:19.</p>
                    </note> and in particular that the Son of God hath loved <hi rend="italic">me</hi> and given himself for <hi rend="italic">me</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See Gal.
                            2:20.</p>
                    </note> and that I, even I, am now reconciled to God by the
                    blood of the cross.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn97" n="97">
                        <p rend="footnote text">A conflation of Rom. 5:10 and Col.
                    1:20.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="11">11. Dost thou thus believe? Then the peace of God is in thy heart, and
                    sorrow and sighing flee away.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn98" n="98">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Isa. 35:10.</p>
                    </note> Thou art no longer in doubt
                    of the love of God; it is clear as the noonday sun. Thou criest out, ‘My song
                    shall be always of the loving-kindness of the Lord: with my mouth will I ever be
                    telling of thy truth, from one generation to another.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn99" n="99">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 89:1 (BCP).</p>
                    </note>
                    Thou art no longer afraid of hell, or death, or him that had once the power of
                    death, the devil: no, nor painfully afraid of God himself; only thou hast a
                    tender, filial fear of offending him. Dost thou believe? Then thy ‘soul doth
                    magnify <pb n="231"/>the Lord, and thy spirit rejoiceth in God thy
                        Saviour’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn100" n="100">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:46-47.</p>
                    </note> Thou rejoicest in that thou hast
                    ‘redemption through his blood, even the forgiveness of sins’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn101" n="101">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Col. 1:14.</p>
                    </note> Thou
                    rejoicest in that ‘Spirit of adoption which crieth in thy heart, Abba,
                        Father!’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn102" n="102">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:15.</p>
                    </note> Thou rejoicest in a ‘hope full of
                        immortality’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn103" n="103">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Wisd. 3:4.</p>
                    </note> in reaching forth unto the
                    ‘mark of the prize of thy high calling’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn104" n="104">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 3:14.</p>
                    </note> in an earnest
                    expectation of all the good things which God hath prepared for them that love
                        him.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn105" n="105">
                        <p rend="footnote text">1
                            Cor. 2:9.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="12">12. Dost thou now believe? Then ‘the love of God is’ now ‘shed abroad in
                    thy heart.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn106" n="106">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 5:5.</p>
                    </note> Thou lovest him, because he first loved
                        us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn107" n="107">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1
                            John 4:19.</p>
                    </note> And because thou lovest God, thou lovest thy
                    brother also.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn108" n="108">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 1 John 4:21.</p>
                    </note> And being filled with ‘love, peace, joy’,
                    thou art also filled with ‘long-suffering, gentleness, fidelity, goodness,
                    meekness, temperance’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn109" n="109">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 5:22-23.</p>
                    </note> and all the other fruits
                    of the same Spirit—in a word, with whatever dispositions are holy, are heavenly
                    or divine. For while thou ‘beholdest with open (uncovered) face’ (the veil now
                    being taken away) ‘the glory of the Lord’, his glorious love, and the glorious
                    image wherein thou wast created, thou art ‘changed into the same image, from
                    glory to glory, by the Spirit of the Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn110" n="110">
                        <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 3:18.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
                <p n="13">13. This repentance, this faith, this peace, joy, love; this change from
                    glory to glory, is what the wisdom of the world has voted to be madness, mere
                    enthusiasm, utter distraction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn111" n="111">
                        <p rend="footnote text">An echo of charges, chiefly against Whitefield, by
                            various critics like <hi rend="italic">The Weekly Advertiser</hi> (June
                            13, 1741), Joseph Trapp, <hi rend="italic">The Nature, Folly, Sin, and
                                Danger of Being Righteous Overmuch</hi> (1739), Richard Smalbroke
                            (Bishop of Lichfield), and others. Cf. Green, <hi rend="italic">Anti-Methodist Publications</hi>, for 1739-45. See also No. 10,
                            ‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, §1 and n.</p>
                    </note> But thou, O man of
                    God, regard them not: be thou moved by none of these things. Thou knowest in
                    whom thou hast believed.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn112" n="112">
                        <p rend="footnote text">See 2 Tim. 1:12.</p>
                    </note> See that no man take
                    thy crown.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn113" n="113">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 3:11.</p>
                    </note> Whereunto thou hast already attained, hold fast,
                    and follow, till thou attain all the great and precious promises. And thou who
                    hast not yet known him, let not vain men make thee ashamed of the gospel of
                    Christ. Be thou in nothing terrified by those who speak evil of the things which
                    they know not. God will soon turn thy heaviness into joy. O let not thy hands
                        <pb n="232"/>hang down. Yet a little longer, and he will take away thy
                    fears, and give thee the spirit of a sound mind. ‘He is nigh that
                        justifieth:’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn114" n="114">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Isa. 50:8.</p>
                    </note> ‘Who is he that
                    condemneth? It is Christ that died; yea, rather, that rose again; who is even
                    now at the right hand of God, making intercession for thee.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn115" n="115">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 8:34.</p>
                    </note>
                    Now cast thyself on the Lamb of God, with all thy sins, how many soever they be;
                    and ‘an entrance shall <hi rend="italic">now</hi> be ministered unto <hi rend="italic">thee</hi> into the kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jesus
                        Christ’!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn116" n="116">
                        <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Pet. 1:11.</p>
                    </note>
                </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>