<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Sermon 12: The Witness of Our Own Spirit</title>
                <author>Wesley, John</author>
                <editor role="text">Van Buskirk, Gregory P.</editor>
                <editor role="digital">Taylor, Michelle M.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>The Wesley Works Digitzation Project</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Tampa, FL</pubPlace>
                <date>2024-02-24</date>
             <idno type="URI">https://wesleyworks.ecdsdev.org/sermons/Sermon012</idno>                  
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <listBibl>
                    <biblStruct>
                        <analytic>
                            <title level="a">Sermon 12: The Witness of Our Own Spirit</title>
                        </analytic>
                        <monogr>
                            <title level="j">The Works of John Wesley, Volume I: Sermons I,
                                1-33</title>
                            <editor role="volume">Outler, Albert</editor>
                            <imprint>
                                <publisher>Abingdon Press</publisher>
                                <pubPlace>Nashville, TN</pubPlace>
                                <date when="2015-05-01">1984-05-01</date>
                                <biblScope unit="volume" n="1"/>
                                <biblScope unit="page" from="299" to="313"/>
                            </imprint>
                        </monogr>
                        <series>
                            <title level="s">The Works of John Wesley</title>
                            <editor role="general">Baker, Frank</editor>
                        </series>
                    </biblStruct>
                </listBibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <p>Greg Van Buskirk created Word docs for all of Wesley's sermons using a combination of
                OCR software and manual proofing. Michelle Taylor converted these docx into XML
                using Oxygen's DITA automatic transformation scenario, then touched them up
                manually.</p>
        </encodingDesc>
        <standOff>
            <taxonomy>
                <keywords>
                    <term/>
                </keywords>
            </taxonomy>
            <!--Include keywords and terms here eventually.-->
        </standOff>
        <revisionDesc/>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="299"/>
            <introduction>
                <!--Confirm introduction is the element I want to use here, especially given that I
                    use it as an attribute for Wesley's introductory paragraphs as well.-->
                <head>
                    <hi rend="italic">An Introductory Comment</hi>
                </head>
                <p>Here is a sequel to the two previous ‘Discourses’ and, like them, was apparently
                    written expressly for publication rather than being a condensate of oral sermons
                    already preached. For one thing, we have no records of Wesley’s ever preaching
                    an oral sermon on 2 Cor. 1:12. For another, this is one of Wesley’s rare sermons
                    with no ‘heads’. Later, in 1788, he will write another sermon from the same text
                    and with much the same argument; see No. 105, ‘On Conscience’.</p>
                <p>The main point to the discourses on ‘The Witness of the Spirit’ had been the <hi rend="italic">objective</hi> ground of Christian assurance, <hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, the direct ‘witness of the Spirit’ as revealing to
                    and convincing the believer of God’s pardoning, regenerating, adopting grace.
                    Here, in the sequel, Wesley undertakes an analysis of the <hi rend="italic">subjective</hi> side of this <hi rend="italic">experience</hi> of grace.
                    His distinctive emphasis, however, is his careful correlation of assurance with
                    a good conscience. What we have, then, is a brief essay on conscience, its marks
                    and norms—and the resultant joy of Christian living ‘in simplicity and godly
                    sincerity…’. Wesley recognizes the logical distinctions between adoption,
                    justification, and regeneration but is even more concerned to show their
                    psychological integration in the Christian experience of assurance and how the
                    process of sanctification, begun with regeneration, is really aimed at ‘the
                    recovery of the image of God’ (an equivalent phrase for holiness).</p>
                <p>Note the clear anticipation here of Kant’s notion of a universal, categorical
                    moral imperative linked to a Puritan view of distinct guidelines for ‘a good
                    conscience’: (1) Scripture, (2) self-understanding, and (3) an observed
                    consonance between intentions and actual behaviour. There is an important
                    identification of God’s grace as his power: ‘the Holy Ghost working in us both
                    to will and to do of [the Father’s] good pleasure’ (§15). The essay concludes
                    with a description of ‘the nature of that joy whereby [a mature] Christian
                    rejoiceth evermore’ as a consequence of ‘a conscience void of offence toward God
                    and man’.</p>
                <p>In 1771 Wesley added a postscript that suggests his awareness of the delicate
                    balance between Christian conscience (as portrayed here) and Christian
                    scrupulosity and unease: ‘It may easily be observed that the <pb n="300"/>preceding discourse describes the experience of those that are <hi rend="italic">strong</hi> in faith, but hereby those that are <hi rend="italic">weak</hi> in faith may be discouraged; to prevent which the
                    following discourse [<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>, <hi rend="italic">On Sin in
                        Believers</hi>] may be of use.’ This, then, is a ‘bridge’ sermon, and should
                    be read with both what precedes and what follows it in mind.</p>
            </introduction>
            <head>The Witness of Our Own Spirit</head>
            <epigraph>
                <p>2 Corinthians 1:12</p>
                <p>
                    <hi rend="italic">This is our rejoicing, the testimony of our conscience, that
                        in simplicity and godly sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace
                        of God, we have had our conversation in the world.</hi>
                </p>
            </epigraph>
            <p n="1">1. Such is the voice of every true believer in Christ, so long as he abides in
                faith and love. ‘He that followeth me’, saith our Lord, ‘walketh not in
                    darkness.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn1" n="1">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        John 8:12.</p>
                </note> And while he hath the light he rejoiceth therein.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn2" n="2">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See John
                    5:35.</p>
                </note> ‘As he hath received the Lord Jesus Christ, so he walketh in
                    him.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn3" n="3">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col.
                        2:6.</p>
                </note> And while he walketh in him, the exhortation of the Apostle
                takes place in his soul day by day: ‘Rejoice in the Lord always; and again I say,
                    rejoice.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn4" n="4">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Phil.
                        4:4.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. But that we may not build our house upon the sand (lest when the rains
                descend, and the winds blow, and the floods arise and beat upon it, it fall, and
                great be the fall thereof)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn5" n="5">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:26-27.</p>
                </note> I intend, in the
                following discourse, to show what is the nature and ground of a Christian’s joy. We
                know, in general, it is that happy peace, that calm satisfaction of spirit, which
                arises from such a testimony of his conscience as is here described by the Apostle.
                But in order to understand this the more throughly,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn6" n="6">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Johnson’s comment on the equivalence of
                        ‘throughly’ and ‘thoroughly’ in his <hi rend="italic">Dictionary</hi>.
                        Although Wesley seems to have used both, he clearly preferred ‘throughly’.
                        In this edn., instead of standardizing one spelling, we use whichever form
                        appears in the preferred printing.</p>
                </note> it will be requisite to weigh
                all his words; whence will easily appear both what we are to <pb n="301"/>understand
                by ‘conscience’, and what by the ‘testimony’ thereof; and also how he that hath this
                testimony rejoiceth evermore.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And, first, what are we to understand by ‘conscience’? What is the meaning
                of this word that is in everyone’s mouth? One would imagine it was an exceeding
                difficult thing to discover this, when we consider how large and numerous volumes
                have been from time to time wrote on this subject; and how all the treasures of
                ancient and modern learning have been ransacked in order to explain it. And yet it
                is to be feared it has not received much light from all those elaborate inquiries.
                Rather, have not most of those writers puzzled the cause, ‘darkening counsel by
                words without knowledge’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn7" n="7">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Job 38:2.</p>
                </note> perplexing a subject plain in
                itself, and easy to be understood? For set aside but hard words, and every man of an
                honest heart will soon understand the thing.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn8" n="8">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s habit of disparaging the existing
                        literature on a given topic is more misleading here than usual. The fact is
                        that ‘conscience’ had been a familiar theme for moralists since St. Thomas
                        Aquinas at least. Joseph Butler had focused the second of his famous Rolls
                        Chapel sermons on it in 1726. Wesley had read this, and Butler’s definition
                        of conscience is strikingly similar to his own (<hi rend="italic">viz.</hi>,
                        ‘a superior principle of reflection in every man, which distinguishes
                        between the internal principles of his heart as well as his external
                        actions, which passes judgment upon himself and them, etc.’); cf. <hi rend="italic">Fifteen Sermons</hi>, pp. 35-36. Wesley had also read Jean
                        La Placette’s <hi rend="italic">Divers traités sur des matières de
                            conscience…</hi> (1647) or, more likely, Basil Kennett’s translation,
                        <hi rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The Christian Casuist; or, a Treatise of Conscience </hi>(1705).
                        Besides these there were similar discussions of conscience in Henry Hammond,
                        Robert South, and in Wesley’s grandfather Samuel Annesley’s sermon in <hi rend="italic">The Morning Exercise at Cripplegate</hi> (1661). In his
                        own later sermon (No. 105) ‘On Conscience’ (1788), Wesley will cite La
                        Placette approvingly and will actually quote from Annesley’s sermon
                        extensively.</p>
                    <p rend="footnote text">In Chambers’s <hi rend="italic">Cyclopaedia</hi>—one of Wesley’s favourite reference books—a similar
                        definition appears: ‘a secret testimony or judgment of the soul where it
                        gives its approbation to things it does that are good and reproaches itself
                        for those that are evil’. Thus, early and late, the same basic notion
                        appears, always with more obvious Anglican nuances than in any of the
                        Lutheran or Reformed discussions of ‘conscience’.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. God has made us thinking beings, capable of perceiving what is present, and
                of reflecting or looking back on what is past. In particular we are capable of
                perceiving whatsoever passes in our own hearts or lives; of knowing whatsoever we
                feel or do; and that either while it passes, or when it is past. This we mean when
                we say man is a ‘conscious’ being: he hath a ‘consciousness’ or inward perception
                both of things present and past relating to himself, of his own tempers and outward
                behaviour. But what we usually term ‘conscience’ implies somewhat more than this. It
                is not barely the knowledge of our present, or the remembrance of our preceding
                life. To remember, to bear witness either of past or <pb n="302"/>present things is
                only one, and the least, office of conscience. Its main business is to excuse or
                accuse, to approve or disapprove, to acquit or condemn.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Some late writers indeed have given a new name to this, and have chose to
                style it a ‘moral sense’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn9" n="9">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The earliest of these was Anthony Ashley Cooper, the
                        third Earl of Shaftesbury (cf. <hi rend="italic">DNB</hi>) The phrase occurs
                        in his <hi rend="italic">Inquiry Concerning Virtue or Merit</hi> (1699),
                        I.iii.1. Another ‘late writer’ was Francis Hutcheson (1694-1746), professor
                        of philosophy at Glasgow, who had expanded and refined Shaftesbury’s ideas.
                        He used the phrase in <hi rend="italic">An Inquiry into the Original of our
                            Ideas of Beauty and Virtue</hi> (1725), Treatise II, Sect. I.v, viii
                        (see also Sect. IV.), and incorporated it into the title of his <hi rend="italic">Essay on the Nature and Conduct of the Passions and
                            Affections, with Illustrations Upon the Moral Sense</hi> (1726).
                        Especially in his later sermons, Wesley cites Hutcheson’s as a horrible
                        example of an autonomous ethical theory divorced from any theonomous ground.
                        Cf. Nos. 49, ‘The Cure of Evil-speaking’, §4; 90, ‘An Israelite Indeed’,
                        §§1-4; 92, ‘On Zeal’, §2; 105, ‘On Conscience’, I.8-10; 106, ‘On Faith, Heb.
                        11:6’, II.2; 120, ‘The Unity of the Divine Being’, §18; 128, ‘The
                        Deceitfulness of the Human Heart’, I.2. See also Wesley’s letters to Samuel
                        Furly, Feb. 18, 1756, and Mar. 8, 1757.</p>
                </note> But the old word seems
                preferable to the new, were it only on this account, that it is more common and
                familiar among men, and therefore easier to be understood. And to Christians it is
                undeniably preferable on another account also; namely, because it is scriptural;
                because it is the word which the wisdom of God hath chose to use in the inspired
                writings.</p>
            <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->And
                according to the meaning wherein it is generally used there, particularly in the
                epistles of St. Paul, we may understand by conscience a faculty or power, implanted
                by God in every soul that comes into the world,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn10" n="10">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The notion of an innate conscience goes back to
                        Plato, and even in Wesley’s lifetime would become the linch-pin of Immanuel
                        Kant’s moral philosophy.</p>
                </note> of perceiving what is right or wrong in
                his own heart or life, in his tempers, thoughts, words, and actions.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But what is the <hi rend="italic">rule</hi> whereby men are to judge of
                right and wrong; whereby their conscience is to be directed? The rule of heathens
                (as the Apostle teaches elsewhere) is ‘the law written in their hearts’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn11" n="11">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 2:15.</p>
                </note>
                ‘These (saith he) not having the (outward) law, are a law unto themselves: who show
                the work of the law’, that which the outward law prescribes, ‘written in their
                heart’ by the finger of God; ‘their conscience also bearing witness’ whether they
                walk by this rule or not; ‘and their thoughts the meanwhile accusing, or even
                excusing’, acquitting, defending them (ἢ καὶ ἀπολογουμένων).<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Rom.
                            2:14-15.</p>
                    </note>
                </hi> But the Christian rule of right and wrong is
                the Word of <pb n="303"/>God, the writings of the Old and New Testament: all which
                the prophets and ‘holy men of old’ wrote ‘as they were moved by the Holy
                    Ghost’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn12" n="12">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2
                        Pet. 1:21.</p>
                </note> ‘all’ that ‘Scripture’ which was ‘given by inspiration
                of God’, and which is indeed ‘profitable for doctrine’, or teaching the whole will
                of God; ‘for reproof’ of what is contrary thereto; ‘for correction’ of error; and
                ‘for instruction (or training us up) in righteousness’.<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">2 Tim. 3:16.</p>
                    </note>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->This ‘is a
                lantern unto a’ Christian’s ‘feet, and a light in all his paths’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn13" n="13">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:105 (cf. BCP).</p>
                </note>
                This alone he receives as his rule of right or wrong, of whatever is really good or
                evil. He esteems nothing good but what is here enjoined, either directly or by plain
                consequence. He accounts nothing evil but what is here forbidden, either in terms or
                by undeniable inference. Whatever the Scripture neither forbids nor enjoins (either
                directly or by plain consequence) he believes to be of an indifferent nature, to be
                in itself neither good nor evil: this being the whole and sole outward rule whereby
                his conscience is to be directed in all things.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn14" n="14">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Here Wesley passes summary judgment on an ancient
                        and vexed question of the dividing line between essentials and <hi rend="italic">adiaphora</hi> (things indifferent); he favours the
                        Melanchthonian tendency to allow a wide latitude in open questions not
                        expressly settled by scriptural injunctions or prohibitions. Lutheran
                        orthodoxy had tended to hold, with Flaccius Illyricus, that ‘nothing is
                        indifferent (ἀδιάφορον) in matters of confession and [potential] abuse (<hi rend="italic">in casu confessionalis et scandali</hi>)’; cf. Seeberg,
                            <hi rend="italic">History of Doctrines</hi>, II.364. Reformed
                        theologians took a more flexible position on this point (cf. Heppe, <hi rend="italic">Reformed Dogmatics</hi>, p. 688); Wesley carried this view
                        much further.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And if it be directed thereby in fact, then hath he ‘the answer of a good
                conscience toward God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn15" n="15">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 Pet. 3:21.</p>
                </note> A ‘good conscience’ is what is
                elsewhere termed by the Apostle a ‘conscience void of offence’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn16" n="16">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Acts 24:16.</p>
                </note> So what he
                at one time expresses thus, ‘I have lived in all good conscience before God until
                this day,’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Acts
                            23:1.</p>
                    </note>
                </hi> he denotes at another by that expression, ‘Herein
                do I exercise myself, to have always a conscience void of offence toward God and
                toward man.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Acts 24:16.</p>
                    </note>
                </hi> Now in order to this there is absolutely
                required, first, a right understanding of the Word of God; of his ‘holy and
                acceptable and perfect will’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn17" n="17">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom 12:1, 2.</p>
                </note> concerning us, as it is
                revealed therein. For it is impossible we should walk by a rule if we do not <pb n="304"/>know what it means. There is, secondly, required (which how few have
                attained!) a true knowledge of ourselves; a knowledge both of our hearts and lives,
                of our inward tempers and outward conversation: seeing, if we know them not, it is
                not possible that we should compare them with our rule. There is required, thirdly,
                an agreement of our hearts and lives, of our tempers and conversation, of our
                thoughts and words and works with that rule, with the written Word of God. For
                without this, if we have any conscience at all, it can be only an evil conscience.
                There is, fourthly, required an inward perception of this agreement with our rule.
                And this habitual perception, this inward consciousness itself, is properly a ‘good
                conscience’; or (in the other phrase of the Apostle) ‘A conscience void of offence
                toward God and toward man’.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But whoever desires to have a conscience thus void of offence, let him see
                that he lay the right foundation. Let him remember, ‘Other foundation’ of this ‘can
                no man lay than that which is laid, even Jesus Christ.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn18" n="18">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 3:11.</p>
                </note> And
                let him also be mindful that no man buildeth on him but by a living faith, that no
                man is a partaker of Christ until he can clearly testify, ‘The life which I now
                live…I live by faith in the Son of God,’ in him who is now <hi rend="italic">revealed</hi> in my heart, ‘who loved me, and gave himself for me’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn19" n="19">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:20; this is
                        the direct witness of the Spirit so strongly stressed in the previous
                        discourses.</p>
                </note> Faith alone is that evidence, that conviction, that
                demonstration of things invisible, whereby the eyes of our understanding being
                opened, and divine light poured in upon them,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn20" n="20">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Nos. 3, <hi rend="italic">‘Awake, Thou That
                            Steepest’</hi>, I.11 and n.; and 10,‘The Witness of the Spirit, I’, I.12
                        and n.</p>
                </note> we ‘see the wondrous things of’ God’s ‘law’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn21" n="21">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Ps. 119:18
                    (BCP).</p>
                </note> the excellency and purity of it; the height and depth and
                length and breadth thereof,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn22" n="22">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 3:18.</p>
                </note> and of every commandment
                contained therein. It is by faith that beholding ‘the light of…the glory of God in
                the face of Jesus Christ’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn23" n="23">
                    <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 4:6.</p>
                </note> we perceive, as in a glass, all
                that is in ourselves, yea, the inmost motions of our souls. And by this alone can
                that blessed love of God be ‘shed abroad in our hearts’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn24" n="24">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 5:5.</p>
                </note> which enables
                us so to love one another as Christ loved us. By this is that gracious promise
                fulfilled unto all the Israel of God, ‘I will put my laws into <pb n="305"/>their
                minds, and write (or engrave) them in their hearts;’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Heb. 8:10 [citing Jer.
                        31:33].</p>
                    </note>
                </hi> hereby producing in their souls an entire agreement
                with his holy and perfect law, and ‘bringing into captivity every thought to the
                obedience of Christ’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn25" n="25">
                    <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 10:5.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->And as an
                evil tree cannot bring forth good fruit, so a good tree cannot bring forth evil
                    fruit.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn26" n="26">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        7:18; cf. Luke 6:43.</p>
                </note> As the heart therefore of a believer, so
                likewise his life is throughly conformed to the rule of God’s commandments. In a
                consciousness whereof he can give glory to God, and say with the Apostle, ‘This is
                our rejoicing, the testimony of our conscience, that in simplicity and godly
                sincerity, not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God, we have had our
                conversation in the world.’</p>
            <p n="9">9. ‘We have had our conversation.’ The Apostle in the original expresses this
                by one single word (ἀνεστράφημεν).<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn27" n="27">
                    <p rend="footnote text">From ἀναστρέφειν, ἀναστρεφή, colloquial terms common in
                        the papyri and signifying ‘conduct’ or ‘lifestyle’, usually with a
                        qualifying adjective; cf. Arndt and Gingrich, <hi rend="italic">Greek-English Lexicon</hi>. Cf. also Johnson’s definition of
                        ‘conversation’ (No. 4): ‘Behaviour; manner of acting in common
                    life.’</p>
                </note> But the meaning thereof is exceeding broad, taking in our
                whole deportment, yea, every inward as well as outward circumstance, whether
                relating to our soul or body. It includes every motion of our heart, of our tongue,
                of our hands and bodily members. It extends to all our actions and words; to the
                employment of all our powers and faculties; to the manner of using every talent we
                have received, with respect either to God or man.</p>
            <p n="10">10. ‘We have had our conversation in the world;’ even in the world of the
                ungodly: not only among the children of God—that were, comparatively, a little
                thing—but among the children of the devil,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn28" n="28">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:10.</p>
                </note> among those that ‘lie in
                wickedness’, ἐν τῷ πονηρῷ,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn29" n="29">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 John 5:19.</p>
                </note> ‘in the wicked one’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn30" n="30">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 John 3:12 (ἐκ τοῦ
                        πονηροῦ). Cf. also ‘The Epistle of Barnabas’, II.10, XXI.3, in <hi rend="italic">The Apostolic Fathers</hi>, Loeb, 24:346, 408. See also
                        Nos. 23, ‘Sermon on the Mount, III’, I.9; 26, ‘Sermon on the Mount, VI’,
                        III.15; and 38, ‘A Caution against Bigotry’, I.1.</p>
                </note> What a world is
                this! How throughly impregnated with the spirit it continually breathes! As our God
                is good and doth good, so the god of this world and all his children are evil, and
                do evil (so far as they are suffered) to all the children of God. Like their father
                they are always lying in wait, or ‘walking <pb n="306"/>about, seeking whom they may
                    devour’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn31" n="31">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                        Pet. 5:8.</p>
                </note> using fraud or force, secret wiles or open violence, to
                destroy those who are not of the world; continually warring against our souls, and
                by old or new weapons and devices of every kind, labouring to bring them back into
                the snare of the devil,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn32" n="32">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim. 3:7; 2 Tim. 2:26. Wesley’s view of ‘the world’
                        and its control is double-sided. When pointing to ‘the mystery of iniquity’,
                        his view is satanocratic (under the dominion of Satan, or the devil—usually
                        personified), as here and in Nos. 23, ‘Sermon on the Mount, III’, III.4; 72,
                        ‘Of Evil Angels’, II.1; 129, ‘Heavenly Treasure in Earthen Vessels’, §2;
                        133, ‘Death and Deliverance’, §2; 138A, ‘On Dissimulation’, §11; see also
                        No. 42, ‘Satan’s Devices’. But in his notions of creation, history,
                        Providence, good angels, and eschatology, Wesley stresses the goodness of
                        creation, the Lordship of Christ, the dominion of Providence. The result is
                        an interesting dialectic between dualism and theomonism.</p>
                </note> into the
                broad road that leadeth to destruction.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn33" n="33">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Matt. 7:13.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. ‘We have had our whole conversation in such a world, in simplicity and
                godly sincerity.’ First, ‘in simplicity’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn34" n="34">
                    <p rend="footnote text">The Erasmian text here reads ἁπλότητι (‘simplicity’);
                        Wesley could hardly have known that better manuscripts read ἁγιότητι
                        (‘holiness’), so that now ἅγιότητι is the preferred reading in D. Eberhard
                        Nestle, ed., <hi rend="italic">Novum Testamentum Graece et Latine</hi>
                        (Stuttgart, 1932), and other modern texts. In any case, ‘simplicity’,
                        ‘sincerity’, ‘a single eye’, are familiar terms in Wesley’s lexicon; cf.
                        Nos. 18, ‘The Marks of the New Birth’, II.2; 19, ‘The Great Privilege of
                        those that are Born of God’, II.10; 30, ‘Sermon on the Mount, X’, §9; 79,
                        ‘On Dissipation’, §17; 90, ‘An Israelite Indeed’, II.9; 95, ‘On the
                        Education of Children’, §10; and 125, ‘On a Single Eye’, §1. [More recent
                        editions of the authoritative Nestle text have returned to ἁπλότητι as the
                        preferred reading, agreeing with Wesley.]</p>
                </note> This is what our Lord
                recommends under the name of a ‘single eye’. ‘The light of the body (saith he) is
                the eye. If therefore thine eye be single, thy whole body shall be full of
                    light.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn35" n="35">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Matt.
                        6:22; cf. Luke 11:34.</p>
                </note> The meaning whereof is this: what the eye
                is to the body, that the intention is to all the words and actions.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn36" n="36">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Wesley’s sources for
                        this general notion would go back to Macarius, Homily IV, in <hi rend="italic">Spiritual Homilies</hi> (1721), pp. 118-19, and would have
                        included John Flavel, ‘Touchstone of Sincerity: or, the Signs of Grace, and
                        the Symptoms of Hypocrisy’, ch. ii, §III (<hi rend="italic">Works</hi>,
                        II.451), and Poole’s <hi rend="italic">Annotations</hi> on Luke 11:36: ‘What
                        the eye is to the body, that the soul, the mind, and affections are to the
                        whole man. Now look, as the eye is the organ by which light is received to
                        guide a man’s steps, so that if that be perfect without any mixture of ill
                        humours, etc., the body from it takes a full and right direction how to move
                        and act. But if that be vitiated by ill humours, the man knows not how to
                        direct his bodily steps. So if a man’s soul (which answereth the bodily eye)
                        more especially a man’s understanding, or judgment be darkened, perverted,
                        prejudiced, or his affections be debauched or depraved, he will not know how
                        to move one step right in his duty; but if his understanding have a right
                        notion of truths, he judgeth aright concerning the things and ways of God,
                        and his affections be not depraved, then the whole man will be in a capacity
                        to receive the light, the revelations of truth, as they shall be
                        communicated to him, even as he who hath a perfect eye receiveth, and is
                        able to make use of the bright shining of a candle.’ This is strikingly
                        similar to Wesley’s general theory of illumination; cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness
                        of the Spirit, I’, I.12 and n.</p>
                </note> If therefore this eye of thy soul
                be <pb n="307"/>single, all thy actions and conversation shall be ‘full of light’,
                of the light of heaven, of love and peace and joy in the Holy Ghost.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn37" n="37">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 14:17; cf. Gal.
                        5:22.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->We are then
                simple of heart when the eye of our mind is singly fixed on God; when in all things
                we aim at God alone, as our God, our portion, our strength, our happiness, our
                exceeding great reward,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn38" n="38">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 15:1.</p>
                </note> our all in time and eternity.
                This is simplicity: when a steady view, a single intention of promoting his glory,
                of doing and suffering his blessed will, runs through our whole soul, fills all our
                heart, and is the constant spring of all our thoughts, desires, and purposes.</p>
            <p n="12">12. ‘We have had our conversation in the world’, secondly, ‘in godly
                    sincerity.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn39" n="39">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        No. 2, <hi rend="italic">The Almost Christian</hi>, I.9 and n.</p>
                </note>
                The difference between simplicity and sincerity seems to be chiefly this: simplicity
                regards the intention itself, sincerity the execution of it. And this sincerity
                relates not barely to our words, but to our whole conversation, as described above.
                It is not here to be understood in that narrow sense wherein St. Paul himself
                sometimes uses it, for speaking the truth, or abstaining from guile, from craft and
                dissimulation, but in a more extensive meaning, as actually hitting the mark which
                we aim at by simplicity. Accordingly it implies in this place that we do in fact
                speak and do all to the glory of God;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn40" n="40">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 Cor. 10:31.</p>
                </note> that all our words are not
                only pointed at this, but actually conducive thereto; that all our actions flow on
                in an even stream, uniformly subservient to this great end; and that in our whole
                lives we are moving straight toward God, and that continually—walking steadily on in
                the highway of holiness, in the paths of justice, mercy, and truth.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn41" n="41">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 89:14
                        (AV).</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. This sincerity is termed by the Apostle ‘godly sincerity’, or the
                sincerity of God (εἰλικρινείᾳ Θεοῦ)<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn42" n="42">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Thus the <hi rend="italic">TR</hi>; modern texts read
                        εἰλικρινεία τοῦ Θεοῦ.</p>
                </note> to prevent our mistaking or confounding it
                with the sincerity of the heathens (for they had also a kind of sincerity among
                them, for which they professed no small veneration); likewise to denote the object
                and end of this, as of every Christian virtue; seeing whatever does not ultimately
                tend to God sinks among ‘the beggarly elements of the world’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn43" n="43">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 4:9.</p>
                </note> By
                styling it ‘the sincerity of God’ he also points out the <pb n="308"/>author of it,
                the ‘Father of lights, from whom every good and perfect gift descendeth’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn44" n="44">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Jas.
                    1:17.</p>
                </note> which is still more clearly declared in the following words,
                ‘not with fleshly wisdom, but by the grace of God’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn45" n="45">
                    <p rend="footnote text">2 Cor. 1:12.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. ‘Not with fleshly wisdom’: as if he had said, ‘We cannot thus converse in
                the world by any natural strength of understanding, neither by any naturally
                acquired knowledge or wisdom. We cannot gain this simplicity or practise this
                sincerity by the force either of good sense, good nature, or good breeding. It
                overshoots all our native courage and resolution, as well as all our precepts of
                philosophy. The power of custom is not able to train us up to this, nor the most
                exquisite rules of human education. Neither could I, Paul, ever attain hereto,
                notwithstanding all the advantages I enjoyed, so long as I was “in the flesh”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn46" n="46">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 7:5,
                    etc.</p>
                </note> (in my natural state) and pursued it only by “fleshly”, natural,
                “wisdom”.’</p>
            <p><!--Decide how to number paragraphs Wesley has not numbered, if at all.-->And yet
                surely, if any man could, Paul himself might have attained thereto by that wisdom.
                For we can hardly conceive any who was more highly favoured with all the gifts both
                of nature and education. Besides his natural abilities, probably not inferior to
                those of any person then upon the earth, he had all the benefits of learning,
                studying at the university of Tarsus,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn47" n="47">
                    <p rend="footnote text">An <hi rend="italic">urbs libera</hi> (‘free city’) in
                        the Syrian province of Cilicia. Jews living and educated there were in
                        contact with a vigorous Hellenistic culture, but that there was a
                        ‘university of Tarsus’ was, of course, Wesley’s own ‘modernization’. Cf.
                        below, No. 25, ‘Sermon on the Mount, V’, IV.2.</p>
                </note> afterwards
                ‘brought up at the feet of Gamaliel’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn48" n="48">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 22:3. This was Gamaliel I, ha-Zaken (‘the
                        elder’), a grandson of Hillel and presiding officer of the Sanhedrin. He is
                        credited, in the tradition of Hillel, with many <hi rend="italic">takkanot</hi> (normative moral regulations) more tolerant than the
                        rigorist rulings of Shammai. This would accord with his tolerant judgment
                        upon the early Christian movement as reported in Acts 5:34-40. It conflicts
                        with Paul’s claim, emphasized here by Wesley, that he had been ‘brought up
                        at Gamaliel’s feet’, as if that amounted to his belonging ‘to the very
                        straitest sect’ of the Pharisees. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Encyclopaedia
                            Judaica</hi> (Jerusalem, 1971), art. ‘Gamaliel’.</p>
                </note> the person
                of the greatest account both for knowledge and integrity that was then in the whole
                Jewish nation. And he had all the possible advantages of religious education, being
                a Pharisee, the son of a Pharisee, trained up in the very straitest sect or
                profession, distinguished from all others by a more eminent strictness. And herein
                he had ‘profited above many others who were his equals in years, being more
                abundantly zealous’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn49" n="49">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 1:14 (cf. <hi rend="italic">Notes</hi>).</p>
                </note> of whatever he
                thought would please <pb n="309"/>God, and ‘as touching the righteousness of the
                law, blameless’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn50" n="50">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Phil. 3:6.</p>
                </note> But it could not be that he should hereby attain this
                simplicity and godly sincerity. It was all but lost labour; in a deep, piercing
                sense of which he was at length constrained to cry out: ‘The things which were gain
                to me, those I counted loss for Christ…. Yea, doubtless, and I count all things but
                loss for the excellency of the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord.’<hi rend="endnote_reference">
                    <note place="end">
                        <p rend="endnote text">Phil.
                            3:7-8.</p>
                    </note>
                </hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">15. It could not be that ever he should attain to this but by the ‘excellent
                knowledge of Jesus Christ our Lord’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn51" n="51">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. main text and Phil. 3:8.</p>
                </note> or ‘by the
                grace of God’—another expression of nearly the same import. By ‘the grace of God’ is
                sometimes to be understood that free love, that unmerited mercy, by which I, a
                sinner, through the merits of Christ am now reconciled to God. But in this place it
                rather means that power of God the Holy Ghost which ‘worketh in us both to will and
                to do of his good pleasure’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn52" n="52">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Phil. 2:13. Cf. No. 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own
                        Salvation’.</p>
                </note> As soon as ever the grace of God (in the former
                sense, his pardoning love) is manifested to our soul, the grace of God (in the
                latter sense, the power of his Spirit) takes place therein. And now we can perform,
                through God, what to man was impossible. Now we can order our conversation aright.
                We can do all things in the light and power of that love, through Christ which
                strengtheneth us.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn53" n="53">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Phil. 4:13.</p>
                </note> We now have ‘the testimony of our conscience’,
                which we could never have by fleshly wisdom, ‘that in simplicity and godly
                sincerity…we have our conversation in the world’.</p>
            <p n="16">16. This is properly the ground of a Christian’s joy. We may now therefore
                readily conceive how he that hath this testimony in himself ‘rejoiceth
                    evermore’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn54" n="54">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1
                        Thess. 5:16.</p>
                </note> ‘“My soul” (may he say) “doth magnify the Lord, and
                my spirit rejoiceth in God my Saviour.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn55" n="55">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Luke 1:46-47.</p>
                </note> I rejoice in him who, of
                his own unmerited love, of his own free and tender mercy, “hath called me into this
                state of salvation”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn56" n="56">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. BCP, Catechism.</p>
                </note> wherein through his power I now stand. I
                rejoice because his Spirit beareth witness to my spirit<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn57" n="57">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Rom. 8:16.</p>
                </note> that I
                am bought with the blood of the Lamb,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn58" n="58">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rev. 7:14; 12:11.</p>
                </note> and that believing in him,
                “I am a member of <pb n="310"/>Christ, a child of God, and an inheritor of the
                kingdom of heaven.”<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn59" n="59">
                    <p rend="footnote text">A composite paraphrase of 1 Cor. 6:15; Rom. 8:16, 17; and Jas.
                    2:5.</p>
                </note> I rejoice because the sense of God’s love to me hath by the same
                Spirit wrought in me to love him, and to love for his sake every child of man, every
                soul that he hath made. I rejoice because he gives me to feel in myself “the mind
                that was in Christ”:<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn60" n="60">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Phil. 2:5.</p>
                </note> simplicity, a single eye to him in every motion
                of my heart; power always to fix the loving eye of my soul on him who “loved me, and
                gave himself for me”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn61" n="61">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Gal. 2:20.</p>
                </note> to aim at him alone, at his
                glorious will, in all I think or speak or do; purity, desiring nothing more but God,
                “crucifying the flesh with its affections and lusts”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn62" n="62">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Gal. 5:24.</p>
                </note> “setting
                my affections on things above, not on things of the earth”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn63" n="63">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Col. 3:2.</p>
                </note> holiness,
                a recovery of the image of God,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn64" n="64">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Gen. 1:27; 9:6. Cf. No. 44, <hi rend="italic">Original
                            Sin</hi>, III.5 and n.</p>
                </note> a renewal of soul after his likeness;
                and godly sincerity, directing all my words and works so as to conduce to his glory.
                In this I likewise rejoice, yea and will rejoice, because my conscience beareth me
                witness in the Holy Ghost, by the light he continually pours in upon it, that “I
                walk worthy of the vocation wherewith” I am “called”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn65" n="65">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 4:1.</p>
                </note> that I
                “abstain from all appearance of evil”,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn66" n="66">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 Thess. 5:22.</p>
                </note> “fleeing from sin as from the
                face of a serpent”;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn67" n="67">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ecclus. 21:2.</p>
                </note> that as I have opportunity I do all possible
                good, in every kind, to all men;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn68" n="68">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See <hi rend="italic">General Rules</hi>,
                    §5.</p>
                </note> that I follow my Lord in all my steps, and do what is acceptable
                in his sight. I rejoice because I both see and feel, through the inspiration of
                God’s Holy Spirit, that all my works are wrought in him, yea, and that it is he who
                worketh all my works in me. I rejoice in seeing, through the light of God which
                shines in my heart, that I have power to walk in his ways, and that through his
                grace I turn not therefrom, to the right hand or to the left.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn69" n="69">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Josh. 23:6.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. Such is the ground and the nature of that joy whereby a Christian
                rejoiceth evermore. And from all this we may easily infer, first, that this is not a
                    <hi rend="italic">natural</hi> joy. It does not arise from any natural cause:
                not from any sudden flow of spirits. This may give a transient start of joy. But the
                Christian ‘rejoiceth always’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn70" n="70">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor. 6:10.</p>
                </note> It cannot be owing to
                bodily health or ease, to strength and soundness of constitution. For it is equally
                strong in sickness and pain; yea, perhaps far stronger than before. Many Christians
                have <pb n="311"/>never experienced any joy to be compared with that which then
                filled their soul, when the body was wellnigh worn out with pain, or consumed away
                with pining sickness. Least of all can it be ascribed to outward prosperity, to the
                favour of men, or plenty of worldly goods. For then chiefly when their faith has
                been tried as with fire, by all manner of outward afflictions, have the children of
                God rejoiced in him ‘whom unseen they loved’, even ‘with joy unspeakable’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn71" n="71">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Pet.
                    1:8.</p>
                </note> And never surely did men rejoice like those who were used as
                ‘the filth and offscouring of the world’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn72" n="72">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 1 Cor. 4:13.</p>
                </note> who wandered to and fro,
                being in want of all things, in hunger, in cold, in nakedness; who ‘had trials’, not
                only ‘of cruel mockings’, but ‘moreover of bonds and imprisonments’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn73" n="73">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Heb.
                    11:36.</p>
                </note> yea, who at last ‘counted not their lives dear unto
                themselves, so they might finish their course with joy’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn74" n="74">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Acts 20:24.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. From the preceding considerations we may, secondly, infer that the joy of
                a Christian does not arise from any <hi rend="italic">blindness of conscience</hi>,
                from his not being able to discern good from evil. So far from it that he was an
                utter stranger to this joy till the eyes of his understanding were opened,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn75" n="75">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Eph.
                    1:18.</p>
                </note> that he knew it not until he had spiritual senses, fitted to
                discern spiritual good and evil.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn76" n="76">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Heb. 5:14; cf. No. 10, ‘The Witness of the Spirit,
                        I’, I.12 and n.</p>
                </note> And now the eye of his soul waxeth not dim. He
                was never so sharpsighted before. He has so quick a perception of the smallest
                things as is quite amazing to the natural man. As a mote is visible in the sunbeam,
                so to him who is walking in the light, in the beams of the uncreated sun, every mote
                of sin is visible.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn77" n="77">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Direct divine illumination; cf. §8 above.</p>
                </note> Nor does he close the
                eyes of his conscience any more. That sleep is departed from him. His soul is always
                broad awake: no more slumber or folding of the hands in rest!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn78" n="78">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Prov. 6:10; 24:33. See also
                        No. 113, <hi rend="italic">The Late Work of God in North America</hi>,
                        II.12.</p>
                </note> He is always standing on the tower, and hearkening what
                his Lord will say concerning him;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn79" n="79">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Isa. 21:8; 37:22. See also 2 Kgs. 19:21; 1 Chr.
                        17:23.</p>
                </note> and always rejoicing in this very thing, in ‘seeing him
                that is invisible’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn80" n="80">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 11:27.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. Neither does the joy of a Christian arise, thirdly, from any <hi rend="italic">dullness</hi> or <hi rend="italic">callousness of conscience</hi>.
                A kind of joy, it is true, may arise from this in those whose ‘foolish hearts are
                    darkened’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn81" n="81">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf.
                        Rom. 1:21.</p>
                </note> whose <pb n="312"/>heart is callous, unfeeling, dull
                of sense, and consequently without spiritual understanding. Because of their
                senseless, unfeeling hearts, they may rejoice even in committing sin; and this they
                may probably call ‘liberty’! Which is indeed mere drunkenness of soul; a fatal
                numbness of spirit, the stupid insensibility of a seared conscience.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn82" n="82">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Tim. 4:2; cf.
                        Nos. 49, ‘The Cure of Evil-speaking’, I.6; 85, ‘On Working Out Our Own
                        Salvation’, III.4; and 149, ‘On Love’, III.5.</p>
                </note> On the contrary, a
                Christian has the most exquisite sensibility, such as he would not have conceived
                before. He never had such a tenderness of conscience as he has had since the love of
                God has reigned in his heart. And this also is his glory and joy, that God hath
                heard his daily prayer:</p>
            <lg>
                <l>O that my tender soul might fly</l>
                <l>The first abhorred approach of ill:</l>
                <l>Quick as the apple of an eye</l>
                <l>The slightest touch of sin to feel.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn83" n="83">
                        <p rend="footnote text">‘Watch in All Things’, st. 10, in <hi rend="italic">Hymns and Sacred Poems</hi> (1742), p. 218 (<hi rend="italic">Poet.
                                Wks.</hi>, II.273). Cf. also No. 105, ‘On Conscience’, I.15. For
                            other quotations from this same hymn, cf. Nos. 95, ‘On the Education of
                            Children’, §18; 106, ‘On Faith, Heb. 11:6’, II.4; and 126, ‘On Worldly
                            Folly’, II.2.</p>
                    </note>
                </l>
            </lg>
            <p n="20">20. To conclude. Christian joy is joy in obedience—joy in loving God and
                keeping his commandments. And yet not in keeping them as if we were thereby to
                fulfil the terms of the <hi rend="italic">covenant of works</hi>;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn84" n="84">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. No. 6, ‘The Righteousness of
                        Faith’, §1 and n.</p>
                </note> as if by any works or righteousness of ours we
                were to <hi rend="italic">procure</hi> pardon and acceptance with God. Not so: we
                are already pardoned and accepted through the mercy of God in Christ Jesus—not as if
                we were by our own obedience to <hi rend="italic">procure</hi> life, life from the
                death of sin. This also we have already through the grace of God. ‘Us hath he
                quickened, who were dead in sin.’<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn85" n="85">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Eph. 2:1.</p>
                </note> And now we are ‘alive to God,
                through Jesus Christ our Lord’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn86" n="86">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Rom. 6:11.</p>
                </note> But we rejoice in walking
                according to the <hi rend="italic">covenant of grace</hi>, in holy love and happy
                obedience. We rejoice in knowing that ‘being justified through his grace’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn87" n="87">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Rom. 3:24; Titus
                        3:7.</p>
                </note> we have ‘not received that grace of God in vain’;<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn88" n="88">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. 2 Cor.
                    6:1.</p>
                </note> that God having freely (not for the sake of our willing or
                running, but through the blood of the Lamb) reconciled us to himself, we run in the
                strength which he hath given us the way of his commandments.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn89" n="89">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See Ps. 119:32.</p>
                </note> He hath
                ‘girded us with strength <pb n="313"/>unto the war’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn90" n="90">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Cf. Ps. 18:39; 2 Sam.
                    22:40.</p>
                </note> and we gladly ‘fight the good fight of faith’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn91" n="91">
                    <p rend="footnote text">1 Tim.
                    6:12.</p>
                </note> We rejoice, through him who liveth in our hearts by faith, to
                ‘lay hold of eternal life’.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn92" n="92">
                    <p rend="footnote text">
                        <hi rend="italic">Ibid.</hi>
                    </p>
                </note> This is our
                rejoicing; that as our ‘Father worketh hitherto’,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn93" n="93">
                    <p rend="footnote text">John 5:17.</p>
                </note> so (not by our own might or
                wisdom, but through the power of his Spirit freely given in Christ Jesus) we also
                work the works of God.<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn94" n="94">
                    <p rend="footnote text">John 6:28.</p>
                </note> And may he work in us whatsoever
                is well-pleasing in his sight,<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn95" n="95">
                    <p rend="footnote text">Heb. 13:21.</p>
                </note> to whom be the praise for ever
                and ever!<note place="foot" xml:id="ftn96" n="96">
                    <p rend="footnote text">See 1 Pet
                        4:11. For Wesley’s use of ascriptions, cf. No. 1, <hi rend="italic">Salvation by Faith</hi>, III.9 and n.</p>
                </note>
            </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>